<article title='Dog_tag'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>identification tags worn by military personnel</arg><arg>the identifying tag worn by pets</arg><arg>Pet tag</arg><arg>other uses</arg></template><template><target>Use American English</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:Dogtags.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>A pair of blank dog tags on a<space/><link><target>ball chain</target></link></part></link>&quot;<bold>Dog tags</bold>&quot; is an informal term for the identification tags worn by<space/><link><target>military personnel</target></link>, because of their resemblance to<space/><link><target>Pet tag</target><part>animal registration tags</part></link>. The tags are primarily used for the identification of dead and wounded soldiers; they have personal info about the soldiers and convey essential basic medical information, such as<space/><link><target>blood type</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>U.S. Soldiers &quot;tagged&quot; for blood transfusion</italics>, Popular Science, February 1942, p71, Scanned by Google Books: http://books.google.com/books?id=pScDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA71-IA1</extension><space/>and history of<space/><link><target>inoculation</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The tags often indicate religious preference as well. Dog tags are usually fabricated from a corrosion-resistant metal. They commonly contain two copies of the information, either in the form of a single tag that can be broken in half or two identical tags on the same chain. This duplication allows one tag (or half-tag) to be collected from a soldier's body for notification and the second to remain with the corpse when battle conditions prevent it from being immediately recovered.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dog tags.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Dog tags of a U.S. Army soldier who served in World War II</part></link>Dog tags were provided to Chinese soldiers as early as the mid-19th century. During the<space/><link><target>Taiping Rebellion</target><part>Taiping revolt</part></link><space/>(185166), both the Imperialists (i.e., the Chinese Imperial Army regular servicemen) and those Taiping rebels wearing a uniform wore a wooden dog tag at the belt, bearing the soldier's name, age, birthplace, unit, and date of enlistment.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heath I., Perry M. The Taping rebellion 1851-66; Men-at-arm series 275; Osprey 1994</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link><space/>from 18611865, some soldiers pinned paper notes<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McCormick</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Inventing Military Dog Tags</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="url">http://web.ebscohost.com.proxylib.csueastbay.edu/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid</arg></template></extension><space/>with their name and home address to the backs of their coats. Other soldiers stenciled identification on their knapsacks or scratched it in the soft lead backing of their army belt buckle.</paragraph><paragraph>Manufacturers of identification badges recognized a market and began advertising in periodicals. Their pins were usually shaped to suggest a branch of service, and engraved with the soldier's name and unit. Machine-stamped tags were also made of<space/><link><target>brass</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>lead</target></link><space/>with a hole and usually had (on one side) an eagle or shield, and such phrases as &quot;War for the Union&quot; or &quot;Liberty, Union, and Equality&quot;. The other side had the soldier's name and unit, and sometimes a list of<space/><link><target>battle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in which he had participated.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Franco-Prussian War</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Prussia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>Army issued identification tags for its troops at the beginning of the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian War</target></link><space/>in 1870. They were nicknamed<space/><italics>Hundemarken</italics><space/>(the German equivalent of &quot;dog tags&quot;) and compared to a similar identification system instituted for dogs in the Prussian capital city of<space/><link><target>Berlin</target></link><space/>at about the same time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Law, Clive M. Article in Military Artifact,<space/><link><target>Service Publications</target></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>First World War</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Erkennungsmarke Georg Redeker , item 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A WWI German army dog tag indicating Name, place of birth, battalion, unit and serial number</part></link>The British Army introduced identity discs in place of identity cards in 1907, in the form of aluminium discs, typically made at Regimental depots using machines similar to those common at fun fairs, the details being pressed into the thin metal one letter at a time.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/westernfrontassociation/4103087039/'>British Regimental Identity Disk circa 1907</link></paragraph><paragraph>By 1915 the British Army required all soldiers to wear two official tags, both made of compressed fibre (which were more comfortable to wear in hot climates) carrying identical details, again impressed one character at a time.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The tags, one an octagonal green tag punched with two holes for cords, the other a red circular tag punched once, were suspended from the serviceman's neck using cord resembling butcher's twine, being passed through one hole in the octagonal green tag, a much shorter cord used to link the two tags, which could be easily separated by cutting.<link type='external' href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/westernfrontassociation/4103087243/'>British Identity Discs 1914-18</link></paragraph><paragraph>On discovering a body with both tags the second could be taken to record the death, others subsequently finding the same body knowing the death either had been (or would soon be) reported, the details on the green tag remaining with the body for the benefit of burial parties who whenever possible would prepare markers.</paragraph><paragraph>British and Empire/Commonwealth forces (Australia, Canada, and New Zealand) were issued identification discs of essentially identical basic pattern during the Great War, Second World War and Korea, though official identity discs were frequently supplemented by private-purchase items such as identity bracelets, particularly favoured by sailors who rightly believed the official discs were unlikely to survive long immersion in water.[Imperial War Museum Website http://www.iwm.org.uk/history/identity-tags &amp; Western Front Association Identifying the dead: a Short Study of the Identification Tags of 1914-1918]</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>U.S. Army</target></link><space/>first authorized identification tags in<space/><link><target>U.S. War Department</target><part>War Department</part></link><space/>General Order No. 204, dated December 20, 1906, which essentially prescribes the Kennedy identification tag:<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>An aluminum identification tag, the size of a silver half dollar and of suitable thickness, stamped with the name,<space/><link><target>military rank</target><part>rank</part></link>,<space/><link><target>company (military unit)</target><part>company</part></link>,<space/><link><target>regiment</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>corps</target></link><space/>of the wearer, will be worn by each officer and enlisted man of the Army whenever the field kit is worn, the tag to be suspended from the neck, underneath the clothing, by a cord or thong passed through a small hole in the tab. It is prescribed as a part of the uniform and when not worn as directed herein will be habitually kept in the possession of the owner. The tag will be issued by the Quartermaster's Department gratuitously to enlisted men and at cost price to officers.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The army changed regulations on July 6, 1916, so that all soldiers were issued two tags: one to stay with the body and the other to go to the person in charge of the burial for record-keeping purposes. In 1918, the army adopted and allotted the<space/><link><target>serial number</target></link><space/>system, and name and serial numbers were ordered stamped on the identification tags. (Serial number 1 was assigned to enlisted man Arthur B. Crane of Chicago in the course of his fifth enlistment period.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>World War II &quot;Notched&quot; tags</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:South African Navy WW2 dogtag.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>One of the two identity discs issued by the South African Navy during WW2 with rank, surname, initials, force number and religious affiliation</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There is a recurring myth about the notch situated in one end of the dog tags issued to United States Army personnel during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, and up until the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link><space/>era. It was rumored that the notch's purpose was that, if a soldier found one of his comrades on the battlefield, he could take one tag to the commanding officer and stick the other between the teeth of the soldier to ensure that the tag would remain with the body and be identified.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In reality, the notch was used with the Model 70<space/><link><target>Addressograph</target></link><space/>Hand Identification Imprinting Machine (a pistol-type imprinter used primarily by the Medical Department during World War II).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.armydogtags.com/a_PurposeNotch.php'></link>, retrieved 22 December 2009</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Barbara Mikkelson.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.snopes.com/military/notch.asp'>&quot;Notch for the Faint Hearted&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>Snopes.com</target></link>, 2 August 2007, retrieved 12 September 2007</extension><space/>American dogtags of the 1930s through 1970s were produced using the<space/><link><target>Graphotype</target></link><space/>system, in which characters are<space/><link><target>debossed</target></link><space/>into metal plates. Some tags are still debossed, using earlier equipment, and some are embossed (with raised letters) on computer-controlled equipment.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Graphotype process, commonly used commercially from the early 1900s through the 1980s, a debossing machine was used to stamp characters into metal plates; the plates could then be used to repetitively stamp such things as addresses onto paper in the same way that a<space/><link><target>typewriter</target></link><space/>functions, except that a single stroke of the printer could produce a block of text rather than requiring each character to be printed individually. The debossing process creates durable, easily legible metal plates, well-suited for military identification tags, leading to adoption of the system by the American military. It was also realized that debossed tags can function the same way the original Graphotype plates do.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The Model 70 took advantage of this fact, and was intended to rapidly print all of the information from a soldier's dogtag directly onto medical and personnel forms, with a single squeeze of the trigger. However, this requires that the tag being inserted with the proper orientation (stamped characters facing down), and it was believed that battlefield stress could lead to errors. To force proper orientation of the tags, the tags are produced with a notch, and there is a locator tab inside the Model 70 which prevents the printer from operating if the tag is inserted with the notch in the wrong place (as it is if the tag is upside down).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>This feature was not as useful in the field as had been hoped, however, due to adverse conditions such as weather, dirt and dust, water, etc. In addition, the Model 70 resembled a pistol, thus attracting the attention of snipers (who might assume that a man carrying a pistol was an officer).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><space/>As a result, use of the Model 70 hand imprinter by field medics was rapidly abandoned (as were most of the Model 70s themselves), and eventually the specification that tags include the locator notch was removed from production orders. Existing stocks of tags were used until depleted, and in the 1960s it was not uncommon for a soldier to be issued one tag with the notch and one tag without. Notched tags are still in production, to satisfy the needs of hobbyists, film production, etc., while the Model 70 imprinter has become a rare collector's item.</paragraph><paragraph>It appears instructions that would confirm the notch's mythical use were issued at least unofficially by the<space/><link><target>Graves Registration Service</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link><space/>to Army troops headed overseas.<extension extension_name='ref'>Col. David G. Fitz-Enz (Ret.):<space/><italics>Why A Soldier? A Signal Corpsman's Tour from Vietnam to the Moscow Hotline</italics>, page 166. Ballantine, 2000. ISBN 0-8041-1938-4</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Dog tags are traditionally part of the makeshift<space/><link><target>Battlefield Cross</target><part>battlefield memorials</part></link><space/>soldiers created for their fallen comrades. The casualty's rifle with<space/><link><target>bayonet</target></link><space/>affixed is stood vertically atop the empty boots, with the helmet over the rifle's stock. The dog tags hang from the rifle's handle or trigger guard.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Non-military usage</heading><heading level='3'>Medical condition identification</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Medical identification tag</arg></template>Some tags (along with similar items such as<space/><link><target>MedicAlert</target></link><space/>bracelets) are used also by civilians to identify their wearers and specify them as having health problems that may<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>(a)</italics><space/>suddenly incapacitate their wearers and render them incapable of providing treatment guidance (as in the cases of heart problems,<space/><link><target>epilepsy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>diabetic coma</target></link>, accident or<space/><link><target>major trauma</target></link>) and/or<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>(b)</italics><space/>interact adversely with medical treatments, especially standard or &quot;first-line&quot; ones (as in the case of an allergy to common medications) and/or<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>(c)</italics><space/>provide<space/><link><target>in case of emergency</target></link><space/>(&quot;ICE&quot;) contact information and/or<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>(d)</italics><space/>state a religious, moral, or other<space/><link><target>Do not resuscitate</target><part>objection to artificial resuscitation</part></link>, if a first responder attempts to administer such treatment when the wearer is non-responsive and thus unable to warn against doing so.</paragraph><paragraph>Military personnel in some jurisdictions may wear a supplementary medical information tag.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Fashion</heading><paragraph>Dog tags have recently found their way into youth fashion by way of<space/><link><target>List_of_chics#Military_chic</target><part>military chic</part></link>. Originally worn as a part of a military uniform by youth wishing to present a tough or militaristic image, dog tags have since seeped out into wider fashion circles. They may be inscribed with a person's details, their beliefs or tastes, a favorite quote, or may bear the name or logo of a band or performer.</paragraph><paragraph>Since the late 1990s, custom dog tags have been fashionable amongst musicians (particularly rappers), and as a marketing give-away item. Numerous companies offer customers the opportunity to create their own personalized dog tags with their own photos, logos, and text. Even high-end jewelers have featured gold and silver dog tags encrusted with diamonds and other jewels.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Variations by country</heading><paragraph><template><target>Unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Austria</heading><paragraph>The Austrian<space/><link><target>Austrian Armed Forces</target><part>Bundesheer</part></link><space/>utilized a single long, rectangular tag, with oval ends, stamped with blood group &amp; Rh factor at the end, with ID number underneath. Two slots and a hole stamped beneath the number allow the tag to be broken in half, and the long bottom portion has both the ID number and a series of holes which allows the tag to be inserted into a<space/><link><target>dosimeter</target></link>. This has been replaced with a more conventional, wider and rounded rectangle which can still be halved, but lacks the dosimeter reading holes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph>The Australian Defence Force issues soldiers two tags of different shapes: Number 1 Tag (the octagonal shaped disc) and Number 2 Tag (the circular disc). The format is as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>AS (denoting Australia, previously both AU and AUST have been used)</listitem><listitem>PMKeyS/ Service Number</listitem><listitem>Surname Initials</listitem><listitem>Religious Preference [RC Roman Catholic; ANG Anglican]</listitem><listitem>Blood Group</listitem></list><paragraph>Example:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>AUST</listitem><listitem>8542873</listitem><listitem>Flanagan C.M</listitem><listitem>CC</listitem><listitem>A POS</listitem></list><paragraph>The information is printed exactly the same on both discs. In the event of a casualty, the circular tag is removed from the body.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Belgium</heading><paragraph>Belgian Forces identity tags are, like the Canadian and Norwegian, designed to be broken in two in case of fatality; the lower half is returned to Belgian Defence tail, while the upper half remains on the body. The tags contain the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Upper half:<list type='bullet'><listitem>Belgisch Leger (Belgian Army) and Date of Birth in DD/MM/YYYY format.</listitem><listitem>Surname with the addition of the first letter of given name.</listitem><listitem>Service number and blood group with RH factor and optionally religion.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Lower half: identical.</listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem>Example:<list type='bullet'><listitem>Belgisch Leger 01/01/1991</listitem><listitem>Surname J</listitem><listitem>1234567 O+ KATH</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CFID.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Canadian Forces ID Disk. Name and service number are redacted.</part></link><link><target>Canadian Forces</target></link><space/>identity discs (abbreviated &quot;I discs&quot;) are designed to be broken in two in the case of fatality; the lower half is returned to<space/><link><target>National Defence Headquarters</target></link><space/>with the member's personal documents, while the upper half remains on the body. The tags contain the following information:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.admfincs.forces.gc.ca/admfincs/subjects/cfao/026-04_e.asp'>Canadian Forces Administrative Order 26-4 Identity Discs</link><space/>Canadian Forces Finance &amp; Corporate Services website</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Upper half:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Service number#Canada</target><part>Service Number (SN)</part></link></listitem><listitem>Initials and surname</listitem><listitem>Religion (or &quot;NRE&quot; if none) and blood group with RH factor</listitem><listitem>The legend &quot;CDN FORCES CDN&quot; (or for foreign nationals, the name of the country the individual represents)</listitem><listitem>The text &quot;DO NOT REMOVE / NE PAS ENLEVER&quot; on the reverse</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Lower half: identical, except the reverse is blank.</listitem></list><paragraph>Before the Service Number was introduced in the 1990s, military personnel were identified on the I discs (as well as other documents) by their<space/><link><target>Social Insurance Number</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>China</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>People's Liberation Army</target></link><space/>issues two long, rectangular tags. All information are stamped in<space/><link><target>Simplified Chinese</target></link>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Full name</listitem><listitem>Gender</listitem><listitem>Date of birth</listitem><listitem><link><target>Resident Identity Card</target><part>RIC number</part></link></listitem><listitem>PLA's ID number</listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem><listitem>Branch</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Colombia</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>National Army of Colombia</target><part>Ejrcito Nacional de Colombia</part></link><space/>uses long, rectangular metal tags with oval ends tags stamped with the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Family Name</listitem><listitem>First Name</listitem><listitem>Military ID Number</listitem><listitem>Blood Type</listitem><listitem>Branch of Service</listitem></list><paragraph>Duplicate tags are issued. Often, tags are issued with a prayer inscribed on the reverse.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cyprus</heading><paragraph>In Cyprus, identification tags include the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>family name</target><part>Surname</part></link></listitem><listitem>First name</listitem><listitem>Service number (E.g., 11111/00/00B, where the first five digits are the ID, the second two are the year the soldier turned 18 years old, the last two digits are the year the soldier enlisted, and the letter is the enlistment group, either A or B)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blood Group</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Denmark</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>military of Denmark</target></link><space/>use dog tags that look like small metal plates.<space/><link><target>Image:Danish military dog tag armytags.co.uk.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Danish military dog tags</part></link><space/>The tag is designed to be broken into two pieces, and convey two copies of the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Personal identification number (Denmark)</target><part>Personal identification number</part></link></listitem><listitem>Surname</listitem><listitem>First name<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>On the right hand side of the tag is engraved<space/><italics>Danmark</italics>, the Danish word for &quot;Denmark&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.armytags.dk/tegn.php?id=0</extension>Starting in 1985, the individual's social security number (which is the same as his service number) is included on the tag. In the army, navy, and air force, the individual's blood type is indicated, while on national guard dog tags it is not. In 2009, Danish dog tag were discontinued for conscripts.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>East Germany</heading><paragraph>The Nationale Volksarmee used a tag nearly identical with that used by both the Wehrmacht and the West German Bundeswehr. The oval aluminum tag was stamped &quot;DDR&quot; (Deutsche Demokratische Republik) above the personal ID number; this information was repeated on the bottom half, which was intended to be broken off in case of death. Oddly, the tag was not worn, but required to be kept in a plastic sleeve in the back of the WDA identity booklet.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ecuador</heading><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Placas de identificacin de campaa</italics><space/>consists of two long, rectangular steel or aluminum tags with rounded corners and a single hole punched in one end. It is suspended by a US-type ball chain, with a shorter chain for the second tag. The information on the tag is:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Family Name &amp; First Name</listitem><listitem>Identification Number</listitem><listitem>Blood Group, plus &quot;RH&quot; and &quot;+&quot; or &quot;-&quot;</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Estonia</heading><paragraph>Estonian dog tags are designed to be broken in two. The dog tag is a metallic rounded rectangle suspended by a ball chain. Information consists of four fields:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>National</listitem><listitem>Nationality</listitem><listitem>Blood Group</listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem></list><paragraph>Example:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>39305231234</listitem><listitem>EN</listitem><listitem>A(II) Rh Pos (+)</listitem><listitem>NONE</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Finland</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Suomalainen tuntolevy.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Blank Finnish dog tag</part></link><link><target>Finnish Defence Forces</target><part>Finnish</part></link><space/>dog tags (sometimes called<space/><italics>raatolaatta</italics>; &quot;corpse plaque&quot;/&quot;corpse plate&quot;-) are also designed to be broken in two; however, the only text on it is the<space/><link><target>National identification number#Finland</target><part>personal identification number</part></link><space/>and the letters<space/><italics>SF</italics><space/>(rarely FI), which stands for Suomi Finland, within a<space/><link><target>Finnish Defence Forces</target><part>tower</part></link><space/>stamped atop of the upper half.</paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>France issues either a metallic rounded rectangle (army) or disk (navy), designed to be broken in half, bearing family name &amp; first name above the ID number.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Germany</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Erkennungsmarke BW.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Frontside of a German ID tag from 1961</part></link>German<space/><link><target>Bundeswehr</target></link><space/>ID tags are an oval-shaped disc designed to be broken in half. The two sides contain different information which are mirrored upside-down on the lower half of the ID tag. They feature the following information on segmented and numbered fields:</paragraph><paragraph>On the front</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Field 1: blank (provided for Gender but never used)</listitem><listitem>Field 2: DEU (for Deutschland) (GE (for Germany) only on older ID tags)</listitem><listitem>Field 3: Religious preference (&quot;K&quot; or &quot;RK&quot; for Roman Catholic, &quot;E&quot; or &quot;EV&quot; for Protestant, &quot;O&quot; for Christian Orthodox, &quot;ISL&quot; for Islamic, &quot;JD&quot; for Jewish, blank if no preference)</listitem><listitem>Field 4: Personenkennziffer (service number: birth date in DDMMYY format, dash, capitalized first letter of last name, dash, and five-digit number based on soldier's home military administrative district, number of persons with the mentioned last name initial and same birthday, and an error-checking number but without dashes), ex. 101281-S-455(-)6(-)8</listitem></list><paragraph>On the back</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Field 5: Blood group (A, AB, B, 0)</listitem><listitem>Field 6:<space/><link><target>Rhesus factor</target></link><space/>(Rh+ or Rh-)</listitem><listitem>Field 7: Vaccination status (&quot;T82&quot; for Tetanus and year of basic immunization)</listitem><listitem>Fields 8 10: blank</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Greece</heading><paragraph>In Greece, identification tags include the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>family name</target><part>Surname</part></link></listitem><listitem>First name</listitem><listitem>Service number (where date of birth is included as &quot;class&quot;)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blood Group</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Hungary</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Military of Hungary</target><part>Hungarian</part></link><space/>army dog tag is made out of steel, forming a 2535&amp;nbsp;mm tag designed to split diagonally. Both sides contain the same information: the soldier's personal identity code, blood group and the word HUNGARIA. Some may not have the blood group on them. These are only issued to soldiers who are serving outside of the country. If the soldier should die, one side is removed and kept for the army's official records, while the other side is left attached to the body.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Iraq</heading><paragraph>The Saddam-era Iraqi Army utilized a single, long, rectangular metal tag with oval ends, inscribed (usually by hand) with Name and Number or Unit, and occasionally Blood Type.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Israel</heading><paragraph><link><target>Israel Defense Forces</target><part>Israeli</part></link><space/>dog tags are designed to be broken in two. The information appears in three lines (twice):</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Army identification number (&quot;mispar ishi&quot;, literally: personal number. A seven-digit number that is different from the nine-digit<space/><link><target>Teudat Zehut</target><part>identification number</part></link><space/>for citizens).</listitem><listitem>Last name</listitem><listitem>First Name</listitem></list><paragraph>Another dog tag is kept inside the military boot in order to identify dead soldiers.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Originally the IDF issued two circular aluminum tags (1948 late 1950s) stamped in three lines with serial number, family name, and first name. The tags were threaded together through a single hole onto a cord worn around the neck.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Japan</heading><paragraph>Japan follows a similar system to the US Army for its Self Defence Force personnel, and the appearance of the tags is similar, although laser etched. The exact information order is as follows.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ground Self-Defense Force<list type='bullet'><listitem>JAPAN GSDF</listitem><listitem>First name, last name</listitem><listitem>Identification number</listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Maritime Self-Defense Force<list type='bullet'><listitem>First name, last name</listitem><listitem>Identification number</listitem><listitem>JAPAN MSDF</listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Japan Air Self-Defense Force<list type='bullet'><listitem>First name, last name</listitem><listitem>Identification number</listitem><listitem>JAPAN ASDF</listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Malaysia</heading><paragraph><link><target>Malaysian Armed Forces</target></link><space/>have two identical oval tags with this information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>National Registration Identity Card Number (Malaysia)</target><part>NRIC number</part></link><space/>(The last digit is an odd number for a male soldier, and an even number for a female soldier.)</listitem><listitem>Service number</listitem><listitem>Full name</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blood type</target></link></listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem><listitem>Branch (e.g.,<space/><link><target>Royal Malaysian Navy</target><part>TLDM</part></link>)</listitem></list><paragraph>If more information needed, another two oval wrist tags are provided. The term<space/><italics>wrist tags</italics><space/>can be used to refer to the<space/><link><target>bracelet</target></link>-like<space/><link><target>wristwatch</target></link>. The additional tags only need to be worn on the wrist, with the main tags still on the neck. All personnel are allowed to attach a small religious<space/><link><target>pendant</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>locket</target></link>; this makes a quick identifiable reference for their funeral services.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mexico</heading><paragraph>The Ejrcito de Mexico uses a single long, rectangular metal tag with oval ends, embossed with Name, serial number, and blood type plus Rh factor.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Netherlands</heading><paragraph><link><target>Military of the Netherlands</target></link><space/>identity tags, like the Canadian and Norwegian ones, are designed to be broken in two in case of a fatality; the lower end is returned to Dutch Defence Headquarters, while the upper half remains on the body. There is a difference in the Army and Airforce service number and the Navy service number:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Army number</target></link><space/>is made up of the date of birth in YY.MM.DD. format, for example 83.01.15, and a three-digit number, such as 123.</listitem><listitem>Navy number is made up out of random five- or six-digit numbers.</listitem></list><paragraph>The tags contain the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Upper half:<list type='bullet'><listitem>Name and family name</listitem><listitem>Service number</listitem><listitem>Nationality (NL) and religion</listitem><listitem>Blood group with<space/><link><target>Rhesus blood group system</target><part>RH</part></link><space/>factor</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Lower half: identical.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Norway</heading><paragraph><link><target>Norway</target><part>Norwegian</part></link><space/>dog tags are designed to be broken in two like the Canadian version:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The top half contains the nationality,<space/><link><target>National identification number#Norway</target><part>the eleven-digit birth number</part></link><space/>and the blood type.</listitem><listitem>The bottom half contains the nationality and birth number and has a hole so the broken-off half can be hung on a ring.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Poland</heading><paragraph>The first dog tags were issued in Poland following the order of the General Staff of December 12, 1920. The earliest design (dubbed<space/><italics>kapala</italics><space/>in Polish, more properly called &quot;kapsel legitymacyjny&quot; - meaning &quot;identification cap&quot;) consisted of a tin-made 3050&amp;nbsp;mm rectangular frame and a rectangular cap fitting into the frame. Soldiers' details were filled in a small ID card placed inside the frame, as well as on the inside of the frame itself. The dog tag was similar to the tags used by the<space/><link><target>Austro-Hungarian Army</target></link><space/>during<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. In case the soldier died, the frame was left with his body, while the lid was returned to his unit together with a note on his death. The ID card was handed over to the chaplain or the rabbi.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1928, a new type of dog tag was proposed by<space/><link><target>genera brygady</target><part>gen. bryg.</part></link><space/><link><target>Stanisaw Rouppert</target></link>, Poland's representative at the<space/><link><target>International Red Cross</target></link>. It was slightly modified and adopted in 1931 under the name of Niemiertelnik wz. 1931 (literally, Immortalizer mark 1931). The new design consisted of an oval piece of metal (ideally steel, but in most cases aluminum alloy was used), roughly 40 by 50 millimeters. There were two notches on both sides of the tag, as well as two rectangular holes in the middle to allow for easier breaking of the tag in two halves. The halves contained the same set of data and were identical, except the upper half had two holes for a string or twine to go through. The data stamped on the dog tag included:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Obverse<list type='bullet'><listitem>Name</listitem><listitem>Surname</listitem><listitem>Optionally: abbreviation of soldiers' religion (KAT for Roman Catholics, GR-KAT for Greek Catholics, PRAW for Orthodox, MOJ for Jewish, AUG for Lutherans, ANG for Anglicans and MAH for Muslims)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Reverse<list type='bullet'><listitem>Soldiers' ID card number and first letter of the<space/><link><target>powiat</target></link><space/>the soldier came from</listitem><listitem>Name of the Recruitment Commission (usually name of the town or city the soldier was attached to)</listitem><listitem>Year of birth</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Sometimes the rank of the soldier was added to the reverse, and most members of the medical corps had a tiny cross stamped near the string holes, regardless of their religion.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Rhodesia</heading><paragraph>The former Republic of Rhodesia used two WW2 British-style compressed asbestos fiber tags, a No. 1 octagonal (green) tag and a No. 2 circular (red) tag, stamped with identical information. The red tag was supposedly fireproof and the green tag rotproof. The following information was stamped on the tags: Number, Name, Initials, &amp; Religion; Blood Type was stamped on reverse. The air force and BSAP often stamped their service on the reverse side above the blood group.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many soldiers state they were issued blank tags and told to punch the information in themselves.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Russia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dog-tag-modern-russia.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>thumbnail</part><part>Russian dog tag</part></link>During the<space/><link><target>Great Patriotic War</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Red Army</target></link><space/>did not issue metal dog tags to its troops. They were issued small ebony cylinders containing a slip of paper with a soldier's s particulars written on it. These do not hold up as well as metal dog tags.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-25589709. Retrieved May 31, 2015.</extension><space/>Today the<space/><link><target>Armed Forces of the Russian Federation</target><part>Russian Armed Forces</part></link><space/>use metal oval tags. Russian dog tags contain the title &quot; &quot; (&quot;Armed Forces of Russia&quot;) and the alphanumeric individual numbers, as shown on the right.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Singapore</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Singapore Armed Forces</target></link>-issued dog tags are inscribed (not embossed) with up to four items:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>NRIC number</target></link></listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem><listitem>Drug allergies (if any; inscribed on the reverse)</listitem></list><paragraph>The dog tags consist of two metal pieces, one oval with two holes and one round with one hole. A synthetic lanyard is threaded through both holes in the oval piece and tied around the wearer's neck. The round piece is tied to the main loop on a shorter loop.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph>The former South African Defense Force used two long, rectangular aluminum tags with oval ends, stamped with serial number, name and initials, religion, and blood type.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Republic of Korea Army</target><part>South Korean Army</part></link><space/>issues two long, rectangular tags with oval ends, stamped (in Korean lettering) with &quot;Yuk-Gun&quot; (<link><target>English language</target><part>English</part></link>: Army) above a personal number, with the name below that and the blood group at the bottom.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Vietnam</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Army of the Republic of Vietnam</target><part>South Vietnamese Army</part></link><space/>used two American-style dog tags. Some tags added religion, e.g., Cng Gio for Catholic. They were stamped or inscribed with:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Name</listitem><listitem>SQ (S Qun, i.e., Service number) a 2-digit year number, followed by a military serial number</listitem><listitem>LM (loi mu, i.e., Blood Group, no rH factor)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Spain</heading><paragraph>Issues a single metal oval, worn vertically, stamped &quot;ESPAA&quot; above and below the 3-slot horizontal break line. It is stamped in 4 lines with:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>1st line Religion</listitem><listitem>2nd line left side = blood group, right side = any medical allergies (SI or NO)</listitem><listitem>3rd line military service (ET, EA ...)</listitem><listitem>4th (longest) line = DNI military number.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Sweden</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Swedogtag.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Swedish civilian dog tag (1970s)</part></link>Swedish dog tags are designed to be able to break apart. The information on them was prior to 2010:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Personal identity number (Sweden)</target><part>Personal identity number</part></link><space/>(twice, once in the upper part and once below)</listitem><listitem>Full name</listitem><listitem>Residence at birth</listitem><listitem>Blood type (only on some)</listitem></list><paragraph>Swedish dog tags issued to troops after 2010 are, for personal security reasons, only marked with personal identity number.</paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>dog tags were issued to everyone, often soon after birth, since the threat of total war also meant the risk of severe civilian casualties. However in 2010, the Swedish government decided that the dog tags were not needed anymore.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Switzerland</heading><paragraph><link><target>Swiss Armed Forces</target></link><space/>ID tag is an oval shaped non reflective plaque, containing the following information:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Social insurance number</listitem><listitem>Surname</listitem><listitem>First name</listitem><listitem>Date of birth in DD.MM.YY format</listitem></list><paragraph>On the back side the letters CH standing for (Confoederatio Helvetica) are engraved next to a Swiss cross.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Second World War British dog tag reverse side (RAF).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>World War II fiber disc type of dog tag</part></link><template><target>citation needed span</target><arg name="text">The [[British Armed Forces]] currently utilise two circular non-reflecting stainless steel tags engraved with the "Big 6"{{citation needed|date</arg><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>United States of America</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:US Dog Tag with Surname, First name, Social Security number, Blood type, Religion.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>An American dog tag showing the recipient's last name, first name, Social Security number, blood type, and religion.</part></link>In the 1990s, the U.S. Army stopped using the term<space/><italics>dog tags</italics>, replacing it with the designation<space/><italics>ID tags</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>A persistent rumor is that debossed (imprinted with stamped in letters) dog tags were issued from World War II till the end of the Vietnam War and that currently the U.S. Armed Forces is issuing embossed (imprinted with raised letters) dog tags. In actuality, the U.S. Armed Forces issues dog tags with both types of imprinting, depending on the machine used at a given facility. The military issued 95% of their identification tags up until recently (within the past 10 years) with debossed text.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.dogtagsrus.com/embossed-debossed.htm</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>United States Armed Forces</target><part>U.S. Armed Forces</part></link><space/>typically carry two identical oval dog tags containing:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Air Force</target><part>U.S. Air Force</part></link><space/>(Format 1)</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name, first name, middle initial<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">AFI 36-3103</arg><arg name="url">http://www.e-publishing.af.mil/shared/media/epubs/AFI36-3103.pdf</arg><arg name="date">1 May 1997</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Social Security number, followed by &quot;AF&quot; indicating branch of service<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>Blood Group<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>&quot;blank&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>Religion<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Air Force</target><part>U.S. Air Force</part></link><space/>(Format 2)</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>First name and middle initial<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>Social Security number, followed by &quot;AF&quot; indicating branch of service<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>Blood Group<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem><listitem>Religion<extension extension_name='ref' name="USAF"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target><part>U.S. Marine Corps</part></link></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name<extension extension_name='ref' name="USMC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">MCO P1070.12K</arg><arg name="url">http://web.archive.org/web/20080409095003/http://www.marines.mil/news/publications/Documents/MCO%20P1070.12K%20W%20CH%201.pdf</arg><arg name="date">14 July 2000</arg><arg name="author">United States Marine Corps</arg><arg name="publisher">United States Department of the Navy</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 April 2008</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>First and middle initials and suffix; blood group<extension extension_name='ref' name="USMC"></extension></listitem><listitem>Social Security number with three/two/four format as follows:123 45 6789<extension extension_name='ref' name="USMC"></extension></listitem><listitem>Branch (&quot;USMC&quot;); Gas mask size (S small, M medium, L large)<extension extension_name='ref' name="USMC"></extension></listitem><listitem>Religious preference, or medical allergy if red medical tag<extension extension_name='ref' name="USMC"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Navy</target><part>U.S. Navy</part></link></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name, first name, middle initial</listitem><listitem>Social Security number with no dashes or spaces followed immediately by &quot;USN&quot;, space, blood group</listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Army</target><part>U.S. Army</part></link></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name</listitem><listitem>First name, middle initial</listitem><listitem>Social Security number</listitem><listitem>Blood type</listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>United States Coast Guard</target><part>U.S. Coast Guard</part></link></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Last name, first name, middle initial</listitem><listitem>Social Security number, no dashes or spaces, followed immediately by branch (i.e., 123456789USCG)</listitem><listitem>Blood group</listitem><listitem>Religion</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Religious designation</heading><paragraph>During World War II, an American dog tag could indicate only one of three religions through the inclusion of one letter: &quot;P&quot; for Protestant, &quot;C&quot; for Catholic, or &quot;H&quot; for Jewish (from the word, &quot;Hebrew&quot;),<extension extension_name='ref' name="tags"><link type='external' href='http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq70-1.htm'>www.history.navy.mil</link>, retrieved May 30, 2011.</extension><space/>or (according to at least one source) &quot;NO&quot; to indicate no religious preference.<extension extension_name='ref' name="no"><link type='external' href='http://www.blitzkriegbaby.de/anc/anc3e.htm'>www.blitzkriegbaby.de</link>, retrieved May 30, 2011.</extension><space/>Army regulations (606-5) soon included X and Y in addition to P,C, and H: the X indicating any religion not included in the first three, and the Y indicating either no religion or a choice not to list religion.<extension extension_name='ref'>Non-commissioned officers guide, 4th edition, pg. 212.</extension>By the time of the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link>, some IDs spelled out the broad religious choices such as PROTESTANT and CATHOLIC, rather than using initials, and also began to show individual denominations such as &quot;METHODIST&quot; or &quot;BAPTIST.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="religions"><link type='external' href='http://www.mooremilitaria.com/dog_tags.htm'>www.mooremilitaria.com</link>, retrieved May 30, 2011.</extension><space/>Tags did vary by service, however, such as the use of &quot;CATH,&quot; not &quot;CATHOLIC&quot; on some Navy tags. For those with no religious affiliation and those who chose not to list an affiliation, either the space for religion was left blank or the words &quot;NO PREFERENCE&quot; or &quot;NO RELIGIOUS PREF&quot; were included.<extension extension_name='ref' name="religions"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although American dog tags include the recipient's religion as a way of ensuring that religious needs will be met, some personnel have them reissued without religious affiliation listedor keep two sets, one with the designation and one withoutout of fear that identification as a member of a particular religion could increase the danger to their welfare or their lives if they fell into enemy hands. Some Jewish personnel avoided flying over German lines during WWII with ID tags that indicated their religion, and some Jewish personnel avoid the religious designation today out of concern that they could be captured by extremists who are<space/><link><target>anti-Semitic</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="no"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jewishjournal.com/los_angeles/article/in_harms_way_20030321'>www.jewishjournal.com</link>, retrieved May 30, 2011.</extension><space/>Additionally, when American troops were first sent to<space/><link><target>Saudi Arabia</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Gulf War</target></link><space/>there were allegations that some U.S. military authorities were pressuring Jewish military personnel to avoid listing their religions on their ID tags.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ajcarchives.org/AJC_DATA/Files/1992_4_USCivicPolitical.pdf'>www.ajcarchives</link>, pages 178179, retrieved May 30, 2011.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Medical tattoo</target></link>, also known as a meat tag</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Dog tags (military identification)</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.historicfairfax.org/HFCI33.pdf'>&quot;A Battlefield Souvenir?&quot; The Story of a Union Identity Disk in the Civil War</link></listitem><listitem>Captain Richard W. Wooley.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.qmfound.com/short_history_of_identification_tags.htm'>&quot;A Short History of Identification Tags&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Quartermaster Professional Bulletin</italics>, December, 1988. Retrieved 12 September 2007.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://findthemia.blogspot.com/'>&quot;Evaluation of the WWII German ID tag system&quot; - Article on the weak points of WWII era German ID tags based on observations made during the recovery of missing soldiers.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://home.att.net/~steinert/us_army_ww2_dog_tags.htm'>A guide for Reenactors and Collectors</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mydogtag.com'>Dogtag Image Generator</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>US Army uniforms</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Dog Tag (Identifier)</target></template><link><target>Category:Personal identification documents</target></link><link><target>Category:Military life</target></link><link><target>Category:Militaria</target></link></paragraph></article>