<article title='Babe_Ruth'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the baseball player</arg></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><template><target>pp-semi</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><template><target>featured article</target></template><template><target>Infobox baseball biography</target><arg name="name">Babe Ruth
</arg><arg name="image">Babe Ruth2.jpg
</arg><arg name="width">256
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Ruth in his New York Yankees uniform, in 1920
</arg><arg name="position">[[Outfielder]] / [[Pitcher]]
</arg><arg name="bats">Left
</arg><arg name="throws">Left
</arg><arg name="birth_date">{{birth date|mf</arg><arg name="birth_place">[[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]]
</arg><arg name="death_date">{{death date and age|mf</arg><arg name="death_place">[[New York City]], [[New York]]
</arg><arg name="debutleague"><space/>MLB
</arg><arg name="debutdate">July 11
</arg><arg name="debutyear">1914
</arg><arg name="debutteam">Boston Red Sox
</arg><arg name="finalleague"><space/>MLB
</arg><arg name="finaldate">May 30
</arg><arg name="finalyear">1935
</arg><arg name="finalteam">Boston Braves
</arg><arg name="statleague"><space/>MLB
</arg><arg name="stat1label">[[Batting average]]
</arg><arg name="stat1value">.342
</arg><arg name="stat3label">[[Home run]]s
</arg><arg name="stat3value">714
</arg><arg name="stat2label">[[Hit (baseball)|Hits]]
</arg><arg name="stat2value">2,873
</arg><arg name="stat4label">[[Run batted in|Runs batted in]]
</arg><arg name="stat4value">2,213
</arg><arg name="stat5label">[[Win–loss record (pitching)|Win–loss record]]
</arg><arg name="stat5value">94–46
</arg><arg name="stat6label">[[Earned run average]]
</arg><arg name="stat6value">2.28
</arg><arg name="teams">
* [[Boston Red Sox]] ({{baseball year|1914}}–{{mlby|1919}})
* [[New York Yankees]] ({{mlby|1920}}–{{mlby|1934}})
* [[Atlanta Braves|Boston Braves]] ({{mlby|1935}})
</arg><arg name="highlights">
* 2× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] ([[1933 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1933]], [[1934 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1934]])
* 7× [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1915}}, {{wsy|1916}}, {{wsy|1918}}, {{wsy|1923}}, {{wsy|1927}}, {{wsy|1928}}, {{wsy|1932}})
* [[AL MVP]] (1923)
* [[List of Major League Baseball batting champions|AL batting champion]] (1924)
* 12× [[List of Major League Baseball annual home run leaders|AL home run leader]] (1918–1921, 1923, 1924, 1926–1931)
* 6× [[List of Major League Baseball annual runs-batted-in leaders|AL RBI leader]] (1919–1921, 1923, 1926, 1928)
* [[List of Major League Baseball annual ERA leaders|AL ERA leader]] (1916)
* [[New York Yankees#Retired numbers|New York Yankees #3]] retired
* [[Major League Baseball All-Century Team]]
* [[Major League Baseball All-Time Team]]
*[[List of career achievements by Babe Ruth|Other career achievements and records]]
</arg><arg name="hoflink"><space/>National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum
</arg><arg name="hoftype"><space/>National
</arg><arg name="hofdate">[[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 1936|1936]]
</arg><arg name="hofvote">95.13%
</arg></template><bold>George Herman</bold><space/>&quot;<bold>Babe</bold>&quot;<space/><bold>Ruth, Jr.</bold><space/>(February 6, 1895&amp;nbsp; August 16, 1948) was an American professional<space/><link><target>baseball</target></link><space/>player whose career in<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball</target></link><space/>(MLB) spanned 22&amp;nbsp;seasons, from 1914 through 1935. Nicknamed &quot;<bold>The Bambino</bold>&quot; and &quot;<bold>The Sultan of Swat</bold>&quot;, he began his MLB career as a stellar left-handed<space/><link><target>pitcher</target></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>Boston Red Sox</target></link>, but achieved his greatest fame as a slugging<space/><link><target>outfielder</target></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>New York Yankees</target></link>. Ruth established many MLB batting (and some pitching) records, including career<space/><link><target>home run</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(714),<space/><link><target>runs batted in</target></link><space/>(RBIs) (2,213),<space/><link><target>bases on balls</target></link><space/>(2,062),<space/><link><target>slugging percentage</target></link><space/>(.690), and<space/><link><target>on-base plus slugging</target></link><space/>(OPS) (1.164); the latter two still stand today.<extension extension_name='ref' name="99facts"></extension><space/>Ruth is regarded as one of the greatest sports heroes in<space/><link><target>Culture of the United States</target><part>American culture</part></link><space/>and is considered by many to be the greatest baseball player of all time. He was one of the first five inductees into the<space/><link><target>National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum</target><part>National Baseball Hall of Fame</part></link><space/>in 1936.</paragraph><paragraph>At age seven, Ruth was sent to<space/><link><target>Cardinal Gibbons School (Baltimore, Maryland)</target><part>St. Mary's Industrial School for Boys</part></link>, a reformatory where he learned life lessons and baseball skills from Brother Matthias Boutlier of the<space/><link><target>Institute of the Brothers of the Christian Schools</target><part>Christian Brothers</part></link>, the school's disciplinarian and a capable baseball player. In 1914, Ruth was signed to play<space/><link><target>Minor League Baseball</target><part>minor-league</part></link><space/>baseball for the<space/><link><target>Baltimore Orioles (minor league)</target><part>Baltimore Orioles</part></link><space/>but was soon sold to the Red Sox. By 1916, he had built a reputation as an outstanding pitcher who sometimes hit long home runs, a feat unusual for any player in the pre-1920<space/><link><target>dead-ball era</target></link>. Although Ruth twice<space/><link><target>Winloss record (pitching)</target><part>won</part></link><space/>23 games in a season as a pitcher and was a member of three<space/><link><target>World Series</target></link><space/>championship teams with Boston, he wanted to play every day and was allowed to convert to an outfielder. With regular playing time, he broke the<space/><link><target>List of Major League Baseball progressive single-season home run leaders</target><part>MLB single-season home run record</part></link><space/>in 1919.</paragraph><paragraph>After that season, Red Sox owner<space/><link><target>Harry Frazee</target></link><space/>controversially sold Ruth to the Yankees, an act that, coupled with Boston's subsequent championship drought, popularized the &quot;<link><target>Curse of the Bambino</target></link>&quot; superstition. In his 15 years with New York, Ruth helped the Yankees win seven<space/><link><target>List of American League pennant winners</target><part>American League (AL) championships</part></link><space/>and four World Series championships. His big swing led to escalating home run totals that not only drew fans to the ballpark and boosted the sport's popularity but also helped usher in the<space/><link><target>live-ball era</target></link><space/>of baseball, in which it evolved from a low-scoring game of strategy to a sport where the home run was a major factor. As part of the Yankees' vaunted &quot;<link><target>Murderer's Row</target></link>&quot; lineup of 1927, Ruth hit 60 home runs, extending his MLB single-season record. He retired in 1935 after a short stint with the<space/><link><target>Atlanta Braves</target><part>Boston Braves</part></link>. During his career, Ruth led the AL in home runs during a season twelve times.</paragraph><paragraph>Ruth's legendary power and charismatic personality made him a larger-than-life figure in the &quot;<link><target>Roaring Twenties</target></link>&quot;. During his career, he was the target of intense press and public attention for his baseball exploits and off-field penchants for drinking and womanizing. His often reckless lifestyle was tempered by his willingness to do good by visiting children at hospitals and orphanages. He was denied a job in baseball for most of his retirement, most likely due to poor behavior during parts of his playing career. In his final years, Ruth made many public appearances, especially in support of American efforts in<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>. In 1946, he became ill with cancer, and died two years later.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth Birthplace.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.1</part><part>Babe Ruth birthplace in Baltimore, Maryland</part></link>George Herman Ruth, Jr., was born in 1895 at 216 Emory Street in<space/><link><target>Pigtown, Baltimore</target><part>Pigtown</part></link>, a working class section of<space/><link><target>Baltimore</target></link>, Maryland, named for its meat packing plants. Its population included recent immigrants from Ireland, Germany and Italy, and African Americans. Ruth's parents, George Herman Ruth, Sr. (18711918), and Katherine Schamberger, were both of<space/><link><target>German American</target></link><space/>ancestry. According to the 1880 census, his parents John and Mary were born in Maryland. The paternal grandparents of Ruth, Sr. were from Prussia and Hanover, respectively. Ruth, Sr. had a series of jobs, including<space/><link><target>lightning rod</target></link><space/>salesman and<space/><link><target>streetcar</target></link><space/>operator, before becoming a counterman in a family-owned combination grocery and saloon on Frederick Street. George Ruth, Jr. was born in the house of his maternal grandfather, Pius Schamberger, a German immigrant and trade unionist.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 2425</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Smelser pp. 58</extension><space/>Only one of young George's seven siblings, his younger sister Mamie, survived infancy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Smelser, pp. 79</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many aspects of Ruth's childhood are undetermined, including the date of his parents' marriage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 11</extension><space/>When young George was a toddler, the family moved to 339 South Goodyear Street, not far from the rail yards; by the time the boy was six, his father had a saloon with an upstairs apartment at 426 West Camden Street. Details are equally scanty about why young George was sent at the age of seven to<space/><link><target>Cardinal Gibbons School (Baltimore, Maryland)</target><part>St. Mary's Industrial School for Boys</part></link>, a reformatory and orphanage. As an adult, Babe Ruth suggested that not only had he been running the streets and rarely attending school, he was drinking beer when his father was not looking. Some accounts say that, after a violent incident at his father's saloon, the city authorities decided this environment was unsuitable for a small child. At St. Mary's, which George Jr. entered on June 13, 1902, he was recorded as &quot;incorrigible&quot;; he spent much of the next twelve years there.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 1314</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 2931</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 811</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although St. Mary's inmates received an education, students were also expected to learn work skills and help operate the school, particularly once the boys turned 12. Ruth became a shirtmaker, and was also proficient as a carpenter. He would adjust his own shirt collars, rather than having a tailor do it, even during his well-paid baseball career. The boys, aged 5 to 21, did most work around the facility, from cooking to shoemaking, and renovated St. Mary's in 1912. The food was simple, and the<space/><link><target>Xaverian Brothers</target></link><space/>who ran the school insisted on strict discipline; corporal punishment was common. Ruth's nickname there was &quot;Niggerlips&quot;, as he had large facial features and was darker than most boys at the all-white reformatory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 1923</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth - St. Mary's Industrial School.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Ruth (top row, center) at St. Mary's Industrial School for Boys in Baltimore, Maryland, in 1912</part></link>Ruth was sometimes allowed to rejoin his family, or was placed at St. James's Home, a supervised residence with work in the community, but he was always returned to St. Mary's.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 3940</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 14</extension><space/>He rarely was visited by his family; his mother died when he was 12 and by some accounts, he was permitted to leave St. Mary's only to attend the funeral.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 32</extension><space/>How Ruth came to play baseball there is uncertain: according to one account, his placement at St. Mary's was due in part to repeatedly breaking Baltimore's windows with long<space/><link><target>hit (baseball)</target><part>hits</part></link><space/>while playing<space/><link><target>stickball</target><part>street ball</part></link>; by another, he was told to join a team on his first day at St. Mary's by the school's athletic director, Brother Herman, becoming a<space/><link><target>catcher</target></link><space/>even though left-handers rarely play that position. During his time there he also played<space/><link><target>third base</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>shortstop</target></link>, again unusual for a left-hander, and was forced to wear mitts and gloves made for right-handers. He was encouraged in his pursuits by the school's Prefect of Discipline, Brother Matthias Boutlier, a native of Nova Scotia. A large man, Brother Matthias was greatly respected by the boys both for his strength and for his fairness. For the rest of his life, Ruth would praise Brother Matthias, and his running and hitting styles closely resembled his teacher's.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 3537.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 2426</extension><space/>Ruth stated, &quot;I think I was born as a hitter the first day I ever saw him hit a baseball.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="c37">Creamer, p. 37</extension><space/>The older man became a mentor and role model to George; biographer<space/><link><target>Robert W. Creamer</target></link><space/>commented on the closeness between the two:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Ruth revered Brother Matthias&nbsp;... which is remarkable, considering that Matthias was in charge of making boys behave and that Ruth was one of the great natural misbehavers of all time.&nbsp;... George Ruth caught Brother Matthias' attention early, and the calm, considerable attention the big man gave the young hellraiser from the waterfront struck a spark of response in the boy's soul&nbsp;... [that may have] blunted a few of the more savage teeth in the gross man whom I have heard at least a half-dozen of his baseball contemporaries describe with admiring awe and wonder as "an animal."<ref name">"c37" />
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The school's influence remained with Ruth in other ways: a lifelong<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target><part>Catholic</part></link>, he would sometimes attend Mass after carousing all night, and he became a well-known member of the<space/><link><target>Knights of Columbus</target></link>. He would visit orphanages, schools, and hospitals throughout his life, often avoiding publicity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 22</extension><space/>He was generous to St. Mary's as he became famous and rich, donating money and his presence at fundraisers, and spending $5,000 to buy Brother Matthias a Cadillac in 1926subsequently replacing it when it was destroyed in an accident. Nevertheless, his biographer Leigh Montville suggests that many of the off-the-field excesses of Ruth's career were driven by the deprivations of his time at St. Mary's.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 2829</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most of the boys at St. Mary's played baseball, with organized leagues at different levels of proficiency. Ruth later estimated that he played 200 games a year as he steadily climbed the ladder of success. Although he played all positions at one time or another (including<space/><link><target>infield</target></link><space/>positions generally reserved for right-handers), he gained stardom as a<space/><link><target>pitcher</target></link>. According to Brother Matthias, Ruth was standing to one side laughing at the bumbling pitching efforts of fellow students, and Matthias told him to go in and see if he could do better. After becoming the best pitcher at St. Mary's, in 1913, when Ruth was 18, he was allowed to leave the premises to play weekend games on teams drawn from the community. He was mentioned in several newspaper articles, for both his pitching prowess and ability to hit long<space/><link><target>home run</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 2628</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 17</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Professional baseball</heading><heading level='3'>Minor league, Baltimore Orioles</heading><paragraph>In early 1914, Ruth was signed to a professional baseball contract by<space/><link><target>Jack Dunn (baseball)</target><part>Jack Dunn</part></link>, owner and manager of the<space/><link><target>Minor League Baseball</target><part>minor-league</part></link><space/><link><target>Baltimore Orioles (minor league)</target><part>Baltimore Orioles</part></link>, an<space/><link><target>International League</target></link><space/>team. The circumstances of Ruth's signing cannot be stated with certainty, with historical fact obscured by stories that cannot all be true. By some accounts, Dunn was urged to attend a game between an all-star team from St. Mary's and one from another Xaverian facility,<space/><link><target>Mount St. Mary's University</target><part>Mount St. Mary's College</part></link>. Some versions have Ruth running away before the eagerly awaited game, to return in time to be punished, and then pitching St. Mary's to victory as Dunn watched. Others have<space/><link><target>Washington Senators (1901-1960)</target><part>Washington Senators</part></link><space/>pitcher<space/><link><target>Joe Engel</target></link>, a Mount St. Mary's graduate, pitching in an alumni game after watching a preliminary contest between the college's freshmen and a team from St. Mary's, including Ruth. Engel watched Ruth play, then told Dunn about him at a chance meeting in Washington. Ruth, in his autobiography, stated only that he worked out for Dunn for a half-hour, and was signed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 4851</extension><space/>According to biographer Kal Wagenheim, there were legal difficulties to be straightened out as Ruth was supposed to remain at the school until he turned 21.<template><target>efn</target><arg>Ruth long thought his birthday was February 7, 1894. This was in fact the birthday of an elder brother of the same name, who died soon after birth. Ruth learned this when he needed a passport in 1934.</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 19.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:1914 Babe Ruth baseball card.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Baseball card</target></link><space/>depicting Ruth as a<space/><link><target>Baltimore Orioles (minor league)</target><part>Baltimore Oriole</part></link>, 1914</part></link>The train journey to spring training in<space/><link><target>Fayetteville, North Carolina</target></link>, in early March was likely Ruth's first outside the Baltimore area.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 2021</extension><space/>The rookie ballplayer was the subject of various pranks by the veterans, who were probably also the source of his famous nickname. There are various accounts of how Ruth came to be called Babe, but most center on his being referred to as &quot;Dunnie's babe&quot; or a variant. &quot;Babe&quot; was at that time a common nickname in baseball, with perhaps the most famous to that point being<space/><link><target>Pittsburgh Pirates</target></link><space/>pitcher and<space/><link><target>1909 World Series</target></link><space/>hero<space/><link><target>Babe Adams</target></link>, who appeared younger than he was.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 36</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 22</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Babe Ruth's first appearance as a professional ballplayer was in an intersquad game on March 7, 1914. Ruth played shortstop, and pitched the last two<space/><link><target>Inning (baseball)</target><part>inning</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of a 159 victory. In his second at bat, Ruth hit a long home run to right, which was reported locally to be longer than a legendary shot hit in Fayetteville by<space/><link><target>Jim Thorpe</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 6162</extension><space/>His first appearance against a team in<space/><link><target>organized baseball</target></link><space/>was an exhibition against the major-league<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Phillies</target></link>: Ruth pitched the middle three innings, giving up two runs in the fourth, but then settling down and pitching a scoreless fifth and sixth. The following afternoon, Ruth was put in during the sixth inning against the Phillies and did not allow a run the rest of the way. The Orioles scored seven runs in the bottom of the eighth to overcome a 60 deficit, making Ruth the winning pitcher.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 6667</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Once the regular season began, Ruth was a star pitcher who was also dangerous at the plate. The team performed well, yet received almost no attention from the Baltimore press. A third major league, the<space/><link><target>Federal League</target></link>, had begun play, and the local franchise, the<space/><link><target>Baltimore Terrapins</target></link>, restored that city to the major leagues for the first time since 1902. Few fans visited<space/><link><target>Oriole Park</target></link>, where Ruth and his teammates labored in relative obscurity. Ruth may have been offered a bonus and a larger salary to jump to the Terrapins; when rumors to that effect swept Baltimore, giving Ruth the most publicity he had experienced to date, a Terrapins official denied it, stating it was their policy not to sign players under contract to Dunn.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 7277</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 3840</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The competition from the Terrapins caused Dunn to sustain large losses. Although by late June the Orioles were in first place, having won over two-thirds of their games, the paid attendance dropped as low as 150. Dunn explored a possible move by the Orioles to<space/><link><target>Richmond, Virginia</target></link>, as well as the sale of a minority interest in the club. These possibilities fell through, leaving Dunn with little choice other than to sell his best players to major league teams to raise money.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 7880.</extension><space/>He offered Ruth to the reigning<space/><link><target>World Series</target></link><space/>champions,<space/><link><target>Connie Mack (baseball)</target><part>Connie Mack's</part></link><space/><link><target>Philadelphia Athletics</target></link>, but Mack had his own financial problems.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 26.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Cincinnati Reds</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>New York Giants</target></link><space/>expressed interest in Ruth, but Dunn sold his contract, along with those of pitchers<space/><link><target>Ernie Shore</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ben Egan</target></link>, to the<space/><link><target>Boston Red Sox</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>American League</target></link><space/>(AL) on July 4. The sale price was announced as $25,000 but other reports lower the amount to half that, or possibly $8,500 plus the cancellation of a $3,000 loan. Ruth remained with the Orioles for several days while the Red Sox completed a road trip, and reported to the team in Boston on July 11.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 4041.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>MLB, Boston Red Sox (191419)</heading><heading level='4'>Developing star</heading><paragraph>Ruth arrived in Boston on July 11, 1914, along with Egan and Shore. Ruth later told of meeting the woman he would first marry, Helen Woodford, that morningshe was then a 16-year-old waitress at Landers Coffee Shop, and Ruth related that she served him when he had breakfast there. Other stories, though, suggest the meeting happened on another day, and perhaps under other circumstances. Regardless of when he began to woo his first wife, he won his first game for the Red Sox that afternoon, he won his first game for the Red Sox, 43, over the<space/><link><target>Cleveland Indians</target><part>Cleveland Naps</part></link>. He pitched to catcher<space/><link><target>Bill Carrigan</target></link>, who was also the Red Sox manager. Shore was given a<space/><link><target>Starting pitcher</target><part>start</part></link><space/>by Carrigan the next day; he won that and his second start and thereafter was pitched regularly. Ruth lost his second start, and was thereafter little used.<extension extension_name='ref' name="debut"></extension><space/>As a batter, in his major-league debut, Ruth went<space/><link><target>batting average</target><part>0-for-2</part></link><space/>against left-hander<space/><link><target>Willie Mitchell (baseball)</target><part>Willie Mitchell</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Strikeout</target><part>striking out</part></link><space/>in his first<space/><link><target>at bat</target></link>, before being removed for a<space/><link><target>pinch hitter</target></link><space/>in the seventh inning.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 87</extension><space/>Ruth was not much noticed by the fans, as Bostonians watched the Red Sox's crosstown rivals, the<space/><link><target>Boston Braves (baseball)</target><part>Braves</part></link>, begin<space/><link><target>1914 Boston Braves season</target><part>a legendary comeback</part></link><space/>that would take them from last place on the Fourth of July to the<space/><link><target>1914 World Series</target></link><space/>championship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="debut">Montville, pp. 4144</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth Boston pitching.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ruth pitching for Boston</part></link>Egan was traded to Cleveland after two weeks on the Boston roster. During his time as a Red Sox, he kept an eye on the inexperienced Ruth, much as Dunn had in Baltimore. When he was traded, no one took his place as supervisor. Ruth's new teammates considered him brash, and would have preferred him, as a rookie, to remain quiet and inconspicuous. When Ruth insisted on taking batting practice despite his being both a rookie who did not play regularly, and a pitcher, he arrived to find his bats sawn in half. His teammates nicknamed him &quot;the Big Baboon&quot;, a name the swarthy Ruth, who had disliked the nickname &quot;Niggerlips&quot; at St. Mary's, detested.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 4344</extension><space/>Ruth had received a raise on promotion to the major leagues, and quickly acquired tastes for fine food, liquor, and women, among other temptations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 2729</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 5255</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Manager Carrigan allowed Ruth to pitch two<space/><link><target>exhibition game</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in mid-August. Although Ruth won both against minor-league competition, he was not restored to the pitching rotation. It is uncertain why Carrigan did not give Ruth additional opportunities to pitch. There are legendsfilmed for the screen in<space/><italics><link><target>The Babe Ruth Story</target></link></italics><space/>(1948)that the young pitcher had a habit of signaling his intent to throw a<space/><link><target>curveball</target></link><space/>by sticking out his tongue slightly, and that he was easy to hit until this changed. Creamer pointed out that it is common for inexperienced pitchers to display such habits, and the need to break Ruth of his would not constitute a reason to not use him at all. The biographer suggested that Carrigan was unwilling to use Ruth due to poor behavior by the rookie.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 8990</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On July 30, 1914, Boston owner<space/><link><target>Joseph Lannin</target></link><space/>had purchased the minor-league<space/><link><target>Providence Grays (minor league)</target><part>Providence Grays</part></link>, members of the International League.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 44</extension><space/>The Providence team had been owned by several people associated with the<space/><link><target>Detroit Tigers</target></link>, including star hitter<space/><link><target>Ty Cobb</target></link>, and as part of the transaction, a Providence pitcher was sent to the Tigers. To soothe Providence fans upset at losing a star, Lannin announced that the Red Sox would soon send a replacement to the Grays. This was intended to be Ruth, but his departure for Providence was delayed when Cincinnati Reds owner<space/><link><target>Garry Herrmann</target></link><space/><link><target>Waivers (MLB)</target><part>claimed him off waivers</part></link>. After Lannin wrote to Herrmann explaining that the Red Sox wanted Ruth in Providence so he could develop as a player, and would not release him to a major league club, Herrmann allowed Ruth to be sent to the minors. Carrigan later stated that Ruth was not sent down to Providence to make him a better player, but to help the Grays win the International League<space/><link><target>pennant (sports)</target><part>pennant</part></link><space/>(league championship).<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 9293</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth joined the Grays on August 18, 1914. What was left of the Baltimore Orioles after Dunn's deals had managed to hold on to first place until August 15, after which they continued to fade, leaving the pennant race between Providence and<space/><link><target>Rochester Red Wings</target><part>Rochester</part></link>. Ruth was deeply impressed by Providence manager<space/><link><target>Bill Donovan</target><part>&quot;Wild Bill&quot; Donovan</part></link>, previously a star pitcher with a 254<space/><link><target>Winloss record (pitching)</target><part>winloss record</part></link><space/>for Detroit in 1907; in later years, he credited Donovan with teaching him much about pitching. Ruth was called upon often to pitch, in one stretch starting (and winning) four games in eight days. On September 5 in Toronto, Ruth pitched a one-hit 90 victory, and hit his first professional home run, his only one as a minor leaguer, off<space/><link><target>Ellis Johnson (baseball)</target><part>Ellis Johnson</part></link>. Recalled to Boston after Providence finished the season in first place, he pitched and won a game for the Red Sox against the<space/><link><target>New York Yankees</target></link><space/>on October 2, getting his first major league hit, a<space/><link><target>double (baseball)</target><part>double</part></link>. Ruth finished the season with a record of 21 as a major leaguer and 238 in the International League (for Baltimore and Providence). Once the season concluded, Ruth married Helen in<space/><link><target>Ellicott City, Maryland</target></link>. Creamer speculated that they did not marry in Baltimore, where the newlyweds boarded with George Ruth, Sr., to avoid possible interference from those at St. Mary'sboth bride and groom were not yet of age<extension extension_name='ref' name="99facts"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 99100</extension><space/>and Ruth remained on parole from that institution until his 21st birthday.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 103</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth reported to his first major league<space/><link><target>spring training</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Hot Springs, Arkansas</target></link>, in March 1915. Despite a relatively successful first season, he was not slated to start regularly for the Red Sox, who had two stellar left-handed pitchers already: the established stars<space/><link><target>Dutch Leonard (left-handed pitcher)</target><part>Dutch Leonard</part></link>, who had broken the record for the lowest<space/><link><target>earned run average</target></link><space/>(ERA) in a single season; and<space/><link><target>Ray Collins (baseball)</target><part>Ray Collins</part></link>, a 20-game winner in both 1913 and 1914. Ruth was ineffective in his first start, taking the loss in the third game of the season. Injuries and ineffective pitching by other Boston pitchers gave Ruth another chance, and after some good<space/><link><target>relief pitcher</target><part>relief</part></link><space/>appearances, Carrigan allowed Ruth another start, and he won a rain-shortened seven inning game. Ten days later, the manager had him start against the New York Yankees at the<space/><link><target>Polo Grounds</target></link>. Ruth took a 32 lead into the ninth, but lost the game 43 in 13 innings. Ruth, hitting ninth as was customary for pitchers, hit a massive home run into the upper deck in<space/><link><target>right fielder</target><part>right field</part></link><space/>off of<space/><link><target>Jack Warhop</target></link>. At the time, home runs were rare in baseball, and Ruth's majestic shot awed the crowd. The winning pitcher, Warhop, would in August 1915 conclude a major league career of eight seasons, undistinguished but for being the first major league pitcher to give up a home run to Babe Ruth.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 106</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Carrigan was sufficiently impressed by Ruth's pitching to give him a spot in the starting rotation. Ruth finished the 1915 season 188 as a pitcher; as a hitter, he batted .315 and had four home runs. The Red Sox won the<space/><link><target>List of American League pennant winners</target><part>AL pennant</part></link>, but with the pitching staff healthy, Ruth was not called upon to pitch in the<space/><link><target>1915 World Series</target></link><space/>against the Philadelphia Phillies. Boston won in five games; Ruth was used as a pinch hitter in Game Five, but<space/><link><target>Ground out (baseball)</target><part>grounded out</part></link><space/>against Phillies ace<space/><link><target>Grover Cleveland Alexander</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 5052</extension><space/>Despite his success as a pitcher, Ruth was acquiring a reputation for long home runs; at<space/><link><target>Sportsman's Park</target></link><space/>against the<space/><link><target>St. Louis Browns</target></link>, a Ruth hit soared over Grand Avenue, breaking the window of a<space/><link><target>Chevrolet</target></link><space/>dealership.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 33</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1916, there was attention focused on Ruth for his pitching, as he engaged in repeated pitching duels with the ace of the Washington Senators,<space/><link><target>Walter Johnson</target></link>. The two met five times during the season, with Ruth winning four and Johnson one (Ruth had a<space/><link><target>Winloss record (pitching)</target><part>no decision</part></link><space/>in Johnson's victory). Two of Ruth's victories were by the score of 10, one in a 13-inning game. Of the 10<space/><link><target>Shutouts in baseball</target><part>shutout</part></link><space/>decided without extra innings, AL President<space/><link><target>Ban Johnson</target></link><space/>stated, &quot;That was one of the best ball games I have ever seen.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 5657</extension><space/>For the season, Ruth went 2312, with a 1.75 ERA and nine shutouts, both of which led the league.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 55.</extension><space/>Ruth's nine shutouts in 1916 set a league record for left-handers that would remain unmatched until<space/><link><target>Ron Guidry</target></link><space/>tied it in 1978.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Schlueter</arg><arg name="first">Roger</arg><arg name="title">Verlander's 2011 was epic</arg><arg name="publisher">MLB.com</arg><arg name="url">http://mlb.mlb.com/news/print.jsp?ymd</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 20, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The Red Sox won the pennant and<space/><link><target>1916 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link><space/>again, this time defeating the<space/><link><target>Brooklyn Dodgers</target><part>Brooklyn Superbas</part></link><space/>(as the Dodgers were then known) in five games. Ruth started and won Game 2, 21, in 14 innings. Until another game of that length was played in<space/><link><target>2005 World Series</target><part>2005</part></link>, this was the longest World Series game, and Ruth's pitching performance is still the longest postseason<space/><link><target>complete game</target></link><space/>victory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="99facts"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Corcoran</arg><arg name="first">Cliff</arg><arg name="url">http://mlb.si.com/2013/07/11/99-cool-facts-about-babe-ruth/</arg><arg name="date">July 11, 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 20, 2014</arg><arg name="title">99 cool facts about Babe Ruth</arg><arg name="work">[[Sports Illustrated]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Berg</arg><arg name="first">Ted</arg><arg name="url">http://ftw.usatoday.com/2013/10/12-longest-games-in-mlb-postseason-history/</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 20, 2014</arg><arg name="title">12 longest games in MLB postseason history</arg><arg name="work">[[USA Today]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 38</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Carrigan retired as player and manager after 1916, returning to his native Maine to be a businessman. Ruth, who played under four managers who are in the<space/><link><target>National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum</target><part>National Baseball Hall of Fame</part></link>, always maintained that Carrigan, who is not enshrined there, was the best skipper he ever played for.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 33, 85</extension><space/>There were other changes in the Red Sox organization that offseason, as Lannin sold the team to a three-man group headed by New York theatrical promoter<space/><link><target>Harry Frazee</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 133</extension><space/><link><target>Jack Barry (baseball)</target><part>Jack Barry</part></link><space/>was hired by Frazee as manager.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 134</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Emergence as a hitter</heading><paragraph>Ruth went 2413 with a 2.01 ERA and six shutouts in 1917, but the Sox finished in second place in the league, nine<space/><link><target>games behind</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Chicago White Sox</target></link><space/>in the standings. On June 23 at Washington, Ruth made a memorable pitching start. When the home plate umpire called the first four pitches as balls, Ruth threw a punch at him, and was ejected from the game and later suspended for ten days. Ernie Shore was called in to relieve Ruth, and was allowed eight warm-up pitches. The runner who had reached base on the<space/><link><target>base on balls</target><part>walk</part></link><space/>was<space/><link><target>caught stealing</target></link>, and Shore retired all 26 batters he faced to win the game. Shore's feat was listed as a<space/><link><target>perfect game</target></link><space/>for many years;<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 138140</extension><space/>in 1991,<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball</target></link>'s (MLB) Committee on Statistical Accuracy caused it to be listed as a combined<space/><link><target>no-hitter</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 59</extension><space/>In 1917, Ruth was used little as a batter, other than his<space/><link><target>plate appearance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>while pitching, and hit .325 with two home runs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats">Wagenheim, pp. 273274</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth Red Sox 1918.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ruth in 1918, his penultimate year with the Red Sox</part></link>The entry of the United States into World War I occurred at the start of the season, and overshadowed the sport. Conscription was introduced in September 1917, and most baseball players in the big leagues were of draft age. This included Barry, who was a player-manager, and who joined the<space/><link><target>United States Naval Reserve</target><part>Naval Reserve</part></link><space/>in an attempt to avoid the draft, only to be called up after the 1917 season. Frazee hired International League President<space/><link><target>Ed Barrow</target></link><space/>as Red Sox manager. Barrow had spent the previous 30 years in a variety of baseball jobs, though he never played the game professionally. With the major leagues shorthanded due to the war, Barrow had many holes in the Red Sox lineup to fill.<extension extension_name='ref' name="m67plus"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth also noticed these vacancies in the lineup, and, dissatisfied in the role of a pitcher who appeared every four or five days, wanted to play every day at another position. Barrow tried Ruth at<space/><link><target>first baseman</target><part>first base</part></link><space/>and in the<space/><link><target>outfield</target></link><space/>during the exhibition season, but as the team moved towards Boston and the season opener, restricted him to pitching. At the time, Ruth was possibly the best left-handed pitcher in baseball; allowing him to play another position was an experiment that could have backfired.<extension extension_name='ref' name="m67plus"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Inexperienced as a manager, Barrow had player<space/><link><target>Harry Hooper</target></link><space/>advise him on baseball game strategy. Hooper urged his manager to allow Ruth to play another position when he was not pitching,<extension extension_name='ref' name="m67plus"></extension><space/>arguing to Barrow, who had invested in the club, that the crowds were larger on days when Ruth played, as they were attracted by his hitting.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c153">Creamer, p. 153</extension><space/>Barrow gave in early in May; Ruth promptly hit home runs in four consecutive games (one an exhibition), the last off of Walter Johnson.<extension extension_name='ref' name="m67plus">Montville, pp. 6769</extension><space/>For the first time in his career (disregarding pinch-hitting appearances), Ruth was allowed a place in the<space/><link><target>Batting order (baseball)</target><part>batting order</part></link><space/>higher than ninth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c153"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Barrow predicted that Ruth would beg to return to pitching the first time he experienced a batting slump, that did not occur. Barrow used Ruth primarily as an outfielder in the war-shortened 1918 season. Ruth hit .300, with 11 home runs, enough to secure him a share of the<space/><link><target>List of Major League Baseball home run champions</target><part>major league home run title</part></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Tillie Walker</target></link><space/>of the Philadelphia Athletics. He was still occasionally used as a pitcher, and had a 137 record with a 2.22 ERA.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 42</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 153170</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Red Sox won their third pennant in four years, and faced the<space/><link><target>Chicago Cubs</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>1918 World Series</target></link>, beginning on September 5, the earliest in history. The season was shortened as the government had ruled that baseball players eligible for the military would have to be inducted or work in critical war industries, such as armaments plants. Ruth pitched Game One for the Red Sox, a 10 shutout. Before Game Four, Ruth injured his left hand in a fight; he pitched anyway. He gave up seven hits and six walks, but was helped by outstanding fielding behind him and by his own batting efforts, as a fourth-inning<space/><link><target>Triple (baseball)</target><part>triple</part></link><space/>by Ruth gave his team a 20 lead. The Cubs tied the game in the eighth inning, but the Red Sox scored to take a 32 again in the bottom of that inning. After Ruth gave up a hit and a walk to start the ninth inning, he was relieved on the mound by<space/><link><target>Bullet Joe Bush</target><part>Joe Bush</part></link>. To keep Ruth and his bat in the game, he was sent to play<space/><link><target>left fielder</target><part>left field</part></link>. Bush retired the side to give Ruth his second win of the Series, and the third and last World Series pitching victory of his career, against no defeats, in three pitching appearances. Ruth's effort gave his team a three-games-to-one lead, and two days later the Red Sox won their third Series in four years, four games to two. Before allowing the Cubs to score in Game Four, Ruth pitched<space/><template><target>frac</target><arg>29</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>3</arg></template><space/>consecutive scoreless innings, a record for the World Series that stood for more than 40 years until 1961, broken by<space/><link><target>Whitey Ford</target></link><space/>after Ruth's death. Ruth was prouder of that record than he was of any of his batting feats.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 170181</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth by Bain, 1919.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Ruth in 1919</part></link>With the World Series over, Ruth gained exemption from the war draft by accepting a nominal position with a Pennsylvania steel mill. Many industrial establishments took pride in their baseball teams and sought to hire major leaguers. The end of the war in November set Ruth free to play baseball without such contrivances.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 7880</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the 1919 season, Ruth pitched in only 17 of his 130 games,<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>compiling an 85 record as Barrow used him as a pitcher mostly in the early part of the season, when the Red Sox manager still had hopes of a second consecutive pennant. By late June, the Red Sox were clearly out of the race, and Barrow had no objection to Ruth concentrating on his hitting, if only because it drew people to the ballpark. Ruth had hit a home run against the Yankees on Opening Day, and another during a month-long batting slump that soon followed. Relieved of his pitching duties, Ruth began an unprecedented spell of slugging home runs, which gave him widespread public and press attention. Even his failures were seen as majesticone sportswriter noted, &quot;When Ruth misses a swipe at the ball, the stands quiver&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 196197</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Two home runs by Ruth on July 5, and one in each of two consecutive games a week later, raised his season total to 11, tying his career best from 1918. The first record to fall was the AL single-season mark of 16, set by<space/><link><target>Socks Seybold</target><part>Ralph &quot;Socks&quot; Seybold</part></link><space/>in 1902. Ruth matched that on July 29, then pulled ahead toward the<space/><link><target>List of Major League Baseball progressive single-season home run leaders</target><part>major league record</part></link><space/>of 24, set by<space/><link><target>Buck Freeman</target></link><space/>in 1899. Ruth reached this on September 8, by which time, writers had discovered that<space/><link><target>Ned Williamson</target></link><space/>of the 1884<space/><link><target>Chicago Cubs</target><part>Chicago White Stockings</part></link><space/>had hit 27though in a ballpark where the distance to right field was only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>215</arg><arg>ft</arg></template>. On September 20, &quot;Babe Ruth Day&quot; at Fenway Park, Ruth won the game with a home run in the bottom of the ninth inning, tying Williamson. He broke the record four days later against the Yankees at the Polo Grounds, and hit one more against the Senators to finish with 29. The home run at Washington made Ruth the first major league player to hit a home run at all eight ballparks in his league. In spite of Ruth's hitting heroics, the Red Sox finished sixth,<space/><template><target>frac</target><arg>20</arg><arg>1</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>games behind the league champion White Sox.<template><target>efn</target><arg>The American League had eight teams from 1901 to 1960.</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 8890</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 203</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sale to New York</heading><paragraph>As an out-of-towner from New York City, Frazee had been regarded with suspicion by Boston's sportswriters and baseball fans when he bought the team. He won them over with success on the field and a willingness to build the Red Sox by purchasing or trading for players. He offered the Senators $60,000 for Walter Johnson, but Washington owner<space/><link><target>Clark Griffith</target></link><space/>was unwilling. Even so, Frazee was successful in bringing other players to Boston, especially as replacements for players in the military. This willingness to spend for players helped the Red Sox secure the 1918 title.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. 45</extension><space/>The 1919 season saw record-breaking attendance, and Ruth's home runs for Boston made him a national sensation. Nevertheless, on December 26, 1919, Frazee sold Ruth's contract to the New York Yankees.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 204205</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth by Paul Thompson, 1920.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ruth as a Yankee in 1920</part></link>Not all of the circumstances concerning the sale are known, but brewer and former congressman<space/><link><target>Jacob Ruppert</target></link>, the New York team's principal owner, reportedly asked Yankee manager<space/><link><target>Miller Huggins</target></link><space/>what the team needed to be successful. &quot;Get Ruth from Boston&quot;, Huggins supposedly replied, noting that Frazee was perennially in need of money to finance his theatrical productions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. 23</extension><space/>In any event, there was precedent for the Ruth transaction: when Boston pitcher<space/><link><target>Carl Mays</target></link><space/>left the Red Sox in a 1919 dispute, Frazee had settled the matter by selling Mays to the Yankees, though over the opposition of AL President Johnson.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to one of Ruth's biographers, Jim Reisler, &quot;why Frazee needed cash in 1919and large infusions of it quicklyis still, more than 80 years later, a bit of a mystery&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r5"></extension><space/>The often-told story is that Frazee needed money to finance the musical<space/><italics><link><target>No, No, Nanette</target></link></italics>, which was a Broadway hit and brought Frazee financial security. That play did not open until 1925, however, by which time Frazee had sold the Red Sox.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c20"></extension><space/>Still, the story may be true in essence:<space/><italics>No, No, Nanette</italics><space/>was based on a Frazee-produced play,<space/><italics>My Lady Friends</italics>, which opened in 1919.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 101102</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There were other financial pressures on Frazee, despite his team's success. Ruth, fully aware of baseball's popularity and his role in it, wanted to renegotiate his contract, signed before the 1919 season for $10,000 per year through 1921. He demanded that his salary be doubled, or he would sit out the season and cash in on his popularity through other ventures.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c20">Creamer, p. 20</extension><space/>Ruth's salary demands were causing other players to ask for more money.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 83</extension><space/>Additionally, Frazee still owed Lannin as much as $125,000 from the purchase of the club.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r5">Reisler, p. 5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Ruppert and his co-owner, Colonel<space/><link><target>Tillinghast L'Hommedieu Huston</target><part>Tillinghast Huston</part></link>, were both wealthy, and had aggressively purchased and traded for players in 1918 and 1919 to build a winning team, Ruppert faced losses in his brewing interests as<space/><link><target>Prohibition in the United States</target><part>Prohibition</part></link><space/>was implemented, and if their team left the Polo Grounds, where the Yankees were the tenants of the New York Giants, building a stadium in New York would be expensive. Nevertheless, when Frazee, who moved in the same social circles as Huston, hinted to the colonel that Ruth was available for the right price, the Yankees owners quickly pursued the purchase.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 205207</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Frazee sold the rights to Babe Ruth for $100,000, the largest sum ever paid for a baseball player. The deal also involved a $350,000 loan from Ruppert to Frazee, secured by a mortgage on Fenway Park. Once it was agreed, Frazee informed Barrow, who, stunned, told the owner that he was getting the worse end of the bargain.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 1</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="creamer208plus">Creamer, pp. 208209</extension><space/>Cynics have suggested that Barrow may have played a larger role in the Ruth sale, as less than a year after, he became the Yankee general manager, and in the following years made a number of purchases of Red Sox players from Frazee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r2">Reisler, p. 2</extension><space/>The $100,000 price included $25,000 in cash, and notes for the same amount due November 1 in 1920, 1921, and 1922; Ruppert and Huston assisted Frazee in selling the notes to banks for immediate cash.<extension extension_name='ref' name="creamer208plus"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The transaction was contingent on Ruth signing a new contract, which was quickly accomplishedRuth agreed to fulfill the remaining two years on his contract, but was given a $20,000 bonus, payable over two seasons. The deal was announced on January 6, 1920. Reaction in Boston was mixed: some fans were embittered at the loss of Ruth; others conceded that the slugger had become difficult to deal with.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 8688</extension><space/><italics>The New York Times</italics><space/>suggested presciently, &quot;The short right field wall at the Polo Grounds should prove an easy target for Ruth next season and, playing seventy-seven games at home, it would not be surprising if Ruth surpassed his home run record of twenty-nine circuit clouts next Summer.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Year1920"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Ruth Bought By New York Americans For $125,000, Highest Price in Baseball Annals</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="date">January 6, 1920</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res</arg></template></extension><space/>According to Reisler, &quot;The Yankees had pulled off the sports steal of the century.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="r2"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Marty Appel in his history of the Yankees, the transaction, &quot;changed the fortunes of two high-profile franchises for decades&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, p. 94</extension><space/>The Red Sox, winners of five of the first sixteen World Series, those played between 1903 and 1919,<template><target>efn</target><arg>There was no World Series in 1904 or 1994.</arg></template><space/>would not win another pennant until 1946, or another World Series until<space/><link><target>2004 World Series</target><part>2004</part></link>, a drought attributed in baseball superstition to Frazee's sale of Ruth and sometimes dubbed the &quot;<link><target>Curse of the Bambino</target></link>&quot;. The Yankees, on the other hand, had not won the AL championship prior to their acquisition of Ruth. They won seven AL pennants and four World Series with Ruth, and lead baseball with 40 pennants and 27 World Series titles in their history.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, pp. 9697</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="wsoutcome"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/history/postseason/mlb_ws.jsp?feature</arg><arg name="title">Results and recaps</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Major League Baseball]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 25, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>New York Yankees (192034)</heading><heading level='4'>Initial success (192023)</heading><paragraph>As a Yankee, Ruth's transition from a pitcher to a power-hitting outfielder became complete. In his fifteen-season Yankee career, consisting of over 2,000 games, Ruth broke many batting records, while making only five widely scattered appearances on the mound, winning all of them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the end of April 1920, the Yankees were 47, with the Red Sox leading the league with a 102 mark. Ruth had done little, having injured himself swinging the bat.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 90</extension><space/>Both situations began to change on May 1, when Ruth hit a ball completely out of the Polo Grounds, a feat believed only to have been previously accomplished by<space/><link><target>Shoeless Joe Jackson</target><part>Joe Jackson</part></link>. The Yankees won, 60, taking three out of four from the Red Sox.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. 7475</extension><space/>Ruth hit his second home run on May 2, and by the end of the month had set a major league record for home runs in a month with 11, and promptly broke it with 13 in June.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 112113</extension><space/>Fans responded with record attendance: on May 16, Ruth and the Yankees drew 38,600 to the Polo Grounds, a record for the ballpark, and 15,000 fans were turned away. Large crowds jammed stadiums to see Ruth play when the Yankees were on the road.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 225</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Harding Cox and Ruth.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>&quot;How Does He Do It?&quot; In this<space/><link><target>Clifford Berryman</target></link><space/>cartoon, presidential candidates<space/><link><target>Warren G. Harding</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>James M. Cox</target></link><space/>wonder at Ruth's record home run pace.</part></link>The home runs kept coming; Ruth tied his own record of 29 on July 15, and broke it with home runs in both games of a doubleheader four days later. By the end of July, he had 37, but his pace slackened somewhat after that.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 226</extension><space/>Nevertheless, on September 4, he both tied and broke the organized baseball record for home runs in a season, snapping<space/><link><target>Perry Werden</target></link>'s 1895 mark of 44 in the minor<space/><link><target>Western League (original)</target><part>Western League</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 75</extension><space/>The Yankees played well as a team, battling for the league lead early in the summer, but slumped in August in the AL pennant battle with Chicago and Cleveland. The championship was won by Cleveland, surging ahead after the<space/><link><target>Black Sox Scandal</target></link><space/>broke on September 28 and led to the suspension of many of the team's top players, including Joe Jackson. The Yankees finished third, but drew 1.2&amp;nbsp;million fans to the Polo Grounds, the first time a team had drawn a seven figure attendance. The rest of the league sold 600,000 more tickets, many fans there to see Ruth, who led the league with 54 home runs, 158<space/><link><target>Run (baseball)</target><part>runs</part></link>, and 137<space/><link><target>runs batted in</target></link><space/>(RBIs).<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 92</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth was aided in his exploits, in 1920 and afterwards, by the fact that the A.J. Reach Company, maker of baseballs used in the major leagues, was using a more efficient machine to wind the yarn found within the baseball. When these went into play in 1920, the start of the<space/><link><target>live-ball era</target></link>, the number of home runs increased by 184 over the previous year across the major leagues.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. 100101</extension><space/>Baseball statistician<space/><link><target>Bill James</target></link><space/>points out that while Ruth was likely aided by the change in the baseball, there were other factors at work, including the gradual abolition of the<space/><link><target>spitball</target></link><space/>(accelerated after the death of<space/><link><target>Ray Chapman</target></link>, struck by a pitched ball thrown by Mays in August 1920) and the more frequent use of new baseballs (also a response to Chapman's death). Nevertheless, James theorizes that Ruth's 1920 explosion might have happened in 1919, had a full season of 154 games been played rather than 140, had Ruth refrained from pitching 133 innings that season, and if he were playing with any other home field but Fenway Park, where he hit only 9 of 29 home runs.<extension extension_name='ref'>James, pp. 120122</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ruth1921.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Babe Ruth in 1921.</part></link>Yankees business manager<space/><link><target>Harry Sparrow</target></link><space/>had died early in the 1920 season; to replace him, Ruppert and Huston hired Barrow.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 93</extension><space/>Ruppert and Barrow quickly made a deal with Frazee for New York to acquire some of the players who would be mainstays of the early Yankee pennant-winning teams, including catcher<space/><link><target>Wally Schang</target></link><space/>and pitcher<space/><link><target>Waite Hoyt</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 131</extension><space/>The 21-year-old Hoyt became close to Ruth:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The outrageous life fascinated Hoyt, the don't-give-a-shit freedom of it, the nonstop, pell-mell charge into excess. How did a man drink so much and never get drunk?&nbsp;... The puzzle of Babe Ruth never was dull, no matter how many times Hoyt picked up the pieces and stared at them. After games he would follow the crowd to the Babe's suite. No matter what the town, the beer would be iced and the bottles would fill the bathtub.<ref>Montville, p. 156</ref>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth hit home runs early and often in the 1921 season, during which he broke<space/><link><target>Roger Connor</target></link>'s mark for home runs in a career, 138. Each of the almost 600 home runs Ruth hit in his career after that extended his own record. After a slow start, the Yankees were soon locked in a tight pennant race with Cleveland, winners of the<space/><link><target>1920 World Series</target></link>. On September 15, Ruth hit his 55th home run, shattering his year-old single season record. In late September, the Yankees visited Cleveland and won three out of four games, giving them the upper hand in the race, and clinched their first pennant a few days later. Ruth finished the regular season with 59 home runs, batting .378 and with a<space/><link><target>slugging percentage</target></link><space/>of .846.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 204, 238240</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Yankees had high expectations when they met the<space/><link><target>San Francisco Giants</target><part>New York Giants</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>1921 World Series</target></link>, and the Yankees won the first two games with Ruth in the lineup. However, Ruth badly scraped his elbow during Game 2, sliding into third base (he had walked and<space/><link><target>stolen base</target><part>stolen</part></link><space/>both second and third bases). After the game, he was told by the team physician not to play the rest of the series.<extension extension_name='ref'>Spatz &amp; Steinberg, p. 355.</extension><space/>Despite this advice, he did play in the next three games, and pinch-hit in Game Eight of the best-of-nine series, but the Yankees lost, five games to three. Ruth hit .316, drove in five runs and hit his first World Series home run.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 9596</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 241243</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth in Stands.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Babe Ruth in the stands on Opening Day, April 12, 1922, at<space/><link><target>Griffith Stadium</target></link><space/>in Washington, D.C.</part></link>After the Series, Ruth and teammates<space/><link><target>Bob Meusel</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bill Piercy</target></link><space/>participated in a<space/><link><target>barnstorm (athletics)</target><part>barnstorming</part></link><space/>tour in the Northeast.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp.&amp;nbsp;142144</extension><space/>A rule then in force prohibited World Series participants from playing in exhibition games during the offseason, the purpose being to prevent Series participants from replicating the Series and undermining its value.<space/><link><target>Baseball Commissioner</target></link><space/><link><target>Kenesaw Mountain Landis</target></link><space/>suspended the trio until May 20, 1922, and fined them their 1921 World Series checks.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 145</extension><space/>In August 1922, the rule was changed to allow limited barnstorming for World Series participants, with Landis's permission required.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p239">Pietrusza, p. 239</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On March 6, 1922, Ruth signed a new contract, for three years at $52,000 a year. The largest sum ever paid a ballplayer to that point, it represented 40% of the team's player payroll.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p239"></extension><space/>Despite his suspension, Ruth was named the Yankees' new on-field captain prior to the<space/><link><target>1922 New York Yankees season</target><part>1922 season</part></link>. During the suspension, he worked out with the team in the morning, and played exhibition games with the Yankees on their off days.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 255</extension><space/>He and Meusel returned on May 20, to a sellout crowd at the Polo Grounds, but Ruth batted 0-for-4, and was booed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pietrusza, p. 240</extension><space/>On May 25, he was thrown out of the game for throwing dust in umpire<space/><link><target>George Hildebrand</target></link>'s face, then climbed into the stands to confront a heckler. Ban Johnson ordered him fined, suspended, and stripped of his captaincy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 258259</extension><space/>In his shortened season, Ruth appeared in 110 games, batted .315, with 35 home runs, and drove in 99 runs,<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>but compared to his previous two dominating years, the 1922 season was a disappointment. Despite Ruth's off-year, Yankees managed to win the pennant to face the New York Giants for the second straight year in the<space/><link><target>1922 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link>. In the Series, Giants manager John McGraw instructed his pitchers to throw him nothing but curveballs, and Ruth never adjusted. Ruth had just two hits in seventeen at bats, and the Yankees lost to the Giants for the second straight year, by 40 (with one tie game). Sportswriter<space/><link><target>Joe Vila</target></link><space/>called him, &quot;an exploded phenomenon&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 103104</extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the season, Ruth was a guest at an<space/><link><target>Elks Club</target></link><space/>banquet, set up by Ruth's agent with Yankee team support. There, each speaker, concluding with future New York mayor<space/><link><target>Jimmy Walker</target></link>, censured him for his poor behavior. An emotional Ruth promised reform, and, to the surprise of many, followed through. When he reported to spring training, he was in his best shape as a Yankee, weighing only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>210</arg><arg>lb</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s104">Stout, p. 104</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Yankees's status as tenants of the Giants at the Polo Grounds had become increasingly uneasy, and in 1922 Giants owner<space/><link><target>Charles Stoneham</target></link><space/>stated that the Yankees's lease, expiring after that season, would not be renewed. Ruppert and Huston had long contemplated a new stadium, and had taken an option on property at 161st Street and River Avenue in<space/><link><target>the Bronx</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Yankee Stadium (1923)</target><part>Yankee Stadium</part></link><space/>was completed in time for the home opener on April 18, 1923,<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, pp. 7576</extension><space/>at which the Babe hit the first home run in what was quickly dubbed &quot;the House that Ruth Built&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s105">Stout, p. 105</extension><space/>The ballpark was designed with Ruth in mind: although the venue's left-field fence was further from home plate than at the Polo Grounds, Yankee Stadium's right-field fence was closer, making home runs easier to hit for left-handed batters. To spare Ruth's eyes, right fieldhis defensive positionwas not pointed into the afternoon sun, as was traditional; left fielder Meusel was soon suffering headaches from squinting toward home plate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s104"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Yankees were never challenged, leading the league for most of the 1923 season and winning the AL pennant by 17 games. Ruth finished the season with a career-high .393 batting average and major-league leading 41 home runs (tied with<space/><link><target>Cy Williams</target></link>). Another career high for Ruth in 1923 was his 45 doubles, and he reached base 379 times, then a major league record.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s105"></extension><space/>For the third straight year, the Yankees faced the Giants in the<space/><link><target>1923 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link>, which Ruth dominated. He batted .368, walked eight times, scored eight runs, hit three home runs and slugged 1.000 during the series, as the Yankees won their first World Series championship, four games to two.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="s105"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Batting title and &quot;bellyache&quot; (192425)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Library of Congress - Ruth knocked out (LOC).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Ruth after<space/><link><target>Unconsciousness</target><part>losing consciousness</part></link><space/>from running into the wall at<space/><link><target>Griffith Stadium</target></link><space/>during a game against the<space/><link><target>Minnesota Twins</target><part>Washington Senators</part></link><space/>on July 5, 1924. Ruth insisted on staying in the game, despite evident pain and a bruised pelvic bone, and hit a double in his next at-bat.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="newspaper">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="date">May 16, 2014</arg><arg name="title">Babe Ruth Knocked Out</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/17/upshot/babe-ruth-unconscious.html?action</arg><arg name="last">Beschloss</arg><arg name="first">Michael</arg></template></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1924, the Yankees were favored to become the first team to win four consecutive pennants. Plagued by injuries, they found themselves in a battle with the Senators. Although the Yankees won 18 of 22 at one point in September, the Senators beat out the Yankees by two games. Ruth hit .378, winning his only AL<space/><link><target>List of Major League Baseball batting champions</target><part>batting title</part></link>, with a league-leading 46 home runs.<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, pp. 101102</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth had kept up his efforts to stay in shape in 1923 and 1924, but by early 1925 weighed nearly<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>260</arg><arg>lb</arg></template>. His annual visit to<space/><link><target>Hot Springs, Arkansas</target></link>, where he exercised and took saunas early in the year, did him no good as he spent much of the time carousing in the resort town. He became ill while there, and suffered relapses during spring training. Ruth collapsed in<space/><link><target>Asheville, North Carolina</target></link>, as the team journeyed north. He was put on a train for New York, where he was briefly hospitalized.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s112">Stout, p. 112</extension><space/>A rumor circulated that he had died, prompting British newspapers to print<space/><link><target>List of premature obituaries</target><part>a premature obituary</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 202.</extension><space/>In New York, Ruth collapsed again and was found unconscious in his hotel bathroom. He was taken to a hospital where he suffered multiple convulsions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 203.</extension><space/>After sportswriter<space/><link><target>W. O. McGeehan</target></link><space/>wrote that Ruth's illness was due to binging on hot dogs and soda pop before a game, it became known as &quot;the bellyache heard 'round the world&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.dailyherald.com/story/?id</arg><arg name="title">Freak sports injuries: Now that's a bad break!</arg><arg name="work">Daily Herald</arg><arg name="author">Robert McCoppin</arg><arg name="date">September 11, 2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">August 31, 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the exact cause of his ailment has never been confirmed and remains a mystery.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 204</extension><space/>Glenn Stout, in his history of the Yankees, notes that the Ruth legend is &quot;still one of the most sheltered in sports&quot;; he suggests that alcohol was at the root of Ruth's illness, pointing to the fact that Ruth remained six weeks at<space/><link><target>St. Vincent's Hospital (Manhattan)</target><part>St. Vincent's Hospital</part></link><space/>but was allowed to leave, under supervision, for workouts with the team for part of that time. He concludes that the hospitalization was behavior-related.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 112113</extension><space/>Playing just 98 games, Ruth had his worst season as a Yankee; he finished with a .290 average and 25 home runs. The Yankees finished next to last in the AL with a 6985 record, their last season with a losing record until 1965.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 113, 460462</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Murderer's Row (192628)</heading><paragraph>Ruth spent part of the offseason of 192526 working out at<space/><link><target>Artie McGovern</target></link>'s gym, getting back into shape. Barrow and Huggins had rebuilt the team, surrounding the veteran core with good young players like<space/><link><target>Tony Lazzeri</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lou Gehrig</target></link>. But New York was not expected to win the pennant.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 116117</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Babe Ruth returned to his normal production during 1926, batting .372 with 47 home runs and 146 RBIs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>The Yankees built a ten-game lead by mid-June, and coasted to win the pennant by three games. The<space/><link><target>St. Louis Cardinals</target></link><space/>had won the National League with the lowest winning percentage for a pennant winner to that point (.578) and the Yankees were expected to win the<space/><link><target>1926 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link><space/>easily.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 304305</extension><space/>Although the Yankees won the opener in New York, St. Louis took Games Two and Three. In Game Four, Ruth hit three home runs, the first time this had been done in a World Series game, to lead the Yankees to victory; in the fifth game Ruth caught a ball as he crashed into the fence, described by baseball writers as a defensive gem. New York took that game, but<space/><link><target>Grover Cleveland Alexander</target></link><space/>won Game Six for St. Louis to tie the Series at three games each, then got very drunk. He was nevertheless inserted into Game Seven in the seventh inning and shut down the Yankees to win the game, 32, and win the Series.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 154155</extension><space/>Ruth had hit his fourth home run of the Series earlier in the game, and was the only Yankee to reach base off Alexander, walking in the ninth inning before being caught stealing to end the game. Although Ruth's attempt to steal second is often deemed a baserunning blunder, Creamer pointed out that the Yankees' chances of tying the game would have been greatly improved with a runner in scoring position.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 306</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 1926 Series was also known for Ruth's promise to<space/><link><target>Johnny Sylvester</target></link>, a hospitalized 11-year-old, that he would hit a home run on his behalf. Sylvester had been injured in a fall from a horse, and a friend of Sylvester's father gave the boy two autographed baseballs signed by Yankees and Cardinals, and relayed a promise from Ruth, who did not know the boy, to hit a home run for him. After the Series, Ruth visited the boy in the hospital. When the matter became public, the press greatly inflated it, and by some accounts, Ruth saved a dying boy's life by visiting him, emotionally promising to hit a home run, and doing so.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 327328</extension>[[File:Babecomeshome-poster-1927.jpg|upright|thumb|Ruth took time off in 1927 to star with<space/><link><target>Anna Q. Nilsson</target></link><space/>in this<space/><link><target>First National Pictures</target><part>First National</part></link><space/><link><target>silent film</target><part>silent</part></link><space/>production<space/><italics><link><target>Babe Comes Home</target></link></italics>. This film is now<space/><link><target>lost film</target><part>lost</part></link>. ]]The 1927 New York Yankees team is considered one of the greatest squads that ever took the field. Known as<space/><link><target>Murderer's Row</target></link><space/>because of the power of its lineup,<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 126131</extension><space/>the team won a then-AL-record 110 games, and took the AL pennant by 19 games, clinching first place on Labor Day.<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, pp. 127134</extension><space/>With little suspense as to the pennant race, the nation's attention turned to Ruth's pursuit of his own single-season home run record of 59. He was not alone in this chase: Gehrig proved to be a slugger capable of challenging Ruth for his home run crown, tying Ruth with 24 home runs late in June. Through July and August, they were never separated by more than two home runs. Gehrig took the lead, 4544, in the first game of a doubleheader at Fenway Park early in September; Ruth responded with two of his own to take the lead, as it proved permanentlyGehrig finished with 47. Even so, as of September 6, Ruth was still several games off his 1921 pace, and going into the final series against the Senators, had only 57. He hit two in the first game of the series, including one off of<space/><link><target>Paul Hopkins (baseball)</target><part>Paul Hopkins</part></link>, facing his first major league batter, to tie the record. The following day, September 30, he broke it with his 60th homer, in the eighth inning off<space/><link><target>Tom Zachary</target></link><space/>to break a 22 tie. &quot;Sixty! Let's see some son of a bitch try to top that one&quot;, Ruth exulted after the game.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 255261</extension><space/>In addition to his career-high 60 home runs, Ruth batted .356, drove in 164 runs and slugged .772.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>In the<space/><link><target>1927 World Series</target></link>, the Yankees swept the<space/><link><target>Pittsburgh Pirates</target></link><space/>in four games; the National Leaguers were disheartened after watching the Yankees take batting practice before Game One, with ball after ball leaving<space/><link><target>Forbes Field</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, pp. 134137</extension><space/>According to Appel, &quot;The 1927 New York Yankees. Even today, the words inspire awe&amp;nbsp;... all baseball success is measured against the '27 team.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, p. 151</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth &amp; Lou Gehrig at West Point 1927.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Babe Ruth and<space/><link><target>Lou Gehrig</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>West Point, New York</target></link><space/>in 1927.</part></link>Before the 1928 season, Ruth signed a new contract for an unprecedented $80,000 per year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, p. 140</extension><space/>The season started off well for the Yankees, who led the league in the early going. But the Yankees were plagued by injuries, erratic pitching and inconsistent play. The<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Athletics</target></link>, rebuilding after some lean years, erased the Yankees' big lead and even took over first place briefly in early September. The Yankees, however, regained first place when they beat the Athletics three out of four games in a pivotal series at Yankee Stadium later that month, and clinched the pennant in the final weekend of the season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Graham, pp. 144146</extension><space/>Ruth's play in 1928 mirrored his team's performance. He got off to a hot start and on August 1, he had 42 home runs. This put him ahead of his 60 home run pace from the previous season. He then slumped for the latter part of the season, and he hit just twelve home runs in the last two months. Ruth's batting average also fell to .323, well below his career average. Nevertheless, he ended the season with 54 home runs. The Yankees swept the favored Cardinals in four games in the<space/><link><target>1928 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link>, with Ruth batting .625 and hitting three home runs in Game Four, including one off Alexander.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 273277</extension><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>&quot;Called shot&quot; and final Yankee years (192934)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Babe Ruth's called shot</arg></template><link><target>File:1933 Goudey Sport Kings 02 Babe Ruth.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>right</part><part>1933 Goudey Sport Kings baseball card</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Before the 1929 season, Ruppert, who had bought out Huston in 1923, announced that the Yankees would wear uniform numbers to allow fans at cavernous Yankee Stadium to tell one player from another. The Cardinals and Indians had each experimented with uniform numbers; the Yankees were the first to use them on both home and away uniforms. As Ruth batted third, he was given number 3.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, pp. 162163</extension><space/>According to a long-standing baseball legend, the Yankees adopted their now-iconic pinstriped uniforms in hopes of making Ruth look slimmer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sh9">Sherman, p. 9</extension><space/>In truth, though, they had been wearing pinstripes since Ruppert bought the team in 1915.<extension extension_name='ref'>Edmondson, Rubie.<space/><link type='external' href='http://ftw.usatoday.com/2013/04/yankees-pinstripes-origin-babe-ruth'>The Yankees permanently adopted pinstripes 98 years ago today</link>.<space/><link><target>USA Today</target></link>, 2013-04-22.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although the Yankees started well, the Athletics soon proved they were the better team in 1929, splitting two series with the Yankees in the first month of the season, then taking advantage of a Yankee losing streak in mid-May to gain first place. Although Ruth performed well, the Yankees were not able to catch the AthleticsConnie Mack had built another great team.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, pp. 140141</extension><space/>Tragedy struck the Yankees late in the year as manager Huggins died of<space/><link><target>erysipelas</target></link>, a bacterial skin infection, on September 25, only ten days after he had last led the team. Despite past differences, Ruth praised Huggins and described him as a &quot;great guy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, pp. 164165</extension><space/>The Yankees finished second, 18 games behind the Athletics.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s461"></extension><space/>Ruth hit .345 during the season, with 46 home runs and 154 RBIs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Yankees hired<space/><link><target>Bob Shawkey</target></link><space/>as manager, their fourth choice. Ruth politicked for the job of player-manager, but was not seriously considered by Ruppert and Barrow; Stout deems this the first hint Ruth would have no future with the Yankees once he was done as a player.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 143</extension><space/>Shawkey, a former Yankees player and teammate of Ruth, was unable to command the slugger's respect. The Athletics won their second consecutive pennant and<space/><link><target>1929 World Series</target><part>World Series</part></link>, as the Yankees finished in third place, sixteen games back.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout, p. 144</extension><space/>During that season Ruth was asked by a reporter what he thought of his yearly salary of $80,000 being more than President<space/><link><target>Herbert Hoover</target><part>Hoover's</part></link><space/>$75,000. His response was, &quot;I know, but I had a better year than Hoover.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A52356-2004Sep26.html</arg><arg name="title">Just a Little History</arg><arg name="work">Washington Post</arg><arg name="author">Norman Chad</arg><arg name="date">September 27, 2004</arg><arg name="accessdate">August 31, 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1930, Ruth hit .359 with 49 home runs (his best in his years after 1928) and 153 RBIs, and pitched his first game in nine years, a complete game victory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>At the end of the season, Shawkey was fired and replaced with Cubs manager<space/><link><target>Joe McCarthy (manager)</target><part>Joe McCarthy</part></link>, though Ruth again unsuccessfully sought the job.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 303</extension></paragraph><paragraph>McCarthy was a disciplinarian, but chose not to interfere with Ruth, and the slugger for his part did not seek conflict with the manager.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 304</extension><space/>The team improved in 1931, but was no match for the Athletics, who won 107 games,<space/><template><target>frac</target><arg>13</arg><arg>1</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>games in front of the Yankees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s148">Stout, p. 148</extension><space/>Ruth, for his part, hit .373, with 46 home runs and 163 RBIs. He had 31 doubles, his most since 1924.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>In the 1932 season, the Yankees went 10747 and won the pennant.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s148"></extension><space/>Ruth's effectiveness had decreased somewhat, but he still hit .341 with 41 home runs and 137 RBIs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>Nevertheless, he twice was sidelined due to injury during the season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sherman, p. 41</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ruth1932-1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A still of Ruth pointing during the at-bat in Game 3 of the 1932 World Series</part></link>The Yankees faced the Cubs, McCarthy's former team, in the<space/><link><target>1932 World Series</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, p. 177</extension><space/>There was bad blood between the two teams as the Yankees resented the Cubs only awarding<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball postseason#Postseason bonuses</target><part>half a World Series share</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Mark Koenig</target></link>, a former Yankee. The games at Yankee Stadium had not been sellouts; both were won by the home team, with Ruth collecting two singles, but scoring four runs as he was walked four times by the Cubs pitchers. In Chicago, Ruth was resentful at the hostile crowds that met the Yankees's train and jeered them at the hotel. The crowd for Game Three included New York Governor<space/><link><target>Franklin D. Roosevelt</target></link>, the Democratic candidate for president, who sat with Chicago Mayor<space/><link><target>Anton Cermak</target></link>. Many in the crowd threw lemons at Ruth, a sign of derision, and others (as well as the Cubs themselves) shouted abuse at Ruth and other Yankees. They were briefly silenced when Ruth hit a three-run home run off<space/><link><target>Charlie Root</target></link><space/>in the first inning, but soon revived, and the Cubs tied the score at 44 in the fourth inning. When Ruth came to the plate in the top of the fifth, the Chicago crowd and players, led by pitcher<space/><link><target>Guy Bush</target></link>, were screaming insults at Ruth. With the<space/><link><target>Count (baseball)</target><part>count</part></link><space/>at two balls and one strike, Ruth gestured, possibly in the direction of<space/><link><target>center fielder</target><part>center field</part></link>, and after the next pitch (a strike), may have pointed there with one hand. Ruth hit the fifth pitch over the center field fence; estimates were that it traveled nearly<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500</arg><arg>ft</arg></template>. Whether or not Ruth intended to indicate where he planned to (and did) hit the ball, the incident has gone down in legend as<space/><link><target>Babe Ruth's called shot</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sherman, pp. 6987</extension><space/>The Yankees won Game Three, and the following day clinched the Series with another victory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 311</extension><space/>During that game, Bush hit Ruth on the arm with a pitch, causing words to be exchanged and provoking a game-winning Yankee rally.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 362</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth remained productive in 1933, as he batted .301, with 34 home runs, 103 RBIs, and a league-leading 114 walks,<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension><space/>as the Yankees finished second, seven games behind the Senators.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s461"></extension><space/>He was selected to play right field by Athletics manager<space/><link><target>Connie Mack</target></link><space/>in the first<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball All-Star Game</target></link>, held on July 6, 1933, at<space/><link><target>Comiskey Park</target></link><space/>in Chicago. He hit the first home run in the All-Star Game's history, a two-run blast against<space/><link><target>Bill Hallahan</target></link><space/>during the third inning, which helped the AL win the game 42.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 371</extension><space/>During the final game of the 1933 season, as a publicity stunt organized by his team, Ruth was called upon and pitched a complete game victory against the Red Sox, his final appearance as a pitcher.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 371372</extension><space/>Despite unremarkable pitching numbers, Ruth had a 50 record in five games for the Yankees, raising his career totals to 9446.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stats"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1934, Ruth played in his last full season. By this time, years of high living were starting to catch up with him. His conditioning had deteriorated to the point that he could no longer field or run.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Neyer42">Neyer, p. 42.</extension><space/>He accepted a pay cut from Ruppert to $35,000, but was still the highest-paid player in the major leagues.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 221</extension><space/>He could still handle a bat, recording a .288 batting average with 22 home runs, statistics Reisler described as &quot;merely mortal&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 256</extension><space/>Ruth was selected to the AL All-Star team for the second consecutive year. During the game, New York Giants pitcher<space/><link><target>Carl Hubbell</target></link><space/>struck out Ruth and four other future<space/><link><target>Baseball Hall of Fame</target><part>Hall-of-Famers</part></link><space/>consecutively.<extension extension_name='ref'>Appel, p. 170</extension><space/>The Yankees finished second again, seven games behind the Tigers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="s461">Stout, p. 461</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Boston Braves (1935)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ruth1935.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>175px</part><part>Ruth in 1935 with the<space/><link><target>History of the Boston Braves</target><part>Boston Braves</part></link>. This was his last year in baseball</part></link>Although Ruth knew he was nearly finished as a player, he desired to remain in baseball as a manager. He was often spoken of as a possible candidate as managerial jobs opened up, but in 1932, when he was mentioned as a contender for the Red Sox position, stated that he was not yet ready to leave the field. There were rumors that Ruth was a likely candidate each time when the<space/><link><target>Cleveland Indians</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cincinnati Reds</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Detroit Tigers</target></link><space/>were looking for a manager, but nothing came of them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Montvillepp">Montville, pp. 322323.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Just before the 1934 season, Ruppert offered to make Ruth manager of the Yankees' top minor-league team, the<space/><link><target>Newark Bears (International League)</target><part>Newark Bears</part></link>, but he was talked out of it by his wife,<space/><link><target>Claire Merritt Ruth</target><part>Claire</part></link><space/>(Helen<space/><link><target>#Personal life</target><part>had died</part></link><space/>in 1929), and his business manager, Christy Walsh.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Neyer42"></extension><space/>Shortly afterward, Tigers owner<space/><link><target>Frank Navin</target></link><space/>made a proposal to Ruppert and Barrowif the Yankees traded Ruth to Detroit, Navin would name Ruth player-manager. Navin believed Ruth would not only bring a winning attitude to a team that hadn't finished higher than third since 1923, but would also revive the Tigers' sagging attendance figures. Navin asked Ruth to come to Detroit for an interview. However, Ruth balked, since Walsh had already arranged for him to take part in a celebrity golf tournament in Hawaii. Ruth and Navin negotiated over the phone while Ruth was in Hawaii, but those talks foundered when Navin refused to give Ruth a portion of the Tigers' box office proceeds.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ferkovich, Scott.<space/><link type='external' href='http://seamheads.com/2014/07/14/a-look-back-at-when-babe-ruth-nearly-became-the-detroit-tigers-player-manager'>A Look Back at When Babe Ruth Nearly Became the Detroit Tigers' Player-Manager</link>. Seamheads.com, 2014-07-14.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Early in the 1934 season, Ruth began openly campaigning to become manager of the Yankees. However, the Yankee job was never a serious possibility. Ruppert always supported McCarthy, who would remain in his position for another 12 seasons. Ruth and McCarthy's relationship had been lukewarm at best, and Ruth's managerial ambitions further chilled their relations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Neyer42"></extension><space/>By the end of the season, Ruth hinted that he would retire unless Ruppert named him manager of the Yankees.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.google.com/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title">Ruth to Quit Unless Given Manager Job</arg><arg name="first">Jimmy</arg><arg name="last">Powers</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]</arg><arg name="date">October 9, 1934</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 22, 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>For his part, Ruppert wanted his slugger to leave the team without drama and hard feelings when the time came.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Montvillepp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the 193435 offseason, Ruth circled the world with his wife, including a barnstorming tour of the Far East. At his final stop before returning home, in the United Kingdom, Ruth was introduced to cricket by Australian player<space/><link><target>Alan Fairfax</target></link>, and after having little luck in a cricketer's stance, stood as a baseball batter and launched some massive shots around the field, destroying the bat in the process. Although Fairfax regretted that he could not have the time to make Ruth a cricket player, Ruth had lost any interest in such a career upon learning that the best batsmen made only about $40 per week.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 336.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Also during the offseason, Ruppert had been sounding out the other clubs in hopes of finding one that would be willing to take Ruth as a manager and/or a player. However, the only serious offer came from Athletics owner-manager Connie Mack, who gave some thought to stepping down as manager in favor of Ruth. However, Mack later dropped the idea, saying that Ruth's wife would be running the team in a month if Ruth ever took over.<extension extension_name='ref'>Neyer, p. 43.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the barnstorming tour was under way, Ruppert began negotiating with Boston Braves owner Judge<space/><link><target>Emil Fuchs (baseball)</target><part>Emil Fuchs</part></link>, who wanted Ruth as a gate attraction. Although the Braves had enjoyed modest recent success, finishing fourth in the National League in both 1933 and 1934, the team performed poorly at the box office. Unable to afford the rent at<space/><link><target>Braves Field</target></link>, Fuchs had considered holding dog races there when the Braves were not at home, only to be turned down by Landis. After a series of phone calls, letters, and meetings, the Yankees traded Ruth to the Braves on February 26, 1935. Ruppert had stated that he would not release Ruth to go to another team as a full-time player. For this reason, it was announced that Ruth would become a team vice president and would be consulted on all club transactions, in addition to playing. He was also made assistant manager to Braves skipper<space/><link><target>Bill McKechnie</target></link>. In a long letter to Ruth a few days before the press conference, Fuchs promised Ruth a share in the Braves' profits, with the possibility of becoming co-owner of the team. Fuchs also raised the possibility of Ruth succeeding McKechnie as manager, perhaps as early as 1936. Ruppert called the deal &quot;the greatest opportunity Ruth ever had&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Neyer, pp.&amp;nbsp;4244.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 337339.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There was considerable attention as Ruth reported for spring training. He did not hit his first home run of the spring until after the team had left Florida, and was beginning the road north in Savannah. He hit two in an exhibition against the Bears.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 339.</extension><space/>Amid much press attention, Ruth played his first home game in Boston in over 16 years. Before an opening-day crowd of over 25,000, including five of New England's six state governors, Ruth accounted for all of the Braves' runs in a 42 defeat of the<space/><link><target>San Francisco Giants</target><part>New York Giants</part></link>, hitting a two-run home run, singling to drive in a third run and later in the inning scoring the fourth. Although age and weight had slowed him, he made a running catch in left field which sportswriters deemed the defensive highlight of the game.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 393.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth had two hits in the second game of the season, but it quickly went downhill both for him and the Braves from there. The season soon settled down to a routine of Ruth performing poorly on the few occasions he even played at all, and the Braves losing most games. As April passed into May, Ruth's deterioration became even more pronounced. While he remained productive at the plate early on, he could do little else. His condition had deteriorated to the point that he could barely trot around the bases. His fielding had become so poor that three Braves pitchers told McKechnie that they would not take the mound if he was in the lineup. Before long, Ruth stopped hitting as well. He grew increasingly annoyed that McKechnie ignored most of his advice.<extension extension_name='ref'>Neyer, pp. 4345.</extension><space/>For his part, McKechnie later said that Ruth's huge salary and refusal to stay with the team while on the road made it nearly impossible to enforce discipline.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Lee Allen (baseball)</target><part>Allen, Lee</part></link>.<space/><italics>The National League Story</italics>. Hill &amp; Wang, 1961.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth soon realized that Fuchs had deceived him, and had no intention of making him manager or giving him any significant off-field duties. He later stated that his only duties as vice president consisted of making public appearances and autographing tickets.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 340.</extension><space/>Ruth also found out that far from giving him a share of the profits, Fuchs wanted him to invest some of<space/><italics>his</italics><space/>money in the team in a last-ditch effort to improve its balance sheet.<extension extension_name='ref' name="neyer44">Neyer, p. 44.</extension><space/>As it turned out, both Fuchs and Ruppert had known all along that Ruth's non-playing positions were meaningless.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 388390.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the end of the first month of the season, Ruth concluded he was finished even as a part-time player. As early as May 12, he asked Fuchs to let him retire.<extension extension_name='ref' name="neyer44"></extension><space/>Ultimately, Fuchs persuaded Ruth to remain at least until after the<space/><link><target>Memorial Day</target></link><space/>doubleheader in Philadelphia. In the interim was a western road trip, at which the rival teams had scheduled days to honor him. In Chicago and St. Louis, Ruth performed poorly, and his batting average sank to .155, with only three home runs. In the first two games in Pittsburgh, Ruth had only one hit, though a long fly caught by<space/><link><target>Paul Waner</target></link><space/>probably would have been a home run in any other ballpark besides<space/><link><target>Forbes Field</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 395397</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth played in the third game of the Pittsburgh series on May 25, 1935, and added one more tale to his playing legend. Ruth went 4-for-4, including three home runs, though the Braves lost the game 117. The last two were off Ruth's old Cubs nemesis, Guy Bush. The final home run, both of the game and of Ruth's career, sailed over the upper deck in right field and out of the ballpark, the first time anyone had hit a fair ball completely out of Forbes Field. Ruth was urged to make this his last game, but he had given his word to Fuchs and played in Cincinnati and Philadelphia. The first game of the doubleheader in Philadelphiathe Braves lost bothwas his final major league appearance. On June 2, after an argument with Fuchs, Ruth retired. He finished 1935 with a .181 averageeasily his worst as a full-time position playerand the final six of his 714 home runs. The Braves, 1027 when Ruth left, finished 38115, at .248 the worst winning percentage in modern National League history.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 396400</extension><space/>Insolvent like his team, Fuchs gave up control of the Braves before the end of the season; the National League took over the franchise at the end of the year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, p. 344.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Retirement</heading><heading level='3'>193546</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Pride of the Yankees2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ruth with<space/><link><target>Gary Cooper</target></link><space/>in the 1942 film ''<link><target>The Pride of the Yankees</target></link>''</part></link>Although Fuchs had given Ruth his unconditional release, no major league team expressed an interest in hiring him in any capacity. Ruth still hoped to be hired as a manager if he could not play anymore, but only one managerial position, Cleveland, became available between Ruth's retirement and the end of the 1937 season. Asked if he had considered Ruth for the job, Indians owner<space/><link><target>Alva Bradley</target></link><space/>replied negatively.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c399a"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The writer Creamer believed Ruth was unfairly treated in never being given an opportunity to manage a major league club. The author believed there was not necessarily a relationship between personal conduct and managerial success, noting that<space/><link><target>John McGraw (baseball)</target><part>McGraw</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Billy Martin</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Bobby Valentine</target></link><space/>were winners despite character flaws.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sherman, p. 17</extension><space/>Team owners and general managers assessed Ruth's flamboyant personal habits as a reason to exclude him from a managerial job; Barrow said of him, &quot;How can he manage other men when he can't even manage himself?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="99facts"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth played much golf and in a few exhibition baseball games, demonstrating a continuing ability to draw large crowds. This appeal contributed to the Dodgers' hiring him as first base coach in 1938. But Brooklyn general manager<space/><link><target>Larry MacPhail</target></link><space/>made it clear when Ruth was hired that he would not be considered for the manager's job if, as expected,<space/><link><target>Burleigh Grimes</target></link><space/>retired at the end of the season. Although much was said about what Ruth could teach the younger players, in practice, his duties were to appear on the field in uniform and encourage base runnershe was not called upon to relay signs. He got along well with everyone except team captain<space/><link><target>Leo Durocher</target></link>, who was hired as Grimes' replacement at season's end. Ruth returned to retirement, never again to work in baseball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c399a">Creamer, pp. 399405.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On July 4, 1939, Ruth spoke on Lou Gehrig Appreciation Day at Yankee Stadium as members of the 1927 Yankees and a sellout crowd turned out to honor the first baseman, forced into premature retirement by<space/><link><target>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</target><part>ALS disease</part></link>, which would kill him in two years. The next week, Ruth went to<space/><link><target>Cooperstown, New York</target></link>, for the formal opening of the<space/><link><target>National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum</target><part>Baseball Hall of Fame</part></link>. Three years earlier he was one of the<space/><link><target>Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 1936</target><part>first five players</part></link><space/>elected to it. As radio broadcasts of baseball became popular, Ruth sought a job in that field, arguing that his celebrity and knowledge of baseball would assure large audiences, but he received no offers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 247249.</extension><space/>During World War II, he made many personal appearances to advance the war effort, including his last appearance as a player at Yankee Stadium, in a 1943 exhibition for the ArmyNavy Relief Fund. He hit a long fly ball off Walter Johnson; the blast left the field, curving foul, but Ruth circled the bases anyway. In 1946, he made a final effort to gain a job in baseball, contacting new Yankees boss MacPhail, but was sent a rejection letter.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 355356.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cancer and death (194648)</heading><paragraph>As early as the war years, doctors had cautioned Ruth to take better care of his health, and he grudgingly followed their advice, limiting his drinking and not going on a proposed trip to support the troops in the South Pacific.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 252253.</extension><space/>In 1946, Ruth began experiencing severe pain over his left eye, and had difficulty swallowing. In November 1946, he entered French Hospital in New York for tests, which revealed Ruth had an inoperable<space/><link><target>cancer</target><part>malignant tumor</part></link><space/>at the base of his skull and in his neck. It was a lesion known as<space/><link><target>nasopharyngeal carcinoma</target></link>, or &quot;lymphoepithelioma.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Maloney WJ, Weinberg MA. A comprehensive analysis of Babe Ruth's head and neck cancer. J Am Dent Assoc. 2008 Jul;139(7):926-32. PubMed PMID 18594078.</extension><space/>His name and fame gave him access to experimental treatments, and he was one of the first cancer patients to receive both drugs and radiation treatment simultaneously.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 357358.</extension><space/>He was discharged from the hospital in February, having lost<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>80</arg><arg>lb</arg></template>, and went to Florida to recuperate. He returned to New York and Yankee Stadium after the season started. The new commissioner,<space/><link><target>Happy Chandler</target></link><space/>(Judge Landis had died in 1944), proclaimed April 27, 1947, Babe Ruth Day around the major leagues, with the most significant observance to be in the Bronx. A number of teammates and others spoke in honor of Ruth, who briefly addressed the crowd of almost 60,000.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 418419.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Around this time, developments in<space/><link><target>chemotherapy</target></link><space/>offered some hope. The doctors had not told Ruth that he had cancer because of his family's fear that he might do himself harm. They treated him with teropterin, a<space/><link><target>folic acid</target></link><space/>derivative; he may have been the first human subject.<extension extension_name='ref' name="montville360"></extension><space/>Ruth showed dramatic improvement during the summer of 1947, so much so that his case was presented by his doctors at a scientific meeting, without using his name. He was able to travel around the country, doing promotional work for the Ford Motor Company on<space/><link><target>American Legion Baseball</target></link>. He appeared again at another day in his honor at Yankee Stadium in September, but was not well enough to pitch in an old-timers game as he had hoped.<extension extension_name='ref' name="montville360">Montville, p. 360.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 418420.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>MLBBioRet</target><arg name="Image"><space/>BabeRuth3.jpg
</arg><arg name="Name"><space/>Babe Ruth
</arg><arg name="Number"><space/>3
</arg><arg name="Team"><space/>New York Yankees
</arg><arg name="Year"><space/>1948
</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The improvement was only a temporary remission, and by late 1947, Ruth was unable to help with the writing of his autobiography,<space/><italics>The Babe Ruth Story</italics>, which was almost entirely ghostwritten. In and out of the hospital in New York, he left for Florida in February 1948, doing what activities he could. After six weeks he returned to New York to appear at a book-signing party. He also traveled to California to witness the filming of the book.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 361362.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On June 5, 1948, a &quot;gaunt and hollowed out&quot; Ruth visited<space/><link><target>Yale University</target></link><space/>to donate a manuscript of<space/><italics>The Babe Ruth Story</italics><space/>to its library.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nhregister.com/general-news/20120919/new-haven-200-babe-ruth-meets-future-president-george-hw-bush-in-1948-at-yale-field</arg><arg name="title">New Haven 200: Babe Ruth meets future President George H.W. Bush in 1948 at Yale Field</arg><arg name="newspaper">New Haven Register</arg><arg name="date">September 19, 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 20, 2013</arg><arg name="first">Chip</arg><arg name="last">Malafronte</arg></template></extension><space/>On June 13, Ruth visited Yankee Stadium for the final time in his life, appearing at the 25th anniversary celebrations of &quot;The House that Ruth Built&quot;. By this time he had lost much weight and had difficulty walking. Introduced along with his surviving teammates from 1923, Ruth used a bat as a cane.<space/><link><target>Nat Fein</target></link>'s photo of Ruth taken from behind, standing near home plate and facing &quot;Ruthville&quot; (right field) became one of baseball's most famous and widely circulated photographs, and won the<space/><link><target>Pulitzer Prize</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 267268.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth made one final trip on behalf of American Legion Baseball, then entered<space/><link><target>Memorial SloanKettering Cancer Center</target><part>Memorial Hospital</part></link>, where he would die. He was never told he had cancer, but before his death, had surmised it. He was able to leave the hospital for a few short trips, including a final visit to Baltimore. On July 26, 1948, Ruth left the hospital to attend the premiere of the film<space/><italics><link><target>The Babe Ruth Story</target></link></italics>. Shortly thereafter, Ruth returned to the hospital for the final time. He was barely able to speak. Ruth's condition gradually became worse; only a few visitors were allowed to see him, one of whom was<space/><link><target>National League</target></link><space/>president and future<space/><link><target>Commissioner of Baseball</target></link><space/><link><target>Ford Frick</target></link>. &quot;Ruth was so thin it was unbelievable. He had been such a big man and his arms were just skinny little bones, and his face was so haggard&quot;, Frick said years later.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 423424</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Thousands of New Yorkers, including many children, stood vigil outside the hospital in Ruth's final days. On August 16, 1948, at 8:01&amp;nbsp;pm, Ruth died in his sleep at the age of 53. Instead of a wake at a funeral home, his casket was taken to Yankee Stadium, where it remained for two days; 77,000 people filed past to pay him tribute. His funeral Mass took place at<space/><link><target>St. Patrick's Cathedral (New York)</target><part>St. Patrick's Cathedral</part></link>; a crowd estimated at 75,000 waited outside. Ruth was buried on a hillside in Section 25 at the<space/><link><target>Gate of Heaven Cemetery</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Hawthorne, New York</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 366367.</extension><space/>An epitaph by<space/><link><target>Cardinal Spellman</target></link><space/>appears on his headstone. His second wife,<space/><link><target>Claire Ruth</target></link>, would be interred with him 28 years later in 1976.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal life</heading><paragraph>Ruth met Helen Woodford, by some accounts, in a coffee shop in Boston where she was a waitress, and they were married on October 17, 1914.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, pp. 84, 100</extension><space/>They adopted a daughter,<space/><link><target>Dorothy Ruth</target><part>Dorothy</part></link>, in 1921. Ruth and Helen separated around 1925, reportedly due to his repeated<space/><link><target>Adultery</target><part>infidelities</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 281</extension><space/>Their last public appearance together came during the 1926 World Series.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 336.</extension><space/>Helen died in a fire in<space/><link><target>Watertown, Massachusetts</target></link>, in 1929, in a house owned by Edward Kinder, a dentist with whom she had been living as &quot;Mrs. Kinder&quot;. In her book,<space/><italics>My Dad, the Babe</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Pirone</arg><arg name="first">Dorothy</arg><arg name="author2">Chris Martens</arg><arg name="title">My Dad, The Babe: Growing up with an American Hero</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg><arg name="publisher">Quinlan Press</arg><arg name="location">Boston</arg><arg name="isbn">1-55770-031-1</arg><arg name="oclc">17652057</arg><arg name="page">250</arg></template></extension><space/>Dorothy claimed that she was Ruth's biological child by a girlfriend named Juanita Jennings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dorothy obit"></extension><space/>She died in 1989.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dorothy obit"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dorothy R. Pirone, 68, Babe Ruth's Daughter<space/></arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="date">May 20, 1989</arg><arg name="accessdate">May 21, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On April 17, 1929, Ruth married actress and model<space/><link><target>Claire Merritt Hodgson</target></link><space/>(18971976) and adopted her daughter Julia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Wiessner</arg><arg name="first">Christian</arg><arg name="title">Baseball says goodbye as Yankee Stadium retired</arg><arg name="date">September 22, 2008</arg><arg name="agency">Reuters</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Thomson Reuters]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.reuters.com/article/2008/09/22/us-baseball-yankeestadium-idUSN1950865620080922</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/634u6KlfD</arg><arg name="archivedate">November 9, 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="last">Kerasotis</arg><arg name="title">Home, at the Other House That Ruth Built</arg><arg name="date">March 10, 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">The New York Times Company</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/11/sports/baseball/yankees-home-at-the-other-house-that-ruth-built.html?_r</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 18, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>By one account, Julia and Dorothy were, through no fault of their own, the reason for the seven-year rift in Ruth's relationship with teammate Lou Gehrig. Sometime in 1932, Gehrig's mother, during a conversation which she assumed was private, remarked, &quot;It's a shame [Claire] doesn't dress Dorothy as nicely as she dresses her own daughter.&quot; When the comment inevitably got back to Ruth, he angrily told Gehrig to tell his mother to mind her own business. Gehrig in turn took offense at what he perceived as Ruth's comment about his mother. The two men reportedly never spoke off the field until they reconciled at Yankee Stadium on Lou Gehrig Appreciation Day in 1939.<extension extension_name='ref'>Creamer, p. 415.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although he was married through most of his baseball career, when Colonel Huston asked Ruth to tone down his lifestyle, the player said, &quot;I'll promise to go easier on drinking and to get to bed earlier, but not for you, fifty thousand dollars, or two-hundred and fifty thousand dollars will I give up women. They're too much fun.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="page">158</arg><arg name="title">Baseball As I Have Known It</arg><arg name="first">Fred</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lieb</arg><arg name="publisher">Cowar, McCann and Geoghagen</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1977</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8032-7962-9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Memorial and museum</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:RuthMonument.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Tribute to Babe Ruth, Monument Park, as seen at the original Yankee Stadium</part></link>On April 19, 1949, the Yankees unveiled a granite monument in Ruth's honor in center field of Yankee Stadium.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.google.com/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title">Six Home Teams Score Victories in Opener</arg><arg name="first">Ralph</arg><arg name="last">Roden</arg><arg name="work">St. Petersburg Times</arg><arg name="page">8</arg><arg name="date">April 20, 1949</arg><arg name="accessdate">September 18, 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>The monument was located<space/><link><target>ground rules</target><part>in the field of play</part></link><space/>next to a flagpole and similar tributes to Huggins and Gehrig until the stadium was remodeled from 19741975, which resulted in the outfield fences moving inward and enclosing the monuments from the playing field. This area was known thereafter as<space/><link><target>Monument Park (Yankee Stadium)</target><part>Monument Park</part></link>. Yankee Stadium, &quot;the House that Ruth Built&quot;, was replaced after the 2008 season with a new<space/><link><target>Yankee Stadium</target></link><space/>across the street from the old one; Monument Park was subsequently moved to the new venue behind the center field fence. Ruth's uniform number 3 has been<space/><link><target>List of Major League Baseball retired numbers</target><part>retired</part></link><space/>by the Yankees, and he is one of five Yankees players or managers to have a granite monument within the stadium.<extension extension_name='ref' name="retired number"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Retired numbers</arg><arg name="publisher">New York Yankees</arg><arg name="url">http://newyork.yankees.mlb.com/nyy/history/retired_numbers.jsp</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 8, 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Babe Ruth, other monuments, settle in new Yankee Stadium home</arg><arg name="last">Coffey</arg><arg name="first">Wayne</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/yankees/babe-ruth-monuments-settle-new-yankee-stadium-home-article-1.389857</arg><arg name="newspaper">New York Daily News</arg><arg name="date">February 25, 2009</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 8, 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Everyone agrees: Steinbrenner's plaque is big</arg><arg name="last">Sandomir</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/22/sports/baseball/22monument.html?_r</arg><arg name="newspaper">New York Daily News</arg><arg name="date">September 21, 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 8, 2013</arg></template><space/>(subscription required)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Babe Ruth Birthplace Museum is located at 216 Emory Street, a Baltimore row house where Ruth was born, and three blocks west of<space/><link><target>Oriole Park at Camden Yards</target></link>, where the AL's<space/><link><target>Baltimore Orioles</target></link><space/>play.<extension extension_name='ref' name="History"><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20110419151458/http://www.baberuthmuseum.com/pagebank/index.html?id=119'>History: Babe Ruth Birthplace Museum</link><space/>webpage. Official website of the Babe Ruth Birthplace Museum and the Sports Legends Museum at Camden Yards. Babe Ruth Birthplace Foundation, Inc. Retrieved August 4, 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20110808101321/http://www.baberuthmuseum.com/locations/locations/'>Locations</link><space/>webpage. Official website of the Babe Ruth Birthplace Museum and the Sports Legends Museum at Camden Yards. Babe Ruth Birthplace Foundation, Inc. Retrieved August 4, 2014.</extension><space/>The property was restored and opened to the public in 1973 by the non-profit Babe Ruth Birthplace Foundation, Inc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="History"></extension><space/>Ruth's widow, Claire, his two daughters, Dorothy and Julia, and his sister, Mamie, helped select and install exhibits for the museum.<extension extension_name='ref' name="History"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contemporary impact</heading><paragraph>Ruth was the first baseball star to be the subject of overwhelming interest by the public. Baseball had developed star players before, such as Cobb and &quot;Shoeless Joe&quot; Jackson, but both men had uneasy relations with fans, in Cobb's case sometimes marked by violence. Ruth's biographers agree that he benefited from the timing of his ascension to &quot;Home Run King&quot;, with an America hit hard by both the war and the<space/><link><target>1918 flu pandemic</target></link><space/>longing for something to help put these traumas behind it. He also resonated in a country which felt, in the aftermath of the war, that it took second place to no one. Montville argues that as a larger-than-life figure capable of unprecedented athletic feats in the nation's largest city, Ruth became an icon of the significant social changes which marked the early 1920s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. xiixiii.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 106107.</extension><space/>Glenn Stout notes in his history of the Yankees, &quot;Ruth was New York incarnateuncouth and raw, flamboyant and flashy, oversized, out of scale, and absolutely unstoppable&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="st86">Stout, p. 86</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth became such a symbol of the United States during his lifetime that during World War II, Japanese soldiers yelled in English, &quot;To hell with Babe Ruth,&quot; to anger American soldiers. (Ruth replied that he hoped that &quot;every Jap that mention[ed] my name gets shot&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref' name="bullock2004"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Playing for Their Nation: Baseball and the American Military during World War II<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Nebraska Press<space/></arg><arg name="author">Bullock, Steven R.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="pages">4<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-8032-1337-9</arg></template></extension><space/>Creamer recorded that &quot;Babe Ruth transcended sport, moved far beyond the artificial limits of baselines and outfield fences and sports pages&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c16">Creamer, p. 16.</extension><space/>Wagenheim stated, &quot;He appealed to a deeply rooted American yearning for the definitive climax: clean, quick, unarguable.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, p. 6.</extension><space/>According to Glenn Stout, &quot;Ruth's home runs were exalted, uplifting experience that meant more to fans than any runs they were responsible for. A Babe Ruth home run was an event unto itself, one that meant anything was possible.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="st86"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth's penchant for hitting home runs altered how baseball is played. Prior to 1920, home runs were unusual, and managers tried to win games by getting a runner on base and bringing him around to score through such means as the stolen base, the<space/><link><target>bunt (baseball)</target><part>bunt</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>hit and run (baseball)</target><part>hit and run</part></link>. Advocates of what was dubbed &quot;inside baseball&quot;, such as Giants manager McGraw, disliked the home run, considering it a blot on the purity of the game.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 18.</extension><space/>According to sportswriter W. A. Phelon after the 1920 season, Ruth's breakout performance that season and the response in excitement and attendance, &quot;settled, for all time to come, that the American public is nuttier over the Home Run than the Clever Fielding or the Hitless Pitching. Viva el Home Run and two times viva Babe Ruth, exponent of the home run, and overshadowing star.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 236.</extension><space/>Bill James noted, &quot;When the owners discovered that the fans<space/><italics>liked</italics><space/>to see home runs, and when the foundations of the games were simultaneously imperiled by disgrace [in the Black Sox Scandal], then there was no turning back.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>James, p. 122</extension><space/>While a few, such as McGraw and Cobb, decried the passing of the old-style play, teams quickly began to seek and develop sluggers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, pp. 237239.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to contemporary sportswriter<space/><link><target>Grantland Rice</target></link>, only two sports figures of the 1920s approached Ruth in popularityboxer<space/><link><target>Jack Dempsey</target></link><space/>and racehorse<space/><link><target>Man o' War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. 200.</extension><space/>One of the factors that contributed to Ruth's broad appeal was the uncertainty about his family and early life. Ruth appeared to exemplify the American success story, that even an uneducated, unsophisticated youth, without any family wealth or connections, can do something better than anyone else in the world. Montville notes that &quot;the fog [surrounding his childhood] will make him forever accessible, universal. He will be the patron saint of American possibility.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 1314.</extension><space/>Similarly, the fact that Ruth played when a relatively small portion of his fans had the opportunity to see him play, in the era before television coverage of baseball, allowed his legend to grow through word of mouth and the hyperbole of sports reporters.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagenheim, pp. 67.</extension><space/>Reisler notes that recent sluggers who surpassed Ruth's 60-home run mark, such as<space/><link><target>Mark McGwire</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Barry Bonds</target></link>, generated much less excitement than when Ruth repeatedly broke the single-season home run record in the 1920s; Ruth dominated a relatively small sports world, while Americans of the present era have many sports available to watch.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reisler, p. xv.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Claire Ruth.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The unveiling of a Babe Ruth memorial plaque in Baltimore's old<space/><link><target>Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)</target><part>Memorial Stadium</part></link><space/>in 1955 with Claire Ruth, his widow, present.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Creamer termed Ruth &quot;a unique figure in the social history of the United States&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c16"></extension><space/>Ruth has even entered the language: a dominant figure in a field, whether within or outside sports, is often referred to as &quot;the Babe Ruth&quot; of that field.<extension extension_name='ref' name="c16"></extension><space/>Similarly, &quot;Ruthian&quot; has come to mean in sports, &quot;colossal, dramatic, prodigious, magnificent; with great power.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Dickson Baseball Dictionary</arg><arg name="edition">3rd</arg><arg name="first">Paul</arg><arg name="last">Dickson</arg><arg name="page">731</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">W.W. Norton & Co.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-393-07349-2</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>More books, Montville noted in 2006, have been written about Ruth than about any other member of the Baseball Hall of Fame. At least five of these books (including Creamer's and Wagenheim's) were written in 1973 and 1974, timed to capitalize on the increase in public interest in Ruth as<space/><link><target>Hank Aaron</target><part>Henry Aaron</part></link><space/>approached his career home run mark, which he broke on April 8, 1974.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 16.</extension><space/>Aaron stated as he approached Ruth's record, &quot;I can't remember a day this year or last when I did not hear the name of Babe Ruth.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="c16"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Montville suggests that Ruth is probably even more popular today than he was when his career home run record was broken by Aaron. The longball era that Ruth started continues in baseball, to the delight of the fans. Owners build ballparks to encourage home runs, which are featured on<space/><italics><link><target>SportsCenter</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Baseball Tonight</target></link></italics><space/>each evening during the season. The questions of<space/><link><target>performance-enhancing drug</target></link><space/>use, which have dogged recent home run hitters such as McGwire and Bonds, do nothing to diminish Ruth's reputation; his overindulgences with beer and hot dogs seem part of a simpler time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montville, pp. 45.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ruth has been named the greatest baseball player of all time in various surveys and rankings. In 1998,<space/><italics><link><target>The Sporting News</target></link></italics><space/>ranked him number one on the list of &quot;Baseball's 100 Greatest Players&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-almanac.com/legendary/lisn100.shtml</arg><arg name="title">Baseball's 100 Greatest Players</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Baseball Almanac</arg><arg name="accessdate">May 18, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1999, baseball fans named Ruth to the<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball All-Century Team</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">All-Century Team final voting</arg><arg name="publisher">ESPN. Associated Press</arg><arg name="date">October 23, 1999</arg><arg name="url">http://static.espn.go.com/mlb/news/1999/1023/129008.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">May 18, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>He was named baseball's Greatest Player Ever in a ballot commemorating the 100th anniversary of professional baseball, in 1969. The<space/><link><target>Associated Press</target></link><space/>reported in 1993 that<space/><link><target>Muhammad Ali</target></link><space/>was tied with Babe Ruth as the most recognized athletes in America.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Retton, Hammill most popular American athletes</arg><arg name="last">Wilstein</arg><arg name="first">Steve</arg><arg name="agency">Associated Press</arg><arg name="date">May 17, 1993</arg></template></extension><space/>In a 1999 ESPN poll, he was ranked as the second-greatest U.S. athlete of the century, behind<space/><link><target>Michael Jordan</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="topathlete2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/athletes.html</arg><arg name="title">ESPN: Top North American Athletes of the Century</arg><arg name="date">September 14, 1999</arg><arg name="work">ESPN SportsCentury</arg><arg name="publisher">ESPN.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 5, 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1983, the<space/><link><target>United States Postal Service</target></link><space/>honored Ruth with the issuance of a twenty-cent stamp.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Babe Ruth</arg><arg name="url">http://uspsstamps.com/stamps/babe-ruth</arg><arg name="publisher">[[United States Postal Service]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">May 13, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Babe Ruth Hall of Fame exhibit 2014.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ruth memorabilia at the<space/><link><target>Baseball Hall of Fame</target></link><space/>(2014)</part></link>One long-term survivor of the craze over Ruth may be the<space/><link><target>Baby Ruth</target></link><space/>candy bar. The original company to market the confectionery, the Curtis Candy Company, maintained that the bar was named after<space/><link><target>Ruth Cleveland</target></link>, daughter of former president<space/><link><target>Grover Cleveland</target></link>. She died in 1904 and the bar was first marketed in 1921, at the height of the craze over the slugger.<extension extension_name='ref'>Smelser, p. 208.</extension><space/>The slugger later sought to market candy bearing his name; he was refused a trademark because of the Baby Ruth bar. Corporate files from 1921 are no longer extant; the brand has changed hands several times and is now owned by the<space/><link><target>Nestl</target></link><space/>company. The Ruth estate licensed his likeness for use in an advertising campaign for Baby Ruth in 1995. Due to a marketing arrangement, in 2005, the Baby Ruth bar became the official candy bar of Major League Baseball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytimes2006"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/06/business/worldbusiness/06iht-web.0606ruth.1900800.html</arg><arg name="title">Baseball adopts a candy, whatever it's named for</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="last">Sandomir</arg><arg name="date">June 6, 2006</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 12, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Montville notes the continuing relevance of Babe Ruth in American culture, over three-quarters of a century after he last swung a bat in a major league game:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>
The fascination with his life and career continues. He is a bombastic, sloppy hero from our bombastic, sloppy history, origins undetermined, a folk tale of American success. His moon face is as recognizable today as it was when he stared out at Tom Zachary on a certain September afternoon in 1927. If sport has become the national religion, Babe Ruth is the patron saint. He stands at the heart of the game he played, the promise of a warm summer night, a bag of peanuts, and a beer. And just maybe, the longest ball hit out of the park.<ref>Montville, p. 367.</ref>
</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Biography</arg><arg>Baseball</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of career achievements by Babe Ruth</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Babe Ruth Award</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Babe Ruth Home Run Award</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Babe Ruth League</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>DHL Hometown Heroes</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball home run records</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball runs batted in records</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Year Babe Ruth Hit 104 Home Runs</target></link></italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Notes</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>notelist</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>References</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>20em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Appel
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Marty
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Marty Appel 
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pinstripe Empire: The New York Yankees From Before the Babe to After the Boss
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Bloombury USA
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-60819-492-6
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Creamer
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert W.
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Robert Creamer 
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992
<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1974
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Babe: The Legend Comes to Life
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>First Fireside
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Simon & Schuster]]
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-671-76070-X
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Graham
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Frank
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Frank Graham (writer)
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1943
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The New York Yankees: An Informal History
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>G.P. Putnam's Sons
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>1825210
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>James
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bill
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003
<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">2001
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>First Free Press trade paperback
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Bill James
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The New Bill James Historical Baseball Abstract
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Free Press
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7432-2722-3
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Montville
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Leigh
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Leigh Montville
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Big Bam: The Life and Times of Babe Ruth
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Broadway Books
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7679-1971-5
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Neyer</arg><arg name="first">Rob</arg><arg name="authorlink">Rob Neyer</arg><arg name="title">Rob Neyer's Big Book of Baseball Blunders</arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fireside Books</arg><arg name="location">New York City</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7432-8491-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Peluso
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ralph
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>512
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Solstice Publishing
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Missouri
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1625261342
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pietrusza
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>David Pietrusza
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Judge and Jury: The Life and Times of Judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Diamond Communications
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>South Bend, IN
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-888698-09-1
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Reisler
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jim
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Babe Ruth: Launching the Legend
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[McGraw-Hill]]
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-07-143244-2
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sherman
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ed
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Babe Ruth's Called Shot: The Myth and Mystery of Baseball's Greatest Home Run
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Lyons Press
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Guilford, CT
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7627-8539-1
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smelser
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Marshall
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1975
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Life That Ruth Built
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Quadrangle/New York Times Book Co
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8129-0540-7
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Spatz
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Lyle
<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Steinberg
<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Lyle
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>1921: The Yankees, The Giants, & The Battle For Baseball Supremacy in New York
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Nebraska Press
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Lincoln, NE
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8032-3999-9
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Stout
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Glenn
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Yankee Century: 100 Years of New York Yankees Baseball
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Houghton Mifflin Company
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-618-08527-0
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Wagenheim
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kal
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1974
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Babe Ruth: His Life and Legend
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Praeger Publishers
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-275-19980-0
</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Sisterlinks</target><arg name="d">Q213812</arg><arg name="species">no</arg><arg name="voy">no</arg><arg name="v">no</arg><arg name="b">no</arg><arg name="s">no</arg><arg name="wikt">no</arg><arg name="n">no</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.baberuth.com/'>BabeRuth.com</link>&amp;nbsp; Official site</listitem><listitem><template><target>Dmoz</target><arg>Sports/Baseball/People/Players/R/Ruth%2C_Babe/</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>bbhof</target><arg>ruth-babe</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.baberuthmuseum.com/'>baberuthmuseum.com</link><space/>Ruth Museum</listitem><listitem><template><target>IMDb name</target><arg name="id">0751899</arg><arg name="name">Babe Ruth</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Worldcat id</target><arg name="id">lccn-n79-141360</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Baseballstats</target><arg name="mlb">121578</arg><arg name="br">r/ruthba01</arg><arg name="fangraphs">1011327</arg><arg name="cube">babe-ruth</arg><arg name="brm">ruth—002geo</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In March 2011, the VOA<space/><link><target>Special English</target></link><space/>service of the<space/><link><target>Voice of America</target></link><space/>broadcast a 15-minute program on Babe Ruth. A transcript and MP3 of the program, intended for English learners, can be found at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.voanews.com/learningenglish/home/usa/Babe-Ruth1895-1948-Americas-Greatest-Baseball-Player--118712254.html'>Babe Ruth,18951948: America's Greatest Baseball Player</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start-collapsible</target><arg name="header">{{S-ach}}</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Bob Groom]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Major League Baseball no-hitters|No-hit game]]</arg><arg name="years">June 23, 1917<br />w/[[Ernie Shore]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Dutch Leonard (left-handed pitcher)|Dutch Leonard]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ach</target><arg>rec</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Roger Connor]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of lifetime home run leaders through history|Career home run record holder]]</arg><arg name="years">1921–74</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Hank Aaron]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Ned Williamson]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Major League Baseball progressive single-season home run leaders#Progression|Single season home run record holder]]</arg><arg name="years">1919–60</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Roger Maris]]</arg></template><template><target>S-sports</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Roger Peckinpaugh]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of New York Yankees team captains|New York Yankees team captain]]</arg><arg name="years">May 20, 1922&nbsp;– May 25, 1922</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Everett Scott]]</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template><template><target>Babe Ruth</target></template><template><target>navboxes</target><arg name="title"><space/>Articles related to Babe Ruth
</arg><arg name="list1">
{{MLBACT}}
{{MLBATT}}
{{Boston Red Sox Opening Day starting pitchers}}
{{New York Yankees}}
{{Yankees Retired Numbers}}
{{New York Yankees team captains}}
{{AL home run champions}}
{{AL batting title}}
{{AL RBI champions}}
{{AL ERA champions}}
{{AL League Award}}
{{500 home run club}}
{{1936 Baseball HOF}}
{{Baseball Hall of Fame outfielders}}
{{New York Yankees HOF}}
{{1915 Boston Red Sox}}
{{1916 Boston Red Sox}}
{{1918 Boston Red Sox}}
{{1923 New York Yankees}}
{{1927 New York Yankees}}
{{1928 New York Yankees}}
{{1932 New York Yankees}}
</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ruth, Babe</target></template><link><target>Category:1895 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1948 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:American League All-Stars</target></link><link><target>Category:American League batting champions</target></link><link><target>Category:American League ERA champions</target></link><link><target>Category:American League home run champions</target></link><link><target>Category:American League RBI champions</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of German descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Prussian descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American Roman Catholics</target></link><link><target>Category:Babe Ruth</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Baltimore Orioles (IL) players</target></link><link><target>Category:Baseball players from Maryland</target></link><link><target>Category:Boston Braves players</target></link><link><target>Category:Boston Red Sox players</target></link><link><target>Category:Brooklyn Dodgers coaches</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Gate of Heaven Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in New York</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from esophageal cancer</target></link><link><target>Category:Major League Baseball first base coaches</target></link><link><target>Category:Major League Baseball left fielders</target></link><link><target>Category:Major League Baseball pitchers</target></link><link><target>Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers</target></link><link><target>Category:Major League Baseball right fielders</target></link><link><target>Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:New York Yankees players</target></link><link><target>Category:Providence Grays (minor league) players</target></link><link><target>Category:Sportspeople from Baltimore, Maryland</target></link><link><target>Category:Vaudeville performers</target></link><link><target>Category:American sportsmen</target></link></paragraph></article>