<article title='Control_engineering'><paragraph><link><target>Image:Space Shuttle Columbia launching.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>320px</part><part>Control systems play a critical role in<space/><link><target>space flight</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Control engineering</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>control systems engineering</bold><space/>is the<space/><link><target>engineering</target></link><space/>discipline that applies<space/><link><target>control theory</target></link><space/>to design systems with desired behaviors. The practice uses<space/><link><target>sensors</target></link><space/>to measure the output performance of the device being controlled and those measurements can be used to give<space/><link><target>feedback</target></link><space/>to the input<space/><link><target>actuators</target></link><space/>that can make corrections toward desired performance. When a device is designed to perform without the need of human inputs for correction it is called<space/><link><target>automatic control</target></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>cruise control</target></link><space/>for regulating the speed of a car).<space/><link><target>Multi-disciplinary</target></link><space/>in nature, control systems engineering activities focus on implementation of control systems mainly derived by<space/><link><target>mathematical model</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>system</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of a diverse range.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview</heading><paragraph>Modern day control engineering is a relatively new field of study that gained significant attention during the 20th century with the advancement of technology. It can be broadly defined or classified as practical application of<space/><link><target>control theory</target></link>. Control engineering has an essential role in a wide range of control systems, from simple household washing machines to high-performance<space/><link><target>F-16</target></link><space/>fighter aircraft. It seeks to understand physical systems, using mathematical modeling, in terms of inputs, outputs and various components with different behaviors, use control systems design tools to develop<space/><link><target>Controller (control theory)</target><part>controller</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for those systems and implement controllers in physical systems employing available technology. A<space/><link><target>control system</target><part>system</part></link><space/>can be<space/><link><target>mechanical engineering</target><part>mechanical</part></link>,<space/><link><target>electrical engineering</target><part>electrical</part></link>,<space/><link><target>fluid</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chemical</target></link>,<space/><link><target>finance</target><part>financial</part></link><space/>and even<space/><link><target>biology</target><part>biological</part></link>, and the mathematical modeling, analysis and controller design uses<space/><link><target>control theory</target></link><space/>in one or many of the<space/><link><target>Time domain</target><part>time</part></link>,<space/><link><target>frequency domain</target><part>frequency</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>S domain</target><part>complex-s</part></link><space/>domains, depending on the nature of the design problem.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>Automatic control systems were first developed over two thousand years ago. The first feedback control device on record is thought to be the ancient<space/><link><target>Ktesibios</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>water clock</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link>, Egypt around the third century B.C. It kept time by regulating the water level in a vessel and, therefore, the water flow from that vessel. This certainly was a successful device as water clocks of similar design were still being made in Baghdad when the Mongols<space/><link><target>Siege of Baghdad (1258)</target><part>captured</part></link><space/>the city in 1258 A.D. A variety of automatic devices have been used over the centuries to accomplish useful tasks or simply to just entertain. The latter includes the automata, popular in Europe in the 17th and 18th centuries, featuring dancing figures that would repeat the same task over and over again; these automata are examples of open-loop control. Milestones among feedback, or &quot;closed-loop&quot; automatic control devices, include the temperature regulator of a furnace attributed to Drebbel, circa 1620, and the centrifugal flyball governor used for regulating the speed of steam engines by James Watt in 1788.</paragraph><paragraph>In his 1868 paper &quot;On Governors&quot;,<space/><link><target>James Clerk Maxwell</target></link><space/>was able to explain instabilities exhibited by the flyball governor using differential equations to describe the control system. This demonstrated the importance and usefulness of mathematical models and methods in understanding complex phenomena, and signaled the beginning of mathematical control and systems theory. Elements of control theory had appeared earlier but not as dramatically and convincingly as in Maxwell's analysis.</paragraph><paragraph>Control theory made significant strides in the next 100 years. New mathematical techniques made it possible to control, more accurately, significantly more complex dynamical systems than the original flyball governor. These techniques include developments in optimal control in the 1950s and 1960s, followed by progress in stochastic, robust, adaptive and optimal control methods in the 1970s and 1980s. Applications of control methodology have helped make possible space travel and communication satellites, safer and more efficient aircraft, cleaner auto engines, cleaner and more efficient chemical processes.</paragraph><paragraph>Before it emerged as a unique discipline, control engineering was practiced as a part of<space/><link><target>mechanical engineering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>control theory</target></link><space/>was studied as a part of<space/><link><target>electrical engineering</target></link><space/>since<space/><link><target>electrical circuits</target></link><space/>can often be easily described using control theory techniques. In the very first control relationships, a current output was represented with a voltage control input. However, not having proper technology to implement electrical control systems, designers left with the option of less efficient and slow responding mechanical systems. A very effective mechanical controller that is still widely used in some hydro plants is the<space/><link><target>Centrifugal governor</target><part>governor</part></link>. Later on, previous to modern<space/><link><target>power electronics</target></link>, process control systems for industrial applications were devised by mechanical engineers using<space/><link><target>pneumatics</target><part>pneumatic</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hydraulic system</target><part>hydraulic</part></link><space/>control devices, many of which are still in use today.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Control theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Control theory</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There are two major divisions in control theory, namely, classical and modern, which have direct implications over the control engineering applications. The scope of classical control theory is limited to<space/><link><target>Single-Input and Single-Output</target><part>single-input and single-output</part></link><space/>(SISO) system design, except when analyzing for disturbance rejection using a second input. The system analysis is carried out in the time domain using<space/><link><target>differential equations</target></link>, in the complex-s domain with the<space/><link><target>Laplace transform</target></link>, or in the frequency domain by transforming from the complex-s domain. Many systems may be assumed to have a second order and single variable system response in the time domain. A controller designed using classical theory often requires on-site tuning due to incorrect design approximations. Yet, due to the easier physical implementation of classical controller designs as compared to systems designed using modern control theory, these controllers are preferred in most industrial applications. The most common controllers designed using classical control theory are<space/><link><target>PID controller</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A less common implementation may include either or both a Lead or Lag filter. The ultimate end goal is to meet a requirements set typically provided in the time-domain called the Step response, or at times in the frequency domain called the Open-Loop response. The Step response characteristics applied in a specification are typically percent overshoot, settling time, etc. The Open-Loop response characteristics applied in a specification are typically Gain and Phase margin and bandwidth. These characteristics may be evaluated through simulation including a dynamic model of the system under control coupled with the compensation model.</paragraph><paragraph>In contrast, modern control theory is carried out in the<space/><link><target>state space (controls)</target><part>state space</part></link>, and can deal with multi-input and multi-output (<link><target>MIMO</target></link>) systems. This overcomes the limitations of classical control theory in more sophisticated design problems, such as fighter aircraft control, with the limitation that no frequency domain analysis is possible. In modern design, a system is represented to the greatest advantage as a set of decoupled first order<space/><link><target>differential equation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>defined using<space/><link><target>state variables</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Nonlinear control</target><part>Nonlinear</part></link>,<space/><link><target>multivariable control</target><part>multivariable</part></link>,<space/><link><target>adaptive control</target><part>adaptive</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>robust control</target></link><space/>theories come under this division. Matrix methods are significantly limited for MIMO systems where linear independence cannot be assured in the relationship between inputs and outputs. Being fairly new, modern control theory has many areas yet to be explored. Scholars like<space/><link><target>Rudolf E. Kalman</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aleksandr Lyapunov</target></link><space/>are well-known among the people who have shaped modern control theory.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Control systems</heading><paragraph>Control engineering is the engineering<space/><link><target>discipline</target></link><space/>that focuses on the<space/><link><target>mathematical model</target><part>modeling</part></link><space/>of a diverse range of<space/><link><target>dynamic systems</target></link><space/>(e.g.<space/><link><target>mechanics</target><part>mechanical</part></link><space/><link><target>system</target><trail>s</trail></link>) and the design of<space/><link><target>controller (control theory)</target><part>controller</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that will cause these systems to behave in the desired manner. Although such controllers need not be electrical many are and hence control engineering is often viewed as a subfield of electrical engineering. However, the falling price of microprocessors is making the actual implementation of a control system essentially trivial<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template>. As a result, focus is shifting back to the mechanical and process engineering discipline, as intimate knowledge of the physical system being controlled is often desired.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Electrical circuit</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>digital signal processor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>microcontroller</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can all be used to implement<space/><link><target>control system</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Control engineering has a wide range of applications from the flight and propulsion systems of<space/><link><target>Airliner</target><part>commercial airliners</part></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>cruise control</target></link><space/>present in many modern<space/><link><target>automobile</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In most of the cases, control engineers utilize<space/><link><target>feedback</target></link><space/>when designing<space/><link><target>control system</target><trail>s</trail></link>. This is often accomplished using a<space/><link><target>PID controller</target></link><space/>system. For example, in an<space/><link><target>automobile</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>cruise control</target></link><space/>the vehicle's<space/><link><target>speed</target></link><space/>is continuously monitored and fed back to the system, which adjusts the<space/><link><target>Internal combustion engine</target><part>motor's</part></link><space/><link><target>torque</target></link><space/>accordingly. Where there is regular feedback,<space/><link><target>control theory</target></link><space/>can be used to determine how the system responds to such feedback. In practically all such systems<space/><link><target>stability theory</target><part>stability</part></link><space/>is important and control theory can help ensure stability is achieved.</paragraph><paragraph>Although feedback is an important aspect of control engineering, control engineers may also work on the control of systems without feedback. This is known as<space/><link><target>open loop control</target></link>. A classic example of<space/><link><target>open loop control</target></link><space/>is a<space/><link><target>washing machine</target></link><space/>that runs through a pre-determined cycle without the use of<space/><link><target>sensor</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Control engineering education</heading><paragraph>At many universities, control engineering courses are taught in<space/><link><target>electrical engineering</target><part>electrical</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>electronic engineering</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mechatronics engineering</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mechanical engineering</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>aerospace engineering</target></link>. In others, control engineering is connected to<space/><link><target>computer science</target></link>, as most control techniques today are implemented through computers, often as<space/><link><target>embedded systems</target></link><space/>(as in the automotive field). The field of control within<space/><link><target>chemical engineering</target></link><space/>is often known as<space/><link><target>process control</target></link>. It deals primarily with the control of variables in a chemical process in a plant. It is taught as part of the undergraduate curriculum of any chemical engineering program and employs many of the same principles in control engineering. Other engineering disciplines also overlap with control engineering as it can be applied to any system for which a suitable model can be derived. However, specialised control engineering departments do exist, for example, the Department of Automatic Control and Systems Engineering at the University of Sheffield<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/acse</arg><arg name="website"></arg><arg name="title">ACSE - The University of Sheffield</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>and the Department of Systems Engineering at the United States Naval Academy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.usna.edu/WSE/</arg><arg name="website">USNA Weapons and Systems Engineering</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 November 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Control engineering has diversified applications that include science, finance management, and even human behavior. Students of control engineering may start with a linear control system course dealing with the time and complex-s domain, which requires a thorough background in elementary mathematics and<space/><link><target>Laplace transform</target></link>, called classical control theory. In linear control, the student does frequency and time domain analysis.<space/><link><target>Digital control</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>nonlinear control</target></link><space/>courses require<space/><link><target>Z transform</target><trail>ation</trail></link><space/>and algebra respectively, and could be said to complete a basic control education.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Recent advancement</heading><paragraph>Originally, control engineering was all about continuous systems. Development of computer control tools posed a requirement of discrete control system engineering because the communications between the computer-based digital controller and the physical system are governed by a<space/><link><target>computer clock</target></link>. The equivalent to<space/><link><target>Laplace transform</target></link><space/>in the discrete domain is the<space/><link><target>Z-transform</target></link>. Today, many of the control systems are computer controlled and they consist of both digital and analog components.</paragraph><paragraph>Therefore, at the design stage either digital components are mapped into the continuous domain and the design is carried out in the continuous domain, or analog components are mapped into discrete domain and design is carried out there. The first of these two methods is more commonly encountered in practice because many industrial systems have many continuous systems components, including mechanical, fluid, biological and analog electrical components, with a few digital controllers.</paragraph><paragraph>Similarly, the design technique has progressed from paper-and-ruler based manual design to<space/><link><target>computer-aided design</target></link><space/>and now to<space/><link><target>computer-automated design</target></link><space/>or CAutoD which has been made possible by<space/><link><target>evolutionary computation</target></link>. CAutoD can be applied not just to tuning a predefined control scheme, but also to controller structure optimisation, system identification and invention of novel control systems, based purely upon a performance requirement, independent of any specific control scheme.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tan, K.C. and Li, Y. (2001) Performance-based control system design automation via evolutionary computing. Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence, 14 (4). pp. 473-486. ISSN 0952-1976, http://eprints.gla.ac.uk/3807/</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Li, Y., et al. (2004). CAutoCSD - Evolutionary search and optimisation enabled computer automated control system design. International Journal of Automation and Computing, 1(1). pp.76-88. ISSN 1751-8520, http://eprints.gla.ac.uk/3818/</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Resilient Control Systems</target></link><space/>extends the traditional focus on addressing only plant disturbances to frameworks, architectures and methods that address multiple types of unexpected disturbance. In particular, adapting and transforming behaviors of the control system in response to malicious actors, abnormal failure modes, undesirable human action, etc. Development of resilience technologies require the involvement of multidisciplinary teams to holistically address the performance challenges.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Adaptive control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Advanced process control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Building automation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Coefficient diagram method</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computer-automated design</target></link><space/>(CAutoD, CAutoCSD)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Control reconfiguration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Control theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Feedback</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>H-infinity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Intelligent control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Laplace transform</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of electrical engineering topics#Control engineering</target><part>List of control engineering topics</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Model predictive control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nonlinear control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Optimal control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>PID controller</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Process control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quantitative feedback theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Unicycle cart</target><part>Robotic unicycle</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robust control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Servomechanism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>State space (controls)</target><part>State space</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sliding mode control</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>TPT (Software)</target><part>Testing controller</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>VisSim</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Control Engineering (magazine)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>EICASLAB</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Time series</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Christopher Kilian<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Modern Control Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Thompson Delmar Learning<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4018-5806-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>IET<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-86341-047-5<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Bennett<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Stuart<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A history of control engineering, 1800-1930<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 1986</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>IET<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-86341-299-8<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Bennett<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Stuart<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A history of control engineering, 1930-1955<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1993<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Arnold Zankl<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Milestones in Automation: From the Transistor to the Digital Factory<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wiley-VCH<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>3-89578-259-9</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikibooks</target><arg>Control Systems</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www-control.eng.cam.ac.uk/extras/Virtual_Library/Control_VL.html'>Control Labs Worldwide</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://controls.engin.umich.edu/wiki'>The Michigan Chemical Engineering Process Dynamics and Controls Open Textbook</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Systems Engineering</target></template><template><target>Technology</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Control Engineering</target></template><link><target>Category:Electrical engineering</target></link><link><target>Category:Control engineering</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Systems engineering</target></link><link><target>Category:Engineering disciplines</target></link></paragraph></article>