<article title='Banquo'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the character in Shakespeare's Macbeth</arg><arg>the small town in the United States</arg><arg>Banquo, Indiana</arg></template><template><target>good article</target></template><template><target>Infobox Shakespearean character</target><arg name="name"><space/>Banquo
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Banquo.jpg
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>Painting showing Elizabethan era men at a dining table, with a ghost sitting on one of the stools.
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>[[Théodore Chassériau]] (1819–1856), ''The Ghost of Banquo'' 1855
</arg><arg name="creator"><space/>[[William Shakespeare]]
</arg><arg name="play"><space/>[[Macbeth]]
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>ca.1603–6
</arg><arg name="source"><space/>[[Holinshed's Chronicles]]
</arg><arg name="other_names"><space/>
</arg><arg name="family"><space/>[[Fleance]], [[James I]]
</arg><arg name="associates"><space/>
</arg><arg name="role"><space/>
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Or have we eaten on the insane root<br>That takes the reason prisoner?
</arg><arg name="portrayed_by"><space/>
</arg><arg name="see_also"><space/>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lord<space/><bold>Banquo</bold><space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>ŋ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>w</arg><arg>oʊ</arg></template>, Thane of Lochaber, is a character in<space/><link><target>William Shakespeare</target></link>'s 1606 play<space/><italics><link><target>Macbeth</target></link></italics>. In the play, he is at first an ally to<space/><link><target>Macbeth (character)</target><part>Macbeth</part></link><space/>(both are generals in the King's army) and they are together when they meet the<space/><link><target>Three Witches</target></link>. After prophesying that Macbeth will become king, the witches tell Banquo that he will not be king himself, but that his descendants will be. Later, Macbeth in his lust for power sees Banquo as a threat and has him murdered; Banquo's son,<space/><link><target>Fleance</target></link>, escapes. Banquo's ghost returns in a later scene, causing Macbeth to react with alarm during a public feast.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Shakespeare borrowed the character of Banquo from<space/><italics>Holinshed's Chronicles</italics>, a history of Britain published by<space/><link><target>Raphael Holinshed</target></link><space/>in 1587. In<space/><italics>Chronicles</italics><space/>Banquo is an accomplice to Macbeth in the murder of the king, rather than a loyal subject of the king who is seen as an enemy by Macbeth. Shakespeare may have changed this aspect of his character in order to please<space/><link><target>James I of England</target><part>King James</part></link>, who was thought at the time to be a descendant of the real Banquo. Critics often interpret Banquo's role in the play as being a<space/><link><target>Foil (literature)</target><part>foil</part></link><space/>to Macbeth, resisting evil where Macbeth embraces it. Sometimes, however, his motives are unclear, and some critics question his purity. He does nothing to accuse Macbeth of murdering the king, even though he has reason to believe Macbeth is responsible.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Source</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Holinshed's Chronicles</arg></template><link><target>Image:Macbeth and Banquo encountering the witches - Holinshed Chronicles.gif</target><part>alt=Two men on horseback meet three women. All are in Elizabethan dress.</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Macbeth and Banquo meeting the witches in a woodcut from ''Holinshed's Chronicles''</part></link><space/>Shakespeare often used<space/><link><target>Raphael Holinshed</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Chronicles of England, Scotland, and Ireland</italics>commonly known as<space/><italics><link><target>Holinshed's Chronicles</target></link></italics>as a source for his plays, and in<space/><italics><link><target>Macbeth</target></link></italics><space/>he borrows from several of the tales in that work.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Coursen<space/></arg><arg name="first">Herbert<space/></arg><arg name="title">Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Greenwood Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Westport<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-313-30047-X<space/></arg><arg name="pages">15–21</arg></template></extension><space/>Holinshed portrays Banquo as a historical figure: he is an accomplice in<space/><link><target>Macbeth of Scotland</target><part>Mac Bethad mac Findlach's</part></link><space/>(Macbeth's) murder of<space/><link><target>Duncan I of Scotland</target><part>Donnchad mac Crnin</part></link><space/>(King Duncan) and plays an important part in ensuring that Macbeth, not<space/><link><target>Malcolm III of Scotland</target><part>Mel Coluim mac Donnchada</part></link><space/>(Malcolm), takes the throne in the coup that follows.<extension extension_name='ref' name="note"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Nagarajan<space/></arg><arg name="first">S.<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Note on Banquo<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Shakespeare Quarterly]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 1956<space/></arg><arg name="volume">7<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">371–6<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Folger Shakespeare Library]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2866356</arg></template></extension><space/>Holinshed in turn used an earlier work, the<space/><italics>Scotorum Historiae</italics><space/>(15267) by<space/><link><target>Hector Boece</target></link>, as his source. Boece's work is the first known record of Banquo and his son<space/><link><target>Fleance</target></link>; and scholars such as<space/><link><target>David Bevington</target></link><space/>generally consider them fictional characters invented by Boece. In Shakespeare's day, however, they were considered historical figures of great repute, and the king,<space/><link><target>James I of England</target><part>James I</part></link>, based his claim to the throne in part on a descent from Banquo.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Four Tragedies<space/></arg><arg name="last">Bevington<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bantam<space/></arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-553-21283-4<space/></arg><arg name="page">714</arg></template></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>House of Stuart</target></link><space/>was descended from<space/><link><target>Walter fitz Alan</target></link>, the first<space/><link><target>High Steward of Scotland</target></link>, and he was believed to have been the grandson of Fleance and<space/><link><target>Gruffydd ap Llywelyn</target></link>'s daughter,<space/><link><target>Nesta verch Gruffydd</target></link>. In reality Walter fitz Alan was the son of<space/><link><target>Alan fitz Flaad</target></link>, a Breton knight.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Palmer<space/></arg><arg name="first">J. Foster<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Celt in Power: Tudor and Cromwell<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Transactions of the Royal Historical Society<space/></arg><arg name="year">1886<space/></arg><arg name="volume">3<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">343–70<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3677851<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Royal Historical Society]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unlike his sources, Shakespeare gives Banquo no role in the King's murder, making it a deed committed solely by Macbeth and his wife. Why Shakespeare's Banquo is so different from the character described by Holinshed and Boece is not known, though critics have proposed several possible explanations. First among them is the risk associated with portraying the king's ancestor as a murderer and conspirator in the plot to overthrow a rightful king, as well as the author's desire to flatter a powerful patron. But Shakespeare may also simply have altered Banquo's character because there was no dramatic need for another accomplice to the murder. There was, however, a need to provide a dramatic contrast to Macbeth; a role that many scholars argue is filled by Banquo.<extension extension_name='ref' name="note"></extension><space/>Similarly, when<space/><link><target>Jean de Schelandre</target></link><space/>wrote about Banquo in his<space/><italics><link><target>Stuartide</target></link></italics><space/>in 1611, he also changed the character by portraying him as a noble and honourable manthe critic D. W. Maskell describes him as Schelandre's paragon of valour and virtueprobably for reasons similar to Shakespeare's.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Transformation of History into Epic: The "Stuartide" (1611) of Jean de Schelandre<space/></arg><arg name="last">Maskell<space/></arg><arg name="first">D. W.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[The Modern Language Review]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 1971<space/></arg><arg name="volume">66<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">53–65<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3722467<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Modern Humanities Research Association]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Banquo's role in the coup that follows the murder is harder to explain. Banquo's loyalty to Macbeth, rather than<space/><link><target>Malcolm (Macbeth)</target><part>Malcolm</part></link>, after Duncan's death makes him a passive accomplice in the coup: Malcolm, as Prince of Cumberland, is the rightful heir to the throne and Macbeth a usurper. Daniel Amneus, however, argues that when Ross and Angus bring King Duncan's praise, and the news that Macbeth has been granted the title of Thane of Cawdor, the &quot;greater honor&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T13.html#104'>''Macbeth'', Act 1, Scene 3, line 104.</link></extension><space/>he ascribes to Macbeth is actually his title as Prince of Cumberland. If Macbeth, rather than Malcolm, is Prince of Cumberland then Macbeth would be next in line to the throne and no coup would be needed, effectively removing this ambiguity from Banquo's character.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Amneus<space/></arg><arg name="first">Daniel<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Macbeth's “Greater Honor”<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Barroll<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">J. Leeds<space/></arg><arg name="title">Shakespeare Studies<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Burt Franklin<space/></arg><arg name="year">1978<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-89102-084-5<space/></arg><arg name="pages">223–30</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Role in the play</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Macbeth and Banquo with the witches JHF.jpg</target><part>alt=Dark painting showing two figures encountering witch-like creatures.</part><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''Macbeth and Banquo with the Witches'' by<space/><link><target>Henry Fuseli</target></link></part></link>Banquo is in a third of the play's scenes, as both a human and a ghost. As significant as he is to the plot, he has fewer lines than the relatively insignificant Ross, a Scottish nobleman who survives the play.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Braunmuller<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. R.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="title">Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">A. R.<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Braunmuller<space/></arg><arg name="series">The New Cambridge Shakespeare<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-29455-X<space/></arg><arg name="page">266</arg></template></extension><space/>In the second scene of the play, King Duncan describes the manner in which Macbeth, Thane of Glamis, and Banquo, Thane of Lochaber, bravely led his army against invaders, fighting side by side. In the next scene, Banquo and Macbeth, returning from the battle together, encounter the<space/><link><target>Three Witches</target></link>, who predict that Macbeth will become Thane of Cawdor, and then king. Banquo, skeptical of the witches, challenges them to predict his own future, and they foretell that Banquo will never himself take the throne, but will beget a line of kings. Banquo remains skeptical after the encounter, wondering aloud if evil can ever speak the truth. He warns Macbeth that evil will offer men a small, hopeful truth only in order to catch them in a deadly trap.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T13.html'>''Macbeth.'' Act 1, Scene 3.</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When Macbeth kills the king and takes the throne, Banquothe only one aware of this encounter with the witchesreserves judgment for God. He is unsure whether Macbeth committed regicide to gain the throne, but muses in a<space/><link><target>soliloquy</target></link><space/>that &quot;I fear / Thou play'dst most foully for 't&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T31.html#2'>''Macbeth'', Act 3, Scene 1, lines 23.</link></extension><space/>He offers his respects to the new King Macbeth and pledges loyalty.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T31.html'>''Macbeth.'' Act 3, Scene 1.</link></extension><space/>Later, worried that Banquo's descendants and not his own will rule<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link>, Macbeth sends men to kill Banquo and his son<space/><link><target>Fleance</target></link>. During the melee, Banquo holds off the assailants so that Fleance can escape, but is himself killed.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T33.html'>''Macbeth.'' Act 3, Scene 3.</link></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Ghosts in European culture</target><part>ghost</part></link><space/>of Banquo later returns to haunt Macbeth at the banquet in act three, scene four. A terrified Macbeth sees him, while the apparition is invisible to his guests. He appears again to Macbeth in a vision granted by the Three Witches, wherein Macbeth sees a long line of kings descended from Banquo.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T41.html'>''Macbeth.'' Act 4, Scene 1.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Analysis</heading><heading level='3'>Foil to Macbeth</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Macbeth and Banquo Meeting the Weird Sisters JW-detail.jpg</target><part>alt=Painting showing men meeting three figures emerging from a cave.</part><part>thumb</part><part>''Macbeth and Banquo Meeting the Three Witches'' by<space/><link><target>John Wootton</target></link></part></link>Many scholars see Banquo as a<space/><link><target>foil (literature)</target><part>foil</part></link><space/>and a contrast to Macbeth. Macbeth, for example, eagerly accepts the Three Witches' prophecy as true and seeks to help it along. Banquo, on the other hand, doubts the prophecies and the intentions of these seemingly evil creatures. Whereas Macbeth places his hope in the prediction that he will be king, Banquo argues that evil only offers gifts that lead to destruction. Banquo steadily resists the temptations of evil within the play, praying to heaven for help, while Macbeth seeks darkness, and prays that evil powers will aid him. This is visible in act two; after Banquo sees Duncan to bed, he says: &quot;There's husbandry in heaven, / Their candles are all out&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="shakespeare-navigators.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T21.html#4'>''Macbeth'', Act 2, Scene 1, lines 45.</link></extension><space/>This premonition of the coming darkness in association with Macbeth's murders is repeated just before Banquo is killed: &quot;it will be rain to-night&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T33.html#16'>''Macbeth'', Act 3, Scene 3, line 16.</link></extension><space/>Banquo tells his son Fleance.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Watson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert N.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">“Thriftless Ambition,” Foolish Wishes, and the Tragedy of Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="title">William Shakespeare's Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Harold<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Bloom<space/></arg><arg name="series">Modern Critical Interpretations<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Chelsea House Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="year">1987<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-87754-930-3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">133–68</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Banquo's status as a contrast to Macbeth makes for some tense moments in the play. In act two, scene one, Banquo meets his son Fleance and asks him to take both his sword and his dagger (&quot;Hold, take my sword&amp;nbsp;... Take thee that too&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="shakespeare-navigators.com"></extension>). He also explains that he has been having trouble sleeping due to &quot;cursed thoughts that nature / gives way to in repose!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T21.html#8'>''Macbeth'', Act 2, Scene 1, lines 89.</link></extension><space/>On Macbeth's approach, he demands the sword returned to him quickly. Scholars have interpreted this to mean that Banquo has been dreaming of murdering the king as Macbeth's accomplice in order to take the throne for his own family, as the Three Witches prophesied to him. In this reading, his good nature is so revolted by these thoughts that he gives his sword and dagger to Fleance to be sure they do not come true, but is so nervous at Macbeth's approach that he demands them back.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>A Note on "Macbeth," Act II, Scene 1<space/></arg><arg name="last">Westbrook<space/></arg><arg name="first">Perry D.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[College English]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 1946<space/></arg><arg name="volume">7<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">219–20<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/371197<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Council of Teachers of English]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Other scholars have responded that Banquo's dreams have less to do with killing the king and more to do with Macbeth. They argue that Banquo is merely setting aside his sword for the night. Then, when Macbeth approaches, Banquo, having had dreams about Macbeth's deeds, takes back his sword as a precaution in this case.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Banquo, Loyal Subject<space/></arg><arg name="last">Henneberger<space/></arg><arg name="first">Olive<space/></arg><arg name="journal">College English<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 1946<space/></arg><arg name="volume">8<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">18–22<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/370443<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">National Council of Teachers of English</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Macbeth eventually sees that Banquo can no longer be trusted to aid him in his evil, and considers his friend a threat to his newly acquired throne. Thus he has him murdered.<extension extension_name='ref' name="note"></extension><space/>Banquo's ability to live on in different ways is another oppositional force, in this case to Macbeth's impending death. His spirit lives on in Fleance, his son, and in his ghostly presence at the banquet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Calderwood<space/></arg><arg name="first">James L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">If It Were Done: Macbeth and Tragic Action<space/></arg><arg name="location">Amherst<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Massachusetts Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986<space/></arg><arg name="pages">96–7<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87023-534-4</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ghost scenes</heading><paragraph>When Macbeth returns to the witches later in the play, they show him an apparition of the murdered Banquo, along with eight of his descendants. The scene carries deep significance: King James, on the throne when<space/><italics>Macbeth</italics><space/>was written, was believed to be separated from Banquo by nine generations. What Shakespeare writes here thus amounts to a strong support of James' right to the throne by lineage, and for audiences of Shakespeare's day, a very real fulfillment of the witches' prophecy to Banquo that his sons would take the throne.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">"Macbeth": King James's Play<space/></arg><arg name="last">Williams<space/></arg><arg name="first">George Walton<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[South Atlantic Review]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 1982<space/></arg><arg name="volume">47<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">12–21<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3199207</arg></template></extension><space/>This apparition is also deeply unsettling to Macbeth, who not only wants the throne for himself, but also desires to father a line of kings.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Apparitions in Macbeth, Part II<space/></arg><arg name="last">Crawford<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. W.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Modern Language Notes]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">November 1924<space/></arg><arg name="volume">39<space/></arg><arg name="issue">7<space/></arg><arg name="pages">383–8<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Johns Hopkins University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2914760</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Banquo's other appearance as a ghost during the banquet scene serves as an indicator of Macbeth's conscience returning to plague his thoughts. Banquo's triumph over death appears symbolically, insofar as he literally takes Macbeth's seat during the feast. Shocked, Macbeth uses words appropriate to the metaphor of usurpation, describing Banquo as &quot;crowned&quot; with wounds. The spirit drains Macbeth's manhood along with the blood from his cheeks; as soon as Banquo's form vanishes, Macbeth announces: &quot;Why, so; being gone, / I am a man again.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.clicknotes.com/macbeth/T34.html#106'>''Macbeth'', Act 3, Scene 4, lines 106107.</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Calder"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Calderwood<space/></arg><arg name="first">James L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">If It Were Done: Macbeth and Tragic Action<space/></arg><arg name="location">Amherst<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Massachusetts Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986<space/></arg><arg name="pages">126–9<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87023-534-4</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Like the vision of Banquo's lineage, the banquet scene has also been the subject of criticism. Critics have questioned whether not one, but perhaps two ghosts appear in this scene: Banquo and Duncan. Scholars arguing that Duncan attends the banquet state that Macbeth's lines to the Ghost could apply equally well to the slain king. &quot;Thou canst not say I did it&quot;, for example, can mean that Macbeth is not the man who actually killed Banquo, or it can mean that Duncan, who was asleep when Macbeth killed him, cannot claim to have seen his killer. To add to the confusion, some lines Macbeth directs to the ghost, such as &quot;Thy bones are marrowless&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.clicknotes.com/macbeth/T34.html#94'>''Macbeth'', Act 3, Scene 4, line 91.</link></extension><space/>cannot rightly be said of Banquo, who has only recently died.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Furness"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Furness<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Horace Howard<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-link">Horace Howard Furness<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Classic Books<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7426-5283-1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">167–9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Scholars debate whether Macbeth's vision of Banquo is real or a hallucination. Macbeth had already seen a hallucination before murdering Duncan: a knife hovering in the air. Several performances of the play have even ignored the stage direction to have the Ghost of Banquo enter at all, heightening the sense that Macbeth is growing mad, since the audience cannot see what he claims to see. Scholars opposing this view claim that while the dagger is unusual, ghosts of murdered victims are more believable, having a basis in the audience's superstitions. Spirits in other Shakespeare playsnotably<space/><italics><link><target>Hamlet</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Midsummer Night's Dream</target></link></italics>exist in ambiguous forms, occasionally even calling into question their own presence.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Calder"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Furness"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bradley<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">A. C. Bradley<space/></arg><arg name="title">Shakespearean Tragedy<space/></arg><arg name="location">Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Adamant Media<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4212-0849-0<space/></arg><arg name="pages">492–3</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The concept of a character being confronted at a triumphant feast with a reminder of their downfall is not unique to Shakespeare and may originate from the<space/><link><target>Belshazzar's feast</target></link><space/>episode of the Bible. The term 'ghost at the feast' is has entered popular culture, and is often used as a metaphor for a subject a person would rather avoid considering, or (considering the general plot of<space/><italics>Macbeth</italics>) a reminder of a person's unpleasant past or likely future.<space/></paragraph><heading level='2'>Performances and interpretations</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Macbeth-07-Lee.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Canada Lee</target></link><space/>as Banquo in the<space/><link><target>Federal Theatre Project</target></link><space/>production of ''<link><target>Voodoo Macbeth</target><part>Macbeth</part></link>'' (1936)</part></link>Banquo's role, especially in the banquet ghost scene, has been subject to a variety of interpretations and mediums. Shakespeare's text states: &quot;Enter Ghost of Banquo, and sits in Macbeth's place.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.shakespeare-navigators.com/macbeth/T34.html#36'>''Macbeth'', Act 3, Scene 4.</link></extension><space/>Several television versions have altered this slightly, having Banquo appear suddenly in the chair, rather than walking onstage and into it. Special effects and camera tricks also allow producers to make the ghost disappear and reappear, highlighting the fact that<space/><italics>only</italics><space/>Macbeth can see it.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Imperial Theme: "Macbeth" on Television<space/></arg><arg name="last">Jones<space/></arg><arg name="first">Claude E.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The Quarterly of Film Radio and Television<space/></arg><arg name="date">April 1955<space/></arg><arg name="volume">9<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">292–8<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of California Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1525/fq.1955.9.3.04a00070</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Stage directors, unaided by post-production effects and camera tricks, have used other methods to depict the ghost. In the late 19th century, elaborate productions of the play staged by<space/><link><target>Henry Irving</target></link><space/>employed a wide variety of approaches for this task. In 1877 a green silhouette was used to create a ghostlike image; ten years later a trick chair was used to allow an actor to appear in the middle of the scene, and then again from the midst of the audience. In 1895 a shaft of blue light served to indicate the presence of Banquo's spirit. In 1933 a Russian director named Theodore Komisarjevsky staged a modern retelling of the play (Banquo and Macbeth were told of their future through<space/><link><target>palmistry</target></link>); he used Macbeth's shadow as the ghost.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barnet"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Barnet<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sylvan<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">''Macbeth'' on Stage and Screen<space/></arg><arg name="title">Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Sylvan<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Barnet<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books<space/></arg><arg name="year">1963<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-451-52444-6<space/></arg><arg name="pages">186–200</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1936<space/><link><target>Orson Welles</target></link><space/>directed the<space/><link><target>Federal Theatre Project</target></link><space/><link><target>Voodoo Macbeth</target><part>production of the play</part></link>, with an<space/><link><target>African-American</target></link><space/>cast that included<space/><link><target>Canada Lee</target></link><space/>in the role of Banquo.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barnet"></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Film adaptations have approached Banquo's character in a variety of ways.<space/><link><target>Akira Kurosawa</target></link>'s 1957 adaptation<space/><italics><link><target>Throne of Blood</target></link></italics><space/>makes the character into Capitan Miki (played by<space/><link><target>Minoru Chiaki</target></link>), slain by Macbeth's equivalent (Captain Washizu) when his wife explains that she is with child. News of Miki's death does not reach Washizu until after he has seen the ghost in the banquet scene. In<space/><link><target>Roman Polanski</target></link>'s 1971<space/><link><target>Macbeth (1971 film)</target><part>adaptation</part></link>, Banquo is played by acclaimed stage actor<space/><link><target>Martin Shaw</target></link>, in a style reminiscent of earlier stage performances.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Braunmuller<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. R.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="title">Macbeth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">A. R.<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Braunmuller<space/></arg><arg name="series">The New Cambridge Shakespeare<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-29455-X<space/></arg><arg name="pages">85–6</arg></template></extension><space/>Polanski's version also emphasises Banquo's objection to Macbeth's ascendency by showing him remaining silent as the other thanes around him hail Macbeth as king.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor1-last">Halio<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Jay L.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Richmond<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Hugh<space/></arg><arg name="title">Shakespearean illuminations: essays in honor of Marvin Rosenberg<space/></arg><arg name="location">Newark<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Delaware Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-87413-657-1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">135–6<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Gleanings: The Residue of Difference in Scripts: The Case of Polanski's ''Macbeth''<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kliman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bernice W.</arg></template></extension><space/>in the 1990 telling of Macbeth in a New York Mafia crime family setting,<space/><italics><link><target>Men of Respect</target></link></italics>, the character of Banquo is named &quot;Bankie Como&quot; and played by American actor<space/><link><target>Dennis Farina</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of ghosts</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template><template><target>Macbeth</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1603</target></link><link><target>Category:Characters in Macbeth</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional generals</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional ghosts</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional Scottish people</target></link><link><target>Category:Male Shakespearean characters</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional lords and ladies</target></link></paragraph></article>