<article title='Transport_in_the_Democratic_Republic_of_the_Congo'><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">March 2013</arg></template><link><target>Image:Congo Transport Map.PNG</target><part>thumb</part><part>550px</part><part>A diagrammatic map of ground and water transport in the DR&amp;nbsp;Congo in 2000 (roads) and 2006 (waterways and railways)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Ground<space/><bold>transport in the<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of Congo</target></link></bold><space/>(DRC) has always been difficult. The terrain and climate of the<space/><link><target>Congo Basin</target></link><space/>present serious barriers to road and rail construction, and the distances are enormous across this vast country. Furthermore, chronic economic mismanagement and internal conflict has led to serious under-investment over many years.</paragraph><paragraph>On the other hand, the<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of Congo</target><part>DRC</part></link><space/>has thousands of kilometres of<space/><link><target>navigable</target></link><space/><link><target>waterway</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and traditionally water transport has been the dominant means of moving around approximately two-thirds of the country.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Transport problems</heading><paragraph>As an illustration of transport difficulties in the DRC, even before wars damaged the infrastructure, the so-called &quot;national&quot; route, used to get supplies to<space/><link><target>Bukavu</target></link><space/>from the seaport of<space/><link><target>Matadi</target></link>, consisted of the following:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Matadi to<space/><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link><space/>rail</listitem><listitem>Kinshasa to<space/><link><target>Kisangani</target></link><space/><link><target>Riverboat</target><part>river boat</part></link></listitem><listitem>Kisangani to<space/><link><target>Ubundu</target></link><space/>rail</listitem><listitem>Ubundu to<space/><link><target>Kindu</target></link><space/>river boat</listitem><listitem>Kindu to<space/><link><target>Kalemie</target></link><space/>rail</listitem><listitem>Kalemie to Kalundu (the lake port at<space/><link><target>Uvira</target></link>) boat on<space/><link><target>Lake Tanganyika</target></link></listitem><listitem>Kalundu to Bukavu road</listitem></list><paragraph>In other words, goods had to be loaded and unloaded eight times and the total journey would take many months.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of the routes listed below are in poor condition and may be operating at only a fraction of their original capacity (if at all), despite recent attempts to make improvements. Up to 2006 the<space/><link><target>United Nations Joint Logistics Centre</target></link><space/>(UNJLC) had an operation in Congo to support<space/><link><target>humanitarian relief</target></link><space/>agencies working there, and its bulletins and maps about the transport situation are archived on the UNJLC web site.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.unjlc.org/23003/DRC/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>First Congo War</target><part>First</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Second Congo War</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>saw great destruction of transport infrastructure from which the country has not yet recovered. Many vehicles were destroyed or commandeered by<space/><link><target>militia</target><trail>s</trail></link>, especially in the north and east of the country, and the fuel supply system was also badly affected. Consequently, outside of<space/><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Matadi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lubumbashi</target></link>, private and commercial road transport is almost non-existent and traffic is scarce even where roads are in good condition. The few vehicles in use outside these cities are run by the<space/><link><target>MONUC</target><part>United Nations</part></link>, aid agencies, the DRC government, and a few larger companies such as those in the mining and energy sectors. It is notable that high-resolution satellite photos on the Internet show large cities such as<space/><link><target>Bukavu</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Butembo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kikwit</target></link><space/>virtually devoid of traffic, compared to similar photos of towns in neighbouring countries.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.earth.google.com'>Google Earth</link><space/>retrieved 24 September 2007.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Air transport is the only effective means of moving between many places within the country. The Congolese government, the United Nations, aid organisations and large companies use air rather than ground transport to move personnel and freight. The UN operates a large fleet of aircraft and helicopters, and compared to other African countries the DRC has a large number of small domestic airlines and air charter companies. The transport (and smuggling) of minerals with a high value for weight is also carried out by air, and in the east, some stretches of paved road isolated by destroyed bridges or impassable sections have been turned into airstrips.</paragraph><paragraph>For the ordinary citizen though, especially in rural areas, often the only options are to cycle, walk or go by dugout canoe.</paragraph><paragraph>Some parts of the DRC are more accessible from neighbouring countries than from<space/><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link>. For example Bukavu itself and<space/><link><target>Goma</target></link><space/>and other north-eastern towns are linked by paved road from the DRC border to the<space/><link><target>Kenya</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>port of<space/><link><target>Mombasa</target></link>, and most goods for these cities have been brought via this route in recent years. Similarly,<space/><link><target>Lubumbashi</target></link><space/>and the rest of<space/><link><target>Katanga Province</target></link><space/>is linked to<space/><link><target>Zambia</target></link>, through which the paved highway and rail networks of Southern Africa can be accessed. Such links through neighbouring countries are generally more important for the east and south-east of the country, and are more heavily used, than surface links to the capital.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Major infrastructure programs</heading><paragraph>In 2007<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>agreed to lend the DRC US$5bn for two major transport infrastructure projects to link mineral-rich Katanga, specifically Lubumbashi, by rail to an ocean port (<link><target>Matadi</target></link>) and by road to the Kisangani river port, and to improve its links to the transport network of Southern Africa in Zambia. The two projects would also link the major parts of the country not served by water transport, and the main centres of the economy. Loan repayments will be from concessions for raw materials which China desperately needs: copper, cobalt, gold and nickel, as well as by toll revenues from the road and railway. In the face of reluctance by the international business community to invest in DRC, this represents a revitalisation of DRC's infrastructure much needed by its government.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.moneyweb.co.za/mw/view/mw/en/page149519?oid=170139&amp;amp;sn=Blog%20detail%20back%20button'>Felicity Duncan: &quot;Turning Chinese?&quot;</link><space/><italics>Moneyweb Undictated</italics><space/>website (South Africa), 12 November 2007.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>China Railway Seventh Group Co. Ltd</target></link><space/>will be in charge of the contract, under signed by the<space/><link><target>China Railway Engineering Corporation</target></link>, with construction to be started from June 2008.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Railways</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Rail transport in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</arg></template><link><target>Image:First train in Kindu, DRC.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Train from<space/><link><target>Lubumbashi</target></link><space/>arriving in<space/><link><target>Kindu</target></link><space/>on newly refurbished line</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Highways</heading><paragraph>The Democratic Republic of the Congo has fewer all-weather paved highways than any country of its population and size in Africa a total of 2250&amp;nbsp;km, of which only 1226&amp;nbsp;km is in good condition (see below). To put this in perspective, the road distance across the country in any direction is more than 2500&amp;nbsp;km (e.g. Matadi to Lubumbushi, 2700&amp;nbsp;km by road). The figure of 2250&amp;nbsp;km converts to 35&amp;nbsp;km of paved road per 1,000,000 of population. Comparative figures for Zambia and Botswana are 721&amp;nbsp;km and 3427&amp;nbsp;km respectively.<extension extension_name='ref'>The figures are obtained by dividing the population figures in the Wikipedia country articles by the paved roads figure in the 'Transport in [country]' articles.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Categories</heading><paragraph>The road network is theoretically divided into four categories (national roads, priority regional roads, secondary regional roads and local roads), however, the<space/><link><target>United Nations Joint Logistics Centre</target></link><space/>(UNJLC) reports that this classification is of little practical use because some roads simply do not exist. For example, National Road 9 is not operational and cannot be detected by<space/><link><target>remote sensing</target></link><space/>methods.<extension extension_name='ref' name="UNJLC"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The two principal highways are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>National Road No. 1</target></link><space/>connecting the Atlantic seaports with Kinshasa and southeast Katanga, the most important economic area of the country due to its copper and other mines.</listitem><listitem><link><target>National Road No. 2</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kisangani</target></link>-<link><target>Bukavu</target></link><link><target>Goma</target></link>, connecting the principal waterway systems of the country, namely Kinshasa-Kisangani on the Congo River and the Lake Kivu and Lake Tanganyika systems on the eastern edge of the country. This road was cut during the war and as of July 2007 was not in use south of Walikale. Note that the so-called<space/><link><target>Kinshasa Highway</target></link><space/>is not a physical road but a metaphor applied to the route by which<space/><link><target>AIDS</target></link><space/>is believed to have been spread east through Uganda and Kenya and neighbouring countries by truck drivers from the Congo. In the DR Congo the only highway which physically matches the route is National Road No. 2, and most passengers and freight moving between Kinshasa and that road goes by boat along the Congo River.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Inventory</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Torday Congo Expedition 03.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The road between<space/><link><target>Kikwit</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Idiofa</target></link>.</part></link>The total road network in 2005, according to the UNJLC, consisted of:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>paved:</italics><space/>2,250&amp;nbsp;km</listitem><listitem><italics>unpaved:</italics><space/>15,000&amp;nbsp;km</listitem><listitem><italics>tracks</italics><space/>43,000&amp;nbsp;km</listitem><listitem><italics>country roads</italics><space/>21,000&amp;nbsp;km</listitem><listitem><italics>local roads or footpaths</italics><space/>90,000&amp;nbsp;km</listitem><listitem><italics>total:</italics><space/>171,250&amp;nbsp;km<extension extension_name='ref' name="UNJLC"><link type='external' href='http://www.unjlc.org/23003/DRC/land/roads/snapshot_roads/2006-07-25.0204384674/view'>UNJLC (2006): DRC Snapshot Roads in DRC.</link></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The UNJLC also points out that the pre-<link><target>Second Congo War</target></link><space/>network no longer exists, and is dependent upon 20,000<space/><link><target>bridge</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and 325<space/><link><target>ferries</target></link>, most of which are in need of repair or replacement. In contrast, a Democratic Republic of the Congo government document shows that, also in 2005, the network of main highways in good condition was as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>paved: 1,226&amp;nbsp;km</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>unpaved: 607&amp;nbsp;km</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.unjlc.org/DRC/land/UNJLC_DRC_Ministrypublicworks_Land_rehabilitationprogram_fr_051130.xls/view'>UNJLC: DRC Ministry of Public Works: Land rehabilitation program</link></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The 2000 Michelin<space/><italics>Motoring and Tourist Map 955 of Southern and Central Africa</italics>, which categorizes roads as &quot;surfaced&quot;, &quot;improved&quot; (generally unsurfaced but with gravel added and graded), &quot;partially improved&quot; and &quot;earth roads&quot; and &quot;tracks&quot; shows that there were 2694&amp;nbsp;km of paved highway in 2000. These figures indicate that, compared to the more recent figures above, there has been a deterioration this decade, rather than improvement.</paragraph><heading level='3'>International highways</heading><paragraph>Three routes in the<space/><link><target>Trans-African Highway network</target></link><space/>pass through DR Congo:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Tripoli-Cape Town Highway</target></link>: this route crosses the western extremity of the country on National Road No. 1 between Kinshasa and<space/><link><target>Matadi</target></link>, a distance of 285&amp;nbsp;km on one of the only paved sections in fair condition.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lagos-Mombasa Highway</target></link>: the DR Congo is the main missing link in this east-west highway and requires a new road to be constructed before it can function.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Beira-Lobito Highway</target></link>: this east-west highway crosses<space/><link><target>Katanga Province</target><part>Katanga</part></link><space/>and requires re-construction over most of its length, being an earth track between the<space/><link><target>Angola</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>border and<space/><link><target>Kolwezi</target></link>, a paved road in very poor condition between Kolwezi and<space/><link><target>Lubumbashi</target></link>, and a paved road in fair condition over the short distance to the<space/><link><target>Zambia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>border.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Waterways</heading><paragraph>The DRC has more navigable rivers and moves more passengers and goods by<space/><link><target>boat</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ferry</target></link><space/>than any other country in Africa. Kinshasa, with 7&amp;nbsp;km of river frontage occupied by<space/><link><target>wharf</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>jetties</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Measured on Google Earth which has high-resolution aerial photos of Kinshasa at coordinates -4.2978 15.3171, showing hundreds of barges and vessels, many apparently derelict ones choking some wharfs.</extension><space/>is the largest<space/><link><target>inland port</target><part>inland waterways port</part></link><space/>on the continent. However, much of the infrastructure vessels and port handling facilities has, like the railways, suffered from poor maintenance and internal conflict.</paragraph><paragraph>The total length of waterways is estimated at 15,000&amp;nbsp;km including the<space/><link><target>Congo River</target></link>, its tributaries, and unconnected<space/><link><target>lake</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1000-kilometre Kinshasa-<link><target>Kisangani</target></link><space/>route on the Congo River is the longest and best-known. It is operated by river tugs pushing several barges lashed together, and for the hundreds of passengers and traders these function like small floating towns. Rather than mooring at riverside communities along the route, traders come out by canoe and small boat alongside the river barges and transfer goods<space/><link><target>Lightering</target><part>on the move</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Most waterway routes do not operate to regular schedules. It is common for an operator to moor a barge at a riverside town and collect freight and passengers over a period of weeks before hiring a river tug to tow or push the barge to its destination.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.unjlc.org/DRC/rivers/unjlcarticle.2005-10-19.0866864829/view'>Description of Inland Waterways in the Congo from the UN Joint Logistics Centre</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>International links via inland waterways</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Kinshasa is linked to<space/><link><target>Brazzaville</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Republic of the Congo</target></link>) by regular boat and ferry services 3.5&amp;nbsp;km across the Congo River.</listitem><listitem>Kinshasa and other river ports via the<space/><link><target>Ubangui River</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Bangui</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Central African Republic</target></link>).</listitem><listitem>Goma and Bukavu on<space/><link><target>Lake Kivu</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Gisenyi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kibuye</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cyangugu</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Rwanda</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Kalemie, Kulundu-Uvira and Moba on Lake Tanganyika to Kigoma (Tanzania), Bujumbura (Burundi) and Mpulungu (Zambia).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kasenga</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pweto</target></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Luapula River</target></link>-<link><target>Lake Mweru</target></link><space/>system to<space/><link><target>Nchelenge</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kashikishi</target></link><space/>and Kashiba in<space/><link><target>Zambia</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lake Albert (Africa)</target><part>Lake Albert</part></link>: two small ports on the DRC side,<space/><link><target>Kisenye</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Bunia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mahadi-Port</target></link><space/>in the north can link to<space/><link><target>Uganda</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>ports at<space/><link><target>Butiabo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pakwach</target></link><space/>(served by<space/><link><target>Uganda Railways</target></link>) on the<space/><link><target>Albert Nile</target></link>, which is navigable as far as<space/><link><target>Nimule</target></link><space/>in southern<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link>. Water transport is conducted principally in small craft, and commercial water transport is relatively absent.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lake Edward</target></link>: located within national parks, settlements are small, water transport is conducted principally in small craft, commercial water transport is absent.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Domestic links via inland waterways</heading><paragraph>The middle Congo River and its tributaries from the east are the principal domestic waterways in the DRC. The two principal river routes are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Kinshasa to Mbandaka and Kisangani on the<space/><link><target>River Congo</target></link></listitem><listitem>Kinshasa to Ilebo on the<space/><link><target>Kasai River</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>See the diagrammatic transport map above for other river waterways.</paragraph><paragraph>The most-used domestic lake waterways are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Kalemie to Kalundu-Uvira on Lake Tanganyika</listitem><listitem>Bukavu to Goma on Lake Kivu</listitem><listitem><link><target>Fimi River</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Inongo</target></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Lake Mai-Ndombe</target></link></listitem><listitem>Irebu on the Congo to Bikoro on<space/><link><target>Lake Tumba</target></link></listitem><listitem>Kasenga to Pweto on the Luapula-Mweru system</listitem><listitem>Kisenye to Mahadi-Port on Lake Albert.</listitem></list><paragraph>Most large Congo river ferry boats were destroyed during the civil war. Only smaller boats are running and they are irregular.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ports and harbors</heading><heading level='4'>Atlantic Ocean</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Matadi</target></link><space/>- largest port, and<space/><link><target>railhead</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>portage railway</target></link><space/>to Kinshasa - draft: 6.4 m</listitem><listitem><link><target>Banana, Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Banana</part></link><space/>-<space/><link><target>oil terminal</target></link><space/>for pipeline to Kinshasa</listitem><listitem><link><target>Boma, Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Boma</part></link><space/>- second-largest port</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Inland river ports</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bumba, Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Bumba</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ilebo</target></link><space/>- railhead</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kindu</target></link><space/>- railhead</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link><space/>- railhead</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kisangani</target></link><space/>- railhead</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mbandaka</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>N'dangi</target></link><space/>- former military harbor</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Lake Tanganyika</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Kalemie</target></link><space/>-<space/><link><target>railhead</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Uvira</target><part>Kalundu-Uvira</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Moba port</target><part>Moba</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Lake Kivu</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bukavu</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Idjwi</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Goma</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Pipelines</heading><paragraph>petroleum products 390&amp;nbsp;km</paragraph><heading level='2'>Merchant marine</heading><paragraph>1 petroleum tanker<extension extension_name='ref' name="CIA"><link type='external' href='https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/cg.html'>The World Factbook: &quot;Democratic Republic of the Congo&quot;.</link><space/>CIA. Retrieved 22 May 2007.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Airports</heading><paragraph><template><target>seealso</target><arg>List of airports in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</arg></template>Kemal Saiki, a<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>spokesman, said that the Democratic Republic of the Congo does not &quot;even have 2,000 miles of roads&quot; and that many people traveling around the country fly on aircraft.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/africa/04/1/congo.crash/index.html'>African air crash kills 18</link>.&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>CNN</target></link></italics>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main passenger airlines of the country are<space/><link><target>flyCongo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Compagnie Africaine d'Aviation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Korongo Airlines</target></link>. All of their hubs are at Kinshasa's<space/><link><target>N'djili Airport</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>The country had 229 airports in 2002 and 232 around 1999.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Airports - with paved runways</heading><paragraph><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>total:</italics>24<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>over 3,047 m:</italics>4<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>2,438 to 3,047 m:</italics>2<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>1,524 to 2,437 m:</italics>16<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>914 to 1,523 m:</italics>2 (2002 est.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Airports - with unpaved runways</heading><paragraph><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>total:</italics>205<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>1,524 to 2,437 m:</italics>19<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>914 to 1,523 m:</italics>95<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>under 914 m:</italics>91 (2002 est.)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Transport safety and incidents</heading><paragraph>All air carriers certified by the Democratic Republic of the Congo have been banned from operating at airports in the European Community by the European Commission because of inadequate safety standards.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ec.europa.eu/transport/air-ban/pdf/list_en.pdf'>List of airlines banned in the EU (24 July 2008)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>2010</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Kasai River disaster</target></link>. A passenger ferry capsized on the<space/><link><target>Kasai River</target></link><space/>in July with at least 80 dead.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>2008</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>2008 Hewa Bora Airways crash</target></link><space/>- April 15 plane crash killed at least 18 people after taking off from the<space/><link><target>Goma International Airport</target></link>, tearing the roofs off houses as it plowed through a densely populated marketplace near the runway.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://edition.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/africa/04/15/congo.crash/index.html'>Plane crashes into African marketplace</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>2007</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>August 1 train derailment killed 100, many riding on roof.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>2005</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Kindu rail accident</target></link>, on November 29, at least 60 people were killed</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Rocketry</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link><space/>has a<space/><link><target>rocket</target><trail>ry</trail></link><space/>program called<space/><link><target>Troposphere (rocket family)</target><part>Troposphere</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://weirdthings.com/2010/12/a-brief-history-of-the-congolese-space-program/<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Brief History of The Congolese Space Program<space/></arg><arg name="last">Crutchfield</arg><arg name="first">Ryan</arg><arg name="date">2010-12-20<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-02-23</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Congo River</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>33em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theworld.org/2011/11/congo-road-trip/'>&quot;Congo Road Trip&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>PRI's The World</italics>, November 25, 2011</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DRC topics</target></template><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Transport in</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Transport In The Democratic Republic Of The Congo</target></template><link><target>Category:Transport in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>