<article title='Achill_Island'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox islands</target><arg name="name"><space/>Achill
</arg><arg name="image name"><space/>Achillsatmap.jpg 
</arg><arg name="image caption"><space/>View of the Island using [[NASA]]'s technology overhead
</arg><arg name="map"><space/>Ireland
</arg><arg name="lat_d"><space/>53.96391
</arg><arg name="long_d"><space/>-10.00303
</arg><arg name="native name"><space/>Acaill, Oileán Acla
</arg><arg name="native name link"><space/>
</arg><arg name="nickname"><space/>
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Atlantic Ocean]]
</arg><arg name="archipelago"><space/>Achill
</arg><arg name="total islands"><space/>3(Achill,Innisbiggle and Achillbeg islands)
</arg><arg name="major islands"><space/>Achill
</arg><arg name="coastline km"><space/>128
</arg><arg name="highest mount"><space/>[[Croaghaun]]
</arg><arg name="elevation m"><space/>688
</arg><arg name="area acre"><space/>36572 
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>[[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions title"><space/>[[Provinces of Ireland|Province]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions"><space/>[[Connacht]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions title 1"><space/>[[Counties of Ireland|County]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions 1"><space/>[[County Mayo|Mayo]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions title 2"><space/>[[Barony (Ireland)|Barony]]
</arg><arg name="country admin divisions 2"><space/>[[Burrishoole]]
</arg><arg name="country capital city"><space/>
</arg><arg name="country largest city"><space/>
</arg><arg name="country largest city population"><space/>
</arg><arg name="country leader title"><space/>
</arg><arg name="country leader name"><space/>
</arg><arg name="population"><space/>2,569
</arg><arg name="population as of"><space/>2011<space/><ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="density km2"><space/>17.3
</arg><arg name="ethnic groups"><space/>
</arg><arg name="additional info"><space/>Ireland's largest island
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Achill Island</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>əl</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>lang-ga</target><arg>Acaill, Oileán Acla</arg></template>) in<space/><link><target>County Mayo</target></link><space/>is the largest island off the coast of<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link>, and is situated off the west coast. It has a population of 2,700. Its area is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>148</arg><arg>km2</arg><arg>sqmi</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. Achill is attached to the mainland by<space/><link><target>Michael Davitt Bridge</target></link>, between the villages of Gob an Choire (<link><target>Achill Sound</target></link>) and Poll Raithn (<link><target>Polranny</target></link>). A<space/><link><target>bridge</target></link><space/>was first completed here in 1887, replaced by another structure in 1949, and subsequently replaced with the current bridge which was completed in 2008. Other centres of population include the villages of Keel,<space/><link><target>Dooagh</target></link>, Dumha ige (<link><target>Dooega</target></link>), Dooniver, The Valley and Dugort. The parish's main<space/><link><target>Gaelic football</target></link><space/>pitch and two<space/><link><target>secondary school</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are on the mainland at Poll Raithn. Early<space/><link><target>human settlement</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are believed to have been established on Achill around 3000 BC. A paddle dating from this period was found at the<space/><link><target>cranng</target></link><space/>near Dookinella.The island is 87%<space/><link><target>peat bog</target></link>. The parish of Achill also includes the<space/><link><target>Curraun peninsula</target></link>. Some of the people of Curraun consider themselves Achill people, and most natives of Achill refer to this area as being &quot;in Achill&quot;. There are between 500-600 native Irish speakers in Achill parish. In the summer of 1996, the<space/><link><target>RNLI</target></link><space/>decided to station a<space/><link><target>lifeboat (rescue)</target><part>lifeboat</part></link><space/>at Kildownet.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>It is believed that at the end of the<space/><link><target>Neolithic Period</target></link><space/>(around 4000 BC), Achill had a population of 5001,000 people. The island would have been mostly forest until the Neolithic people began<space/><link><target>agriculture</target><part>crop cultivation</part></link>. Settlement increased during the<space/><link><target>Iron Age</target></link>, and the dispersal of small<space/><link><target>promontory fort</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>around the coast indicate the warlike nature of the times.<space/><link><target>Megalithic tomb</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(see picture, right) and forts can be seen at Slievemore, along the Atlantic Drive and on<space/><link><target>Achillbeg</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Overlords</heading><paragraph>Achill Island lies in the Barony of<space/><link><target>Burrishoole</target></link>, in the territory of ancient<space/><link><target>Umaill</target><part>Umhall</part></link><space/>(Umhall Uactarach and Umhall Ioctarach), that originally encompassed an area extending from the<space/><link><target>County Galway</target></link>/Mayo border to Achill Head.</paragraph><paragraph>The hereditary chieftains of Umhall were the O'Malleys, recorded in the area in 814 AD when they successfully repelled an onslaught by the Vikings in<space/><link><target>Clew Bay</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Anglo-Norman</target></link><space/>invasion of<space/><link><target>Connacht</target></link><space/>in 1235 AD saw the territory of Umhall taken over by the Butlers and later by the de Burgos. The Butler Lordship of Burrishoole continued into the late 14th century when Thomas le Botiller was recorded as being in possession of Akkyll &amp; Owyll.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Immigration</heading><paragraph>In the 17th and 18th centuries, there was much migration to Achill from other parts of Ireland, particularly<space/><link><target>Ulster</target></link>, due to the political and religious turmoil of the time. For a while there were two different<space/><link><target>dialect</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of Irish being spoken on Achill. This led to many townlands being recorded as having two names during the 1824<space/><link><target>Ordnance Survey</target></link>, and some maps today give different names for the same place. Achill Irish still has many traces of<space/><link><target>Ulster Irish</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Specific historical sites and events</heading><heading level='4'>Grace O'Malley's Castle</heading><paragraph>Grace O'Malley's Kildamhnait Castle is a 15th-century tower house associated with the O'Malley Clan, who were once a ruling family of Achill.<space/><link><target>Grace O' Malley</target></link>, or Granuaile, the most famous of the O'Malleys, was born on<space/><link><target>Clare Island</target></link><space/>around 1530.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><space/>Her father was the chieftain of the barony of<space/><link><target>Murrisk</target></link>. The O'Malleys were a powerful seafaring family, who traded widely. Grace became a fearless leader and gained fame as a sea captain and pirate. She is reputed to have met with<space/><link><target>Queen Elizabeth I</target></link><space/>in 1593. She died around 1603 and is buried in the O'Malley family tomb on Clare Island.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Achill Mission</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Colony, Achill (21330853923).jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>left</part><part>View of the &quot;Colony&quot;, prior to 1900.</part></link>One of Achill's most famous historical sites is that of the<space/><link><target>Achill Mission</target></link><space/>or 'the Colony' at Dugort. In 1831 the<space/><link><target>Church of Ireland</target></link><space/>Reverend Edward Nangle founded a<space/><link><target>proselytising</target></link><space/>mission at Dugort. The Mission included schools, cottages, an orphanage, an infirmary and a guesthouse. The Colony was very successful for a time and regularly produced a newspaper called the<space/><italics>Achill Herald and Western Witness</italics>. Nangle expanded his mission into Mweelin, where a school was built. The Achill Mission began to decline slowly after Nangle was moved from Achill and was finally closed in the 1880s. Nangle died in 1883.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Railway</heading><paragraph>In 1894, the Westport - Newport railway line was extended to Achill Sound. The train station is now a hostel. The train provided a great service to Achill, but it also fulfilled an ancient prophecy. Brian Rua O' Cearbhain had prophesied that 'carts on iron wheels' would carry bodies into Achill on their first and last journey. In 1894, the first train on the Achill railway carried the bodies of victims of the<space/><link><target>Clew Bay Drowning</target></link>. This tragedy occurred when a boat overturned in Clew Bay, drowning thirty two young people. They had been going to meet the steamer which would take them to Scotland for potato picking.</paragraph><heading level='5'>Kirkintilloch Fire</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Kirkintilloch Fire</target></link><space/>in 1937 fulfilled the second part of the prophecy, when the bodies of ten victims were carried by rail to Achill. These people had died in a fire in a<space/><link><target>bothy</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Kirkintilloch</target></link>. This term referred to the temporary accommodation provided for those who went to Scotland to pick potatoes, a migratory pattern that had been established in the early nineteenth century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Memorial for the victims of the Clew Bay Drowning on 15 June 1894 at Kildavenet Graveyard, Achill Island.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Memorial for the victims of the<space/><link><target>Clew Bay Drowning</target></link><space/>on 15 June 1894 at<space/><link><target>Kildavenet</target></link><space/>Graveyard</part></link></paragraph><heading level='4'>Kildamhnait</heading><paragraph>Kildamhnait on the south east coast of Achill is named after St. Damhnait, or Dymphna, who founded a church there in the 16th century. There is also a holy well just outside the graveyard. The present church was built in the 1700s and the graveyard contains memorials to the victims of two of Achill's greatest tragedies, the Kirchintilloch Fire (1937) and the<space/><link><target>Clew Bay Drowning</target></link><space/>(1894).</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Monastery</heading><paragraph>In 1852, Dr. John McHale, Archbishop of Tuam set aside land in Bunnacurry for the building of a monastery. A Franciscan Monastery was built which, for many years provided an education for local children. The ruins of this monastery are still to be seen in Bunnacurry today.</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Valley House</heading><paragraph>The historic Valley House is located in The Valley, near Dugort in the north-east of Achill Island. The present building sits on the site of a hunting lodge built by the Earl of Cavan in the 19th century. Its notoriety arises from an incident in 1894 in which the then owner, an English landlady named Agnes McDonnell, was savagely beaten and the house set alight, allegedly by a local man, James Lynchehaun. Lynchehaun had been employed by McDonnell as her land agent, but the two fell out and he was sacked and told to quit his accommodation on her estate. A lengthy legal battle ensued, with Lynchehaun refusing to leave. At the time, in the 1890s, the issue of land ownership in Ireland was politically charged, and after the events at the Valley House in 1894 Lynchehaun was to claim that his actions were motivated by politics. He escaped custody and fled to the United States, where he successfully defeated legal attempts by the British authorities to have him extradited to face charges arising from the attack and the burning of the Valley House. Agnes McDonnell suffered terrible injuries from the attack but survived and lived for another 23 years, dying in 1923. Lynchehaun is said to have returned to Achill on two occasions, once in disguise as an American tourist, and eventually died in Girvan, Scotland, in 1937. The Valley House is now a hostel and Bar.</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Deserted Village</heading><paragraph>Close by Dugort, at the base of Slievemore mountain lies the Deserted Village. There are approximately 80 ruined houses in the village.</paragraph><paragraph>The houses were built of unmortared stone, which means that no cement or mortar was used to hold the stones together. Each house consisted of just one room and this room was used as kitchen, living room, bedroom and even stable.</paragraph><paragraph>If one looks at the fields around the Deserted Village and right up the mountain, one can see the tracks in the fields of 'lazy beds', which is the way crops like potatoes were grown. In Achill, as in many areas of Ireland, a system called 'Rundale' was used for farming. This meant that the land around a village was rented from a landlord. This land was then shared by all the villagers to graze their cattle and sheep. Each family would then have two or three small pieces of land scattered about the village, which they used to grow crops.</paragraph><paragraph>For many years people lived in the village and then in 1845 Famine struck in Achill as it did in the rest of Ireland. Most of the families moved to the nearby village of Dooagh, which is beside the sea, while some others emigrated. Living beside the sea meant that fish and shellfish could be used for food. The village was completely abandoned which is where the name 'Deserted Village' came from.</paragraph><paragraph>No one has lived in these houses since the time of the Famine, however the families that moved to Dooagh and their descendants, continued to use the village as a 'booley village'. This means that during the summer season, the younger members of the family, teenage boys and girls, would take the cattle to graze on the hillside and they would stay in the houses of the Deserted Village. This custom continued until the 1940s. Boolying was also carried out in other areas of Achill, including Annagh on Croaghaun mountain and in Curraun.</paragraph><paragraph>At Ailt, Kildownet, you can see the remains of a similar deserted village. This village was deserted in 1855 when the tenants were evicted by the local landlord so the land could be used for cattle grazing, the tenants were forced to rent holdings in Currane, Dooega and Slievemore. Others emigrated to America.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Archaeology</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:KeemBayAchillJune.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Keem Bay</target></link></part><trail>Achill</trail></link><space/>Archaeological Field School is based at the Achill Archaeology Centre in Dooagh, which has served as a catalyst for a wide array of archaeological investigations on the island. It was founded in 1991 and is a training school for students of<space/><link><target>archaeology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>anthropology</target></link>. Since 1991, several thousand students from 21 countries have come to Achill to study and participate in ongoing excavations. The school is involved in a study of the prehistoric and historic landscape at<space/><link><target>Slievemore</target></link>, incorporating a research excavation at a number of sites within the deserted village of Slievemore. Slievemore is rich in archaeological monuments that span a 5,000 year period from the<space/><link><target>Neolithic</target></link><space/>to the Post Medieval.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Achill Archaeological Field School 2009<space/></arg><arg name="work">Achill Archaeological Field School<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.achill-fieldschool.com/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 March 2009</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20090228224527/http://www.achill-fieldschool.com/</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>28 February 2009<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension><space/>Recent archaeological research suggests the village was occupied year-round at least as early as the 19th century, though it is known to have served as a seasonally occupied<space/><link><target>booley village</target></link><space/>by the first half of the 20th century. A booley village (a number of which exist in a ruined state on the island) is a village occupied only during part of the year, such as a resort community, a<space/><link><target>lake</target></link><space/>community, or (as the case on Achill) a place to live while<space/><link><target>Transhumance</target><part>tending flocks or herds</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>ruminant</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>during winter or summer<space/><link><target>pasture</target><part>pasturing</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.achill247.com/pictures/slievemore-7.html'>''Deserted village, Slievemore, Achill Island'', achill247.com</link><space/>Retrieved on 17 February 2008.</extension><space/>Specifically, some of the people of Dooagh and<space/><link><target>Pollagh, Achill</target><part>Pollagh</part></link><space/>would migrate in the summer to Slievemore and then go back to Dooagh in the autumn. The summer 2009 field school excavated Round House 2 on Slievemore Mountain under the direction of archaeologist Stuart Rathbone. Only the outside northwall, entrance way and inside of the Round House were completely excavated.<extension extension_name='ref'>Amanda Burt, member of Achill Field School, Summer 2009.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From 2004 to 2006, the Achill Island Maritime Archaeology Project directed by<space/><link><target>Chuck Meide</target></link><space/>was sponsored by the<space/><link><target>College of William and Mary</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Institute of Maritime History</target></link>, the Achill Folklife Centre (now the Achill Archaeology Centre), and the<space/><link><target>St. Augustine Light</target><part>Lighthouse Archaeological Maritime Program (LAMP)</part></link>. This project focused on the documentation of archaeological resources related to Achill's rich maritime heritage. Maritime archaeologists recorded 19th century fishing station, ice house, and boat house ruins, a number of anchors which had been salvaged from the sea, 19th century and more recent<space/><link><target>currach</target></link><space/>pens, a number of traditional vernacular watercraft including a possibly 100-year-old Achill yawl, and the remains of four historic shipwrecks.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.maritimehistory.org/content/achill-island-maritime-archaeology-project<space/></arg><arg name="title">Achill Island Maritime Archaeology Project &#124; Institute of Maritime History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Maritimehistory.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 February 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 March 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs11457-013-9123-3#page-1<space/></arg><arg name="title">Meide, Chuck and Kathryn Sikes (2014) Manipulating the Maritime Cultural Landscape: Vernacular Boats and Economic Relations on Nineteenth-Century Achill Island, Ireland. Journal of Maritime History 9(1):115-141<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 June 2014<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 June 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other places of interest</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Croaghaun cliff.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Croaghaun</target></link>, the third highest sea cliff in Europe</part></link><link><target>File:Slievemore.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Slievemore</target></link><space/>mountain dominates the centre of the island</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Despite some development, the island retains a striking natural beauty. The cliffs of<space/><link><target>Croaghaun</target></link><space/>on the western end of the island are the third highest sea<space/><link><target>cliff</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link><space/>but are inaccessible by road. Near the westernmost point of Achill,<space/><link><target>Achill Head</target></link>, is<space/><link><target>Keem Bay</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Keel Beach</target></link><space/>is quite popular with<space/><link><target>tourist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and some locals as a<space/><link><target>surfing</target></link><space/>location. South of Keem beach is<space/><link><target>Moytoge Head</target></link>, which with its rounded appearance drops dramatically down to the<space/><link><target>ocean</target></link>. An old<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>British</part></link><space/>observation post, built during<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>to prevent the<space/><link><target>Germany</target><part>Germans</part></link><space/>from landing arms for the<space/><link><target>Irish Republican Army (191722)</target><part>Irish Republican Army</part></link>, is still standing on Moytoge. During the Second World War this post was rebuilt by the Irish Defence Forces as a Look Out Post for the Coast Watching Service wing of the Defence Forces. It operated from 1939 to 1945.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Michael Kennedy, 'Guarding Neutral Ireland' (Dublin, 2008), p. 50</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>mountain</target></link><space/><link><target>Slievemore</target></link><space/>(672&amp;nbsp;m) rises dramatically in the north of the island and the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Drive</target></link><space/>(along the south/west of the island) has some dramatically beautiful views. On the slopes of Slievemore, there is an<space/><link><target>abandoned village</target></link><space/>(the &quot;Deserted Village&quot;) The Deserted Village is traditionally thought to be a remnant village from An Gorta Mr (<link><target>Irish Potato Famine (18451849)</target><part>The Great Hunger of 1845-1849</part></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>Just west of the deserted village is an old<space/><link><target>Martello tower</target></link>, again built by the British to warn of any possible<space/><link><target>France</target><part>French</part></link><space/>invasion during the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>. The area also boasts an approximately 5000-year-old<space/><link><target>Neolithic tomb</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Achillbeg</target></link><space/>(<italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>ga</arg><arg>Acaill Beag</arg></template></italics>,<space/><italics>Little Achill</italics>) is a small island just off Achill's southern tip. Its inhabitants were resettled on Achill in the 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jonathan Beaumont (2005),<space/><italics>Achillbeg: The Life of an Island</italics>, ISBN 0-85361-631-0</extension><space/>A plaque to<space/><link><target>Johnny Kilbane</target></link><space/>is situated on<space/><link><target>Achillbeg</target></link><space/>and was erected to celebrate 100 years since his first championship win.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.facebook.com/events/242473492507858/'></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The villages of<space/><link><target>Dooniver</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Askill</target></link><space/>have very picturesque scenery and the cycle route is popular with tourists.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Economy</heading><paragraph>While a number of attempts at setting up small industrial units on the island have been made, the economy of the island is largely dependent on<space/><link><target>tourism</target></link>. Subventions from Achill people working abroad, in particular in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and Africa allowed many families to remain living in Achill throughout the 19th and 20th centuries.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2008</arg></template><space/>Since the advent of Ireland's &quot;<link><target>Celtic Tiger</target></link>&quot;<space/><link><target>economy of the Republic of Ireland</target><part>economy</part></link><space/>fewer Achill people were forced to look for work abroad.<space/><link><target>Agriculture</target></link><space/>plays a small role and the fact that the island is mostly bog means that its potential for agriculture is limited largely to<space/><link><target>sheep farming</target></link>. In the past,<space/><link><target>fishing</target></link><space/>was a significant activity but this aspect of the economy is small now. At one stage, the island was known for its<space/><link><target>shark</target></link><space/>fishing,<space/><link><target>basking shark</target></link><space/>in particular was fished for its valuable<space/><link><target>liver oil</target></link>. There was a big spurt of growth in tourism in the 1960s and 1970s before which life was tough and difficult on the island. Despite healthy visitor numbers each year, the common perception is that tourism in Achill has been slowly declining since its heyday. Currently the largest employers on Achill are two hotels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.irelandbyways.com/top-irish-peninsulas/the-west/the-western-isles/achill-island-co-mayo/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Achill Island (Co. Mayo)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Irelandbyways.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>In late 2009 Ireland's only<space/><link><target>Turbot</target></link><space/>farm opened in the<space/><link><target>Bunnacurry</target></link><space/>Business Park.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Religion</heading><paragraph>Most people on Achill are either<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/>or Anglican (<link><target>Church of Ireland</target></link>). There are three priests on Achill and eight<space/><link><target>church (building)</target><part>churches</part></link><template><target>Clarify</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg><arg name="reason">list mentions 11 chuches</arg></template><space/>in total.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Catholic:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bunnacurry</target></link><space/>Church (<link><target>Saint Joseph</target><trail>s</trail></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tin an tSeanbhaile</target><part>The Valley</part></link><space/>Church; Only open for certain events.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dookinella</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Currane</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pollagh</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Derreens</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dooega</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Belfarsed</target></link><space/>Church</listitem><listitem><link><target>Achill Sound</target></link><space/>Church</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Church of Ireland:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dugort</target></link><space/>Church (St.Thomas's church)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Innisbiggle</target></link><space/>Island church</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Education</heading><paragraph>Hedge schools existed in most villages of Achill in various periods of history. A university was started by the missions to Achill in Mweelin. In modern age, there used to be two<space/><link><target>secondary school</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in Achill,<space/><link><target>Mc Hale College</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Scoil Damhnait</target></link>. However, in August 2011, the two schools amalgamated to form<space/><link><target>Coliste Pobail Acla</target></link>. For primary education, there are nine<space/><link><target>National Schools</target></link><space/>including Bullsmouth NS, Valley NS, Bunnacurry NS, Dookinella NS, Dooagh NS, Saulia NS, Achill Sound NS, Tonragee NS and Curanne NS. National schools closed down include Dooega NS, Crumpaun NS, Ashleam NS.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Transport</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Achill railway station</target></link><space/>opened on 13 May 1895, but finally closed on 1 October 1937.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Achill station<space/></arg><arg name="work">Railscot - Irish Railways<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.railscot.co.uk/Ireland/Irish_railways.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 September 2007</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20070926042407/http://www.railscot.co.uk/Ireland/Irish_railways.pdf</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>26 September 2007<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Great Western Greenway</target></link><space/>is a<space/><link><target>greenway (landscape)</target><part>greenway</part></link><space/><link><target>rail trail</target></link><space/>that follows the line of the former<space/><link><target>Midland Great Western Railway</target></link><space/>branch line from<space/><link><target>Westport, County Mayo</target><part>Westport</part></link><space/>to Achill via<space/><link><target>Newport, County Mayo</target><part>Newport</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mulranny</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.greenway.ie/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Home<space/></arg><arg name="work">Great Western Greenway<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 August 2011<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>This has proved to be very successful in attracting visitors Achill and the surrounding areas.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bus ireann</target></link><space/>440 daily commutes to<space/><link><target>Westport, County Mayo</target><part>Westport</part></link><space/>and beyond from the island's scattered villages.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bus ireann</target></link><space/>provide transport for the areas secondary school children</listitem><listitem>There are many<space/><link><target>Taxicab</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hackney carriage</target></link><space/>services on the<space/><link><target>Island</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Cuisine</heading><paragraph>As a popular tourist destination Achill has many bars, cafes and restaurants which serve a full range of food. However, with the island's<space/><link><target>Atlantic</target></link><space/>location seafood is a speciality on Achill with common foods including<space/><link><target>Homarus gammarus</target><part>lobster</part></link>,<space/><link><target>mussel</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>salmon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>trout</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Common periwinkle</target><part>winkles</part></link>. With a large sheep population, Achill lamb is a very popular meal on the island too. Furthermore, Achill has a big population of cows which produces excellent beef.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sport</heading><paragraph>Achill has a<space/><link><target>Gaelic football</target></link><space/>club which competes in the intermediate championship and division 1C of the Mayo League. There are also an<space/><link><target>association football</target></link><space/>club,<space/><link><target>Achill Rovers</target></link>, which competes in the<space/><link><target>Mayo Football League</target></link><space/>division 1,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://inform.fai.ie/League/Clubs/portals/AchillRoversFC/'>FAI Club Portal for Achill Rovers</link></extension><space/>and Achill Golf Club.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/><link><target>Card game</target><trail>s</trail></link>, including<space/><link><target>Whist</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>24 card game</target></link><space/>are also popular on Achill.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template>The island's primary recreational outdoor centre is Achill Outdoor Education Centre.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.achilloutdoor.com/'>achilloutdoor.com</link></extension><space/>Achill Island's rugged landscape and the surrounding ocean offers a prime location for outdoor adventure activities, like surfing, kite-surfing and sea kayaking.<space/><link><target>Fishing</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>watersports</target></link><space/>are popular with tourists and locals alike. Sailing regattas featuring a local vessel type, the Achill Yawl, have been popular since the 19th century, though most present-day yawls, unlike their traditional working boat ancestors, have been structurally modified to promote greater speed under sail. The island's waters and striking underwater sites are occasionally visited by scuba divers, though Achill's unpredictable weather generally has precluded a commercially successful recreational diving industry.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Population</heading><paragraph>In 2011, the population was 2,569. The island's population has declined from around 6,000 before the<space/><link><target>Great Famine (Ireland)</target><part>Great Hunger</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Demographics</heading><paragraph>The table below reports data on Achill Island's population taken from<space/><italics>Discover the Islands of Ireland</italics><space/>(Alex Ritsema, Collins Press, 1999) and the<space/><link><target>census</target></link><space/>of Ireland.<space/><template><target>Historical populations</target><arg name="align"><space/>none
</arg><arg name="cols"><space/>2
</arg><arg name="footnote"><space/>Source: {{cite web |url</arg><arg>1841<space/></arg><arg>4901 
</arg><arg>1851<space/></arg><arg>4030 
</arg><arg>1901<space/></arg><arg>4825 
</arg><arg>1951<space/></arg><arg>4906 
</arg><arg>1996<space/></arg><arg>2718 
</arg><arg>2002<space/></arg><arg>2620
</arg><arg>2006<space/></arg><arg>2620 
</arg><arg>2011<space/></arg><arg>2569 
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Architecture</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template>Because of the inhospitable climate, few inhabited houses date from before the 20th century, though there are many examples of abandoned stone structures dating to the 19th century.<link><target>File:Desert Village sullo Slievemore, Achill Island.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The &quot;Deserted Village&quot; at the foot of Slievemore was a<space/><link><target>booley village</target></link>; see<space/><link><target>Transhumance</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Deserted Village in the Shadow of Slievemore.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>The location of the village is relatively sheltered</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The best known of these earlier can be seen in the &quot;Deserted Village&quot; ruins near the graveyard at the foot of Slievemore. Even the houses in this village represent a relatively comfortable class of dwelling as, even as recently as a hundred years ago, some people still used &quot;Beehive&quot; style houses (small circular single roomed dwellings with a hole in ceiling to let out smoke).</paragraph><paragraph>Many of the oldest and most picturesque inhabited cottages date from the activities of the<space/><link><target>Congested Districts Board for Ireland</target></link>a body set up around the turn of the 20th century in Ireland to improve the welfare for inhabitants of small villages and towns. Most of the homes in Achill at the time were very small and tightly packed together in villages. The CDB subsidised the building of new, more spacious (though still small by modern standards) homes outside of the traditional villages.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of the recent building development (1980 and onwards) on the island does fit as nicely in the landscape as the earlier style of<space/><link><target>whitewash</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>raised gable<space/><link><target>cottage</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Many holiday homes have been built but many of these houses have been built in prominent scenic areas and have damaged traditional views of the island while lying empty for most of the year.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notable people</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Manus Sweeney</target></link><space/>from Achill was hanged in<space/><link><target>Newport, County Mayo</target><part>Newport</part></link><space/>for his part in the<space/><link><target>1798 rebellion</target></link>. There is a monument to him at the eastern end of Keel beach</listitem><listitem><link><target>Charles Boycott</target></link><space/>(18321897) - Unpopular landowner from whom the term<space/><italics>Boycott</italics><space/>arose.</listitem><listitem>The artist<space/><link><target>Paul Henry (painter)</target><part>Paul Henry</part></link><space/>stayed on the island for a number of years in the early 1900s and some of his most famous paintings are of the dramatic landscape of the island. Not long after arriving, he threw his return train ticket into the sea near<space/><link><target>Purteen Harbour</target></link></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Nobel Prize</target></link><space/>winning author,<space/><link><target>Heinrich Bll</target></link>, visited the island and wrote of his experience in his &quot;Irish Journal&quot; (<italics>Irisches Tagebuch</italics>). The Blls later bought a cottage near Dugort and lived in it periodically until 2001 when they donated it to be used as an artists' residence</listitem><listitem>Novelist<space/><link><target>Graham Greene</target></link>, visited and stayed on Achill Island a number of times in the late 1940s. He wrote parts of the novels<space/><italics><link><target>The Heart of the Matter</target></link></italics><space/>(subsequently banned in Ireland) and<space/><italics>The Fallen Idol</italics><space/>in Dooagh, and Achill Island is also said to have inspired Greene to write some of his best poetry. He retained a special affection for Achill Island, which he mentioned frequently in his letters and notes, although this was largely due to the circumstances of his visits, as he was introduced to Achill by his mistress,<space/><link><target>Catherine Walston</target></link>. She rented a cottage in Dooagh, with no electricity, one outside tap for water, and a corrugated iron roof on the traditional stone cottage, now since demolished.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Graham Greene & Achill Island<space/></arg><arg name="work">Achill 24/7<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.achill247.com/writers/ggreene.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 March 2009</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20090202124344/http://www.achill247.com/writers/ggreene.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2 February 2009<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Artist<space/><link><target>Robert Henri</target></link><space/>came to Achill on a regular basis in the early decades of the 20th century. It was during his early trips to Achill prior to the outbreak of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>that Henri painted extensively and is reputed to have done portraits of almost all the children in Dooagh village. He bought Corrymore House on the hill above Dooagh in 1924. He died in America in 1929.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Their portraits are famous in America but - Whatever happened to the Commins family of Achill?<space/></arg><arg name="work">Western People - 1 April 1998</arg><arg name="url">http://archives.tcm.ie/westernpeople/1998/04/01/News.htm<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 March 2009</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas Patten (socialist)</target><part>Thomas Patten</part></link><space/>from Dooega died fighting<space/><link><target>Francisco Franco</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>fascist</target></link><space/>forces during the<space/><link><target>Siege of Madrid</target></link><space/>in December 1936. There is a monument to him in his native village.</listitem><listitem>English writer<space/><link><target>Honor Tracy</target></link><space/>lived there until her death in 1989</listitem><listitem>In the centre of Dooagh is a commemoration plaque to<space/><link><target>Don Allum</target></link>, the first man to row across the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target></link><space/>in both directions. He landed close to the memorial on Dooagh beach on 4 September 1987, completing the second leg of his voyage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Don Allum<space/></arg><arg name="work">Doc Brown.info</arg><arg name="url">http://www.docbrown.info/docspics/irishviews/ivpage115.htm<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 March 2009</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Singer<space/><link><target>James Kilbane</target></link>, also known for his research on traditional Achill watercraft, lives on the island.</listitem><listitem>Belgian graphic artist, photographer, printmaker and publisher<space/><link><target>Francis Van Maele</target></link><space/>lives and works on the island. He runs fine art publishers Redfox Press in<space/><link><target>Dugort</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">CV Francis Van Maele</arg><arg name="work">redfoxpress.com</arg><arg name="url">http://www.redfoxpress.com/me.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2013</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Literature</heading><paragraph><link><target>Heinrich Bll</target></link>:<space/><italics>Irisches Tagebuch</italics>, Berlin 1957<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Kingston, Bob:<space/><italics>The Deserted Village at Slievemore</italics>, Castlebar 1990<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>McDonald, Theresa:<space/><italics>Achill: 5000 B.C. to 1900 A.D. Archeology History Folklore</italics>, I.A.S. Publications [1992]<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Meehan, Rosa:<space/><italics>The Story of Mayo</italics>, Castlebar 2003<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Carney, James:<space/><italics>The Playboy &amp; the Yellow lady</italics>, 1986 POOLBEG<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">James Carney<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://openlibrary.org/b/OL2431852M/playboy_the_yellow_lady<space/></arg><arg name="title">The playboy & the yellow lady<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Open Library<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 March 2012</arg></template></extension><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Hugo Hamilton (writer)</target><part>Hugo Hamilton</part></link>: The Island of Talking,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/25469746?uid=3737864&amp;amp;uid=2&amp;amp;uid=4&amp;amp;sid=21102113059701'>''The Island of Talking''</link><space/>Hugo Hamilton in the footsteps of Heinrich Bll, 50 years after</extension><space/>2007</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Achillbeg</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Achill Sound</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Askill</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bunnacurry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Connacht Irish</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Darren Fletcher</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dooagh</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dooniver</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gallowglass</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Innisbiggle</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>James Kilbane</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kevin Kilbane</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of RNLI stations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mid West Radio</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nevin (surname)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Saula (achill)</target><part>Saula</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wild Atlantic Way</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikivoyage</target><arg>Achill Island</arg></template><template><target>commons</target><arg>Achill Island</arg><arg>Achill Island</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target><arg>Achill</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ouririshheritage.org/category_id__29_path__0p2p.aspx'>Colaiste Pobail Acla students project on the Achill area</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.staugustinelighthouse.org/LAMP/Research/achill-island'>Achill Island Maritime Archaeology Project</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.visitachill.com'>VisitAchill multilingual visitor's site</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Mountains and hills of Connacht</target></template><template><target>County Mayo</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Islands of County Mayo</target></link><link><target>Category:Achill Island</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Gaeltacht places in County Mayo</target></link></paragraph></article>