<article title='Blue_Angels'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg></arg><arg>the 1960 television series</arg><arg>The Blue Angels (TV series)</arg><arg>the Scottish outlaw motorcycle club</arg><arg>Blue Angels Motorcycle Club</arg><arg>the hip-hop song</arg><arg>Blue Angels (song)</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military unit</target><arg name="unit_name"><space/>'''Blue Angels'''<br/>'''United States Navy Flight Exhibition Team'''
</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Blueangelsformationpd.jpg|300px]]
</arg><arg name="caption">The Blue Angels F/A-18 Hornets fly in their trademark tight [[diamond formation]], maintaining 18-inch wing tip to canopy separation.
</arg><arg name="dates"><space/>24 April 1946 to present
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>[[File:Flag of the United States.svg|20px]] United States
</arg><arg name="allegiance">
</arg><arg name="branch"><space/>{{Flagicon image|Flag of the United States Navy.svg|size</arg><arg name="website">{{URL|blueangels.navy.mil}}
</arg><arg name="type">
</arg><arg name="role"><space/>[[Aerobatic]] flight demonstration team
</arg><arg name="size"><space/>16 officers, 110 enlisted
</arg><arg name="command_structure">
</arg><arg name="garrison"><space/>[[Naval Air Station Pensacola|NAS Pensacola]]<space/><br/>[[Naval Air Facility El Centro|NAF El Centro]] (Winter Airfield)
</arg><arg name="garrison_label">
</arg><arg name="nickname">
</arg><arg name="patron">
</arg><arg name="motto">
</arg><arg name="colors"><space/>"Blue Angel" blue<br/>"Insignia" yellow
</arg><arg name="colors_label">
</arg><arg name="march">
</arg><arg name="mascot">
</arg><arg name="equipment">
</arg><arg name="equipment_label">
</arg><arg name="battles">
</arg><arg name="anniversaries">
</arg><arg name="decorations">
</arg><arg name="battle_honours">
</arg><arg name="disbanded">
<space/></arg><arg name="commander1">
</arg><arg name="commander1_label">
</arg><arg name="commander2">
</arg><arg name="commander2_label">
</arg><arg name="commander3_label">
</arg><arg name="notable_commanders">
<space/></arg><arg name="identification_symbol">[[File:Blue Angels Insignia.svg|200px]]
</arg><arg name="identification_symbol_label">
</arg><arg name="identification_symbol_2">
</arg><arg name="identification_symbol_2_label">
<space/></arg><arg name="aircraft_electronic">
</arg><arg name="aircraft_fighter">10 – [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18C Hornets]] (single seat)<space/><br/><space/>2 – [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18D Hornets]] (two seat)<space/><br/><space/>*Note – four aircraft are spares
</arg><arg name="aircraft_transport">1 – [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules|C-130T Hercules]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Blue Angels</bold><space/>is the<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target></link>'s flight demonstration squadron, with aviators from the Navy and Marines. The Blue Angels team was formed in 1946,<extension extension_name='ref' name="OFFICIAL"><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20110224175521/http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/history.htm'>&quot;History of the Blue Angels&quot;</link>. Blue Angels official site.</extension><space/>making it the second oldest formal flying aerobatic team (under the same name) in the world, after the French<space/><link><target>Patrouille de France</target></link><space/>formed in 1931. The Blue Angels' six demonstration pilots fly the<space/><link><target>McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet</target><part>F/A-18 Hornet</part></link>, typically in more than 70 shows at 34 locations throughout the United States each year, where they still employ many of the same practices and techniques used in their aerial displays in 1946. An estimated 11 million spectators view the squadron during air shows each full year. The Blue Angels also visit more than 50,000 people in a standard show season (March through November) in schools and hospitals.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blueangels.navy.mil"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/show/faq.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels: Frequently Asked Questions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blueangels.navy.mil<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>Since 1946, the Blue Angels have flown for more than 260 million spectators.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.navy.mil/navydata/aircraft/b-angels/blues.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">United States Navy: The Blue Angels History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Navy.mil<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 1 March 2013 the U.S. Navy announced that due to<space/><link><target>Sequester (2013)</target><part>sequestration actions</part></link><space/>aerial demonstration team performances including that of the Blue Angels would cease from 1 April 2013.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/03/01/17149624-military-spending-cuts-ground-blue-angels-thunderbirds?lite/'>Military spending cuts ground Blue Angels, Thunderbirds</link><space/>1 March 2013 NBC News;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.navy.mil/submit/display.asp?story_id=73264'>U.S. Navy Cancels Blue Angels 2013 Performances</link><space/>10 April 2013, U.S. Navy</extension><space/>In October 2013, Secretary of Defense Chuck Hagel, stating that &quot;community and public outreach is a crucial Departmental activity&quot;, announced that the Blue Angels (along with the U.S. Air Force's<space/><link><target>United States Air Force Thunderbirds</target><part>Thunderbirds</part></link>) would resume appearing at air shows starting in 2014, although the number of flyovers will continue to be severely reduced.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/politics/2013/10/thunderbirds-and-blue-angels-to-resume-air-shows-but-no-more-flyovers/</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Missions</heading><paragraph>The mission of the United States Navy Flight Demonstration Squadron is &quot;to showcase the pride and professionalism of the United States Navy and Marine Corps by inspiring a culture of excellence and service to country through flight demonstrations and community outreach.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blueangels.navy.mil"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Air show</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Blue Angels' show season runs each year from March until November. They perform at both military and civilian airfields, and often perform directly over major cities such as San Francisco's &quot;<link><target>Fleet Week</target></link>&quot; maritime festival,<space/><link><target>Cleveland</target></link>'s annual Labor Day Air Show, the<space/><link><target>Chicago Air and Water Show</target></link>, Milwaukee Air and Water Show, and<space/><link><target>Seattle</target></link>'s annual<space/><link><target>Seafair</target></link><space/>festival.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Blue Angels Flying in Delta Formation at Miramar.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The Blue Angels flying in a Delta Formation at<space/><link><target>Miramar, San Diego</target></link><space/>in 2011</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>During their<space/><link><target>aerobatics</target><part>aerobatic</part></link><space/>demonstration, the Blues fly six F/A-18 Hornet aircraft, split into the<space/><link><target>diamond formation</target><part>Diamond Formation</part></link><space/>(Blue Angels 1 through 4) and the Lead and Opposing<space/><italics>Solos</italics><space/>(Blue Angels 5 and 6). Most of the show alternates between<space/><link><target>Aerobatic maneuver</target><part>maneuver</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>performed by the Diamond Formation and those performed by the Solos. The Diamond, in tight formation and usually at lower speeds (400&amp;nbsp;mph), performs maneuvers such as formation loops, barrel rolls, and transitions from one formation to another. The Solos showcase the high performance capabilities of their individual aircraft through the execution of high-speed passes, slow passes, fast rolls, slow rolls, and very tight turns. The highest speed flown during an air show is 700&amp;nbsp;mph (just under Mach 1) and the lowest speed is 120&amp;nbsp;mph.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blueangels.navy.mil"></extension><space/>Some of the maneuvers include both solo aircraft performing at once, such as opposing passes (toward each other in what appears to be a collision course) and mirror formations (back-to-back. belly-to-belly, or wingtip-to-wingtip, with one jet flying inverted). The Solos join the Diamond Formation near the end of the show for a number of maneuvers in the<space/><link><target>Delta Formation</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The parameters of each show must be tailored in accordance with local weather conditions at showtime: in clear weather the<space/><italics>high</italics><space/>show is performed; in overcast conditions a<space/><italics>low</italics><space/>show is performed, and in limited visibility (weather permitting) the<space/><italics>flat</italics><space/>show is presented.The<space/><italics>high</italics><space/>show requires at least an<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>-2</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/><link><target>Flight ceiling</target><part>ceiling</part></link><space/>and visibility of at least<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3</arg><arg>nmi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>from the show's centerpoint. The maximum ceilings allowed for low and flat shows are 3,500 feet (~1&amp;nbsp;km) and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1500</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>-1</arg></template>, respectively.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.king5.com/news/local/high-show-low-show-Blue-Angels-100150074.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">What determines high show vs. low show for Blue Angels? &#124; KING5.com Seattle<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">King5.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">6 August 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origin of squadron name, insignia and paint scheme</heading><paragraph>When initially formed, the unit was called the<space/><italics>Navy Flight Exhibition Team</italics>. The squadron was officially redesignated as the United States Navy Flight Demonstration<space/><italics>Squadron</italics><space/>in December 1974.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://a4skyhawk.org/3e/blues/blues.htm</extension><space/>The original team was christened the<space/><italics>Blue Angels</italics><space/>in 1946, when one of the pilots came across the name of New York City's Blue Angel Nightclub in<space/><italics><link><target>New Yorker Magazine</target><part>The New Yorker</part></link></italics><space/>magazine; the team introduced themselves as the &quot;Blue Angels&quot; to the public for the first time on 21 July 1946, in<space/><link><target>Omaha, Nebraska</target><part>Omaha</part></link>, Nebraska.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The official Blue Angels insignia was designed by then team leader Lt. Cmdr. R. E. &quot;Dusty&quot; Rhodes and Virginia Porter (Illustrator for Naval Air Advanced Training Command), then approved by<space/><link><target>Chief of Naval Operations</target></link><space/>in 1949. It is nearly identical to the current design. In the cloud in the upper right quadrant, the aircraft were originally shown heading down and to the right. Over the years, the plane silhouettes have changed along with the squadron's aircraft. Additionally, the lower left quadrant, which contains the Chief of Naval Air Training insignia, has occasionally contained only<space/><link><target>Naval Aviator</target></link><space/>wings.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Originally, demonstration aircraft were navy blue (nearly black) with gold lettering. The current shades of blue and yellow were adopted when the team transitioned to the Bearcat in 1946. For a single year in 1949, the team performed in an all-yellow scheme with blue markings.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell,<space/><italics>War Paint</italics>, p. 171.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Current aircraft</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:BlueAngelsFA18.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Prandtl-Glauert singularity</target><part>Water condensation</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Strake (aviation)</target><part>strake</part></link><space/>vortices of a Hornet during a tight maneuver.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Blues' F/A-18 Hornets are former fleet aircraft that are nearly combat-ready. Modifications to each aircraft include removal of the aircraft gun and replacement with the tank that contains smoke-oil used in demonstrations, and outfitting with the control stick spring system for more precise aircraft control input. The standard demonstration configuration has a spring tensioned with<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>of force installed on the control stick as to allow the pilot minimal room for uncommanded movement. The Blues do not wear<space/><link><target>G-suit</target><trail>s</trail></link>, because the air bladders inside them would repeatedly deflate and inflate, interfering with the control stick between the pilot's legs. Instead, Blue Angel pilots tense their muscles to prevent blood from rushing from their heads and rendering them unconscious.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ba_faq"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/show/faq.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Frequently Asked Questions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blueangels.navy.mil<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:C-130 Herculues with JATO.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>&quot;Fat Albert&quot; conducting a<space/><link><target>RATO</target><part>Rocket Assisted Take Off</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The show's narrator flies Blue Angel 7, a two-seat F/A-18D Hornet, to show sites. The Blues use this jet for backup, and to give demonstration rides to VIP civilians. Three backseats at each show are available; one of them goes to members of the press, the other two to &quot;Key Influencers&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flyfighterjet.com/jetflights/fly-with-the-blue-angels.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Flights with the Blue Angels<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Flyfighterjet.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>The No.4 slot pilot often flies the No. 7 aircraft in Friday's &quot;practice&quot; shows.</paragraph><paragraph>The Blue Angels use a<space/><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target></link><space/><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target><part>C-130T Hercules</part></link>, nicknamed &quot;Fat Albert&quot;, for their logistics, carrying spare parts, equipment, and to carry support personnel between shows. Beginning in 1975, &quot;Bert&quot; was used for<space/><link><target>JATO</target><part>Jet Assisted Take Off</part></link><space/>(JATO) and short aerial demonstrations just prior to the main event at selected venues, but the JATO demonstration ended in 2009 due to dwindling supplies of rockets.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FA JATO"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Abort Launch: Air shows to do without Fat Albert’s famed JATO</arg><arg name="last">McCullough</arg><arg name="first">Amy</arg><arg name="date">9 November 2009</arg><arg name="work">[[Marine Corps Times]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Gannett Company]]</arg><arg name="page">6</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 November 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>&quot;Fat Albert Airlines&quot; flies with an all-Marine crew of three officers and five enlisted personnel.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Team members</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Voris and 1st Blue Angel team 1946.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The first Blue Angel Flight Demonstration Squadron (19461947), assembled in front of one of their<space/><link><target>F6F Hellcat</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(l to r): Lt. Al Taddeo, Solo; Lt. (J.G.) Gale Stouse, Spare; Lt. Cdr. R.M. &quot;Butch&quot; Voris, Flight Leader; Lt. Maurice &quot;Wick&quot; Wickendoll, Right Wing; Lt. Mel Cassidy, Left Wing.</part></link><link><target>File:Blues Support Crew watching Diamond Formation at Show.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The &quot;Blues&quot; support crew watches the team perform in the<space/><link><target>Grumman F9F-2 Panther</target></link><space/>jet fighter.</part></link><link><target>File:Blue Angels Pilot.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A Blue Angels Flight Demonstration Squadron pilot sits in the cockpit of an<space/><link><target>F/A-18 Hornet</target></link><space/>aircraft</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>All team members, both officer and enlisted, pilots and staff officers, come from the ranks of regular Navy and<space/><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target></link><space/>units. The demonstration pilots and narrator are made up of Navy and USMC<space/><link><target>Naval Aviator</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Pilots serve two to three years,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blueangels.navy.mil"></extension><space/>and position assignments are made according to team needs, pilot experience levels, and career considerations for members.</paragraph><paragraph>The officer selection process requires pilots and support officers (flight surgeon, events coordinator, maintenance officer, supply officer, and public affairs officer) wishing to become Blue Angels to apply formally via their chain-of-command, with a personal statement, letters of recommendation and flight records. Navy and Marine Corps F/A-18 demonstration pilots and naval flight officers are required to have a minimum of 1,250 tactical jet hours and be carrier-qualified. Marine Corps C-130 demonstration pilots are required to have 1,200 flight hours and be an aircraft commander.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://archives.gosportpensacola.com/gosport-03-02-2012.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Gosport article, March 02, 2012, "Blue Angels Seek Officer Applicants", page 2</arg><arg name="publisher">Gosport NAS Pensacola Base Newspaper</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Applicants &quot;rush&quot; the team at one or more airshows, paid out of their own finances, and sit in on team briefs and post-show activities and social events. Rushes are asked to tell a joke prior to the brief, and graded by the team as part of the rigorous selection process. Team members vote in secret on the next year's members, with no accountability to the higher Navy authority why an applicant was or was not selected. Selections must be unanimous. There have been female and racial minority staff officers as official Blue Angel members, in support of the Blue Angels recruiting for the Navy and Marine Corps. The most recent minority Blue Angel pilot was LCDR Keith Hoskins on the 2000 team.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels-usn.org/blues_pilots2000.html</arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Alumni 2000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">blueangels-usn.org</arg></template></extension><space/>Flight surgeons serve a two-year term, and act as the team recorder during air shows, and help oversee emergency response planning with the various air show planners. The first female Blue Angel flight surgeon was LT Tamara Schnurr, as a member of the 2001 team.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels-usn.org/blues_pilots2001.html</arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Alumni 2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">blueangels-usn.org</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The team leader (#1) is the Commanding Officer and is always a Navy Commander, who may be promoted to Captain mid-tour if approved for Captain by the selection board. Pilots of numbers 27 are Navy Lieutenants or Lieutenant Commanders, or Marine Corps Captains or Majors. The number 7 pilot narrates for a year, and then typically flies Opposing and then Lead Solo the following two years, respectively. The number 3 pilot moves to the number 4 (slot) position for his second year. Blue Angel No.4 serves as the demonstration safety officer, due largely to the perspective he is afforded from the slot position within the formation, as well as his status as a second-year demonstration pilot. There are a number of other officers in the squadron, including a<space/><link><target>Naval Flight Officer</target></link>, the USMC C-130 pilots, a Maintenance Officer, an Administrative Officer, and a Flight Surgeon. Enlisted members range from E-4 to E-9, and perform all maintenance, administrative, and support functions. They serve three to four years in the squadron.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blueangels.navy.mil"></extension><space/>After serving with the Blues, members return to fleet assignments.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>As of</target><arg>2014</arg><arg name="alt">Members of the 2015</arg></template><space/>U.S. Navy Blue Angels are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.1, Captain Thomas Frosch, USN (Commanding Officer/Flight Leader)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.2, Lieutenant Matt Suyderhoud, USN (Right Wing)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.3, Lieutenant Andrew Talbott, USN (Left Wing)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.4, Lieutenant Commander Nate Barton, USN (Slot)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.5, Lieutenant Mark Tedrow, USN (Lead Solo)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.6, Lieutenant Ryan Chamberlain, USN (Opposing Solo)</listitem><listitem>Flying Blue Angel No.7, Captain Jeff Kuss, USMC (Advance Pilot/Narrator)</listitem><listitem>Events Coordinator, Blue Angel No.8, Captain Corrie Mays, USMC</listitem><listitem>Flying Fat Albert, M1, Captain Dusty Cook, USMC</listitem><listitem>Flying Fat Albert, Major Mark Hamilton, USMC</listitem><listitem>Flying Fat Albert, Captain Katie Higgins, USMC</listitem><listitem>Executive Officer, Commander Bob Flynn, USN</listitem><listitem>Maintenance Officer, Lieutenant Commander Declan Hartney, USN</listitem><listitem>Flight Surgeon, Lieutenant Joe Schwartz, MC USN</listitem><listitem>Administrative Officer, Lieutenant junior grade Phillip Harper, USN</listitem><listitem>Supply Officer, Lieutenant Gregory Bollinger, USN</listitem><listitem>Public Affairs Officer, Lieutenant junior grade Amber Daniel, USN</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Commanding officer</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Commander Tom Frosch.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Captain Tom Frosch</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Capt. (then Commander) Tom Frosch relieved Capt. Greg McWherter as Blue Angel commanding officer/flight leader on 4 November 2012. Frosch has more than 3,000 flight hours, 830 carrier arrested landings, and is a graduate of U.S. Naval Test Pilot School aboard NAS Patuxent River, where he subsequently was an F/A-18 E/F Super Hornet test pilot with VX-23 (Air Test and Evaluation Squadron TWO THREE) STRIKE TEST. His decorations include the Defense Meritorious Service Medal, two<space/><link><target>Meritorious Service Medal (United States)</target><part>Meritorious Service Medal</part><trail>s</trail></link>, two Individual Air Medals with Combat &quot;V&quot; (Six Strike Flight), three Navy Commendation Medals, one with Combat &quot;V&quot;, and numerous unit, campaign and service awards.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Training and weekly routine</heading><paragraph>Annual winter training takes place at<space/><link><target>NAF El Centro</target></link>, California, where new and returning pilots hone skills learned in the fleet. During winter training, the pilots fly two practice sessions per day, six days a week, in order to fly the 120 training missions needed to perform the demonstration safely. Separation between the formation of aircraft and their maneuver altitude is gradually reduced over the course of about two months in January and February. The team then returns to their home base in<space/><link><target>Pensacola</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Florida</target></link>, in March, and continues to practice throughout the show season. A typical week during the season has practices at NAS Pensacola on Tuesday and Wednesday mornings. The team then flies to its show venue for the upcoming weekend on Thursday, conducting &quot;circle and arrival&quot; orientation maneuvers upon arrival. The team flies a &quot;practice&quot; airshow at the show site on Friday. This show is attended by invited guests but is often open to the general public. The main airshows are conducted on Saturdays and Sundays, with the team returning home to NAS Pensacola on Sunday evenings after the show. Monday is the Blues' day off.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>1940s</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Blue Angels Vinage Insignia.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright=0.8</part><part>The original team insignia</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On 24 April 1946<space/><link><target>Chief of Naval Operations</target></link><space/><link><target>Admiral</target></link><space/><link><target>Chester Nimitz</target></link><space/>issued a directive ordering the formation of a flight exhibition team to boost Navy morale, demonstrate naval air power, and maintain public interest in naval aviation. However, an underlying mission was to help the Navy generate public and political support for a larger allocation of the shrinking defense budget. In April of that year, Rear Admiral Ralph Davison personally selected<space/><link><target>Lieutenant Commander</target></link><space/><link><target>Roy Marlin Voris</target><part>Roy Marlin &quot;Butch&quot; Voris</part></link>, a World War II<space/><link><target>fighter ace</target></link>, to assemble and train a flight demonstration team, naming him Officer-in-Charge and Flight Leader. Voris selected three fellow instructors to join him (Lt. Maurice &quot;Wick&quot; Wickendoll, Lt. Mel Cassidy, and Lt. Cmdr. Lloyd Barnard, veterans of the War in the Pacific), and they spent countless hours developing the show. The group perfected its initial maneuvers in secret over the Florida<space/><link><target>Everglades</target></link><space/>so that, in Voris' words, &quot;if anything happened, just the alligators would know&quot;. The team's first demonstration before Navy officials took place on 10 May 1946 and was met with enthusiastic approval.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:F6F-5 Blue Angels NAN10 46.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Grumman F6F Hellcat</target><part>Grumman F6F-5 Hellcats</part></link><space/>in 1946</part></link>On 15 June Voris led a trio of<space/><link><target>Grumman F6F Hellcat</target><part>Grumman F6F-5 Hellcats</part></link>, specially modified to reduce weight and painted sea blue with gold leaf trim, through their inaugural 15-minute-long performance at their Florida home base,<space/><link><target>Naval Air Station Jacksonville</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OFFICIAL"></extension><space/>The team employed an<space/><link><target>T-6 Texan</target><part>SNJ Texan</part></link>, painted and configured to simulate a<space/><link><target>Japanese Zero</target></link>, to simulate aerial combat. This aircraft was later painted yellow and dubbed the &quot;Beetle Bomb&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The team thrilled spectators with low-flying maneuvers performed in tight formations, and (according to Voris) by &quot;keeping something in front of the crowds at all times. My objective was to beat the Army Air Corps. If we did that, we'd get all the other side issues. I felt that if we weren't the best, it would be my naval career.&quot; The Blue Angels' first public demonstration also netted the team its first trophy, which sits on display at the team's current home at<space/><link><target>Naval Air Station Pensacola</target><part>NAS Pensacola</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:F8F-1 Blue Angels 1946.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>In 1947 the Blue Angels introduced the famous &quot;diamond&quot; formation.</part></link>The team soon became known worldwide for its spectacular aerobatic maneuvers. On 25 August 1946 the squadron upgraded their aircraft to the<space/><link><target>F8F Bearcat</target><part>F8F-1 Bearcat</part></link>. In May 1947, flight leader Lt. Cmdr. Bob Clarke replaced Butch Voris as the leader of the team and introduced the famous Diamond Formation, now considered the Blue Angels' trademark.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1949, the team acquired a Douglas<space/><link><target>C-47</target><part>R4D Sky Train</part></link><space/>for logistics to and from show sites. The team's SNJ was also replaced by a F8F-1 &quot;Bearcat&quot;, painted yellow for the air combat routine. The Blues transitioned to the straight-wing Grumman<space/><link><target>F9F Panther</target><part>F9F-2 Panther</part></link><space/>on 13 July 1949, wherein the F8F-1 &quot;Beetle Bomb&quot; was relegated to solo aerobatics before the main show, until it crashed on takeoff at a training show in Pensacola in 1950.</paragraph><paragraph>Team headquarters shifted from<space/><link><target>NAS Corpus Christi</target></link>, Texas, to<space/><link><target>Naval Air Station Whiting Field</target><part>NAAS Whiting Field</part></link>, Florida, in the fall of 1949, announced 14 July 1949.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fort Walton, Florida, &quot;<italics>'Blue Angels' To Pensacola Navy Flight Exhibition Team Is Transferred</italics>&quot;, Playground News, Thursday 14 July 1949, Volume 4, Number 24, page 2.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>1950s</heading><paragraph>The &quot;Blues&quot; continued to perform nationwide until the start of the<space/><link><target>Korean War</target></link><space/>in 1950, when (due to a shortage of pilots, and no planes were available) the team was disbanded and its members were ordered to combat duty. Once aboard the aircraft carrier<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Princeton</arg><arg>CV-37</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>the group formed the core of<space/><link><target>VF-191</target><part>VF-191, Satan's Kittens</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:F9F-8 Blue Angles1 NAN1-57.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>F9F-8 Cougar formation in 1956</part></link>The Blue Angels were officially recommissioned on 25 October 1951, and reported to<space/><link><target>Naval Air Station Corpus Christi</target><part>NAS Corpus Christi</part></link>, Texas. Lt. Cdr. Voris was again tasked with assembling the team (he was the first of only two commanding officers to lead them twice). In 1953 the team traded its Sky Train for a Curtiss<space/><link><target>C-46</target><part>R5C Commando</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target><part>Marine Corps</part></link><space/>pilot, Capt Chuck Hiett, joined the team and they relocated to their current home of<space/><link><target>NAS Pensacola</target></link><space/>in the winter of 1954. It was here they progressed to the swept-wing Grumman<space/><link><target>F9F Cougar</target><part>F9F-8 Cougar</part></link>. In August 1954, &quot;Blues&quot; leader<space/><link><target>Arthur Ray Hawkins</target><part>LCDR Ray Hawkins</part></link><space/>became the first naval aviator to survive an ejection at supersonic speeds when his F9F-6 became uncontrollable on a cross-country flight.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Grumman F11F-1 Tiger Blue Angels.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Grumman F11F-1 Tiger, 195769</part></link>In Sept 1956, the team added a sixth aircraft to the flight demonstration in the Opposing Solo position, and gave its first performance outside the United States at the International Air Exposition in<space/><link><target>Toronto, Canada</target></link>. It also upgraded its logistics aircraft to the Douglas<space/><link><target>C-54</target><part>R5D Skymaster</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In January 1957, the team left its winter training facility at<space/><link><target>Naval Air Facility El Centro</target></link>, California for a ten-year period. For the next ten years, the team would winter at<space/><link><target>NAS Key West</target></link>, Florida. For the 1957 show season, the Blue Angels transitioned to the supersonic Grumman<space/><link><target>F11F Tiger</target><part>F11F-1 Tiger</part></link>, first flying the short-nosed, and then the long-nosed versions. The first Six-Plane Delta Maneuvers were added in the 1958 season.</paragraph><heading level='3'>1960s</heading><paragraph>In July 1964, the Blue Angels participated in the Aeronaves de Mexico Anniversary Air Show over<space/><link><target>Mexico City</target></link>, Mexico, before an estimated crowd of 1.5&amp;nbsp;million people.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1965, the Blue Angels conducted a<space/><link><target>Caribbean</target></link><space/>island tour, flying at five sites. Later that year, they embarked on a European tour to a dozen sites, including the<space/><link><target>Paris Air Show</target></link>, where they were the only team to receive a standing ovation.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Blues</italics><space/>toured Europe again in 1967 touring six sites. In 1968 Skymaster transport aircraft was replaced with a<space/><link><target>Lockheed C-121 Constellation</target><part>C-121J Constellation</part></link>. The<space/><italics>Blues</italics><space/>transitioned to the two-seat<space/><link><target>McDonnell Douglas</target></link><space/><link><target>F-4 Phantom II</target><part>F-4J Phantom II</part></link><space/>in 1969, nearly always keeping the back seat empty for flight demonstrations. The<space/><italics>Phantom</italics><space/>was the only plane to be flown by both the &quot;Blues&quot; and the<space/><link><target>United States Air Force Thunderbirds</target></link>. That year they also upgraded to the Lockheed<space/><link><target>Lockheed Constellation</target><part>C-121 Super Constellation</part></link><space/>for logistics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>1970s</heading><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Blues</italics><space/>received their first U.S. Marine Corps Lockheed<space/><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target><part>KC-130F Hercules</part></link><space/>in 1970. An all-Marine crew manned it. That year, they went on their first South American tour. In 1971, the team conducted its first Far East Tour, performing at a dozen locations in Korea, Japan, Taiwan, Guam, and the Philippines. In 1972, the Blue Angels were awarded the Navy's<space/><link><target>Meritorious Unit Commendation</target></link><space/>for the two-year period from 1 March 1970 31 December 1971. Another European tour followed in 1973, including air shows in Tehran, Iran, England, France, Spain, Turkey, Greece, and Italy.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:A-4Fs Blue Angels Fleur de Lis 1984.JPEG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>All six Blue Angel<space/><link><target>Douglas A-4 Skyhawk</target><part>A-4F Skyhawk</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>executing a &quot;fleur de lis&quot; maneuver.</part></link>In December 1974 the Navy Flight Demonstration Team downsized to the subsonic<space/><link><target>Douglas A-4 Skyhawk</target><part>Douglas A-4F Skyhawk II</part></link><space/>and was reorganized into the Navy Flight Demonstration Squadron. This reorganization permitted the establishment of a commanding officer (the flight leader), added support officers, and further redefined the squadron's mission emphasizing the support of recruiting efforts. Commander Tony Less was the squadron's first official commanding officer.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>1980s</heading><paragraph>On 8 November 1986 the Blue Angels completed their 40th anniversary year during ceremonies unveiling their present aircraft, the McDonnell Douglas<space/><link><target>F/A-18 Hornet</target></link>, the first multi-role fighter/attack aircraft. The power and aerodynamics of the Hornet allows them to perform a slow, high<space/><link><target>angle of attack</target></link><space/>&quot;tail sitting&quot; maneuver, and to fly a &quot;dirty&quot; (landing gear down) formation loop, the last of which is not duplicated by the USAF Thunderbirds.</paragraph><paragraph>Also in 1986, LCDR<space/><link><target>Donnie Cochran</target></link>, joined the Blue Angels as the first<space/><link><target>Black people</target><part>African-American</part></link><space/>Naval Aviator to be selected. He would return to lead the team in 1993.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>rquote</target><arg>right</arg><arg>Today is a very special and memorable day in your military career that will remain with you throughout your lifetime. You have survived the ultimate test of your peers and have proven to be completely deserving to wear the crest of the U.S. Navy Blue Angels. The prestige of wearing the Blue Angels uniform carries with it an extraordinary honor – one that reflects not only on you as an individual, but on your teammates and the entire squadron. To the crowds at the air shows and to the public at hospitals and schools nationwide, you are a symbol of the Navy and Marine Corps' finest. You bring pride, hope and a promise for tomorrow's Navy and Marine Corps in the smiles and handshakes of today's youth. Remember today as the day you became a Blue Angel; look around at your teammates and commit this special bond to memory. "Once a Blue Angel, always a Blue Angel," rings true for all those who wear the crest of the U.S. Navy Blue Angels. Welcome to the team.</arg><arg name="The Blue Angels Creed, written by JO1 Cathy Konn,{{Citation needed|date">May 2011}} 1991–1993</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Blue Angels flying in formation1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>F/A-18s Performing in San Francisco</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>1990s</heading><paragraph>In 1992 the Blue Angels deployed for a month-long European tour, their first in 19 years, conducting shows in Sweden, Finland, Russia (the first foreign flight demonstration team to perform there), Romania, Bulgaria, Italy, the United Kingdom and Spain.In 1998, CDR Patrick Driscoll made the first &quot;Blue Jet&quot; landing on a &quot;<link><target>haze gray and underway</target></link>&quot; aircraft carrier,<space/><link><target>USS Harry S. Truman</target><part>USS ''Harry S. Truman''</part></link><space/>(CVN-75).</paragraph><heading level='3'>2000s</heading><paragraph>In 2006, the Blue Angels marked their 60th year of performing.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.navy.com/about/navylife/onduty/blueangels/history/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Monumental Moments<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Navy.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>On 30 October 2008 a spokesman for the team announced that the team would complete its last three performances of the year with five jets instead of six. The change was because one pilot and another officer in the organization had been removed from duty for engaging in an &quot;inappropriate relationship&quot;. The Navy stated that one of the individuals was a man and the other a woman, one a Marine and the other from the Navy, and that Rear Admiral Mark Guadagnini, chief of Naval air training, was reviewing the situation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.pnj.com/article/20081031/SPORTS1001/810310363<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blues Angels Pilot, Other Grounded<space/></arg><arg name="last">Moon<space/></arg><arg name="first">Troy<space/></arg><arg name="date">31 October 2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Pensacola News Journal]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20081204073915/http://pnj.com:80/article/20081031/SPORTS1001/810310363<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">4 December 2008<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>At the next performance at<space/><link><target>Lackland Air Force Base</target></link><space/>following the announcement the No.4 or slot pilot, was absent from the formation. A spokesman for the team would not confirm the identity of the pilot removed from the team.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.pnj.com/article/20081102/NEWS01/811020335/1006/NEWS01<space/></arg><arg name="title">No. 4 jet missing from Blue Angels<space/></arg><arg name="last">Griggs<space/></arg><arg name="first">Travis<space/></arg><arg name="date">2 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Pensacola News Journal]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20090202170237/http://www.pnj.com:80/article/20081102/NEWS01/811020335/1006/NEWS01<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2 February 2009<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>On 6 November 2008 both officers were found guilty at an<space/><link><target>Nonjudicial punishment</target><part>admiral's mast</part></link><space/>on unspecified charges but the resulting punishment was not disclosed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scutro, Andrew, &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.militarytimes.com/news/2008/11/navy_blueangels_110708/'>2 Blue Angels found guilty, await punishment</link>&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Military Times</target></link></italics>, 8 November 2008.</extension><space/>The names of the two members involved were later released on the Pensacola News Journal website/forum as pilot No. 4 USMC Maj. Clint Harris and the administrative officer, Navy Lt. Gretchen Doane.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://defensetech.org/2008/10/31/a-potentially-disgraced-angel-updated/'>&quot;A (Potentially) Disgraced Angel (updated)&quot;</link>, Defensetech.org</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Fat Albert performed its final JATO demonstration at the 2009 Pensacola Homecoming show, spending their 8 remaining JATO bottles. This demonstration not only was the last JATO performance of the squadron, but also the final JATO profile of the entire U.S. Marine Corps.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/docs/pr_20090909.pdf'>&quot;End of JATO for Blue Angels!&quot;</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">July 2011</arg></template>, blueangels.navy.mil, November 2009</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>2010s</heading><paragraph>On 22 May 2011, the Blue Angels were performing at the Lynchburg Regional Airshow in<space/><link><target>Lynchburg, Virginia</target><part>Lynchburg</part></link>, Virginia, when the Diamond formation flew the Barrel Roll Break maneuver at an altitude that was lower than the required minimum altitude.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blue_Angels_Comparison"><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dlUWQlXQB20&amp;amp;feature=related'>Barrel Roll Break as performed on 21 May 2011 and 22 May 2011</link>,<space/><link><target>YouTube.com</target></link></extension><space/>The maneuver was aborted, the remainder of the demonstration canceled and all aircraft landed safely. The next day, the Blue Angels announced that they were initiating a safety stand-down, canceling their upcoming Naval Academy Airshow and returning to their home base in Pensacola, Florida, for additional training and airshow practice.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/media/news/20110523_001.pdf'>Blue Angels Cancel Naval Academy Airshow</link>. blueangels.navy.mil.</extension><space/>On 26 May, the Blue Angels announced they would not be flying their traditional fly-over of the Naval Academy Graduation Ceremony and that they were canceling their 2829 May 2011 performances at the Millville Wings and Wheels Airshow in<space/><link><target>Millville, New Jersey</target><part>Millville</part></link>, New Jersey.</paragraph><paragraph>On 27 May 2011, the Blue Angels announced that Commander Dave Koss, the squadron's Commanding Officer, would be stepping down. He was replaced by Captain Greg McWherter, the team's previous Commanding Officer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cnn2011"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Blue Angels commander steps down after subpar performance</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/05/27/virginia.blue.angels/<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>27 May 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CNN<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 May 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The squadron canceled performances at the<space/><link><target>Rockford, Illinois</target><part>Rockford</part></link>, Illinois Airfest 45 June and the<space/><link><target>Evansville, Indiana</target><part>Evansville</part></link>, Indiana Freedom Festival Air Show 1112 June to allow additional practice and demonstration training under McWherter's leadership.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cnn2011"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Between 2 and 4 September 2011 on<space/><link><target>Labor Day</target></link><space/>weekend, the Blue Angels flew for the first time with a 5050 blend of conventional JP-5 jet fuel and a<space/><link><target>camelina</target></link>-based biofuel at<space/><link><target>Naval Air Station Patuxent River</target></link><space/>airshow at<space/><link><target>Patuxent River</target></link>, Maryland.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aero-news.net/index.cfm?do</arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Use Biofuel At Patuxent Air Show &#124; Aero-News Network<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Aero-news.net<space/></arg><arg name="date">6 September 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">John Pike<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/2011/09/mil-110901-nns02.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels to Soar on Biofuel During Labor Day Weekend Air Show<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Globalsecurity.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 January 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>McWherter flew an F/A-18 test flight on 17 August and stated there were no noticeable differences in performance from inside the cockpit.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Austell<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jason<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nbcsandiego.com/news/local/128900393.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Go Green<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">NBC San Diego<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 September 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.military.com/news/article/navy-news/blue-angels-use-biofuel-at-patuxent-air-show.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels Use Biofuel at Patuxent Air Show<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Military.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 September 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 9 April 2013, the U.S. Navy released a statement that it was cancelling all remaining 2013 performances due to budget constraints,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Navy_Cancels"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/media/news/20130409_001.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>U.S. Navy Cancels Blue Angels 2013 Performances<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 April 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>which ends the 2013 Blue Angels season after 2 of 35 scheduled shows were performed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/media/show/2013ShowSchedule.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">U.S. Navy 2013 Show Schedule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 April 2013<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 April 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>The Navy also stated it continues to believe the value of inspiring future generations,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Navy_Cancels"></extension><space/>and that the 2014 Blue Angels Schedule has not been subject to any cancellations, the schedule itself was released in September 2013.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/media/show/2014ShowSchedule.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">U.S. Navy 2014 Show Schedule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In June 2014, Captain Greg McWherter, flight leader of the Blue Angels for 2008-2010 and 2011-2012, received letter of reprimand from Adm.<space/><link><target>Harry B. Harris Jr.</target><part>Harry Harris</part></link><space/>after an<space/><link><target>Non-judicial punishment</target><part>admiral's mast</part></link><space/>for failing to stop obvious and repeated instances of sexual harassment, condoning widespread lewd practices within the squadron and engaging in inappropriate and unprofessional discussions with his junior officers&quot; during his second tour with the team.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.navytimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID</arg><arg name="title">Former Blue Angels CO reprimanded for 'toxic' climate</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Navy Times]]</arg><arg name="date">June 3, 2014</arg><arg name="accessdate">June 10, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July 2014, Marine Corps Capt. Katie Higgins, 27, became the first female pilot to join the Blue Angels.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pope2014"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.flyingmag.com/news/jdK7LcHf6g0emiTC.99<space/></arg><arg name="title">First Female Pilot Joins Blue Angels<space/></arg><arg name="date">July 24, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 9, 2015<space/></arg><arg name="author">Pope, Stephen<space/></arg><arg name="work">Flying<space/></arg><arg name="via">flyingmag.com<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="prudente2015"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Breaking a gender barrier at 370 mph: Severna Park pilot becomes first woman to fly with elite Blue Angels<space/></arg><arg name="author">Prudente, Tim<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 6, 2015<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 9, 2015<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Baltim. Sun]]<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.baltimoresun.com/sports/outdoors/ph-ac-cn-higgins-0507-20150506-story.html<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aircraft timeline</heading><paragraph>The &quot;Blues&quot; have flown eight different demonstration aircraft and five support aircraft models:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/aircraft/historical.aspx</extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Demonstration aircraft</defkey></listitem></list><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>Grumman F6F-5 Hellcat</target></link>: JuneAugust 1946</listitem><listitem><link><target>Grumman F8F-1 Bearcat</target></link>: August 1946 1949</listitem><listitem><link><target>Grumman F9F-2 Panther</target></link>: 1949 June 1950 (first jet); F9F-5 Panther: 1951 - Winter 1954/55</listitem><listitem><link><target>Grumman F9F-8 Cougar</target></link>: Winter 1954/55 - mid-season 1957 (swept-wing)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Grumman F11F-1 (F-11) Tiger</target></link>: mid-season 1957 1969 (first supersonic jet)</listitem><listitem><link><target>McDonnell Douglas F-4J Phantom II</target></link>: 1969 December 1974</listitem><listitem><link><target>Douglas A-4F Skyhawk</target></link>: December 1974 November 1986</listitem><listitem><link><target>McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet</target><part>McDonnell Douglas F/A-18A/B/C/D Hornet</part></link><space/>(F/A-18B/D are #7 aircraft): November 1986 present</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Support aircraft</defkey></listitem></list><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>Douglas R4D Skytrain</target></link>: 19491955</listitem><listitem><link><target>Curtiss R5C Commando</target></link>: 1953</listitem><listitem><link><target>Douglas R5D Skymaster</target></link>: 19561968</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lockheed C-121 Super Constellation</target></link>: 19691973</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target></link><space/>&quot;Fat Albert&quot;: 1970present</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Miscellaneous aircraft</defkey></listitem></list><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>North American SNJ Texan</target></link><space/>(used to simulate a Japanese<space/><link><target>Mitsubishi A6M Zero</target><part>A6M Zero</part></link><space/>aircraft in demonstrations during the late 1940s)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lockheed T-33 Shooting Star</target></link><space/>(Used during the 1950s as a VIP transport aircraft for the team)<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vought F7U Cutlass</target></link><space/>(two of the unusual F7Us were received in late 1952 and flown as a side demonstration during the 1953 season but they were not a part of their regular formations which at the time used the F9F Panther. Pilots and ground crew found it unsatisfactory and plans to use it as the team's primary aircraft were cancelled).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Show routine</heading><paragraph>The following is the show routine used on 17 May 2008:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Joint Services Open House (Andrews AFB) 2008<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.airshowstuff.com/andrewsafb2008.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">AirshowStuff.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 May 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:US Navy 040815-N-7559C-001 Blue Angels perform the opposing Knife-Edge Pass.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The solos make a &quot;knife-edge&quot; pass. The far aircraft is actually slightly higher than the near aircraft to make them appear in-line to the audience.</part></link><link><target>File:Blue angels double farvel.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blue Angels in the double farvel formation.</part></link><link><target>File:Blue Angels - Section High-Alpha Pass.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blue Angels aircraft perform the &quot;Section High Alpha&quot;, the slowest maneuver of their show. During the maneuver the two jets slow down to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>125</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>as they pitch the nose of the F/A-18 up to 45 degrees.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Solo Blue Angel USCG.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blue Angel number seven roars past during the Fleet Week 2007 air show over the<space/><link><target>San Francisco Bay</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Blue Angels on Delta Formation.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blue Angels on<space/><link><target>Delta Formation</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Fat Albert (C-130) high performance takeoff (Low Transition)</listitem><listitem>Fat Albert Parade Pass (Photo Pass. The plane banks around the front of the crowd)</listitem><listitem>Fat Albert Flat Pass</listitem><listitem>Fat Albert Head on Pass</listitem><listitem>Fat Albert Short-Field Assault Landing</listitem><listitem>FA-18 Engine Start-Up and Taxi Out</listitem><listitem>Diamond Take-off (Either a low transition with turn, loop on takeoff, a half-Cuban 8 takeoff, or a Half Squirrel Cage)</listitem><listitem>Solos Take-off (Blue Angel #5: Dirty Roll on Take-Off; Blue Angel #6: Low Transition to High Performance Climb)</listitem><listitem>Diamond 360: Aircraft 1, 2, 3 and 4 are in their signature 18&quot; wingtip-to-canopy diamond formation.</listitem><listitem>Opposing Knife-Edge Pass</listitem><listitem>Diamond Roll: The whole diamond formation rolls as a single entity.</listitem><listitem>Opposing Inverted to Inverted Rolls</listitem><listitem>Diamond Aileron Roll: All 4 diamond jets perform simultaneous<space/><link><target>aileron roll</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem>Fortus: Solos flying in carrier landing configuration with No.5 inverted, establishing a &quot;mirror image&quot; effect.</listitem><listitem>Diamond Dirty Loop: The diamond flies a loop with all 4 jets in the carrier landing configuration.</listitem><listitem>Minimum Radius Turn (Highest G maneuver. No.5 flies a &quot;horizontal loop&quot; pulling 7 Gs to maintain a tight radius)</listitem><listitem>Double Farvel: Diamond formation flat pass with aircraft 1 and 4 inverted.</listitem><listitem>Opposing Minimum Radius Turn</listitem><listitem>Echelon Parade</listitem><listitem>Opposing Horizontal Rolls</listitem><listitem>Left Echelon Roll: The roll is made into the Echelon, which is somewhat difficult for the outside aircraft.</listitem><listitem>Sneak Pass: the fastest speed of the show is about 700&amp;nbsp;mph (just under Mach 1 at sea level)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jumpcut.com/view?id=C009AF72755211DC9F89000423CF037A'>Video</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">July 2011</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Line-Abreast Loop the most difficult formation maneuver to do well. No.5 joins the diamond as the 5 jets fly a loop in a straight line</listitem><listitem>Opposing Four-Point Hesitation Roll</listitem><listitem>Vertical Break</listitem><listitem>Opposing Vertical Pitch</listitem><listitem>Barrel Roll Break</listitem><listitem>Section High-Alpha Pass: (tail sitting), the show's slowest maneuver<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/show/faq.aspx'>Blue Angels FAQ</link></extension><space/><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UGVWg_gMW38'>Video</link></listitem><listitem>Low Break Cross</listitem><listitem>Inverted Tuck Over Roll</listitem><listitem>Tuck Under Break</listitem><listitem>Delta Roll</listitem><listitem>Fleur de Lis</listitem><listitem>Solos Pass to Rejoin, Diamond flies a loop</listitem><listitem>Loop Break Cross (Delta Break): After the break the aircraft separate in six different directions, perform half<space/><link><target>Cuban Eight</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>then cross in the center of the performance area.</listitem><listitem>Delta Breakout</listitem><listitem>Delta Pitch Up Carrier Break to Land</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Accidents</heading><paragraph>During its history, 26 Blue Angels pilots have been killed in air show or training accidents.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18248797/'>Investigators probe Blue Angels crash</link>, MSNBC, 22 April 2007</extension><space/>Through the 2006 season there have been 262 pilots in the squadron's history,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangelsalumni.org/FAQ.htm'>Blue Angels Alumni FAQ</link>, last updated 17 March 2007.</extension><space/>giving the job a 10% fatality rate.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>1946 September: Lt. &quot;Robby&quot; Robinson was killed during a performance when a wingtip broke off his Bearcat, sending him into an unrecoverable spin.</listitem><listitem>1952 Two Panthers collided during a demonstration in<space/><link><target>Corpus Christi, Texas</target><part>Corpus Christi</part></link>, Texas and one pilot was killed. The team resumed performances two weeks later.</listitem><listitem>2 August 1958 - Lt. John R. Dewenter landed, wheels up at<space/><link><target>Buffalo Niagara International Airport</target></link><space/>after experiencing engine troubles during a show in<space/><link><target>Clarence, NY</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Grumman F-11 Tiger</target></link><space/>landed on Runway 23 but exited airport property coming to rest in the intersection of Genesee Street and Dick Road, nearly hitting a gas station. Lt. Dewenter was uninjured and the plane was a total loss.</listitem><listitem>14 October 1958 Cmdr. Robert Nicholls Glasgow died during an orientation flight just days after reporting for duty as the new Blue Angels leader.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5ipAxGUkLKt7E55ff4uZ-UAMMiQ0QD96MHOK00'>Blue Angels crash artifacts found 50 years later</link>, Associated Press, 3 March 2009<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5ipAxGUkLKt7E55ff4uZ-UAMMiQ0QD96MHOK00<space/></arg><arg name="date">20090310231414<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>15 March 1964 Lt. George L. Neale, 29, was killed during an attempted emergency landing at Apalach Airport near<space/><link><target>Apalachicola, Florida</target><part>Apalachicola</part></link>, Florida. Lt. Neale's<space/><link><target>F-11 Tiger</target><part>F-11A Tiger</part></link><space/>had experienced mechanical difficulties during a flight from<space/><link><target>West Palm Beach, Florida</target><part>West Palm Beach</part></link>, Florida to<space/><link><target>NAS Pensacola</target></link>, causing him to attempt the emergency landing. Failing to reach the airport, he ejected from the aircraft on final approach, but his parachute did not have sufficient time to fully deploy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Basham, Dusty, &quot;<italics>Blue Angel Pilot Killed Jet Fighter Falls Near Apalachicola</italics>&quot;, Playground Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, Monday Morning, 16 March 1964, Volume 18, Number 27, pages 1, 2.</extension></listitem><listitem>2 September 1966 Lt. Cmdr. Dick Oliver crashed his Tiger and was killed at the<space/><link><target>Canadian International Air Show</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Toronto</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>1 February 1967 Lt Frank Gallagher was killed when his Tiger stalled during a practice Half Cuban 8 maneuver and spun into the ground.</listitem><listitem>18 February 1967 Capt. Ronald Thompson was killed when his Tiger struck the ground during a practice formation loop.</listitem><listitem>14 January 1968 Opposing solo Lt. Bill Worley was killed when his Tiger crashed during a practice double immelman.</listitem><listitem>30 August 1970 Lt. Ernie Christensen belly-landed his F-4J Phantom at the<space/><link><target>Eastern Iowa Airport</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cedar Rapids</target></link><space/>with one engine stuck in afterburner. He ejected safely, while the aircraft ran off the runway.</listitem><listitem>4 June 1971 CDR Harley Hall safely ejected after his Phantom caught fire and crashed during practice over Narragansett Bay near the ex-NAS Quonset Point in Rhode Island.</listitem><listitem>14 February 1972 Lt. Larry Watters was killed when his F-4J Phantom II struck the ground, upright, while practicing inverted flight, during winter training at NAF El Centro.</listitem><listitem>8 March 1973 Capt. John Fogg, Lt. Marlin Wiita and LCDR Don Bentley survived a multi-aircraft mid-air collision during practice over the Superstition Mountains in California.</listitem><listitem>26 July 1973 2 pilots and a crew chief were killed in a mid-air collision between 2 Phantoms over Lakehurst, NJ during an arrival practice. Team Leader LCDR Skip Umstead, Capt. Mike Murphy and ADJ1 Ron Thomas perished. The rest of the season was cancelled after this incident.</listitem><listitem>22 February 1977 Opposing solo Lt. Nile Kraft was killed when his Skyhawk struck the ground during practice.</listitem><listitem>8 November 1978 One of the solo Skyhawks struck the ground after low roll during arrival maneuvers at<space/><link><target>MCAS Miramar</target><part>NAS Miramar</part></link>. Navy Lieutenant Michael Curtin was killed.</listitem><listitem>April 1980 Lead Solo Lt. Jim Ross was unhurt when his Skyhawk suffered a fuel line fire during a show at<space/><link><target>NS Roosevelt Roads</target></link>, Puerto Rico. LT Ross stayed with and landed the plane which left the end of the runway and taxied into the woods after a total hydraulic failure upon landing.</listitem><listitem>22 February 1982 Lt. Cmdr Stu Powrie, Lead Solo was killed when his Skyhawk struck the ground during winter training at Naval Air Facility El Centro, California just after a dirty loop.</listitem><listitem>13 July 1985 Lead and Opposing Solo Skyhawks collided during a show at Niagara Falls, killing opposing solo Lt. Cmdr. Mike Gershon. Lt. Andy Caputi ejected and parachuted to safety.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://usmilitary.about.com/library/weekly/aa102899.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Navy Blue Angel Aviators Die in Crash", 28 October 1999, accessed 23 April 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Usmilitary.about.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>12 February 1987 Lead solo Lt. Dave Anderson ejected from his Hornet after a dual engine flameout during practice near El Centro, CA.</listitem><listitem>23 January 1990 Two Blue Angel Hornets suffered a mid-air collision during a practice at El Centro. Marine Corps Maj. Charles Moseley ejected safely. Cmdr. Pat Moneymaker was able to land his airplane, which then required a complete right wing replacement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Clausen<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://moneymaker.rootsweb.com/newspapers/clip08.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Pilot Blamed In Blue Angel Crash<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Pensacola News Journal<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 June 1990<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>28 October 1999 Lt. Cmdr. Kieron O'Connor, flying in the front seat of a two-seat Hornet, and recently selected demonstration pilot Lt. Kevin Colling (in the back seat) struck the ground during circle and arrival maneuvers in<space/><link><target>Valdosta, Georgia</target><part>Valdosta</part></link>, Georgia. Neither pilot survived.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cnn.com/US/9910/28/missing.angel.04/<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Blue Angel crash victims identified", CNN, 28 October 1999, accessed 23 April 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CNN<space/></arg><arg name="date">28 October 1999<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>1 December 2004 Lt. Ted Steelman ejected from his F/A-18 approximately one mile off Perdido Key after his aircraft struck the water, suffering catastrophic engine and structural damage. He suffered minor injuries.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,140233,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Blue Angels Pilot Ejects Before Plane Crashes", '&#39;Fox News'&#39;, 2 December 2004, accessed 23 April 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fox News<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 December 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>21 April 2007 Lt. Cmdr. Kevin J. Davis<space/><link><target>2007 Blue Angels South Carolina crash</target><part>crashed his ''Hornet''</part></link><space/>near the end of the<space/><link><target>MCAS Beaufort</target><part>Marine Corps Air Station Beaufort</part></link><space/>airshow in<space/><link><target>Beaufort, South Carolina</target><part>Beaufort</part></link>, South Carolina, and was killed.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN2122401820070421'>U.S. Navy &quot;Blue Angels&quot; jet crashes</link>. Reuters</extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other incidents involving former Blue Angels</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>8 March 1951<space/><link><target>Lieutenant Commander</target><part>LCDR</part></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;amp;GSln=magda&amp;amp;GSbyrel=all&amp;amp;GSdy=1951&amp;amp;GSdyrel=in&amp;amp;GSob=n&amp;amp;GRid=3302605&amp;amp;df=all&amp;amp;'>Johnny Magda</link>, while flying in Korea, was the first former Blue Angel killed in combat.</listitem><listitem>27 January 1973 CDR Harley Hall (1970 team leader) was shot down flying an F-4J over<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>, and was officially listed as<space/><link><target>missing in action</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>In the media</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Blue Angels Newton-John Travolta cropped.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>John Travolta</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Olivia Newton-John</target></link><space/>with Blue Angels, 1982</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>The Blue Angels (TV series)</target><part>The Blue Angels</part></link></italics><space/>was a dramatic television series, starring<space/><link><target>Dennis Cross</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Don Gordon (actor)</target><part>Don Gordon</part></link>, inspired by the team's exploits and filmed with the cooperation of the Navy. It aired in<space/><link><target>Television syndication</target><part>syndication</part></link><space/>from 26 September 1960 to 3 July 1961.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0053485/'>Blue Angels TV series, 1960</link></extension></listitem><listitem>The Blue Angels were the subject of &quot;Flying Blue Angels&quot;, a pop song recorded by George, Johnny and the Pilots (Coed Co 555), that debuted on<space/><italics><link><target>Billboard Magazine</target></link></italics>'s &quot;Bubbling Under the Hot 100&quot; chart on 11 September 1961.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Threshold: The Blue Angels Experience</target></link></italics><space/>is a 1975 documentary film, written by<space/><italics><link><target>Dune</target></link></italics><space/>author<space/><link><target>Frank Herbert</target></link>, featuring the team in practice and performance during their F-4J Phantom era; many of the aerial photography techniques pioneered in<space/><italics>Threshold</italics><space/>were later used in the film<space/><italics><link><target>Top Gun</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0163870/'>IMDb.com</link></extension></listitem><listitem>In 2005, the<space/><link><target>Discovery Channel</target></link><space/>aired a documentary miniseries,<space/><italics>Blue Angels: A Year in the Life</italics>, focusing on the intricate day-to-day details of that year's training and performance schedule.<extension extension_name='ref' name="discovery"><link type='external' href='http://shopping.discovery.com/product-59147.html?jzid=40588004-59-0'>Blue Angels: A Year in the Life</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://shopping.discovery.com/product-59147.html?jzid</arg><arg name="date">20120210060847<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="discovery2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://imdb.com/title/tt0450901/<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Blue Angels: A Year in the Life" (2005)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Imdb.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The video for the American rock band<space/><link><target>Van Halen</target></link>'s 1986 release &quot;<link><target>Dreams (Van Halen song)</target><part>Dreams</part></link>&quot; consists of Blue Angels performance footage. The video was originally shot featuring the Blues in the A-4 Skyhawk. A later video features the F/A-18 Hornet.</listitem><listitem>The Blue Angels appeared in the episodes &quot;Death Begins at Forty&quot; and &quot;Insult to Injury&quot; of<space/><link><target>Tim Allen</target></link>'s television sitcom<space/><italics><link><target>Home Improvement (TV series)</target><part>Home Improvement</part></link></italics><space/>as themselves.</listitem><listitem>The Blue Angels made a brief appearance on<space/><italics><link><target>I Love Toy Trains</target></link></italics><space/>part 3.</listitem><listitem>The Blue Angels were featured in the<space/><link><target>IMAX</target></link><space/>film<space/><italics><link><target>Magic of Flight</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem>In 2009, the<space/><italics><link><target>MythBusters</target></link></italics><space/>enlisted the aid of Blue Angels to help test the myth that a sonic boom could shatter glass.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.aero-news.net/index.cfm?do=main.textpost&amp;id=d3efb603-f4f2-4120-bafb-3db867c52d90</extension></listitem><listitem>The Blue Angels are a major part of the novel<space/><italics>Shadows of Power</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>James W. Huston (author)</target><part>James W. Huston</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jameswhuston.com/books/shadows-of-power/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Shadows of Power<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">jameswhuston.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 June 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Blue Angels and the<space/><link><target>United States Air Force Thunderbirds</target><part>Thunderbirds</part></link></italics><space/>is a 4 disc<space/><italics><link><target>SkyTrax</target></link></italics><space/>DVD set 2012<space/><link><target>TOPICS Entertainment, Inc.</target></link><space/>It features highlights from airshows performed in the U.S.A. shot from inside and outside the cockpit including interviews of squadron aviators, plus aerial combat footage taken during<space/><link><target>Desert Storm</target></link>, histories of the two flying squadrons from 1947 through 2008 including on-screen notes on changes in Congressional budgeting and research program funding, photo gallery slide shows, and two &quot;forward-looking&quot; sequences<space/><italics>Into the 21st Century</italics><space/>detailing developments of the<space/><link><target>F/A-18 Hornet</target></link>'s C and E and F models (10 min.) and footage of the<space/><link><target>F-22</target></link><space/>with commentary (20 min.).</listitem><listitem>In the television micro-series<space/><italics>Star Wars: Clone Wars</italics>, Anakin Skywalker's starfighter is named Azure Angel, after the Blue Angels team.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://web.archive.org/web/http://blogs.starwars.com/holocron/16</extension></listitem><listitem>In<space/><link><target>My Little Pony: Friendship Is Magic</target></link>, the Wonderbolts are based on the Blue Angels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://twitter.com/goldenrusset/status/147573636369354752</arg><arg name="title">Jayson Thiessen (@goldenrusset)</arg><arg name="publisher">Twitter.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notable alumni</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Captain<space/><link><target>Chuck Brady</target></link><space/>Astronaut</listitem><listitem>Captain<space/><link><target>Donnie Cochran</target></link><space/>first African-American Blue Angels aviator and commander</listitem><listitem>Rear Admiral<space/><link><target>Edward L. Feightner</target></link><space/>World War II<space/><link><target>flying ace</target><part>fighter ace</part></link><space/>and Lead Solo</listitem><listitem>Captain<space/><link><target>Robert L. Rasmussen</target></link><space/>Aviation Artist</listitem><listitem>Commander<space/><link><target>Raleigh Rhodes</target></link><space/>World War II veteran and third leader of the Blue Angels<extension extension_name='ref' name="lat"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Combat pilot in two wars led Blue Angels</arg><arg name="url">http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/california/la-me-rhodes7dec07,1,4242966.story?coll</arg><arg name="work">Los Angeles Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 December 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 December 2007<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080111064544/http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/california/la-me-rhodes7dec07,1,4242966.story?coll</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>11 January 2008</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Captain<space/><link><target>Roy Marlin Voris</target></link><space/>First Blue Angel leader</listitem><listitem><link><target>Patrick M. Walsh</target><part>Admiral Patrick M. Walsh</part></link><space/>Left Wingman and Slot Pilot, 19851987; Commander of the<space/><link><target>United States Pacific Fleet</target><part>U.S. Pacific Fleet</part></link>, Former<space/><link><target>Vice Chief of Naval Operations</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>White House Fellow</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Budget</heading><paragraph>In November 2011, the Blue Angels received $37 million annually, out of the annual DoD budget.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/military/story/2011-11-23/navy-blue-angels/51365536/1<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels fly into age of budget woes<space/></arg><arg name="work">USA Today<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 November 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/show/faq.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blue Angels FAQ<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>All 2013 shows after the Naval Air Station Key West, Fla. Southernmost Air Spectacular on 2324 March 2013 were canceled due to the<space/><link><target>Budget sequestration in 2013</target><part>sequestration</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>United States Navy</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of United States Navy aircraft squadrons</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Air Force Thunderbirds</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Marine Corps Aviation</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>(2012).<space/><link type='external' href='http://alpharetta.11alive.com/news/news/113965-my-incredible-flight-aboard-blue-angels'>&quot;My incredible flight aboard the Blue Angels&quot; By Charles Atkeison</link></listitem><listitem>(2005). &quot;The First Blue Angel.&quot;<space/><italics>Miramar 50th Air Show Special Commemorative Program</italics><space/>18.</listitem><listitem>(2005). &quot;The Blue Angels History.&quot;<space/><italics>Miramar 50th Air Show Special Commemorative Program</italics><space/>22.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangels.com/timeline.shtml#46'>Blue Angels Timeline (19461980)</link><space/>accessed 10 November 2005.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.grummanpark.org/blueangels.htm'>&quot;Grumman and the Blue Angels&quot;</link><space/>article by William C. Barto at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.grummanpark.org/'>Grumman Memorial Park</link><space/>official website accessed 15 October 2005.</listitem><listitem>&quot;First Blue: The story of World War II Ace Butch Voris and the Creation of the Blue Angels&quot; by Robert K. Wilcox, Thomas Dunne Books/St.Martins Press, 2004,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.robertkwilcox.com/'>robertkwilcox.com</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target><arg>Blue Angels</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.blueangels.navy.mil/'>Blue Angels, official U.S. Navy web site</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>US Navy navbox</target></template><template><target>Modern aerobatic teams</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Aircraft squadrons of the United States Navy</target></link><link><target>Category:American aerobatic teams</target></link></paragraph></article>