<article title='Severus_Alexander'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox Roman emperor</target><arg name="name"><space/>Severus Alexander
</arg><arg name="full name"><space/>Marcus Julius Gessius Bassianus Alexianus<space/><br />(from birth to adoption);<br /><space/>Caesar Marcus Aurelius Alexander (from adoption to accession);<br /><space/>Caesar Marcus Aurelius Severus Alexander Augustus<space/><br />(as emperor)
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Alexander Severus Musei Capitolini MC471.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Bust of Severus Alexander
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[Roman emperor|26th Emperor]] of the [[Roman Empire]]
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>11 March 222 – 18/19 March 235
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Elagabalus]]
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Maximinus Thrax]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Sallustia Orbiana]]<br/>[[Sulpicia Memmia]]
</arg><arg name="issue">
</arg><arg name="royal house"><space/>[[Severan dynasty|Severan]]
</arg><arg name="house-type"><space/>Imperial Dynasty
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Marcus Julius Gessius Marcianus]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>[[Julia Avita Mamaea]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{Birth date|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Arqa|Arca Caesarea]], [[Phoenicia|Syria Phoenicia Province]] (modern [[Akkar District|Akkar]], [[Lebanon]])
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>19 March 235 (aged 26)
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Mainz|Moguntiacum]], [[Germania Superior]]
</arg><arg name="place of burial">
</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>Severan dynasty</target><arg name="image">[[File:Severan dynasty - tondo.png|200px]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>The [[Severan Tondo]]
</arg></template><bold>Severus Alexander</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-la</target><arg>Marcus Aurelius Severus Alexander Augustus</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'>In<space/><link><target>Classical Latin</target></link>, Alexander's name would be inscribed as MARCVS AVRELIVS SEVERVS ALEXANDER AVGVSTVS.</extension><space/>1 October 208 19 March 235) was<space/><link><target>Roman Emperor</target></link><space/>from 222 to 235. Alexander was the last emperor of the<space/><link><target>Severan dynasty</target></link>. He succeeded his cousin<space/><link><target>Elagabalus</target></link><space/>upon the latter's<space/><link><target>assassination</target></link><space/>in 222, and was ultimately assassinated himself, marking the<space/><link><target>epoch event</target></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>Crisis of the Third Century</target></link><space/>nearly fifty years of civil wars, foreign invasion, and collapse of the monetary economy.</paragraph><paragraph>Alexander was the<space/><link><target>heir apparent</target></link><space/>to his cousin, the eighteen-year-old Emperor who had been murdered along with his mother<space/><link><target>Julia Soaemias</target></link><space/>by his own guards, who, as a mark of contempt, had their remains cast into the<space/><link><target>Tiber river</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dio, 60:20:2</extension><space/>He and his cousin were both grandsons of the influential and powerful<space/><link><target>Julia Maesa</target></link>, who had arranged for Elagabalus' acclamation as emperor by the famous<space/><link><target>Legio III Gallica</target><part>Third Gallic Legion</part></link>. It was the rumor of Alexander's death that triggered the assassination of Elagabalus and his mother.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodian, 5:8:5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As emperor, Alexander's peace time reign was prosperous. However militarily Rome was confronted with the rising<space/><link><target>Sassanid Empire</target></link>. He managed to check the threat of the Sassanids, but when campaigning against<space/><link><target>Germanic peoples</target><part>Germanic tribes</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Germania</target></link>, Alexander attempted to bring peace by engaging in diplomacy and bribery. This alienated many in the<space/><link><target>Roman legion</target><part>legions</part></link><space/>and led to a conspiracy to assassinate and replace him.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Domestic achievements</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Severus alexander.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>''<link><target>Denarius</target></link>'' of Severus Alexander.</part></link>Under the influence of his mother, Alexander did much to improve the morals and condition of the people, and to enhance the dignity of the state.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benario, Alexander Severus"></extension><space/>He employed noted<space/><link><target>jurist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to oversee the administration of justice, such as the famous jurist<space/><link><target>Ulpian</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 61"></extension><space/>His advisers were men like the<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target><part>senator</part></link><space/>and historian<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>and it is claimed that he created a select board of sixteen senators,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 60">Southern, pg. 60</extension><space/>although this claim is disputed.<extension extension_name='ref'>from the chapter entitled Administrative Strategies of the Emperor Severus Alexander and his Advisers, written by Lukas de Blois in the book Herrschaftsstrukturen und Herrschaftspraxis, chapter by</extension><space/>He also created a municipal council of fourteen who assisted the<space/><link><target>urban prefect</target></link><space/>in administering the affairs of the fourteen districts of Rome.<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 33:1</extension><space/>Excessive luxury and extravagance at the imperial court were diminished.<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 15:1</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Upon his accession he reduced the silver purity of the<space/><link><target>denarius</target></link><space/>from 46.5% to 43% the actual silver weight dropping from 1.41&amp;nbsp;grams to 1.30&amp;nbsp;grams; however, in 229 he revalued the denarius, increasing the silver purity and weight to 45% and 1.46&amp;nbsp;grams respectively. The following year he decreased the amount of base metal in the denarius while adding more silver raising the silver purity and weight again to 50.5% and 1.50&amp;nbsp;grams.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tulane.edu/~august/handouts/601cprin.htm'>Tulane University &quot;Roman Currency of the Principate&quot;</link></extension><space/>Also during his reign taxes were lightened; literature, art and science were encouraged;<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 21:6</extension><space/>and, for the convenience of the people, loan offices were instituted for lending money at a moderate rate of interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 21:2</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In religious matters, Alexander preserved an open mind. It is said that he was desirous of erecting a temple to<space/><link><target>Jesus</target></link>, but was dissuaded by the<space/><link><target>Paganism</target><part>pagan</part></link><space/>priests.<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 43:67</extension><space/>He allowed a<space/><link><target>synagogue</target></link><space/>to be built in Rome, and he gave as a gift to this synagogue a scroll of the<space/><link><target>Torah</target></link><space/>known as the<space/><link><target>Severus Scroll</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;amp;artid=1153'>19011906 Jewish Encyclopedia article &quot;Alexander Severus&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In legal matters, Alexander did much to aid<space/><link><target>Military justice</target><part>the rights of his soldiers</part></link>. He confirmed that soldiers could name anyone as heirs in their<space/><link><target>Will and testament</target><part>will</part></link>, whereas civilians had strict restrictions over who could become heirs or receive a legacy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pg. 221</extension><space/>Alexander also confirmed that soldiers could free their slaves in their wills.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pg. 224</extension><space/>Additionally, he protected the rights of soldiers to their property when they are off on campaign<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pg. 239</extension><space/>and reasserted that a soldier's property acquired in or because of military service (his<space/><italics>castrense peculium</italics>) could be claimed by no one else, not even the soldier's father.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pg. 234</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Persian War</heading><paragraph>On the whole, however, the reign of Alexander was prosperous until the rise, in the east, of the<space/><link><target>Sassanid Empire</target><part>Sassanids</part></link><space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 61">Southern, pg. 61</extension><space/>under<space/><link><target>Ardashir I</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Severus Alexander.&quot; Encyclopaedia Britannica. Encyclopaedia Britannica Online Academic Edition. Encyclopdia Britannica Inc., 2014. Web. 02 May. 2014. &lt;http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/536782/Severus-Alexander&gt;.</extension><space/>Of the war that followed there are various accounts. According to<space/><link><target>Herodian</target></link>, the Roman armies suffered a number of humiliating setbacks and defeats,<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodian, 6:56:6</extension><space/>while according to the<space/><link><target>Historia Augusta</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 55:13</extension><space/>as well as Alexander's own dispatch to the<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target></link>, he gained great victories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 62">Southern, pg. 62</extension><space/>Making<space/><link><target>Antioch</target></link><space/>his base, he marched at the head of his troops towards<space/><link><target>Ctesiphon</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 61">Southern, pg. 61</extension><space/>but a second army was destroyed by the Persians,<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodian, 6:5:10</extension><space/>and further losses were incurred by the retreating Romans in<space/><link><target>Roman Armenia</target><part>Armenia</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodian, 6:6:3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, although the Sassanids were checked for the time,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 62">Southern, pg. 62</extension><space/>the conduct of the<space/><link><target>Imperial Roman army</target><part>Roman army</part></link><space/>showed an extraordinary lack of discipline.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 61">Canduci, pg. 61</extension><space/>In 232 there was a mutiny in the Syrian legion, who proclaimed<space/><link><target>Taurinus</target></link><space/>emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Victor, 24:2</extension><space/>Alexander managed to suppress the uprising, and Taurinus drowned while attempting to flee across the<space/><link><target>Euphrates</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 59">Canduci, pg. 59</extension><space/>The emperor returned to<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link><space/>and celebrated a triumph in 233.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 62">Southern, pg. 62</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Germanic War</heading><paragraph>After the Persian war, Alexander returned to Antioch with the famous<space/><link><target>Origen</target></link>, one of the greatest Fathers of the Christian Church. Alexander's mother, Julia Mammaea, asked for him to tutor Alexander in<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>. While Alexander was being educated in the Christian doctrines, the northern portion of his empire was being invaded by Germanic and Sarmatian tribes. A new and menacing enemy started to emerge directly after Alexander's success in the Persian war. In A.D 234, the barbarians crossed the Rhine and Danube in hordes that even caused panic at the gates of Rome. The soldiers serving under Alexander, who were already demoralized after their costly war against the Persians, were further discontented with their emperor when their homes were destroyed by the barbarian invaders.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, 54</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As word of the invasion spread, the Emperor took the front line and went to battle against the Germanic invaders. The Romans prepared heavily for the war against the Germanics, building a brigade of ships to carry the entire battalion across. However, at this point in Alexander's career, he still knew little about being a general. Because of this, he hoped the sole threat of his armies might be enough to persuade the Germanics to surrender.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Alexander Severus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.roman-empire.net/decline/alex-severus-index.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Capitoline Museums</arg></template></extension><space/>Severus enforced a strict military discipline in his men that sparked a rebellion among the Germanic legions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Western Press Association"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Library of World History: Containing a Record of the Human Race from the Earliest Historical Period to the Present Time; Embracing a General Survey of the Progress of Mankind in National and Social Life, Civil Government, Religion, Literature, Science and Art, Volume 3</arg><arg name="publisher">Western Press Association</arg><arg name="location">New York Public Library</arg><arg name="pages">1442</arg></template></extension><space/>Due to incurring heavy losses against the Persians, and on the advice of his mother, Alexander attempted to buy the Germanic tribes off, so as to gain time.</paragraph><paragraph>It was this decision that resulted in the<space/><link><target>Legionary</target><part>legionaries</part></link><space/>looking down upon Alexander. They considered him dishonorable and feared he was unfit to be Emperor. Under these circumstances the army swiftly looked to replace Alexander. Gaius Iulius Verus Maximinus was the next best option. He was a soldier from Thrace who had a golden reputation and was working hard to increase his military status.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Western Press Association"></extension><space/>He was also a man with superior personal strength, rising from peasantry to ultimately being the one chosen for the throne. With the Thracian's hailing came the end of the Severan Dynasty.<extension extension_name='ref' name="The Saylor Foundation"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Severus Alexander (222–235 AD): The Calm before the Storm</arg><arg name="url">http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/HIST301-7.2-SeverusAlexander-FINAL.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">The Saylor Foundation</arg></template></extension><space/>With his own army growing with animosity and turning against him, the path for his assassination was paved.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Death</heading><paragraph>Alexander was forced to face his German enemies in the early months of 235. By the time he and his mother arrived, the situation had settled, and so his mother convinced him that to avoid violence, trying to bribe the German army to surrender was the more sensible course of action.<extension extension_name='ref'>Canduci, pg.61</extension><space/>According to historians, it was this tactic combined with insubordination from his own men that destroyed his reputation and popularity. Pusillanimity was responsible for the revolt of Alexanders army, resulting in Severus falling victim to the swords of his own men.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Valentine Nind Hopkins 240"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Valentine Nind Hopkins</arg><arg name="first">Sir Richard</arg><arg name="title">The Life of Alexander Severus</arg><arg name="publisher">The University Press</arg><arg name="location">Princeton University</arg><arg name="pages">240</arg></template></extension><space/>This was following the nomination of Maximinus as emperor. Alexander was assassinated March 19, 235 together with his mother, in a mutiny of the<space/><link><target>Legio XXII Primigenia</target><part>Legio XXII ''Primigenia''</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Mainz</target><part>Moguntiacum (Mainz)</part></link><space/>while at a meeting with his generals.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Southern, pg. 63">Southern, pg. 63</extension><space/>These assassinations secured the throne for Maximinus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benario, Alexander Severus">Benario,<space/><italics>Alexander Severus</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Aelius Lampridius</target><part>Lampridius</part></link><space/>documents two theories that elaborate on the assassination of Alexander Severus. The first claims that the disaffection of Mammaea was the main motive behind the homicide. However, Lampridius makes it clear that he is more supportive of an alternative theory where Alexander is murdered in Sicilia, located in Britain. In an open tent after his lunch, Alexander was consulting with his insubordinate troops. They compared him to<space/><link><target>Elagabalus</target></link>, a divisive and unpopular Emperor whose own assassination paved the way for Alexander's reign. A German servant entered the tent and initiated the call for the Emperors assassination, an attack in which many of the troops joined. Alexander's attendants fought against the other troops but could not hold off the combined might of those seeking the Emperor's assassination. Within minutes, Alexander was dead.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Valentine Nind Hopkins 240"></extension><space/>After Alexander's death, his economic policies were completely discarded and the Roman currency was devalued. This marked the beginning of the Crisis of the Third Century, a time period in which the Roman empire came close to falling apart entirely.<extension extension_name='ref' name="The Saylor Foundation"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph>Alexander was the last of the Syrian emperors and the first emperor to be overthrown by military discontent on a wide scale.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pg. 55</extension><space/>His death signaled the end of the<space/><link><target>Severan dynasty</target></link><space/>and the beginning of the chaotic period known as the<space/><link><target>Crisis of the Third Century</target></link><space/>which brought the empire to near collapse.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 61">Canduci, pg. 61</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexander's death at the hands of his troops can also be seen as the heralding of a new role for Roman Emperors. Though they were not yet expected to personally fight in battle during Alexander's time, emperors were increasingly expected to display general competence in military affairs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 69">Campbell, pg. 69</extension><space/>Thus, Alexander's taking of his mother's advice not to get involved in battle, his dishonorable and unsoldierly methods of dealing with the Germanic threat, and the relative failure of his military campaign against the Persians were all deemed highly unacceptable by the soldiers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 69">Campbell, pg. 69</extension><space/>Indeed, Maximinus was able to overthrow Alexander by &quot;harping on his own military excellence in contrast to that feeble coward.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 69">Campbell, pg. 69</extension><space/>Yet by arrogating the power to dethrone their emperor, the legions paved the way for a half-century of widespread chaos and instability.</paragraph><paragraph>Alexander's reign was also characterized by a significant breakdown of military discipline.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 196">Campbell, pg. 196</extension><space/>In 223 the<space/><link><target>Praetorian Guard</target></link><space/>murdered their<space/><link><target>Praetorian prefect</target><part>prefect</part></link>, Ulpian,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 196"></extension><space/>and did so in Alexander's presence and despite the emperor's pleas.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 61"></extension><space/>The soldiers then fought a three-day battle against the populace of Rome, and this battle ended after several parts of the city were set on fire.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 197">Campbell, pg. 197</extension><space/>Dio also gave a highly critical account of military discipline during the time, saying that they would rather just surrender to the enemy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 197"></extension><space/>Different reasons are given for this breakdown of military discipline: Campbell points to<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;...the decline in the prestige of the Severan dynasty, the feeble nature of Alexander himself, who appeared to be no soldier and to be completely dominated by his mother's advice, and lack of real military success at a time during which the empire was coming under increasing pressure.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 197"></extension></extension>Herodian, on the other hand, was convinced that &quot;the emperor's miserliness (partly the result of his mother's greed) and slowness to bestow donatives&quot; were instrumental in the fall of military discipline under Alexander.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell, pg. 197"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Canduci, Alexander is remembered as an emperor who was &quot;level headed, well meaning, and conscientious,&quot; but his fatal flaw was his domination by his mother and grandmother.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 61"></extension><space/>Not only did this undermine his authority, but his mother's influence was the cause of Alexander's least popular actions (convincing him not to take part in battle and trying to buy off the warring Germanic barbarians).</paragraph><paragraph>Although the emperor and his rule were declared damned by the Senate at the news of his death and the ascension of a new emperor in his place, Alexander was<space/><link><target>Apotheosis</target><part>deified</part></link><space/>after the death of Maximinus in 238.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Severus Alexander.&quot; Encyclopaedia Britannica. Encyclopaedia Britannica Online Academic Edition. Encyclopdia Britannica Inc., 2014. Web. 02 May. 2014 &lt;http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/536782/Severus-Alexander&gt;.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal life</heading><paragraph>Severus Alexander became emperor when he was 13 years old, making him the youngest Emperor in Rome's history until the ascension of Gordian III. His grandmother believed that he had more potential to rule than her other grandson, the increasingly unpopular then-emperor Elagabalus.<extension extension_name='ref'>Canduci, pg. 60</extension><space/>Thus, to preserve her own position, she had Elagabalus adopt the young Alexander and then arranged for his assassination, securing the throne for Alexander.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wells, pg. 266</extension><space/>The Roman army hailed Alexander emperor on March 13, 222, immediately instilling him with the titles of Augustus, pater patriae, and pontifex maximus. Throughout his life, Alexander relied heavily on guidance from his grandmother, Maesa, and mother, Mamaea. Alexander's grandmother died in 223, leaving his mother as the sole influence upon Alexander's actions. As a young, immature, and inexperienced 13-year-old, Alexander knew little about government and the role of ruling over an empire. Because of this, throughout his entire reign he was a puppet of his mother's advice and entirely under her jurisdiction, a prospect that was not popular among the soldiers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Canduci, pg. 60-61</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexander was married three times. His most famous wife was<space/><link><target>Sallustia Orbiana</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Augusta (honorific)</target><part>Augusta</part></link>,</italics><space/>whom he married in 225. Sallustia Orbiana was 16 years old when marrying Alexander Severus, as the result of an arranged marriage by Alexander's mother, Julia Mamaea. However, as soon as Orbiana received the title of<space/><italics>Augusta,</italics><space/>Mamaea became increasingly jealous and resentful of Alexander's wife due to her excessive desire of all regal female titles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benario, Alexander Severus"></extension><space/>He divorced and exiled her in 227, after her father,<space/><link><target>Seius Sallustius</target></link>, was executed after being accused of attempting to assassinate the emperor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 59">Canduci, pg. 59</extension><space/>Another wife was Sulpicia Memmia, a member of one of the most ancient Patrician families in Rome. Her father was a man of consular rank; her grandfather's name was<space/><italics>Catulus</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Historia Augusta,<space/><italics>Life of Severus Alexander</italics>, 20:3</extension><space/>The identity of Alexander's third wife is unknown. Alexander fathered no children with all three wives.</paragraph><paragraph>Concerning religious matters, Alexander prayed every morning in his private chapel, and had the motto, &quot;Do unto others as thou wouldst have them do unto thee&quot; inscribed on his palace and upon various public buildings. He was extremely tolerant of not only Christians, but also<space/><link><target>Jews</target></link>, as he continued all privileges towards Jews during his reign.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Alexander Severus</arg><arg name="url">http://jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/1153-alexander-severus</arg><arg name="publisher">Jewish Encyclopedia</arg></template></extension><space/>Alexander also claimedly placed images of Abraham and Jesus in his oratory, along with other Roman deities and classical figures.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Alexander Severus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13743a.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Catholic Encyclopedia</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Severan dynasty family tree</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">20em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Primary</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/80*.html'>''Roman History, Book 80''</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Herodian</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/he-hg/herodian/hre601.html'>''Roman History, Book 6''</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Historia Augusta</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Historia_Augusta/Severus_Alexander/1*.html'>''Life of Severus Alexander''</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Aurelius Victor</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.roman-emperors.org/epitome.htm'>''Epitome de Caesaribus''</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Joannes Zonaras</target></link>, Compendium of History<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ancientsites.com/aw/Post/1049415'>extract: ''Zonaras: Alexander Severus to Diocletian: 222284''</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Zosimus</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/zosimus01_book1.htm'>''Historia Nova''</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Secondary</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Birley, A.R.,<space/><italics>Septimius Severus: The African Emperor</italics>, Routledge, 2002</listitem><listitem>Southern, Pat.<space/><italics>The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine</italics>, Routledge, 2001</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.roman-emperors.org/alexsev.htm'>Benario, Herbert W., ''Alexander Severus (A.D. 222235)'', ''De Imperatoribus Romanis''</link><space/>(2001)</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Canduci<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="title">Triumph & Tragedy: The Rise and Fall of Rome's Immortal Emperors<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pier 9<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-74196-598-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Gibbon. Edward<space/><italics>Decline &amp; Fall of the Roman Empire</italics><space/>(1888)</listitem><listitem>Campbell, J.B.,<space/><italics>The Emperor and the Roman Army 31 BC - AD 235</italics>, Clarenden, 1984</listitem><listitem>Wells, Colin,<space/><italics>The Roman Empire</italics>, Harvard University Press, 1997</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Attribution</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Alexander Severus<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource author</target></template><template><target>Commons-inline</target><arg>Severus Alexander</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite CE1913</target><arg name="wstitle">Alexander Severus<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.severusalexander.com/Severus'>Alexander</link><space/>a site devoted to this emperor</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.forumancientcoins.com/numiswiki/view.asp?key=Severus%20Alexander'>Severus Alexander on NumisWiki</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.forumancientcoins.com/Roman-Coins.asp?e=Severus_Alexander&amp;amp;par=578&amp;amp;pos=1&amp;amp;target=55'>Coins of Severus Alexander</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg>[[Severan dynasty]]</arg><arg>1 October</arg><arg>208</arg><arg>18/19 March</arg><arg>235</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>S-reg</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Elagabalus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Roman Emperor]]</arg><arg name="years">222–235</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Maximinus I (Thrax)]]</arg></template><template><target>s-off</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Gaius Vettius Gratus Sabinianus]],<br/><space/>[[Seleucus (Roman usurper)|Marcus Flavius Vitellius Seleucus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]</arg><arg name="years">222</arg><arg name="regent1"><space/>[[Elagabalus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Marius Maximus]],<space/><br/>[[Luscius Roscius Aelianus Paculus Salvius Julianus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Tiberius Manilius Fuscus]],<br/><space/>[[Servius Calpurnius Domitius Dexter]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]</arg><arg name="years">226</arg><arg name="regent1"><space/>[[Gaius Aufidius Marcellus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Marcus Nummius Senecio Albinus]],<space/><br/>[[Marcus Laelius Fulvius Maximus Aemilianus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Quintus Aiacius Modestus Crescentianus]],<br/><space/>[[Marcus Pomponius Maecius Probus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]</arg><arg name="years">229</arg><arg name="regent1"><space/>[[Cassius Dio]]</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Lucius Virius Agricola]],<space/><br/>[[Sextus Catius Clementinus Priscillianus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Roman Emperors</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Severus, Alexander</target></template><link><target>Category:208 births</target></link><link><target>Category:235 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:3rd-century Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Imperial Roman consuls</target></link><link><target>Category:Severan dynasty</target></link><link><target>Category:Crisis of the Third Century</target></link><link><target>Category:Murdered Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Deified Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient child rulers</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Homs</target></link><link><target>Category:Royal Family of Emesa</target></link><link><target>Category:Iulii</target></link><link><target>Category:Aurelii</target></link><link><target>Category:People of Roman Syria</target></link><link><target>Category:Severus Alexander</target></link></paragraph></article>