<article title='Blue_Streak_%28missile%29'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox rocket</target><arg name="image"><space/>Blue Streak.JPG
</arg><arg name="imsize"><space/>300
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Blue Streak at the ''Deutsches Museum'', Schleissheim, [[Munich]]
<space/></arg><arg name="name"><space/>Blue Streak
</arg><arg name="function"><space/>Nuclear strike, satellite vehicle
</arg><arg name="manufacturer"><space/>[[de Havilland Propellers]], [[Hawker Siddeley Dynamics]]
</arg><arg name="country-origin"><space/>UK
</arg><arg name="place-origin"><space/>Hatfield, Hertfordshire
<space/></arg><arg name="cpl"><space/>
</arg><arg name="cpl-year"><space/>
</arg><arg name="alt-cpl"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="height"><space/>
</arg><arg name="diameter"><space/>
</arg><arg name="mass"><space/>
</arg><arg name="stages"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="capacities"><space/>
 {{Infobox rocket/Payload
 |location<space/></arg><arg name="family"><space/>
</arg><arg name="derivatives"><space/>
</arg><arg name="comparable"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="status"><space/>Retired since 1971
</arg><arg name="sites"><space/>[[Woomera Test Range]]
[[Guiana Space Centre]]
</arg><arg name="launches"><space/>
</arg><arg name="success"><space/>
</arg><arg name="fail"><space/>
</arg><arg name="partial"><space/>
</arg><arg name="other_outcome"><space/>
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>5 June 1964
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>5 November 1971
</arg><arg name="only"><space/>
</arg><arg name="payloads"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="stagedata"><space/>
 {{Infobox rocket/Stage
 |type<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>de Havilland Propellers</target></link><space/><bold>Blue Streak</bold><space/>was a British<space/><link><target>medium-range ballistic missile</target></link><space/>(MRBM), and later the first stage of the<space/><link><target>Europa (rocket)</target><part>Europa</part></link><space/><link><target>satellite</target></link><space/><link><target>launch vehicle</target></link>. Blue Streak was cancelled without entering full production.</paragraph><paragraph>The project was intended to maintain an independent British<space/><link><target>nuclear deterrent</target></link>, replacing the<space/><link><target>V bomber</target></link><space/>fleet which would become obsolete by 1965. The operational requirement for the missile was issued in 1955 and the design was complete by 1957. However, during development it became clear that the missile system was too expensive and too vulnerable to a<space/><link><target>pre-emptive strike</target></link>. The missile project was cancelled in 1960, with US-led<space/><link><target>GAM-87 Skybolt</target><part>Skybolt</part></link><space/>the preferred replacement.</paragraph><paragraph>Partly to avoid political embarrassment from the cancellation, the UK Government proposed that the rocket be used as the first stage of a civilian satellite launcher called<space/><link><target>Black Prince (rocket)</target><part>Black Prince</part></link>. However, the cost was thought to be too great for the UK alone, and international collaboration was sought. This led to the formation of the<space/><link><target>European Launcher Development Organisation</target></link><space/>(ELDO), with Blue Streak used as the first stage of a carrier rocket named<space/><link><target>Europa rocket</target><part>Europa</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Europa was tested at<space/><link><target>Woomera Test Range</target></link>, Australia, and later at<space/><link><target>Guiana Space Centre</target><part>Kourou</part></link><space/>in French Guiana. Following launch failures, the ELDO project was cancelled in 1972 and development of Blue Streak was halted.<template><target>TOC limit</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph>Post-<link><target>World War II</target><part>war</part></link><space/>Britain's<space/><link><target>nuclear weapon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>armament was initially based on<space/><link><target>free-fall bomb</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>delivered by the<space/><link><target>V bomber</target></link><space/>force. It soon became clear that if Britain wanted to have a credible<space/><link><target>nuclear deterrent</target></link><space/>threat, a ballistic missile was essential. There was a political need for an independent deterrent, so that Britain could remain a major<space/><link><target>world power</target></link>. Britain was unable to purchase American weapons wholesale due to the restrictions of the<space/><link><target>Atomic Energy Act of 1946</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In April 1954 the Americans proposed a joint development programme for ballistic missiles. The<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>would develop an<space/><link><target>intercontinental ballistic missile</target></link><space/>(ICBM) of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5,000</arg><arg>nmi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>range (<link><target>SM-65 Atlas</target></link>), while the United Kingdom with United States support would develop a<space/><link><target>medium-range ballistic missile</target></link><space/>(MRBM) of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2,000</arg><arg>nmi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>range. The proposal was accepted as part of the<space/><link><target>Wilson-Sandys Agreement</target></link><space/>of August 1954, which provided for collaboration, exchange of information, and mutual planning of development programmes. The decision to develop was influenced by what could be learnt about missile design and development in the US. Initial requirements for the<space/><link><target>booster (rocketry)</target></link><space/>were made by the<space/><link><target>Royal Aircraft Establishment</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Farnborough, Hampshire</target><part>Farnborough</part></link><space/>with input on the<space/><link><target>rocket engine</target></link><space/>design from the<space/><link><target>Rocket Propulsion Establishment</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Westcott, Buckinghamshire</target><part>Westcott</part></link>. British Operational Requirement 1139 demanded a rocket of at least 1500 n.m. and the initially proposed rocket would have just reached that threshold.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Development</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>de Havilland Propellers</target></link><space/>company won the contract to build the missile, which was to be powered by an uprated liquid-fuelled<space/><link><target>Rocketdyne</target></link><space/>S3D engine, developed by<space/><link><target>Rolls-Royce Limited</target><part>Rolls-Royce</part></link>, called<space/><link><target>RZ2</target></link>. Two variants of this engine were developed: the first provided a static<space/><link><target>thrust</target></link><space/>of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>137000</arg><arg>lbf</arg><arg>kN</arg><arg>-1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>and the second (intended for the three stage<space/><link><target>satellite launch vehicle</target></link>)<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150000</arg><arg>lbf</arg><arg>kN</arg><arg>-1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. The engines were unique at that time in that they could be<space/><link><target>Thrust vectoring</target><part>vectored</part></link><space/>by seven degrees in flight and could therefore be used to guide the vehicle. This configuration, however, put considerable pressure on the<space/><link><target>autopilot</target></link><space/>which had to cope with the problem of a vehicle whose weight was diminishing rapidly and that was steered by large engines whose thrust remained more or less constant. The<space/><link><target>vibration</target></link><space/>was also a problem, particularly at engine cut-off, and the later development of the autopilot for the satellite launcher was, in itself, a considerable achievement.</paragraph><paragraph>Subcontractors included the<space/><link><target>Sperry Gyroscope Company</target></link><space/>who produced the<space/><link><target>missile guidance system</target></link><space/>whilst the<space/><link><target>nuclear warhead</target></link><space/>was designed by the<space/><link><target>Atomic Weapons Research Establishment</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Aldermaston</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The missiles used<space/><link><target>liquid oxygen</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>kerosene</target></link><space/><link><target>propellants</target></link>. Whilst the vehicle could be left fully laden with over 20 tonnes of kerosene, the 60 tonnes of liquid oxygen had to be loaded immediately before launch or icing became a problem. Due to this, fuelling the rocket took 4.5 minutes, which would have made it useless as a rapid response to an attack. The missile was vulnerable to a<space/><link><target>pre-emptive nuclear strike</target></link>, launched without warning or in the absence of any heightening of tension sufficient to warrant readying the missile. To negate this problem de Havilland created a stand-by feature. A missile could be held at 30 seconds' notice to launch for ten hours. As the missiles were to be deployed in pairs and it took ten hours for one missile to be prepared for stand-by, one of the two missiles could always be ready for rapid launch.</paragraph><paragraph>To protect the missiles against a pre-emptive strike while being fuelled, the idea of siting the missiles in underground launchers was developed. These would have been designed to withstand a one<space/><link><target>TNT equivalent</target><part>megaton</part></link><space/>blast at a distance of half a mile (800 m) and were a British innovation, subsequently exported to the United States. However, finding sites for these silos proved extremely difficult and<space/><link><target>RAF Spadeadam</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cumberland</target></link><space/>(now Cumbria) was the only site where construction was started on a full scale underground launcher, although test borings were undertaken at a number of other locations. The remains of this test silo, known as U1, were rediscovered by tree felling at Spadeadam. This was also the site where the RZ2 rocket engines and also the complete Blue Streak missile were tested. The best sites for silo construction were the more stable rock strata in parts of southern and north-east England and eastern Scotland, but the construction of many underground silos in the countryside carried enormous economic, social, and political costs. Development of the underground launchers presented a major technical challenge. 1/60th and 1/6th scale models base on a U shaped design were constructed and tested at RPE Westcott. Three alternative designs were drawn up with one chosen as the prototype, designated K11.<space/><link><target>RAF Upavon</target></link><space/>would appear to have been the preferred location for the prototype operational launcher with the former RNAS at Crail as the likely first operational site.</paragraph><paragraph>As no site in Britain provided enough space for test flights, a test site was established at<space/><link><target>Woomera, South Australia</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cancellation as a military project</heading><paragraph>Doubts arose as the cost escalated from the first tentative figure of 50m submitted to the<space/><link><target>HM Treasury</target><part>Treasury</part></link><space/>in early 1955, to 300m in late 1959. Its detractors in the civil service claimed that the programme was crawling along when compared with the speed of development in the US and the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">However considering the low base which Britain had started from the speed of the programme and its cost effectiveness were far greater than in any other nuclear nation.</arg><arg name="date">September 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Estimates within the Civil Service for completion of the project ranged from a total spend of 550 million to 1.3 billion, as different ministers were set on either abandoning or continuing the project.</paragraph><paragraph>Whitehall opposition to the project grew, and it was eventually cancelled in 1960 on the ostensible grounds that it would be too vulnerable to a first-strike attack. Admiral of the Fleet<space/><link><target>Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma</target><part>Lord Mountbatten</part></link><space/>had spent considerable effort arguing that the project should be cancelled at once in favour of his Navy being armed with nuclear weapons, capable of pre-emptive strike.</paragraph><paragraph>Some considered the cancellation of Blue Streak to be not only a blow to British military-industrial efforts, but also to<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of Nations</target><part>Commonwealth</part></link><space/>ally Australia, which had its own vested interest in the project.</paragraph><paragraph>The British military transferred its hopes for a strategic nuclear delivery system to the Anglo-American<space/><link><target>Skybolt missile</target></link>, before the project's cancellation by the USA as its ICBM program reached maturity. The British instead purchased the<space/><link><target>Polaris missile</target><part>Polaris</part></link><space/>system from the Americans, carried in British-built<space/><link><target>submarine</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Civilian programmes - Black Prince and ELDO</heading><paragraph>After the cancellation as a military project, there was reluctance to cancel the project because of the huge cost incurred. Blue Streak would have become the first stage of a projected all British satellite launcher known as &quot;<link><target>Black Prince (rocket)</target><part>Black Prince</part></link>&quot;: the second stage was derived from the<space/><italics><link><target>Black Knight (rocket)</target><part>Black Knight</part></link></italics><space/>test vehicle, and the orbital injection stage was a small hydrogen peroxide/kerosene motor.</paragraph><paragraph>Black Prince proved too expensive for the UK, and the<space/><link><target>European Launcher Development Organisation</target></link><space/>(ELDO) was set up. This used Blue Streak as the first stage, with French and German second and third stages. The Blue Streak first stage was successfully tested three times at the<space/><link><target>Woomera Prohibited Area</target><part>Woomera test range</part></link><space/>in Australia as part of the ELDO programme.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Black Prince</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Black Prince (rocket)</arg></template>In 1959, a year before the cancellation of the Blue Streak as a missile, the government requested that the RAE and<space/><link><target>Saunders-Roe</target></link><space/>design a carrier rocket based on Blue Streak and Black Knight. This design used Blue Streak as a first stage and a 54&amp;nbsp;inch (137 centimetre) second stage based on the Black Knight.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p124">Hill, p. 124</extension><space/>Several different third stages would be available, depending on the required payload and orbit.</paragraph><paragraph>The cost of developing Black Prince was estimated to be<space/><link><target>pound sterling</target><part></part></link>35 million.</paragraph><paragraph>It was planned that Black Prince would be a<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of Nations</target><part>Commonwealth</part></link><space/>project. However, since the government of<space/><link><target>John Diefenbaker</target></link><space/>in Canada was already spending more money than publicly acknowledged on<space/><link><target>Alouette 1</target><part>Alouette</part></link><space/>and Australia was not interested in the project, these two countries were unwilling to contribute. South Africa was no longer a member of the Commonwealth. New Zealand was only likely to make &quot;modest&quot; contributions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p126">Hill, p. 126</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>European Launcher Development Organisation</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>European Launcher Development Organisation</arg><arg>Europa rocket</arg></template><link><target>File:Blue Streak rocket remains.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The placard reads: &quot;Remains of the first Blue Streak rocket launched from Woomera 5 June 1964. Discovered 50km SE of Giles in 1980.&quot;</part></link>Britain instead proposed a collaboration with other European countries to build a three-stage launcher capable of placing a one-ton payload into low<space/><link><target>Earth orbit</target></link>. Consisting of<space/><link><target>Belgium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>Britain</part></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>, with<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link><space/>as an associate member.</paragraph><paragraph>Preliminary work began in 1962 and ELDO was formally signed into existence in 1964.</paragraph><paragraph>Britain with Blue Streak became the first stage of the European launch vehicle with France providing the<space/><link><target>Coralie</target></link><space/>second stage and Germany the third. Italy worked on the satellite project, the Netherlands and Belgium concentrated on tracking and telemetry systems and Australia supplied the launch site.</paragraph><paragraph>The combined launcher was named<space/><link><target>Europa rocket</target><part>Europa</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>After ten test launches, the Woomera launch site was not suitable for putting satellites into geosynchronous orbit, and in 1966 it was decided to move to the French site of<space/><link><target>Kourou</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>. F11 was fired from here in November 1971, but the failure of the autopilot caused the vehicle to break up. The launch of F12 was postponed whilst a project review was carried out, which led to the decision to abandon the<space/><link><target>Europa (rocket)</target><part>Europa</part></link><space/>design.</paragraph><paragraph>ELDO was merged with the<space/><link><target>European Space Research Organisation</target></link><space/>to form the<space/><link><target>European Space Agency</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>List of Blue Streak launches as part of ELDO</heading><paragraph>(Taken from the &quot;Europa SLV Historiograph&quot;, produced by HSD Ltd)</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Flight No.</tablehead><tablehead>Second stage (Corali)</tablehead><tablehead>Third stage (Astris)</tablehead><tablehead>Payload</tablehead><tablehead>Launch date</tablehead><tablehead>Mission notes</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F1</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>5 June 1964</tablecell><tablecell>uncontrollable oscillations during final phase of burn due to fuel sloshing in tanks</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F2</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>21 October 1964</tablecell><tablecell>Successful flight</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F3</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>23 March 1965</tablecell><tablecell>Successful flight</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F4</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>24 May 1966</tablecell><tablecell>Successful flight</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F5</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>15 November 1966</tablecell><tablecell>Successful flight</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F6.1</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>4 June 1967</tablecell><tablecell>2nd stage failed to ignite</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F6.2</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>6 December 1967</tablecell><tablecell>2nd stage failed to separate</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F7</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>29 November 1968</tablecell><tablecell>3rd stage failure after separation</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F8</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>3 July 1969</tablecell><tablecell>3rd stage failure after separation</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F9</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>24 June 1970</tablecell><tablecell>Fairing failed to separate</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F11</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>successful</tablecell><tablecell>failed</tablecell><tablecell>5 November 1971</tablecell><tablecell>Guidance system failed</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F12</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Delivered to French Guiana</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F13</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Delivered to<space/><link><target>National Museum of Flight</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F14</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Delivered to Deutsches Museum,<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F15</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Delivered to Euro Space Center, Redu, Belgium</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F16</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>untested</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>On display at NSC Leicester, on loan from Liverpool Museums</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F17</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Parts only completed</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>F18</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>n/a</tablecell><tablecell>Parts only completed</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Related projects</heading><paragraph>Aside from Black Prince, a range of other proposals was made between 1959 and 1972 for a<space/><link><target>launch vehicle</target><part>carrier rocket</part></link><space/>based on Blue Streak,<extension extension_name='ref' name="p117">Hill, p. 117</extension><space/>however, none of these were ever built in full and today only exist in design.</paragraph><heading level='3'>De Havilland/British Interplanetary Society proposal</heading><paragraph>In 1959 de Havilland suggested solving the problem of the Blue Streak/Black Knight geometry by compressing the 10 by 1 metre (30 by 3 foot) Black Knight into a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="adj">mid</arg><arg>-diameter</arg></template><space/>sphere. Although this seemed logical, the development costs proved to be too high for the limited budget of the programme.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p119">Hill, p. 119</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Westland Helicopters Black Arrow</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Black Arrow</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Following its merger with Saunders Roe,<space/><link><target>Westland Helicopters</target></link><space/>developed the three-stage Black Arrow satellite carrier rocket, derived from the<space/><link><target>Black Knight (rocket)</target><part>Black Knight</part></link><space/>test vehicle. The first stage of Black Arrow was given the same diameter as the French Coralie (the second stage of Europa) in order to make it compatible with Blue Streak. Using Blue Streak as an additional stage would have increased Black Arrow's payload capacity. To maintain this compatibility, the first stage diameter was given in metres, although the rest of the rocket was defined in imperial units.</paragraph><paragraph>Black Arrow carried out four test launches (without an additional Blue Streak stage) from Woomera between 1969 and 1971, with the final launch carrying the satellite<space/><link><target>Prospero X-3</target></link><space/>into orbit. The United Kingdom remains the only country to have successfully developed and then abandoned a satellite launch capability.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hawker Siddeley Dynamics proposal</heading><paragraph>In 1972,<space/><link><target>Hawker Siddeley Dynamics</target></link><space/>(HSD) produced a brochure for a design using Blue Streak as the first stage of a<space/><link><target>two-stage to orbit</target></link><space/>rocket, with an American<space/><link><target>Centaur (rocket stage)</target><part>Centaur</part></link><space/>upper stage. The Centaur second stage would have either been built in the UK under licence or imported directly from the USA. Both the Centaur and Blue Streak had proved to be very reliable up to this point, and since they were both already designed development costs would have been low. Furthermore, it had a payload of 870920&amp;nbsp;kg to a<space/><link><target>geosynchronous</target></link><space/>orbit with, and 650700&amp;nbsp;kg without the use of additional booster rockets.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hill<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Blue Streak With Centaur Upper Stage<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.spaceuk.org/bstreak/bs/bs_centaur.html<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Blue Streak today</heading><paragraph>Following the cancellation of the Blue Streak project some of the remaining rockets were preserved at:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>National Space Centre</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Leicester</target></link>, England.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Deutsches Museum</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Oberschleiheim</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>National Museum of Flight</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>East Fortune</target></link>, Scotland.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Euro Space Center</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Redu</target></link>, Belgium.</listitem></list><paragraph>A section of the propulsion bay, engines and equipment can be found at the<space/><link><target>Solway Aviation Museum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carlisle Lake District Airport</target></link>. Only a few miles from the Spadeadam testing site, the museum carries many exhibits, photographs and models of the Blue Streak programme, having inherited the original Spadeadam collection that used to be displayed on site.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>RZ2</target></link><space/>engines are on display at<space/><link><target>National Space Centre</target></link><space/>a pair on cradles alongside the Blue Streak rocket, and at the<space/><link><target>Armagh Planetarium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Northern Ireland</target></link><space/>and The<space/><link><target>Euro Space Center</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Redu</target></link>, Belgium.</paragraph><paragraph>Footage from the Blue Streak launch was briefly incorporated into<space/><italics><link><target>The Prisoner</target></link></italics><template><target>'</target></template>s final episode, &quot;<link><target>Fall Out (The Prisoner)</target><part>Fall Out</part></link>&quot;. A part of the Blue Streak rocket launched on 5 June 1964 from<space/><link><target>Woomera, South Australia</target><part>Woomera</part></link>, Australia, found 50&amp;nbsp;km SE of Giles in 1980 (c.1000km) is on display at<space/><link><target>Giles Weather Station</target></link>. Another piece was located in 2006, but its exact location has been kept secret by the finders. The titanium structure of a German third stage was, for some time, sited on the edge of a gravel pit in Gloucestershire. Images of the Blue Streak 1 are incorporated in the 1997 film<space/><italics><link><target>Contact (1997 American film)</target><part>Contact</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of missiles</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rainbow Codes</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Black Arrow</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Black Knight (rocket)</target><part>Black Knight</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Skylark (rocket)</target><part>Skylark</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nuclear weapons and the United Kingdom</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Martu (Indigenous Australian)</target><part>Martu</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hill<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>C.N.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Vertical Empire: The History of the UK Rocket and Space Programme, 1950-1971<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Imperial College Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-86094-267-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Boyes, J. (2013).<space/><italics>The Blue Streak Underground Launchers.</italics><space/>Airfield Review No 140.<space/><link><target>Airfield Research Group</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Boyes, J. (2014).<space/><italics>The Blue Streak Underground Launchers.</italics><space/>Royal Air Force Historical Society Journal No. 58.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>http://www.spaceuk.org/bstreak/bstreak.htm</listitem><listitem>http://www.skomer.u-net.com/projects/bluestreak.htm</listitem><listitem>http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/CapeCanaveral/Launchpad/6133/bluestreak.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+06:41:18</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.makingthemodernworld.org.uk/stories/defiant_modernism/05.ST.07/?scene=5'>Blue Streak including newsreel footage</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafspadeadam/aboutus/history.cfm'>RAF Spadeadam</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nms.ac.uk/flight/collections/rockets.asp?m=5&amp;amp;s=12'>National Museum of Scotland description of the Museum of Flight exhibit</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nielspapermodels.com/bluestreak.htm'>Free papermodel of a Blue Streak missile</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/films/1951to1964/filmpage_rocket.htm'>British Public information film on the Blue Streak at the National Archives (15 minutes QuickTime and Windows Media formats)</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>BBC Radio 4</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/archivehour/pip/d97r6/'>''&quot;The Archive Hour Britain's Space Race&quot;''</link>. 11 August 2007.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/photos/missilespacesystemscutaways/de-havilland-dh-blue-streak-cutaway-9672.aspx'></link><space/>A cutaway drawing of the Blue Streak.</listitem><listitem>U1 underground launcher Spadeadam.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.spaceuk.org/journal/prospero3.pdf'>www.spaceuk.org/journal/prospero3.pdf</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>UKmissiles</target></template><template><target>UKColdWarProjects</target></template><template><target>Strategic nuclear weapon systems of the United Kingdom</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Blue Streak (Missile)</target></template><link><target>Category:Abandoned military projects of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Cold War missiles of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Collections of the National Museums of Scotland</target></link><link><target>Category:De Havilland</target></link><link><target>Category:Medium-range ballistic missiles</target></link><link><target>Category:Space launch vehicles of the United Kingdom</target></link></paragraph></article>