<article title='Affidavit'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Vasil Levski's Affidavit.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Vasil Levski</target></link>'s affidavit, 16 June 1872, Bucharest, Romania</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><bold>affidavit</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>f</arg><arg>ɨ</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>eɪ</arg><arg>v</arg><arg>ɨ</arg><arg>t</arg></template><space/><template><target>Respell</target><arg>A</arg><arg>fə</arg><arg>DAY</arg><arg>vət</arg></template>) is a written<space/><link><target>Oath</target><part>sworn statement of fact</part></link><space/>voluntarily made by an<space/><italics>affiant</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>deponent</italics><space/>under an oath or affirmation administered by a person authorized to do so by law. Such statement is witnessed as to the authenticity of the affiant's<space/><link><target>signature</target></link><space/>by a taker of oaths, such as a<space/><link><target>notary public</target></link><space/>or commissioner of oaths. The name is<space/><link><target>Medieval Latin</target></link><space/>for<space/><italics>he/she has declared upon oath</italics>. An affidavit is a type of verified statement or showing, or in other words, it contains a verification, meaning it is under oath or penalty of perjury, and this serves as evidence to its veracity and is required for court proceedings.It is done with the help of court, with a stamp paperAffidavits may be written in the first or third person, depending on who drafted the document. If in the first person, the document's component parts are typically as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A<space/><italics>commencement</italics><space/>which identifies the &quot;affiant of truth&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.duhaime.org/LegalDictionary/A/Affiant.aspx'>Legal Dictionary</link><space/>retrieved on 11 October 2012</extension><space/>generally stating that everything is true, under penalty of perjury, fine, or imprisonment</listitem><listitem>An<space/><italics>attestation</italics><space/>clause, usually a<space/><link><target>jurat (clause)</target><part>jurat</part></link>, at the end certifying the affiant made oath and the date</listitem><listitem>Signatures of the author and witness</listitem></list><paragraph>If an affidavit is notarized or authenticated, it will also include a caption with a venue and title in reference to judicial proceedings. In some cases, an introductory clause, called a<space/><italics>preamble</italics>, is added attesting that the affiant personally appeared before the authenticating authority.</paragraph><heading level='2'>India</heading><paragraph>In Indian Law although an affidavit may be taken as proof of the facts stated therein, the Courts have no jurisdiction to admit evidence by way of affidavit. Affidavit is treated as Evidence within the meaning of Section 3 of the Evidence Act.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.indiankanoon.org/doc/70092/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Smt. Sudha Devi vs M s Narayana & Ors on 26 April, 1988<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Indiankanoon.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2 July 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>However, it was held by the Supreme Court that an affidavit can be used as an evidence only if the Court so orders for sufficient reasons namely, the right of the opposite party to have the deponent produced for cross-examination ( Khandesh Spg &amp; Wvg Mills CO. Ltd. Vs Rashtriya Girni Kamgar Sangh ) citation 1960 AIR571, 1960 SCR(2) 841. Therefore, an affidavit cannot ordinarily be used as evidence in absence of specific order of the Court.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ireland</heading><paragraph>Affidavits are made in a similar way as to England and Wales, although &quot;make oath&quot; is sometimes omitted. A declaration may be substituted for an affidavit in most cases for those opposed to swearing oaths. The person making the affidavit is known as the deponent but does not sign the affidavit. The affidavit concludes in the standard format &quot;sworn (declared) before me, [name of commissioner for oaths/solicitor], a commissioner for oaths (solicitor), on the [date] at [location] in the county/city of [county/city], and I know the deponent (declarant)&quot;, and it is signed and stamped by the commissioner for oaths.</paragraph><heading level='2'>United States</heading><paragraph>In American<space/><link><target>jurisprudence</target></link>, under the rules for<space/><link><target>Hearsay in United States law</target><part>hearsay</part></link>, admission of an unsupported affidavit as evidence is unusual (especially if the affiant is not available for<space/><link><target>cross-examination</target></link>) with regard to material facts which may be dispositive of the matter at bar. Affidavits from persons who are dead or otherwise incapacitated, or who cannot be located or made to appear may be accepted by the court, but usually only in the presence of<space/><link><target>corroborating evidence</target></link>. An affidavit which reflected a better grasp of the facts close in time to the actual events may be used to refresh a witness's recollection. Materials used to refresh recollection are admissible as evidence. If the affiant is a party in the case, the affiant's opponent may be successful in having the affidavit admitted as evidence, as statements by a party-opponent are admissible through an exception to the hearsay rule.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Australia</heading><paragraph>Affidavits are typically included in the response to<space/><link><target>interrogatories</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.law.cornell.edu/rules/frcp/rule_33'>Rule 33. Interrogatories to Parties</link>. Cornell Legal Information Institute.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.davidjreed.com/litigation/discovery/interrogatories.htm'>Interrogatories</link>.</extension><space/><link><target>Requests for admissions</target></link><space/>under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 36, however, are not required to be sworn.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.law.cornell.edu/rules/frcp/rule_36'>Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 36</link>.Cornell Legal Information Institute.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Naar<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alan S.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://greenbaumlaw.com/Rsc_FilesView.asp?fileCode</arg><arg name="title">Requests for Admission: an underutilized litigation tool<space/></arg><arg name="work">New Jersey Lawyer, the Magazine</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some types of motions will not be accepted by the court unless accompanied by an independent sworn statement or other evidence, in support of the need for the motion. In such a case, a court will accept an affidavit from the filing attorney in support of the motion, as certain assumptions are made, to wit: The affidavit in place of sworn testimony promotes<space/><link><target>judicial economy</target></link>. The lawyer is an<space/><link><target>officer of the court</target></link><space/>and knows that a false swearing by him, if found out, could be grounds for severe penalty up to and including<space/><link><target>disbarment</target></link>. The lawyer if called upon would be able to present independent and more detailed evidence to prove the facts set forth in his affidavit.</paragraph><paragraph>The acceptance of an affidavit by one society does not confirm its acceptance as a legal document in other jurisdictions. Equally, the acceptance that a lawyer is an officer of the court (for swearing the affidavit) is not a given. This matter is addressed by the use of the<space/><link><target>Apostille</target></link>, a means of certifying the legalization of a document for international use under the terms of the 1961 Hague Convention Abolishing the Requirement of Legalization for Foreign Public Documents. Documents which have been notarized by a notary public, and certain other documents, and then certified with a conformant apostille are accepted for legal use in all the nations that have signed the Hague Convention. Thus most Affidavits now require to be Apostilled if used for cross border issues.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Declaration (law)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Deposition (law)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Statutory declaration</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Affidavits</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://coral.uchicago.edu:8443/display/chicago68/McCarthyism+and+Academic+Freedom+on+the+University+of+Chicago+Campus'>McCarthyism and Academic Freedom on the University of Chicago Campus</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Evidence law</target></link><link><target>Category:Legal documents</target></link><link><target>Category:Notary</target></link></paragraph></article>