<article title='Compost'><paragraph><link><target>File:Compost site germany.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A community-level composting plant in a rural area in Germany</part></link><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Compost</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>p</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>p</arg><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg></template>) is<space/><link><target>organic matter</target></link><space/>that has been<space/><link><target>Biodegradation</target><part>decomposed</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>recycle</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>fertilizer</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>soil amendment</target></link>. Compost is a key ingredient in<space/><link><target>organic farming</target></link>. At the simplest level, the process of composting simply requires making a heap of wetted organic matter known as<space/><link><target>green waste</target></link><space/>(leaves, food waste) and waiting for the materials to break down into<space/><link><target>humus</target></link><space/>after a period of weeks or months. Modern, methodical composting is a multi-step, closely monitored process with measured inputs of water, air, and carbon- and nitrogen-rich materials. The decomposition process is aided by shredding the plant matter, adding water and ensuring proper aeration by regularly turning the mixture. Worms and fungi further break up the material. Bacteria requiring oxygen to function (<link><target>aerobic bacteria</target></link>) and fungi manage the chemical process by converting the inputs into heat,<space/><link><target>carbon dioxide</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ammonium</target></link>. The ammonium (NH<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>) is the form of nitrogen used by plants. When available ammonium is not used by plants it is further converted by bacteria into<space/><link><target>nitrate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(NO<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>) through the process of<space/><link><target>nitrification</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Compost is rich in nutrients. It is used in<space/><link><target>gardens</target></link>,<space/><link><target>landscaping</target></link>,<space/><link><target>horticulture</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>agriculture</target></link>. The compost itself is beneficial for the land in many ways, including as a<space/><link><target>soil conditioner</target></link>, a fertilizer, addition of vital humus or<space/><link><target>humic acids</target></link>, and as a natural<space/><link><target>pesticide</target></link><space/>for soil. In ecosystems, compost is useful for erosion control, land and stream reclamation, wetland construction, and as landfill cover (see<space/><link><target>compost uses</target></link>). Organic ingredients intended for composting can alternatively be used to generate<space/><link><target>biogas</target></link><space/>through<space/><link><target>anaerobic digestion</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>TOC limit</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Terminology</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;composting&quot; is used worldwide with differing meanings. Some composting textbooks narrowly define composting as being an aerobic form of decompostion, primarily by microbes. For many people, however, composting is used to refer to several different types of biological process. In North America, &quot;anaerobic composting&quot; is still a common term, but in much of the rest of the world and in technical publications the more accurate term<space/><link><target>anaerobic digestion</target></link><space/>is used as the microbes used and the processes involved are quite different.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ingredients</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Composting in the Escuela Barreales.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Home compost barrel in the Escuela Barreales,<space/><link><target>Santa Cruz, Chile</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Carbon, nitrogen, oxygen, water</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Compost pile.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Materials in a compost pile.</part></link><link><target>File:Food-scraps-compost.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Food scraps compost heap.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Composting organisms require four equally important ingredients to work effectively:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Carbon for energy; the microbial<space/><link><target>oxidation</target></link><space/>of carbon produces the heat, if included at suggested levels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://web.extension.illinois.edu/homecompost/science.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Composting for the Homeowner - University of Illinois Extension<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Web.extension.illinois.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-18</arg></template></extension><space/><list type='bullet'><listitem>High carbon materials tend to be brown and dry.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Nitrogen to grow and reproduce more organisms to oxidize the carbon.<list type='bullet'><listitem>High nitrogen materials tend to be green (or colorful, such as fruits and vegetables) and wet.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Oxygen for oxidizing the carbon, the decomposition process.</listitem><listitem>Water in the right amounts to maintain activity without causing anaerobic conditions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="uiuc-mat"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://web.extension.uiuc.edu/homecompost/materials.html</arg><arg name="title">Composting for the Homeowner -Materials for Composting</arg><arg name="work">uiuc.edu</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Certain ratios of these materials will provide beneficial bacteria with the nutrients to work at a rate that will heat up the pile. In that process much water will be released as<space/><link><target>evaporation</target><part>vapor</part></link><space/>(&quot;steam&quot;), and the oxygen will be quickly depleted, explaining the need to actively manage the pile. The hotter the pile gets, the more often added air and water is necessary; the air/water balance is critical to maintaining high temperatures (135-160 Fahrenheit / 50 - 70 Celsius) until the materials are broken down. At the same time, too much air or water also slows the process, as does too much carbon (or too little nitrogen).</paragraph><paragraph>The most efficient composting occurs with an optimal carbon:nitrogen ratio of about 10:1 to 20:1.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Radovich"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Radovich, T</arg><arg name="author2">Hue, N</arg><arg name="author3">Pant, A</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Radovich, T</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Arancon, N</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ctahr.hawaii.edu/huen/nvh/compost.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tea Time in the Tropics - a handbook for compost tea production and use</arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 1: Compost Quality</arg><arg name="date">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">College of Tropical Agriculture and Human Resources, University of Hawaii</arg><arg name="pages">8-16</arg><arg></arg></template></extension><space/>Rapid composting is favored by having a C/N ratio of ~30 or less. Theoretical analysis is confirmed by field tests that above 30 the substrate is nitrogen starved, below 15 it is likely to outgas a portion of nitrogen as ammonia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Haug</arg><arg name="first1">Roger</arg><arg name="title">The Practical Handbook of Compost Engineering</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">CRC Press,</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 October 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>If nitrogen needs to be increased, it has been suggested to add 0.15 pounds of<space/><italics>actual</italics><space/>nitrogen per three bushels (3.75 cubic feet) of lower nitrogen material.<extension extension_name='ref' name="uiuc-mat"></extension><space/>[For those not familiar with these types of units: 0.64g/L or 640 grams of actual nitrogen per cubic meter.] Two to 3 pounds of organic nitrogen supplement (blood meal, manure, bonemeal, alfalfa meal) per 100 pounds of low nitrogen materials (for example, straw or sawdust), supplies generally ample nitrogen and trace minerals in high carbon mixes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Martin & Gershuny eds.</arg><arg name="title">The Rodale Book of Composting: Easy Methods for Every Gardener</arg><arg name="date">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">Rodale Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 October 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nearly all plant and animal materials have both carbon and nitrogen, but amounts vary widely, with characteristics noted above (dry/wet, brown/green).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.klickitatcounty.org/SolidWaste/fileshtml/organics/compostCalc.htm'>Klickitat County WA, USA Compost Mix Calculator</link></extension><space/>Fresh grass clippings have an average ratio of about 15:1 and dry autumn leaves about 50:1 depending on species. Mixing equal parts by volume approximates the ideal C:N range. Few individual situations will provide the ideal mix of materials at any point. Observation of amounts, and consideration of different materials<extension extension_name='ref' name="compost.css.cornell.edu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://compost.css.cornell.edu/calc/lignin.html</arg><arg name="title">The Effect of Lignin on Biodegradability - Cornell Composting</arg><arg name="work">cornell.edu</arg></template></extension><space/>as a pile is built over time, can quickly achieve a workable technique for the individual situation.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Animal manure and bedding</heading><paragraph>On many farms, the basic composting ingredients are animal<space/><link><target>manure</target></link><space/>generated on the farm and bedding. Straw and sawdust are common bedding materials. Non-traditional bedding materials are also used, including newspaper and chopped cardboard. The amount of manure composted on a livestock farm is often determined by cleaning schedules, land availability, and weather conditions. Each type of manure has its own physical, chemical, and biological characteristics. Cattle and horse manures, when mixed with bedding, possess good qualities for composting. Swine manure, which is very wet and usually not mixed with bedding material, must be mixed with straw or similar raw materials. Poultry manure also must be blended with carbonaceous materials - those low in nitrogen preferred, such as sawdust or straw.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dougherty, Mark. (1999). Field Guide to On-Farm Composting. Ithaca, New York: Natural Resource, Agriculture, and Engineering Service.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Microorganisms</heading><paragraph>With the proper mixture of water, oxygen, carbon, and nitrogen, micro-organisms are allowed to break down organic matter to produce compost. The composting process is dependent on micro-organisms to break down organic matter into compost. There are many types of microorganisms found in active compost of which the most common are:<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://compost.css.cornell.edu/microorg.html</arg><arg name="title">Composting - Compost Microorganisms</arg><arg name="work">[[Cornell University]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 October 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bacteria</target></link>- The most numerous of all the<space/><link><target>microorganism</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>found in compost. Depending on the phase of composting,<space/><link><target>mesophile</target><part>mesophilic</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>thermophile</target><part>thermophilic</part></link><space/>bacteria may predominate.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Actinobacteria</target></link>- Necessary for breaking down paper products such as newspaper,<space/><link><target>bark</target></link>, etc.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Fungi</target></link>-<space/><link><target>Molds</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>yeast</target></link><space/>help break down materials that bacteria cannot, especially<space/><link><target>lignin</target></link><space/>in woody material.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Protozoa</target></link>- Help consume bacteria, fungi and micro organic particulates.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Rotifers</target></link>- Rotifers help control populations of bacteria and small protozoans.</listitem></list><paragraph>In addition,<space/><link><target>earthworm</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>not only ingest partly composted material, but also continually re-create aeration and drainage tunnels as they move through the compost.</paragraph><paragraph>A lack of a healthy micro-organism community is the main reason why composting processes are slow in<space/><link><target>landfills</target></link><space/>with environmental factors such as lack of oxygen, nutrients or water being the cause of the depleted biological community.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Phases of composting</heading><paragraph>Under ideal conditions, composting proceeds through three major phases:<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>An initial, mesophilic phase, in which the decomposition is carried out under moderate temperatures by mesophilic microorganisms.</listitem><listitem>As the temperature rises, a second, thermophilic phase starts, in which in decomposition is carried out by various thermophilic bacteria under high temperatures.</listitem><listitem>As the supply of high-energy compounds dwindles, the temperature starts to decrease, and the mesophiles once again predominate in the maturation phase.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Human waste</heading><paragraph><link><target>Human waste</target></link><space/>(excreta) can also be added as an input to the composting process, like it is done in<space/><link><target>composting toilets</target></link>, as human waste is a nitrogen-rich organic material.</paragraph><paragraph>People excrete far more<space/><link><target>water-soluble</target></link><space/>plant nutrients (<link><target>nitrogen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>phosphorus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>potassium</target></link>) in<space/><link><target>urine</target></link><space/>than in<space/><link><target>feces</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://esa.un.org/iys/docs/san_lib_docs/ESR2web%5B1%5D.pdf'>Stockholm Environment Institute - EcoSanRes - Guidelines on the Use of Urine and Feces in Crop Production</link></extension><space/>Human<space/><link><target>Fertilizer#Animal</target><part>urine can be used directly as fertilizer</part></link><space/>or it can be put onto compost. Adding a healthy person's urine to compost usually will increase temperatures and therefore increase its ability to destroy pathogens and unwanted seeds. Urine from a person with no obvious symptoms of infection is much more sanitary than fresh feces. Unlike feces, urine does not attract disease-spreading<space/><link><target>flies</target></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>house flies</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>blow flies</target></link>), and it does not contain the most hardy of pathogens, such as<space/><link><target>parasitic worm</target></link><space/>eggs. Urine usually does not<space/><link><target>odor</target><part>stink</part></link><space/>for long, particularly when it is fresh, diluted, or put on<space/><link><target>sorbent</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Urine is primarily composed of water and<space/><link><target>urea</target></link>. Although metabolites of urea are nitrogen fertilizers, it is easy to over-fertilize with urine, or to utilize urine containing pharmaceutical (or other) content, creating too much ammonia for plants to absorb, acidic conditions, or other<space/><link><target>phytotoxicity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://doku.b.tu-harburg.de/volltexte/2009/557/pdf/PhD_Thesis_Winker.pdf</arg><arg name="title">TUBdok: Pharmaceutical Residues in Urine and Potential Risks related to Usage as Fertiliser in Agriculture</arg><arg name="work">tu-harburg.de</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Humanure</heading><paragraph>&quot;Humanure&quot; is a combination of the words<space/><italics>human</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>manure</italics>, designating human excrement (<link><target>feces</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>urine</target></link>) that is<space/><link><target>recycling</target><part>recycled</part></link><space/>via composting for agricultural or other purposes. The term was first used in a 1994 book by Joseph Jenkins that advocates the use of this<space/><link><target>organic material</target><part>organic</part></link><space/>soil amendment.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":0"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Humanure Handbook: A Guide to Composting Human Manure</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Jenkins</arg><arg name="first">J.C.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Joseph Jenkins, Inc.; 3rd edition</arg><arg name="location">Grove City, PA<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-9644258-3-5</arg><arg name="page">255<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.humanurehandbook.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The term humanure is used by compost enthusiasts in the US but not generally elsewhere. Because the term &quot;humanure&quot; has no authoritative definition it is subject to various uses; news reporters occasionally fail to correctly distinguish between humanure and<space/><link><target>sewage sludge</target></link><space/>or &quot;biosolids&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yourottawaregion.com/feature/article/1224782--humanure-dumping-sickens-homeowner<space/></arg><arg name="title">'Humanure' dumping sickens homeowner<space/></arg><arg name="author">Courtney Symons<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 October 2011<space/></arg><arg name="work">YourOttawaRegion<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Metroland Media Group Ltd.<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 October 2011<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Uses</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Uses of compost</arg></template>Compost is generally recommended as an additive to soil, or other matrices such as<space/><link><target>coir</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>peat</target></link>, as a<space/><link><target>tilth</target></link><space/>improver, supplying humus and nutrients. It provides a rich<space/><italics>growing medium</italics>, or a porous, absorbent material that holds moisture and soluble minerals, providing the support and<space/><link><target>nutrients</target></link><space/>in which plants can flourish, although it is rarely used alone, being primarily mixed with<space/><link><target>soil</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sand</target></link>, grit, bark chips,<space/><link><target>vermiculite</target></link>,<space/><link><target>perlite</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>clay</target></link><space/>granules to produce<space/><link><target>loam</target></link>. Compost can be tilled directly into the soil or growing medium to boost the level of organic matter and the overall fertility of the soil. Compost that is ready to be used as an additive is dark brown or even black with an earthy smell.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.epa.gov/wastes/conserve/rrr/greenscapes/pubs/asla-soil.pdf'>Healthy Soils, Healthy Landscapes</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Generally, direct seeding into a compost is not recommended due to the speed with which it may dry and the possible presence of<space/><link><target>phytotoxin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that may inhibit germination,<extension extension_name='ref'>Morel, P. and Guillemain, G. 2004. Assessment of the possible phytotoxicity of a substrate using an easy and representative biotest. Acta Horticulture 644:417423</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Itvaara et al. Compost maturity - problems associated with testing. in Proceedings of Composting. Innsbruck Austria 18-21.10.2000</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18585031</arg><arg name="title">Development of models for predicting carbon mineralization and associated phytotoxicity in compost-amended soil.<space/></arg><arg name="vauthors">Aslam DN, etal<space/></arg><arg name="work">nih.gov</arg></template></extension><space/>and the possible tie up of nitrogen by incompletely decomposed lignin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="compost.css.cornell.edu"></extension><space/>It is very common to see blends of 2030% compost used for transplanting<space/><link><target>seedlings</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>cotyledon</target></link><space/>stage or later.</paragraph><paragraph>Composting can destroy<space/><link><target>pathogen</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or unwanted<space/><link><target>seed</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Unwanted living plants (or<space/><link><target>weed</target><trail>s</trail></link>) can be discouraged by<space/><link><target>Mulch#Mulching (composting) over unwanted plants</target><part>covering with mulch/compost</part></link>. The &quot;<link><target>biopesticide</target><part>microbial pesticides</part></link>&quot; in compost may include<space/><link><target>thermophile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mesophile</target><trail>s</trail></link>, however certain composting<space/><link><target>detritivores</target></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>black soldier fly larvae</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>redworm</target><trail>s</trail></link>, also reduce many pathogens. Thermophilic (high-temperature) composting is well known to destroy many seeds and nearly all types of pathogens (exceptions may include<space/><link><target>prion</target><trail>s</trail></link>). The<space/><link><target>Disinfection</target><part>sanitizing</part></link><space/>qualities of (<link><target>thermophilic</target></link>) composting are desirable where there is a high likelihood of pathogens, such as with<space/><link><target>manure</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composting technologies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tumbler.skips.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A homemade compost tumbler</part></link><link><target>File:Green compost bin.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A modern compost bin constructed from plastics</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Overview</heading><paragraph>In addition to the traditional compost pile, various approaches have been developed to handle different composting processes, ingredients, locations, and applications for the composted product.</paragraph><paragraph>There is a large number of different<space/><link><target>list of composting systems</target><part>composting systems</part></link><space/>on the market, for example:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>At the household level:<space/><link><target>Composting toilet</target></link>, container composting, vermicomposting</listitem><listitem>At the industrial composting (large scale):<space/><link><target>Aerated Static Pile Composting</target></link>, vermicomposting,<space/><link><target>windrow composting</target></link><space/>etc.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Examples</heading><heading level='4'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Vermicompost</arg></template>Vermicomposting</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Worm.casts.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Rotary screen harvested worm castings</part></link><link><target>File:Komposztl.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Food waste - after three years</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Vermicomposting</arg></template><link><target>Vermicompost</target></link><space/>is the product or process of composting through the utilization of various species of worms, usually<space/><link><target>Eisenia fetida</target><part>red wigglers</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Enchytraeus buchholzi</target><part>white worms</part></link>, and earthworms, to create a heterogeneous mixture of decomposing vegetable or food waste (excluding meat, dairy, fats, or oils), bedding materials, and vermicast. Vermicast, also known as<space/><link><target>worm castings</target></link>, worm humus or worm manure, is the end-product of the breakdown of organic matter by<space/><link><target>species</target></link><space/>of earthworm.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://southwoodsforestgardens.blogspot.com/2009/01/paper-on-invasive-european-worms.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Paper on Invasive European Worms<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 February 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>Vermicomposting is widely used in North America for on-site institutional processing of food waste, such as in hospitals and shopping malls.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>This type of composting is sometimes suggested as a feasible indoor home composting method.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>Vermicomposting has gained popularity in both these industrial and domestic settings because, as compared with conventional composting, it provides a way to compost organic materials more quickly (as defined by a higher rate of<space/><link><target>carbon-to-nitrogen ratio</target></link><space/>increase) and to attain products that have lower<space/><link><target>salinity</target></link><space/>levels that are therefore more beneficial to plant mediums.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lacanzo, 2008"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Lazcano, Cristina; Gómez-Brandón, María; Domínguez, Jorge<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Comparison of the effectiveness of composting and vermicomposting for the biological stabilization of cattle manure<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Chemosphere<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>72<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1013–1019<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2008.04.016</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://webs.uvigo.es/jdguez/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/Comparison-of-the-effectiveness-of-composting-and-vermicomposting.pdf</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The earthworm species (or<space/><bold>composting worms</bold>) most often used are red wigglers (<italics><link><target>Eisenia fetida</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>Eisenia andrei</target></link></italics>), though European nightcrawlers (<italics><link><target>Eisenia hortensis</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>Eisenia hortensis</target><part>Dendrobaena veneta</part></link></italics>) could also be used. Red wigglers are recommended by most vermiculture experts, as they have some of the best appetites and breed very quickly. Users refer to European nightcrawlers by a variety of other names, including<space/><italics>dendrobaenas</italics>,<space/><italics>dendras</italics>, Dutch Nightcrawlers, and Belgian nightcrawlers.</paragraph><paragraph>Containing water-soluble nutrients, vermicompost is a nutrient-rich<space/><link><target>organic fertilizer</target></link><space/>and soil conditioner in a form that is relatively easy for plants to absorb.<extension extension_name='ref'>Coyne, Kelly and Erik Knutzen.<space/><italics>The Urban Homestead: Your Guide to Self-Sufficient Living in the Heart of the City.</italics><space/>Port Townsend: Process Self Reliance Series, 2008.</extension><space/>Worm castings are sometimes used as an organic fertilizer. Because the earthworms grind and uniformly mix minerals in simple forms, plants need only minimal effort to obtain them. The worms' digestive systems also add beneficial microbes to help create a &quot;living&quot; soil environment for plants.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Vermicompost tea in conjunction with 10% castings has been shown to cause up to a 1.7 times growth in plant mass over plants grown without.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wormsetc.com/worms-etc-blog/2010/04/worm-castings/</arg><arg name="title">Worm casting organic fertilizer benefits and uses</arg><arg name="work">Worms Etc</arg></template></extension><template><target>Dubious</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Researchers from the<space/><link><target>Pondicherry University</target></link><space/>discovered that worm composts can also be used to clean up heavy metals. The researchers found substantial reductions in heavy metals when the worms were released into the garbage and they are effective at removing<space/><link><target>lead</target></link>,<space/><link><target>zinc</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cadmium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>copper</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>manganese</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.mining.com/remediating-heavy-metals-using-a-worm-compost/
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cleaning up heavy metals using worms
</arg><arg name="year">	 2012
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>mining.com
</arg><arg name="publication-place"><space/>International
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>3 October 2012
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Hgelkultur (raised garden beds or mounds)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:End point (4315712587).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>An almost completed Hgelkultur bed (does not have dirt on it yet).</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Hügelkultur</arg></template>The practice of making raised garden beds or mounds filled with rotting wood is also called &quot;Hgelkultur&quot; in German.<extension extension_name='ref' name="richsoil.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.richsoil.com/hugelkultur/<space/></arg><arg name="title">hugelkultur: the ultimate raised garden beds<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Richsoil.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2007-07-27<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-18</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="permaculture.org.au"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://permaculture.org.au/2010/08/03/the-art-and-science-of-making-a-hugelkultur-bed-transforming-woody-debris-into-a-garden-resource/<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Art and Science of Making a Hugelkultur Bed - Transforming Woody Debris into a Garden Resource Permaculture Research Institute - Permaculture Forums, Courses, Information & News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-18</arg></template></extension><space/>It is in effect creating a<space/><link><target>Nurse log</target></link>, however, covered with dirt.</paragraph><paragraph>Benefits of hgelkultur garden beds include water retention and warming of soil.<extension extension_name='ref' name="richsoil.com"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://permaculture.org.au/2012/01/04/hugelkultur-composting-whole-trees-with-ease/#more-6825<space/></arg><arg name="title">Hugelkultur: Composting Whole Trees With Ease Permaculture Research Institute - Permaculture Forums, Courses, Information & News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-18</arg></template></extension><space/>Buried wood becomes like a<space/><link><target>sponge (material)</target><part>sponge</part></link><space/>as it decomposes, able to capture water and store it for later use by crops planted on top of the hgelkultur bed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="richsoil.com"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Hemenway, Toby (2009). Gaia's Garden: A Guide to Home-Scale Permaculture. Chelsea Green Publishing. pp. 84-85. ISBN 978-1-60358-029-8.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The buried decomposing wood will also give off heat, as all compost does, for several years. These effects have been used by<space/><link><target>Sepp Holzer</target></link><space/>for one to allow fruit trees to survive at otherwise inhospitable temperatures and altitudes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="permaculture.org.au"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Black soldier fly larvae composting</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Hermetia illucens#Uses in composting or as food for animals</arg></template>Black Soldier Fly (<italics>Hermetia illucens</italics>) larvae have been shown to be able to rapidly consume large amounts of organic waste when kept at 31.8C, the optimum temperature for reproduction.<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="DienerStudt Solano2011"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Diener</arg><arg name="first1">Stefan</arg><arg name="last2">Studt Solano</arg><arg name="first2">Nandayure M.</arg><arg name="last3">Roa Gutiérrez</arg><arg name="first3">Floria</arg><arg name="last4">Zurbrügg</arg><arg name="first4">Christian</arg><arg name="last5">Tockner</arg><arg name="first5">Klement</arg><arg name="title">Biological Treatment of Municipal Organic Waste using Black Soldier Fly Larvae</arg><arg name="journal">Waste and Biomass Valorization</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="pages">357–363</arg><arg name="issn">1877-2641</arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s12649-011-9079-1</arg></template></extension><space/>Enthusiasts have experimented with a large number of different waste products<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">E</arg><arg name="url">http://www.esrint.com/pages/bioconversion.html</arg><arg name="website">Bio-Conversion of Putrescent Waste</arg><arg name="publisher">ESR International</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>and some even sell starter kits to the public.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">BSF Farming - marketplace</arg><arg name="url">http://www.blacksoldierflyfarming.com/bsf-marketplace</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Cockroach composting</heading><paragraph>Cockroach composting is another insect-mediated composting method. In this case the adults of any number of cockroach species (such as the<space/><link><target>Turkestan cockroach</target></link><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>Blaptica dubia</target></link></italics>) are used to quickly convert manure or kitchen waste to nutrient dense compost. Depending on species used and environmental conditions, excess composting insects can be used as an excellent animal feed for farm animals and pets.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://theunconventionalfarmer.com/natural-techniques/cockroach-composting/</arg><arg name="title">Cockroach Composting</arg><arg name="work">The Unconventional Farmer</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Bokashi</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bokashi bin - inside.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Inside a recently started bokashi bin. The aerated base is just visible through the food scraps and bokashi bran.</part></link>Bokashi is a method that uses a mix of microorganisms to cover food waste to decrease smell. It derives from the practice of<space/><link><target>Japan</target><trail>ese</trail></link><space/>farmers centuries ago of covering food waste with rich, local soil that contained the microorganisms that would ferment the waste. After a few weeks, they would bury the waste.<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="lindsay"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Lindsay</arg><arg name="first">Jay</arg><arg name="title">Japanese composting may be new food waste solution</arg><arg name="url">http://bigstory.ap.org/article/japanese-composting-may-be-new-food-waste-solution</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 November 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">AP</arg><arg name="date">12 June 2012</arg></template></extension><template><target>Better source</target><arg name="reason">news report from 2012 does not count as a good source for these claims</arg><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Most practitioners obtain the microorganisms from the product<space/><link><target>Effective Microorganisms</target></link><space/>(EM1),<extension extension_name='ref' name="lindsay"></extension><space/>first sold in the 1980s. EM1 is mixed with a carbon base (e.g. sawdust or bran) that it sticks to and a sugar for food (e.g. molasses). The mixture is layered with waste in a sealed container and after a few weeks, removed and buried.<extension extension_name='ref' name="lindsay"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Newspaper fermented in a lactobacillus culture can be substituted for bokashi bran for a successful bokashi bucket.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://bocashi.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/bokashicomposting1.pdf'>&quot;Make your own FREE bokashi starter&quot;</link>, 12 September 2008. Retrieved 7 November 2013.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Compost tea</heading><paragraph>Compost teas are defined as water extracts brewed from composted materials and can be derived from aerobic or anaerobic processes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sinha"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Gómez-Brandón, M</arg><arg name="last2">Vela, M</arg><arg name="last3">Martinez Toledo, MV</arg><arg name="last4">Insam, H</arg><arg name="last5">Domínguez, J</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Sinha, S</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Plant, KK</arg><arg name="editor3-last">Bajpai, S</arg><arg name="title">Advances in Fertilizer Technology: Synthesis (Vol1)</arg><arg name="chapter">12: Effects of Compost and Vermicompost Teas as Organic Fertilizers</arg><arg name="date">2015</arg><arg name="publisher">Stadium Press LLC</arg><arg name="isbn">1-62699-044-1</arg><arg name="pages">300-318</arg></template></extension><space/>Compost teas are generally produced from adding one volume of compost to 4-10 volumes of water, but there has also been debate about the benefits of aerating the mixture.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sinha"></extension><space/>Field studies have shown the benefits of adding compost teas to crops due to the adding of organic matter, increased nutrient availability and increased microbial activity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sinha"></extension><space/>They have also been shown to have an effect on plant pathogens.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Santos, M</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Dianez, F</arg><arg name="last3">Carretero,F</arg><arg name="chapter">12: Suppressive Effects of Compost Tea on Phytopathogens</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>242-262</arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Dubey,NK<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Natural products in plant pest management<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>CABI<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxfordshire, UK Cambridge, MA<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781845936716<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Composting toilets<template><target>anchor</target><arg>Humanure</arg></template></heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Composting toilet</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>composting toilet</target></link><space/>does not require water or electricity, and when properly managed does not smell. A composting toilet collects human excreta which is then added to a compost heap together with sawdust and straw or other carbon rich materials, where pathogens are destroyed to some extent. The amount of pathogen destruction depends on the temperature (mesophilic or thermophilic conditions) and composting time.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":1">Stenstrm, T.A., Seidu, R., Ekane, N., Zurbrgg, C. (2011).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.susana.org/en/resources/library/details/1236'>Microbial exposure and health assessments in sanitation technologies and systems</link><space/>- EcoSanRes Series, 2011-1. Stockholm Environment Institute (SEI), Stockholm, Sweden, page 88</extension><space/>A composting toilet tries to process the excreta in situ although this is often coupled with a secondary external composting step. The resulting compost product has been given various names, such as humanure and EcoHumus.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":1"></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>A composting toilet can aid in the conservation of<space/><link><target>fresh water</target></link><space/>by avoiding the usage of potable water required by the typical flush<space/><link><target>toilet</target></link>. It further prevents the pollution of ground water by controlling the fecal matter decomposition before entering the system. When properly managed, there should be no ground contamination from<space/><link><target>leachate</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Compost and land-filling</heading><paragraph>As concern about<space/><link><target>landfill</target></link><space/>space increases, worldwide interest in recycling by means of composting is growing, since composting is a process for converting decomposable organic materials into useful stable products.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.stormcon.com/mw_0107_history.html'>A Brief History of Solid Waste Management</link></extension><space/>Composting is one of the only ways to revitalize soil vitality due to<space/><link><target>phosphorus</target></link><space/>depletion in soil.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Preventing Contaminants in Home Compost Piles<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.networx.com/article/preventing-contaminants-in-home-compost</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 June 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>Industrial scale composting in the form of<space/><link><target>in-vessel composting</target></link>,<space/><link><target>aerated static pile composting</target></link>, and anaerobic digestion takes place in most Western countries now, and in many areas is mandated by law. There are process and product guidelines in Europe that date to the early 1980s (Germany, the Netherlands, Switzerland) and only more recently in the UK and the US. In both these countries, private trade associations within the industry have established loose standards, some say as a stop-gap measure to discourage independent government agencies from establishing tougher consumer-friendly standards.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.compostingcouncil.org/<space/></arg><arg name="title">US Composting Council<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Compostingcouncil.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-18</arg></template></extension><space/>The USA is the only Western country that does not distinguish sludge-source compost from green-composts, and by default in the USA 50% of states expect composts to comply in some manner with the federal EPA 503 rule promulgated in 1984 for sludge products.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work">U.S. Government Printing Office</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Electronic Code of Federal Regulations. Title 40, part 503. Standards for the use or disposal of sewage sludge<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?c</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 March 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>Compost is regulated in Canada and Australia as well.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Industrial systems</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bomberos2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A large compost pile that is steaming with the heat generated by<space/><link><target>thermophile</target><part>thermophilic</part></link><space/>microorganisms.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Industrial composting systems are increasingly being installed as a waste management alternative to landfills, along with other<space/><link><target>advanced waste processing systems</target></link>. Mechanical sorting of mixed waste streams combined with anaerobic digestion or in-vessel composting is called<space/><link><target>mechanical biological treatment</target></link>, and are increasingly being used in developed countries due to regulations controlling the amount of organic matter allowed in landfills. Treating<space/><link><target>biodegradable waste</target></link><space/>before it enters a landfill reduces<space/><link><target>global warming</target></link><space/>from fugitive<space/><link><target>methane</target></link>; untreated waste breaks down<space/><link><target>Anaerobic respiration</target><part>anaerobically</part></link><space/>in a landfill, producing<space/><link><target>landfill gas</target></link><space/>that contains<space/><link><target>atmospheric methane</target><part>methane</part></link>, a potent greenhouse gas.</paragraph><paragraph>Vermicomposting, also known as vermiculture, is used for medium-scale on-site institutional composting, such as for food waste from universities and shopping malls: selected either as a more environmental choice, or to reduce the cost of commercial waste removal.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Large-scale composting systems are used by many urban areas around the world. Co-composting is a technique that combines solid waste with de-watered biosolids, although difficulties controlling inert and plastics contamination from<space/><link><target>municipal solid waste</target></link><space/>makes this approach less attractive. The World's largest MSW co-composter is the<space/><link><target>Edmonton Composting Facility</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Edmonton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Alberta</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>, which turns 220,000 tonnes of residential solid waste and 22,500 dry tonnes of biosolids per year into 80,000 tonnes of compost. The facility is 38,690&amp;nbsp;meters<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup><space/>(416,500&amp;nbsp;ft<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>), equivalent to 4<space/><link><target>Canadian football</target></link><space/>fields, and the operating structure is the largest stainless steel building in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link>, the size of 14<space/><link><target>NHL</target></link><space/>rinks.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>In 2006, the<space/><link><target>State of Qatar</target></link><space/>awarded Keppel Seghers Singapore, a subsidiary of<space/><link><target>Keppel Corporation</target></link><space/>to begin construction on a 275,000 tonne/year Anaerobic Digestion and Composting Plant licensed by<space/><template><target>Ill</target><arg>de</arg><arg>Kompogas</arg></template><space/>Switzerland. This plant, with 15 independent anaerobic digestors will be the world's largest composting facility once fully operational in early 2011 and forms part of the<space/><link><target>Qatar Domestic Solid Waste Management Center</target></link>, the largest integrated<space/><link><target>waste management</target></link><space/>complex in the<space/><link><target>Middle East</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another large MSW composter is the<space/><link><target>Lahore Composting Facility</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Lahore</target></link>, Pakistan, which has a capacity to convert 1,000 tonnes of municipal solid waste per day into compost. It also has a capacity to convert substantial portion of the intake into<space/><link><target>Refuse-derived fuel</target></link><space/>(RDF) materials for further combustion use in several energy consuming industries across Pakistan e.g., in cement manufacturing companies where it is used to heat up the<space/><link><target>Cement Kiln</target></link><space/>systems. This project has also been approved by the Executive Board of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (<link><target>UNFCCC</target></link>) for reduction of emission of methane gas into the climate and has been registered with a capacity of reducing 108,686 metric tonnes CO2 equivalent per annum.<extension extension_name='ref'>Details on project design and its validation and monitoring reports are available at:<space/><link type='external' href='http://cdm.unfccc.int/Projects/DB/SGS-UKL1248265320.71/view'>Project 2778 : Composting of Organic Content of Municipal Solid Waste in Lahore</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Related technologies</heading><paragraph><link><target>Anaerobic digestion</target></link><space/>is another possible process for converting organic waste into a useful produce (<link><target>biogas</target></link>). In central Europe, anaerobic digestion is now more common than composting as a process for treating organic waste.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><space/>The two processes can also be used in combination:<space/><link><target>sewage sludge</target></link><space/>is often anaerobically digested first, followed by a composting process before selling or giving away the compost to farmers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>Composting as a recognized practice dates to at least the early Roman Empire since<space/><link><target>Pliny the Elder</target></link><space/>(AD 23-79). Traditionally, composting involved piling organic materials until the next planting season, at which time the materials would have decayed enough to be ready for use in the soil. The advantage of this method is that little working time or effort is required from the composter and it fits in naturally with agricultural practices in temperate climates. Disadvantages (from the modern perspective) are that space is used for a whole year, some nutrients might be leached due to exposure to rainfall, and disease-producing organisms and insects may not be adequately controlled.</paragraph><paragraph>Composting was somewhat modernized beginning in the 1920s in Europe as a tool for organic farming.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link here</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>The first industrial station for the transformation of urban organic materials into compost was set up in<space/><link><target>Wels</target></link>, Austria in the year 1921.<extension extension_name='ref'>Welser Anzeiger vom 05. Januar 1921, 67. Jahrgang, Nr. 2, S. 4</extension><space/>Early frequent citations for propounding composting within farming are for the German-speaking world<space/><link><target>Rudolf Steiner</target></link>, founder of a farming method called<space/><link><target>biodynamics</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Annie Franc-Harrar</target></link>, who was appointed on behalf of the government in<space/><link><target>Mexico</target></link><space/>and supported the country 19501958 to set up a large humus organization in the fight against erosion and soil degradation.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><space/></paragraph><paragraph>In the English-speaking world it was<space/><link><target>Sir Albert Howard</target></link><space/>who worked extensively in<space/><link><target>India</target></link><space/>on sustainable practices and<space/><link><target>Lady Eve Balfour</target></link><space/>who was a huge proponent of composting. Composting was imported to America by various followers of these early European movements by the likes of<space/><link><target>Jerome Irving Rodale</target><part>J.I. Rodale</part></link><space/>(founder of Rodale Organic Gardening), E.E. Pfeiffer (who developed scientific practices in biodynamic farming),<space/><link><target>Paul Keene</target></link><space/>(founder of Walnut Acres in Pennsylvania), and<space/><link><target>Scott Nearing</target><part>Scott</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Helen Nearing</target></link><space/>(who inspired the<space/><link><target>back-to-the-land movement</target></link><space/>of the 1960s). Coincidentally, some of the above met briefly in India - all were quite influential in the U.S. from the 1960s into the 1980s.</paragraph><paragraph>There are many modern proponents of rapid composting that attempt to correct some of the perceived problems associated with traditional, slow composting. Many advocate that compost can be made in 2 to 3 weeks.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://vric.ucdavis.edu/pdf/compost_rapidcompost.pdf'>The Rapid Compost Method by Robert Raabe, Professor of Plant Pathology, Berkeley</link></extension><space/>Many such short processes involve a few changes to traditional methods, including smaller, more homogenized pieces in the compost, controlling carbon-to-nitrogen ratio (C:N) at 30 to 1 or less, and monitoring the moisture level more carefully. However, none of these parameters differ significantly from the early writings of Howard and Balfour, suggesting that in fact modern composting has not made significant advances over the traditional methods that take a few months to work. For this reason and others, many modern scientists who deal with carbon transformations are sceptical that there is a &quot;super-charged&quot; way to get nature to make compost rapidly.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">Very old reference, find a better one</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In fact, both sides are right to some extent. The bacterial activity in rapid high heat methods breaks down the material to the extent that pathogens and seeds are destroyed, and the original feedstock is unrecognizable. At this stage, the compost can be used to prepare fields or other planting areas. However, most professionals recommend that the compost be given time to cure before using in a nursery for starting seeds or growing young plants. The curing time allows fungi to continue the decomposition process and eliminating<space/><link><target>phytotoxic</target></link><space/>substances.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many countries such as<space/><link><target>Wales</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gwynedd.gov.uk/gwy_doc.asp?doc=25454&amp;amp;language=1&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;c=1'>Gwynedd Council food recycling</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.edie.net/news/5/Anglesey-households-achieve-100-food-waste-recycling/19101/</arg><arg name="title">Anglesey households achieve 100% food waste recycling</arg><arg name="work">edie.net</arg></template></extension><space/>and some individual cities such as Seattle and<space/><link><target>San Francisco Mandatory Recycling and Composting Ordinance</target><part>San Francisco</part></link><space/>require food and yard waste to be sorted for composting.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">San Francisco Signs Mandatory Recycling & Composting Laws<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.inhabitat.com/2009/06/24/san-francisco-mandates-recycling-composting/</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">The case for mandatory composting<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/magazine/articles/2010/03/21/the_case_for_mandatory_composting/</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2010</arg><arg name="work">[[The Boston Globe]]</arg><arg name="first">Aubin</arg><arg name="last">Tyler</arg><arg name="date">21 March 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Kew Gardens</target></link><space/>in London has one of the biggest non-commercial compost heaps in Europe.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">broken link</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>1</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of composting systems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>San Francisco Mandatory Recycling and Composting Ordinance</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Terra preta</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Urban agriculture</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Waste sorting</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Sustainable development</arg><arg>Gardening</arg></template><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Composting</arg></template><template><target>Wikibooks</target><arg>Category:Composting</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Recycling</target></template><template><target>waste</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Composting</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Organic gardening</target></link><link><target>Category:Organic farming</target></link><link><target>Category:Organic fertilizers</target></link><link><target>Category:Waste management</target></link><link><target>Category:Gardening aids</target></link><link><target>Category:Sanitation</target></link><link><target>Category:Soil improvers</target></link><link><target>Category:Soil</target></link><link><target>Category:Sustainable food system</target></link></paragraph></article>