<article title='Epiphenomenalism'><paragraph><template><target>Cleanup-reorganize</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg><arg name="reason">Just about the body sections, not necessarily a guidelines problems. The history is mixed with a description in the "Background" section, but the body needs an overall reorganization too</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Epiphenomenalism</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Mindbody dichotomy</target><part>mindbody philosophy</part></link><space/>marked by the belief that basic physical events (sense organs, neural impulses, and muscle contractions) are causal with respect to mental events (thought, consciousness, and cognition). Mental events are viewed as completely dependent on physical functions and, as such, have no independent existence or causal efficacy; it is a mere appearance. Fear seems to make the heart beat faster; though, according to epiphenomenalism, the state of the nervous system causes the heart to beat faster.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Walter</arg><arg name="first">Sven</arg><arg name="title">Epiphenomenalism</arg><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/epipheno/#H2</arg><arg name="work">Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Bielefeld</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 October 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Because mental events are a kind of overflow that cannot cause anything physical, yet have non-physical properties, epiphenomenalism is viewed as a form of property dualism.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Development</heading><paragraph>During the seventeenth century,<space/><link><target>Rene Descartes</target></link><space/>argued that animals are subject to mechanical laws of nature. He defended the idea of<space/><link><target>automatic behavior</target></link>, or the performance of actions without conscious thought. Descartes questioned how the immaterial mind and the material body can interact causally.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"></extension><space/>His interactionist model (1649) held that the body relates to the mind through the pineal gland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Robinson</arg><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="title">Epiphenomenalism</arg><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epiphenomenalism/</arg><arg name="publisher">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 November 2013</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Julien Offray de La Mettrie</target><part>La Mettrie</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Gottfried Leibniz</target><part>Leibniz</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Baruch Spinoza</target><part>Spinoza</part></link><space/>all in their own way began this way of thinking. The idea that even if the animal were conscious nothing would be added to the production of behavior, even in animals of the human type, was first voiced by La Mettrie (1745), and then by<space/><link><target>Pierre Jean George Cabanis</target><part>Cabanis</part></link><space/>(1802), and was further explicated by<space/><link><target>Hodgson</target></link><space/>(1870)<space/><xhtml:sup>[Which Hodgson?]</xhtml:sup><space/>and<space/><link><target>T.H. Huxley</target><part>Huxley</part></link><space/>(1874).<extension extension_name='ref'>Huxley, T. H. (1874). &quot;On the Hypothesis that Animals are Automata, and its History&quot;,<space/><italics>The Fortnightly Review</italics>, n.s.16:555-580. Reprinted in<space/><italics>Method and Results: Essays by Thomas H. Huxley</italics><space/>(New York: D. Appleton and Company, 1898)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gallagher, S. 2006. &quot;Where's the action?: Epiphenomenalism and the problem of free will&quot;. In W. Banks, S. Pockett, and S. Gallagher.<space/><italics>Does Consciousness Cause Behavior? An Investigation of the Nature of Intuition</italics><space/>(109-124). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Henry Huxley</target></link><space/>agreed with Descartes that behavior is determined solely by physical mechanisms, but he also believed that humans enjoy an intelligent life. In 1874, Huxley argued that animals are<space/><link><target>Conscious automatism</target><part>conscious automata</part></link><space/>in the Presidential Address to the<space/><link><target>British Science Association</target><part>British Association for the Advancement of Science</part></link>. Huxley proposed that psychical changes are collateral products of physical changes. He termed the stream of consciousness an epiphenomenon; like the bell of a clock that has no role in keeping the time, consciousness has no role in determining behavior.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Huxley defended<space/><link><target>automatic behavior</target><part>automatism</part></link><space/>by testing reflex actions, originally supported by Descartes. Huxley hypothesized that frogs that undergo lobotomy would swim when thrown into water, despite being unable to initiate actions. He argued that the ability to swim was solely dependent on the molecular change in the brain, concluding that consciousness is not necessary for reflex actions. According to epiphenomenalism, animals experience pain only as a result of<space/><link><target>neurophysiology</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1870, Huxley conducted a case study on a French soldier who had sustained a shot in the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian war</target><part>Franco-Prussian War</part></link><space/>that fractured his left parietal bone. Every few weeks the soldier would enter a trance-like state, smoking, dressing himself, and aiming his cane like a rifle all while being insensitive to pins, electric shocks, odorous substances, vinegar, noise, and certain light conditions. Huxley used this study to show that consciousness was not necessary to execute these purposeful actions, justifying the assumption that humans are insensible machines. Huxleys mechanistic attitude towards the body convinced him that the brain alone causes behavior.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the early 1900s<space/><link><target>behaviorism</target><part>scientific behaviorists</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Ivan Pavlov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John B. Watson</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>B. F. Skinner</target></link><space/>began the attempt to uncover laws describing the relationship between stimuli and responses, without reference to inner mental phenomena. Instead of adopting a form of<space/><link><target>eliminative materialism</target><part>eliminativism</part></link><space/>or mental<space/><link><target>fictionalism</target></link>, positions that deny that inner mental phenomena exist, a behaviorist was able to adopt epiphenomenalism in order to allow for the existence of mind.<space/><link><target>George Santayana</target></link><space/>(1905) believed that all motion has merely physical causes. Because consciousness is accessory to life and not essential to it, natural selection is responsible for ingraining tendencies to avoid certain contingencies without any conscious achievement involved.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Scott</arg><arg name="first">Alwyn</arg><arg name="title">Stairway to the Mind</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Copernicus</arg><arg name="location">New York, New York</arg><arg name="isbn">9780387943817</arg><arg name="page">109</arg></template></extension><space/>By the 1960s, scientific behaviourism met substantial difficulties and eventually gave way to the<space/><link><target>cognitive revolution</target></link>. Participants in that revolution, such as<space/><link><target>Jerry Fodor</target></link>, reject epiphenomenalism and insist upon the efficacy of the mind. Fodor even speaks of &quot;epiphobia&quot;&amp;mdash;fear that one is becoming an epiphenomenalist.</paragraph><paragraph>However, since the cognitive revolution, there have been several who have argued for a version of epiphenomenalism. In 1970,<space/><link><target>Keith Campbell (philosopher)</target><part>Keith Campbell</part></link><space/>proposed his new epiphenomenalism, which states that the body produces a spiritual mind that does not act on the body. How the brain causes a spiritual mind, according to Campbell, is destined to remain beyond our understanding forever (see<space/><link><target>New Mysterianism</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Griffin</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Unsnarling the World-Knot</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="location">Berkeley, California</arg><arg name="isbn">9781556357558</arg><arg name="page">5</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2001,<space/><link><target>David Chalmers</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Frank Cameron Jackson</target><part>Frank Jackson</part></link><space/>argued that claims about conscious states should be deduced a priori from claims about physical states alone. They offered that epiphenomenalism bridges, but does not close, the explanatory gap between the physical and the phenomenal realms.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Polger</arg><arg name="first">Thomas</arg><arg name="title">Natural Minds</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, Massachusetts</arg><arg name="isbn">9780262661966</arg><arg name="pages">37–38</arg></template></extension><space/>These more recent versions maintain that only the subjective, qualitative aspects of mental states are epiphenomenal. Imagine both Pierre and a robot eating a cupcake. Unlike the robot, Pierre is conscious of eating the cupcake while the behavior is under way. This subjective experience is often called a<space/><italics>quale</italics><space/>(plural<space/><link><target>qualia</target></link>), and it describes the private &quot;raw feel&quot; or the subjective &quot;<link><target>Thomas Nagel</target><part>what-it-is-like</part></link>&quot; that is the inner accompaniment of many mental states. Thus, while Pierre and the robot are both doing the same thing, only Pierre has the inner conscious experience.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Frank Cameron Jackson</target><part>Frank Jackson</part></link><space/>(1982), for example, once espoused the following view:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>I am what is sometimes known as a "qualia freak". I think that there are certain features of bodily sensations especially, but also of certain perceptual experiences, which no amount of purely physical information includes. Tell me everything physical there is to tell about what is going on in a living brain... you won't have told me about the hurtfulness of pains, the itchiness of itches, pangs of jealousy....<ref>Jackson, 1982, p. 127.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>According to epiphenomenalism, mental states like Pierre's pleasurable experience&amp;mdash;or, at any rate, their distinctive qualia&amp;mdash;are<space/><link><target>epiphenomenon</target><part>epiphenomena</part></link>; they are side-effects or by-products of physical processes in the body. If Pierre takes a second bite, it is not caused by his pleasure from the first; If Pierre says, &quot;That was good, so I will take another bite&quot;, his speech act is not caused by the preceding pleasure. The conscious experiences that accompany brain processes are causally impotent. The mind might simply be a byproduct of other properties such as brain size or pathway activation synchronicity, which are adaptive.</paragraph><paragraph>Some thinkers draw distinctions between different varieties of epiphenomenalism. In<space/><italics><link><target>Consciousness Explained</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Daniel Dennett</target></link><space/>distinguishes between a purely metaphysical sense of epiphenomenalism, in which the epiphenomenon has no causal impact at all, and Huxley's &quot;steam whistle&quot; epiphenomenalism, in which effects exist but are not functionally relevant.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Arguments for epiphenomenalism</heading><paragraph>A large body of neurophysiological data seems to support epiphenomenalism. Some of the oldest such data is the<space/><link><target>Bereitschaftspotential</target></link><space/>or &quot;readiness potential&quot; in which electrical activity related to voluntary actions can be recorded up to two seconds before the subject is aware of making a decision to perform the action. More recently<space/><link><target>Benjamin Libet</target></link><space/>et al. (1979) have shown that it can take 0.5 seconds before a stimulus becomes part of conscious experience even though subjects can respond to the stimulus in reaction time tests within 200 milliseconds. Recent research on the Event Related Potential also shows that conscious experience does not occur until the late phase of the potential (P3 or later) that occurs 300 milliseconds or more after the event. In Bregman's<space/><link><target>Illusory continuity of tones</target><part>Auditory Continuity Illusion</part></link>, where a pure tone is followed by broadband noise and the noise is followed by the same pure tone it seems as if the tone occurs throughout the period of noise. This also suggests a delay for processing data before conscious experience occurs. Popular science author<space/><link><target>Tor Nrretranders</target></link><space/>has called the delay &quot;<link><target>The User Illusion</target></link>&quot; implying that we only have the illusion of conscious control, most actions being controlled automatically by non-conscious parts of the brain with the conscious mind relegated to the role of spectator.</paragraph><paragraph>The scientific data seem to support the idea that conscious experience is created by non-conscious processes in the brain (i.e., there is subliminal processing that becomes conscious experience). These results have been interpreted to suggest that people are capable of action before conscious experience of the decision to act occurs. Some argue that this supports epiphenomenalism, since it shows that the feeling of making a decision to act is actually an epiphenomenon; the action happens before the decision, so the decision did not cause the action to occur.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Arguments against epiphenomenalism</heading><paragraph>The most powerful argument against epiphenomenalism is that it is self contradictory: If we have knowledge about epiphenomenalism, then we know about the existence of the mind, but if epiphenomenalism were correct, then we should not have any knowledge about the mind, as it does not affect anything physical.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="first">William<space/></arg><arg name="last">Robinson<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Edward N. Zalta<space/></arg><arg name="year">2015<space/></arg><arg name="title">Epiphenomenalism<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Fall 2015<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/epiphenomenalism/#SelStu</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some philosophers, such as Dennett, reject both epiphenomenalism and the existence of qualia with the same charge that<space/><link><target>Gilbert Ryle</target></link><space/>leveled against a Cartesian &quot;<link><target>ghost in the machine</target></link>&quot;, that they too are<space/><link><target>category mistake</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A quale or conscious experience would not belong to the category of objects of reference on this account, but rather to the category of ways of doing things.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Functionalism (philosophy of mind)</target><part>Functionalists</part></link><space/>assert that mental states are well described by their overall role, their activity in relation to the organism as a whole. This doctrine is rooted in Aristotle's conception of the soul, and has antecedents in Hobbes's conception of the mind as a calculating machine, but it has become fully articulated (and popularly endorsed) only in the last third of the 20th century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sep-functionalism"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="first">Janet<space/></arg><arg name="last">Levin<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Edward N. Zalta<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="title">Functionalism<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Summer 2010<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2010/entries/functionalism/</arg></template></extension><space/>In so far as it mediates stimulus and response, a mental<space/><link><target>Function (computer science)</target><part>function</part></link><space/>is analogous to a program that processes<space/><link><target>input/output</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>automata theory</target></link>. In principle,<space/><link><target>multiple realisability</target></link><space/>would guarantee<space/><link><target>Universal Turing machine</target><part>platform dependencies</part></link><space/>can be avoided, whether in terms of hardware and operating system or,<space/><italics>ex hypothesi</italics>, biology and philosophy. Because a<space/><link><target>high-level language</target></link><space/>is a practical requirement for developing the most complex programs, functionalism implies that a<space/><link><target>non-reductive physicalism</target></link><space/>would offer a similar advantage over a strictly eliminative materialism.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Eliminative materialism</target><part>Eliminative materialists</part></link><space/>believe &quot;<link><target>folk psychology</target></link>&quot; is so unscientific that, ultimately, it will be better to eliminate primitive concepts such as<space/><italics>mind,</italics><space/><italics>desire</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>belief,</italics><space/>in favor of a future neuro-scientific account. A more moderate position such as<space/><link><target>J. L. Mackie</target></link>'s<space/><italics>error theory</italics><space/>suggests that false beliefs should be stripped away from a mental concept without eliminating the concept itself, the legitimate core meaning being left intact.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Benjamin Libet</target></link>'s results are quoted<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Daniel Wegner</target><part>Wegner D.</part></link>, 2002. The Illusion of Conscious Will. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</extension><space/>in favor of epiphenomenalism, but he believes subjects still have a &quot;conscious veto&quot;, since the readiness potential does not invariably lead to an action. In<space/><italics><link><target>Freedom Evolves</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Daniel Dennett</target></link><space/>argues that a no-free-will conclusion is based on dubious assumptions about the location of consciousness, as well as questioning the accuracy and interpretation of Libet's results. Similar criticism of Libet-style research has been made by neuroscientist Adina Roskies and cognitive theorists Tim Bayne and Alfred Mele.</paragraph><paragraph>Others have argued that data such as the<space/><link><target>Bereitschaftspotential</target></link><space/>undermine epiphenomenalism for the same reason, that such experiments rely on a subject reporting the point in time at which a conscious experience occurs, thus relying on the subject to be able to consciously perform an action. That ability would seem to be at odds with early epiphenomenalism, which according to Huxley is the broad claim that consciousness is completely without any power as the steam-whistle which accompanies the work of a locomotive engine is without influence upon its machinery.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Flanagan1992"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">O.J.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Flanagan<space/></arg><arg name="year">1992<space/></arg><arg name="title">Consciousness Reconsidered<space/></arg><arg name="series">Bradford Books<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MIT Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-262-56077-1<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">lc92010057<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="page">131</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Adrian G. Guggisberg and Annas Mottaz have also challenged those findings.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3746176/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A study by Aaron Schurger and colleagues published in PNAS<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.pnas.org/content/109/42/E2904/1</extension><space/>challenged assumptions about the causal nature of the readiness potential itself (and the &quot;pre-movement buildup&quot; of neural activity in general), casting doubt on conclusions drawn from studies such as Libet's<extension extension_name='ref' name="LGW"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1093/brain/106.3.623<space/></arg><arg name="title">Time of Conscious Intention to Act in Relation to Onset of Cerebral Activity (Readiness-Potential)<space/></arg><arg name="year">1983<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Libet<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Gleason<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Curtis A.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Wright<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Elwood W.<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Pearl<space/></arg><arg name="first4">Dennis K.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Brain<space/></arg><arg name="volume">106<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">623–42<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">6640273</arg></template></extension><space/>and Fried's.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fried"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2010.11.045<space/></arg><arg name="title">Internally Generated Preactivation of Single Neurons in Human Medial Frontal Cortex Predicts Volition<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Fried<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Itzhak<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Mukamel<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Roy<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Kreiman<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Gabriel<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Neuron<space/></arg><arg name="volume">69<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">548–62<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">21315264<space/></arg><arg name="pmc">3052770</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In favor of interactionism,<space/><link><target>Celia Green</target></link><space/>(2003) argues that epiphenomenalism does not even provide a satisfactory out from the problem of interaction posed by substance dualism. Although it does not entail substance dualism, according to Green, epiphenomenalism implies a one-way form of interactionism that is just as hard to conceive of as the two-way form embodied in substance dualism. Green suggests the assumption that it is less of a problem may arise from the unexamined belief that physical events have some sort of primacy over mental ones.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Donald Symons</target></link><space/>dismisses epiphenomenalism from an evolutionary perspective. He says that the view that mind is an epiphenomenon of brain activity is not consistent with evolutionary theory, because if mind were functionless, it would have disappeared long ago, as it would not have been favoured by evolution.<extension extension_name='ref'>Symons, Donald. The evolution of human sexuality. Oxford University Press. 1979.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>columns-list</target><arg>2</arg><arg>
* [[Anomalous monism]]
* [[Dualism (philosophy of mind)]]
* [[Emergentism]]
* [[Frank Cameron Jackson|Frank Jackson]]
* [[George Santayana]]
* [[Physicalism|Nonreductive physicalism]]
* [[Philosophy of mind]]
* [[Problem of mental causation]]
* [[Property dualism]]
* [[Specious present]]
* [[Supervenience]]
* [[Qualia]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References and further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Chalmers, David. (1996)<space/><italics>The Conscious Mind: In Search of a Fundamental Theory</italics>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</listitem><listitem>Dennett, Daniel. (2003)<space/><italics>Freedom evolves</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Green, Celia. (2003)<space/><italics>The Lost Cause: Causation and the Mind-Body Problem</italics>, Oxford: Oxford Forum.</listitem><listitem>Huxley, Thomas. (1874) &quot;On the Hypothesis that Animals are Automata, and its History&quot;,<space/><italics>The Fortnightly Review</italics>, n.s. 16, pp.&amp;nbsp;555580. Reprinted in Method and Results: Essays by Thomas H. Huxley (New York: D. Appleton and Company, 1898).</listitem><listitem>Jackson, Frank. (1982) &quot;Epiphenomenal Qualia&quot;,<space/><italics>The Philosophical Quarterly</italics>, 32, pp.&amp;nbsp;127136.<space/><link type='external' href='http://members.aol.com/NeoNoetics/Mary.html'>Online text</link></listitem><listitem>James, William. (1890)<space/><italics>The Principles of Psychology</italics>, Henry Holt And Company.<space/><link type='external' href='http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/James/Principles/index.htm'>Online text</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Libet<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Wright<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>E. W.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Feinstein<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>B.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Pearl<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>D. K.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Subjective Referral of the Timing for a Conscious Sensory Experience<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Brain<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>102<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>191–221</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/brain/102.1.193<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Libet<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Unconscious Cerebral Initiative and the Role of Conscious Will in Voluntary Action<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Behavioral and Brain Sciences<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>8<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>529–566<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/s0140525x00044903</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Robinson, William. (2003) &quot;Epiphenomenalism&quot;,<space/><italics>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</italics>, Edward Zalta (ed.).<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2003/entries/epiphenomenalism/'>Online text</link></listitem><listitem>Walter, Sven. (2007) &quot;Epiphenomenalism,&quot;<space/><italics>The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy</italics>, James Fieser and Bradley Dowden (eds.).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/e/epipheno.htm'>Online text</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template><template><target>Wikibooks</target><arg>Consciousness studies</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>epiphenomenalism</arg></template><space/>by William Robinson.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/e/epipheno.htm'>Epiphenomenalism</link><space/>- an article by Sven Walter in<space/><italics>The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy</italics>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.txtxs.nl/artikel.asp?artid=624'>Exit Epiphenomenalism</link><space/>- Analysis by Rivas and Van Dongen.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.consciousentities.com/deadends.htm#epiphenomenalism'>Strange Ideas</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://philosophynow.org/issues/81/Epiphenomenalism_Explained'>Epiphenomenalism Explained</link>, an article by Norman Bacrac in<space/><italics><link><target>Philosophy Now</target></link></italics></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>philosophy of mind</target></template><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Dualism (philosophy of mind)</target></link><link><target>Category:Theories of mind</target></link></paragraph></article>