<article title='Computational_linguistics'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the scientific field</arg><arg>the journal</arg><arg>Computational Linguistics (journal)</arg></template><template><target>linguistics</target></template><bold>Computational linguistics</bold><space/>is an<space/><link><target>interdisciplinary</target></link><space/>field concerned with the statistical or rule-based modeling of<space/><link><target>natural language</target></link><space/>from a computational perspective.</paragraph><paragraph>Traditionally, computational linguistics was usually performed by<space/><link><target>computer scientist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who had specialized in the application of computers to the processing of a<space/><link><target>natural language</target></link>. Computational linguists often work as members of interdisciplinary teams, including linguists (specifically trained in linguistics), language experts (persons with some level of ability in the languages relevant to a given project), and computer scientists. In general, computational linguistics draws upon the involvement of<space/><link><target>linguistics</target><part>linguists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>computer science</target><part>computer scientists</part></link>, experts in<space/><link><target>artificial intelligence</target></link>, mathematicians,<space/><link><target>logic</target><trail>ians</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>philosophy</target><part>philosophers</part></link>,<space/><link><target>cognitive science</target><part>cognitive scientists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>cognitive psychology</target><part>cognitive psychologists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>psycholinguistics</target><part>psycholinguists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>anthropology</target><part>anthropologists</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>neuroscience</target><part>neuroscientists</part></link>, among others.</paragraph><paragraph>Computational linguistics has theoretical and applied components, where theoretical computational linguistics takes up issues in<space/><link><target>theoretical linguistics</target></link><space/>and cognitive science, and applied computational linguistics focuses on the practical outcome of modeling human language use.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hans Uszkoreit. What Is Computational Linguistics?<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.coli.uni-saarland.de/~hansu/what_is_cl.html'></link><space/>Department of Computational Linguistics and Phonetics of Saarland University</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph>Computational linguistics as a field predates<space/><link><target>artificial intelligence</target></link>, a field under which it is often grouped. Computational linguistics originated with efforts in the United States in the 1950s to use computers to automatically translate texts from foreign languages, particularly Russian scientific journals, into English.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Hutchins:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hutchinsweb.me.uk/MTS-1999.pdf'>Retrospect and prospect in computer-based translation.</link><space/>Proceedings of MT Summit VII, 1999, pp. 3044.</extension><space/>Since computers can make<space/><link><target>arithmetic</target></link><space/>calculations much faster and more accurately than humans, it was thought to be only a short matter of time before the technical details could be taken care of that would allow them the same remarkable capacity to process language.<extension extension_name='ref'>Arnold B. Barach:<space/><link type='external' href='https://secure.flickr.com/photos/bostworld/2152048032/in/set-72157603898383698/'>Translating Machine</link><space/>1975: And the Changes To Come.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When<space/><link><target>machine translation</target></link><space/>(also known as mechanical translation) failed to yield accurate translations right away, automated processing of human languages was recognized as far more complex than had originally been assumed. Computational linguistics was born as the name of the new field of study devoted to developing<space/><link><target>algorithm</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and software for intelligently processing language data. When artificial intelligence came into existence in the 1960s, the field of computational linguistics became that sub-division of artificial intelligence dealing with human-level comprehension and production of natural languages.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In order to translate one language into another, it was observed that one had to understand the<space/><link><target>grammar</target></link><space/>of both languages, including both<space/><link><target>morphology (linguistics)</target><part>morphology</part></link><space/>(the grammar of word forms) and<space/><link><target>syntax</target></link><space/>(the grammar of sentence structure). In order to understand syntax, one had to also understand the<space/><link><target>semantics</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>lexicon</target></link><space/>(or 'vocabulary'), and even to understand something of the<space/><link><target>pragmatics</target></link><space/>of language use. Thus, what started as an effort to translate between languages evolved into an entire discipline devoted to understanding how to represent and process natural languages using computers.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www-nlpir.nist.gov/MINDS/FINAL/NLP.web.pdf'>Natural Language Processing by Liz Liddy, Eduard Hovy, Jimmy Lin, John Prager, Dragomir Radev, Lucy Vanderwende, Ralph Weischedel</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nowadays research within the scope of computational linguistics is done at computational linguistics departments,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.coli.uni-saarland.de'>Computational linguistics and phonetics at Saarland University</link></extension><space/>computational linguistics laboratories,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://yatsko.zohosites.com/home.html'>Yatsko's computational linguistics laboratory</link></extension><space/><link><target>computer science</target></link><space/>departments,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://wiki.umiacs.umd.edu/clip/index.php/Main_Page'>Clip: Computational Linguistics and Information Processing</link></extension><space/>and linguistics departments.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://linguistics.georgetown.edu/programs/graduate/computational/'>Computational Linguistics&amp;nbsp; Department of Linguistics&amp;nbsp; Georgetown College</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ling.upenn.edu/research/computational.html'>UPenn Linguistics: Computational Linguistics</link></extension><space/>Some research in the field of computational linguistics aims to create working speech or text processing systems while others aim to create a system allowing human-machine interaction. Programs meant for human-machine communication are called<space/><link><target>Embodied agent</target><part>conversational agents</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jurafsky, D., &amp; Martin, J. H. (2009). Speech and language processing: An introduction to natural language processing, computational linguistics, and speech recognition. Upper Saddle River, N.J: Pearson Prentice Hall.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Approaches</heading><paragraph>Just as computational linguistics can be performed by experts in a variety of fields, and through a wide assortment of departments, so too can the research fields broach a diverse range of topics. The following sections discuss some of the literature available across the entire field broken into four main area of discourse: developmental linguistics, structural linguistics, linguistic production, and linguistic comprehension.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Developmental Approaches</heading><paragraph>Language is a skill which develops throughout the life of an individual. This developmental process has been examined using a number of techniques, and a computational approach is one of them. Human<space/><link><target>language development</target></link><space/>does provide some constraints which make it feasible to apply a computational method to understanding it. For instance, during<space/><link><target>language acquisition</target></link>, human children are largely only exposed to positive evidence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bowerman, M. (1988). The &quot;no negative evidence&quot;problem: How do children avoid constructing an overly general grammar. Explaining language universals. Retrieved from http://pubman.mpdl.mpg.de/pubman/item/escidoc:468143:4/component/escidoc:532427/bowerman_1988_The-No.pdf</extension><space/>This means that during the linguistic development of an individual, only evidence for what is a correct form is provided, and not evidence for what is not correct. This is insufficient information for a simple hypothesis testing procedure for information as complex as language,<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1971">Braine, M.D.S. (1971). On two types of models of the internalization of grammars. In D.I. Slobin (Ed.), The ontogenesis of grammar: A theoretical perspective. New York: Academic Press.</extension><space/>and so provides certain boundaries for a computational approach to modeling language development and acquisition in an individual.</paragraph><paragraph>Attempts have been made to model the developmental process of language acquisition in children from a computational angle, leading to both<space/><link><target>stochastic grammar</target><part>statistical grammars</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>connectionism</target><part>connectionist models</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="powers1989">Powers, D.M.W. &amp; Turk, C.C.R. (1989).<space/><italics>Machine Learning of Natural Language</italics>. Springer-Verlag. ISBN 978-0-387-19557-5.</extension><space/>Work in this realm has also been proposed as a method to explain the<space/><link><target>evolution of language</target></link><space/>through history. Using models, it has been shown that languages can be learned with a combination of simple input presented incrementally as the child develops better memory and longer attention span.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1993">Elman, J. (1993). Learning and development in neural networks: The importance of starting small. Cognition, 71-99. Retrieved from http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0010027793900584</extension><space/>This was simultaneously posed as a reason for the long developmental period of human children.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1993"></extension><space/>Both conclusions were drawn because of the strength of the<space/><link><target>neural network</target></link><space/>which the project created.</paragraph><paragraph>The ability of infants to develop language has also been modeled using robots<extension extension_name='ref'>Salvi, G., Montesano, L., Bernardino, A., &amp; Santos-Victor, J. (2012). Language bootstrapping: learning word meanings from perception-action association. IEEE transactions on systems, man, and cybernetics. Part B, Cybernetics: a publication of the IEEE Systems, Man, and Cybernetics Society, 42(3), 660-71.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1109/TSMCB.2011.2172420</arg></template></extension><space/>in order to test linguistic theories. Enabled to learn as children might, a model was created based on an<space/><link><target>affordance</target></link><space/>model in which mappings between actions, perceptions, and effects were created and linked to spoken words. Crucially, these robots were able to acquire functioning word-to-meaning mappings without needing grammatical structure, vastly simplifying the learning process and shedding light on information which furthers the current understanding of linguistic development. It is important to note that this information could only have been empirically tested using a computational approach.</paragraph><paragraph>As our understanding of the linguistic development of an individual within a lifetime is continually improved using neural networks and learning robotic systems, it is also important to keep in mind that languages themselves change and develop through time. Computational approaches to understanding this phenomenon have unearthed very interesting information. Using the<space/><link><target>Price Equation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Plya urn</target></link><space/>dynamics, researchers have created a system which not only predicts future linguistic evolution, but also gives insight into the evolutionary history of modern day languages.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gong, T., Shuai, L., Tamariz, M., &amp; Jger, G. (2012). Studying Language Change Using Price Equation and Plya-urn Dynamics. (E. Scalas, Ed.)PLoS ONE, 7(3), e33171.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1371/journal.pone.0033171</arg></template></extension><space/>This modeling effort achieved, through computational linguistics, what would otherwise have been impossible.</paragraph><paragraph>It is clear that the understanding of linguistic development in humans as well as throughout evolutionary time has been fantastically improved because of advances in computational linguistics. The ability to model and modify systems at will affords science an ethical method of testing hypotheses that would otherwise be intractable.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Structural Approaches</heading><paragraph>In order to create better computational models of language, an understanding of languages structure is crucial. To this end, the<space/><link><target>English language</target></link><space/>has been meticulously studied using computational approaches to better understand how the language works on a structural level. One of the most important pieces of being able to study linguistic structure is the availability of large linguistic corpora. This grants computational linguists the raw data necessary to run their models and gain a better understanding of the underlying structures present in the vast amount of data which is contained in any single language. One of the most cited English linguistic corpora is the Penn<space/><link><target>Treebank</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marcus, M., &amp; Marcinkiewicz, M. (1993). Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn Treebank. Computational linguistics. Retrieved from http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=972475</extension><space/>Containing over 4.5 million words of<space/><link><target>American English</target></link>, this corpus has been annotated for<space/><link><target>part-of-speech</target></link><space/>information. This type of annotated corpus allows other researchers to apply hypotheses and measures that would otherwise be impossible to perform.</paragraph><paragraph>Theoretical approaches to the structure of languages have also been developed. These works allow computational linguistics to have a framework within which to work out hypotheses that will further the understanding of the language in a myriad of ways. One of the original theoretical theses on internalization of<space/><link><target>grammar</target></link><space/>and structure of language proposed two types of models.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1971"></extension><space/>In these models, rules or patterns learned increase in strength with the frequency of their encounter.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1971"></extension><space/>The work also created a question for computational linguists to answer: how does an infant learn a specific and non-normal grammar (<link><target>Chomsky Normal Form</target></link>) without learning an overgeneralized version and getting stuck?<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1971"></extension><space/>Theoretical efforts like these set the direction for research to go early in the lifetime of a field of study, and are crucial to the growth of the field.</paragraph><paragraph>Structural information about languages allows for the discovery and implementation of similarity recognition between pairs of text utterances.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2">Angus, D., Smith, A., &amp; Wiles, J. (2012). Conceptual recurrence plots: revealing patterns in human discourse. IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics, 18(6), 988-97.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1109/TVCG.2011.100</arg></template></extension><space/>For instance, it has recently been proven that based on the structural information present in patterns of human discourse, conceptual<space/><link><target>recurrence plots</target></link><space/>can be used to model and visualize trends in data and create reliable measures of similarity between natural textual utterances.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2"></extension><space/>This technique is a strong tool for further probing the structure of human<space/><link><target>discourse</target></link>. Without the computational approach to this question, the vastly complex information present in discourse data would have remained inaccessible to scientists.</paragraph><paragraph>Information regarding the structural data of a language is not simply available for<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>English</part></link>, but can also be found in other languages, such as<space/><link><target>Japanese language</target><part>Japanese</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated3">Furuhashi, S., &amp; Hayakawa, Y. (2012). Lognormality of the Distribution of Japanese Sentence Lengths. Journal of the Physical Society of Japan, 81(3), 034004.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1143/JPSJ.81.034004</arg></template></extension><space/>Using computational methods, Japanese sentence corpora were analyzed and a pattern of<space/><link><target>log-normality</target></link><space/>was found in relation to sentence length.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated3"></extension><space/>Though the exact cause of this lognormality remains unknown, it is precisely this sort of intriguing information which computational linguistics is designed to uncover. This information could lead to further important discoveries regarding the underlying structure of Japanese, and could have any number of effects on the understanding of Japanese as a language. Computational linguistics allows for very exciting additions to the scientific knowledge base to happen quickly and with very little room for doubt.</paragraph><paragraph>Without a computational approach to the structure of linguistic data, much of the information that is available now would still be hidden under the vastness of data within any single language. Computational linguistics allows scientists to parse huge amounts of data reliably and efficiently, creating the possibility for discoveries unlike any seen in most other approaches.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Production Approaches</heading><paragraph><template><target>Original research section</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The production of language is equally as complex in the information it provides and the necessary skills which a fluent producer must have. That is to say, comprehension is only half the problem of communication. The other half is how a system produces language, and computational linguistics has made some very interesting discoveries in this area.</paragraph><paragraph>In a now famous paper published in 1950<space/><link><target>Alan Turing</target></link><space/>proposed the possibility that machines might one day have the ability to &quot;think&quot;. As a thought experiment for what might define the concept of thought in machines, he proposed an &quot;imitation test&quot; in which a human subject has two text-only conversations, one with a fellow human and another with a machine attempting to respond like a human. Turing proposes that if the subject cannot tell the difference between the human and the machine, it may be concluded that the machine is capable of thought.<extension extension_name='ref'>Turing, A. M. (1950). Computing machinery and intelligence. Mind, 59(236), 433-460. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/2251299</extension><space/>Today this test is known as the<space/><link><target>Turing test</target></link><space/>and it remains an influential idea in the area of artificial intelligence.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the earliest and best known examples of a computer program designed to converse naturally with humans is the<space/><link><target>ELIZA</target></link><space/>program developed by<space/><link><target>Joseph Weizenbaum</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>MIT</target></link><space/>in 1966. The program emulated a<space/><link><target>Rogerian psychotherapy</target><part>Rogerian</part></link><space/><link><target>psychotherapist</target></link><space/>when responding to written statements and questions posed by a user. It appeared capable of understanding what was said to it and responding intelligently, but in truth it simply followed a pattern matching routine that relied on only understanding a few keywords in each sentence. Its responses were generated by recombining the unknown parts of the sentence around properly translated versions of the known words. For example, in the phrase &quot;It seems that you hate me&quot; ELIZA understands &quot;you&quot; and &quot;me&quot; which matches the general pattern &quot;you [some words] me&quot;, allowing ELIZA to update the words &quot;you&quot; and &quot;me&quot; to &quot;I&quot; and &quot;you&quot; and replying &quot;What makes you think I hate you?&quot;. In this example ELIZA has no understanding of the word &quot;hate&quot;, but it is not required for a logical response in the context of this type of psychotherapy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Weizenbaum, J. (1966). ELIZA---a computer program for the study of natural language communication between man and machine. Communications of the ACM, 9(1), 36-45.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1145/365153.365168</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some projects are still trying to solve the problem which first started computational linguistics off as its own field in the first place. However, the methods have become more refined and clever, and consequently the results generated by computational linguists have become more enlightening. In an effort to improve computer translation, several models have been compared, including<space/><link><target>hidden Markov models</target></link>, smoothing techniques, and the specific refinements of those to apply them to verb translation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Och, F. J., &amp; Ney, H. (2003). A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models. Computational Linguistics, 29(1), 19-51.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1162/089120103321337421</arg></template></extension><space/>The model which was found to produce the most natural translations of<space/><link><target>German language</target><part>German</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>French language</target><part>French</part></link><space/>words was a refined alignment model with a first-order dependence and a fertility model[16]. They also provide efficient training algorithms for the models presented, which can give other scientists the ability to improve further on their results. This type of work is specific to computational linguistics, and has applications which could vastly improve understanding of how language is produced and comprehended by computers.</paragraph><paragraph>Work has also been done in making computers produce language in a more naturalistic manner. Using linguistic input from humans, algorithms have been constructed which are able to modify a systems style of production based on a factor such as linguistic input from a human, or more abstract factors like politeness or any of the five main dimensions of personality.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mairesse, F. (2011). Controlling user perceptions of linguistic style: Trainable generation of personality traits. Computational Linguistics, (January 2009). Retrieved from http://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/COLI_a_00063</extension><space/>This work takes a computational approach via<space/><link><target>parameter estimation</target></link><space/>models to categorize the vast array of linguistic styles we see across individuals and simplify it for a computer to work in the same way[11], making<space/><link><target>human-computer interaction</target></link><space/>much more natural.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Comprehension Approaches</heading><paragraph>Much of the focus of modern computational linguistics is on comprehension. WIth the proliferation of the internet and the abundance of easily accessible written human language, the ability to create a program capable of understanding human language would have many broad and exciting possibilities, including improved search engines, automated customer service, and online education.</paragraph><paragraph>Early work in comprehension included applying Bayesian statistics to the task of optical character recognition, as illustrated by Bledsoe and Browing in 1959 in which a large dictionary of possible letters were generated by &quot;learning&quot; from example letters and then the probability that any one of those learned examples matched the new input was combined to make a final decision.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bledsoe, W. W., &amp; Browning, I. (1959). Pattern recognition and reading by machine. Papers presented at the December 13, 1959, eastern joint IRE-AIEE-ACM computer conference on - IRE-AIEE-ACM 59 (Eastern), 225-232. New York, New York, USA: ACM Press.<space/><template><target>DOI</target><arg>10.1145/1460299.1460326</arg></template></extension><space/>Other attempts at applying Bayesian statistics to language analysis included the work of Mosteller and Wallace (1963) in which an analysis of the words used in<space/><link><target>The Federalist Papers</target><part>''The Federalist'' Papers</part></link><space/>was used to attempt to determine their authorship (concluding that Madison most likely authored the majority of the papers).<extension extension_name='ref'>Mosteller, F. (1963). Inference in an authorship problem. Journal of the American Statistical Association, 58(302), 275-309. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/2283270</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1971<space/><link><target>Terry Winograd</target></link><space/>developed an early<space/><link><target>natural language processing</target></link><space/>engine capable of interpreting naturally written commands within a simple rule governed environment. The primary language parsing program in this project was called<space/><link><target>SHRDLU</target></link>, which was capable of carrying out a somewhat natural conversation with the user giving it commands, but only within the scope of the toy environment designed for the task. This environment consisted of different shaped and colored blocks, and SHRDLU was capable of interpreting commands such as &quot;Find a block which is taller than the one you are holding and put it into the box.&quot; and asking questions such as &quot;I don't understand which pyramid you mean.&quot; in response to the user's input.<extension extension_name='ref'>Winograd, T. (1971). Procedures as a Representation for Data in a Computer Program for Understanding Natural Language. Retrieved from http://www.dtic.mil/docs/citations/AD0721399</extension><space/>While impressive, this kind of<space/><link><target>natural language processing</target></link><space/>has proven much more difficult outside the limited scope of the toy environment. Similarly a project developed by<space/><link><target>NASA</target></link><space/>called<space/><link><target>LUNAR</target></link><space/>was designed to provide answers to naturally written questions about the geological analysis of lunar rocks returned by the Apollo missions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Woods, W., Kaplan, R., &amp; Nash-Webber, B. (1972). The lunar sciences natural language information system. Retrieved from http://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=19850068999</extension><space/>These kinds of problems are referred to as<space/><link><target>question answering</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Initial attempts at understanding spoken language were based on work done in the 1960s and 70s in signal modeling where an unknown signal is analyzed to look for patterns and to make predictions based on its history. An initial and somewhat successful approach to applying this kind of signal modeling to language was achieved with the use of hidden Markov models as detailed by Rabiner in 1989.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rabiner, L. (1989). A tutorial on hidden Markov models and selected applications in speech recognition. Proceedings of the IEEE. Retrieved from http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=18626</extension><space/>This approach attempts to determine probabilities for the arbitrary number of models that could be being used in generating speech as well as modeling the probabilities for various words generated from each of these possible models. Similar approaches were employed in early speech recognition attempts starting in the late 70s at IBM using word/part-of-speech pair probabilities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bahl, L., Baker, J., Cohen, P., &amp; Jelinek, F. (1978). Recognition of continuously read natural corpus. Speech, and Signal, 422-424. Retrieved from http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=1170402</extension></paragraph><paragraph>More recently these kinds of statistical approaches have been applied to more difficult tasks such as topic identification using Bayesian parameter estimation to infer topic probabilities in text documents.<extension extension_name='ref'>Blei, D., &amp; Ng, A. (2003). Latent dirichlet allocation. The Journal of Machine Learning, 3, 993-1022. Retrieved from http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=944937</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Subfields</heading><paragraph>Computational linguistics can be divided into major areas depending upon the medium of the language being processed, whether spoken or textual; and upon the task being performed, whether analyzing language (recognition) or synthesizing language (generation).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Speech recognition</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>speech synthesis</target></link><space/>deal with how spoken language can be understood or created using computers. Parsing and generation are sub-divisions of computational linguistics dealing respectively with taking language apart and putting it together. Machine translation remains the sub-division of computational linguistics dealing with having computers translate between languages. The possibility of automatic language translation, however, has yet to be realized and remains a notorious branch of computational linguistics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Oettinger, A. G. (1965). Computational Linguistics. The American Mathematical Monthly, Vol. 72, No. 2, Part 2: Computers andComputing, pp. 147-150. Retrieved from http://www.jstor.org/stable/2313322</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some of the areas of research that are studied by computational linguistics include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Analysis of algorithms</target><part>Computational complexity</part></link><space/>of natural language, largely modeled on<space/><link><target>automata theory</target></link>, with the application of<space/><link><target>context-sensitive grammar</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Linear bounded automaton</target><part>linearly bounded</part></link><space/><link><target>Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Computational semantics</target></link><space/>comprises defining suitable logics for<space/><link><target>linguistic meaning</target></link><space/>representation, automatically constructing them and reasoning with them</listitem><listitem>Computer-aided<space/><link><target>corpus linguistics</target></link>, which has been used since the 1970s as a way to make detailed advances in the field of discourse analysis<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McEnery</arg><arg name="first">Thomas</arg><arg name="title">Corpus Linguistics: An Introduction</arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="publisher">Edinburgh University Press</arg><arg name="location">Edinburgh</arg><arg name="isbn">0748611657</arg><arg name="page">114</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.ca/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>Design of<space/><link><target>parser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>phrase chunking</target><part>chunkers</part></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>natural language</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem>Design of taggers like<space/><link><target>Part-of-speech tagging</target><part>POS-taggers (part-of-speech taggers)</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Machine translation</target></link><space/>as one of the earliest and most difficult applications of computational linguistics draws on many subfields.</listitem><listitem>Simulation and study of language evolution in<space/><link><target>historical linguistics</target></link>/<link><target>glottochronology</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Association for Computational Linguistics</target></link><space/>defines computational linguistics as:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>...the scientific study of<space/><link><target>language</target></link><space/>from a computational perspective. Computational linguists are interested in providing<space/><link><target>computational model</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of various kinds of linguistic phenomena.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Association for Computational Linguistics<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aclweb.org/archive/misc/what.html'>What is Computational Linguistics?</link>Published online, Feb, 2005.</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>AI</arg><arg>Mind and Brain</arg></template><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-1-of-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Association for Computational Linguistics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Collostructional analysis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computational lexicology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computational Linguistics (journal)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computational science</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computational semiotics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computer-assisted reviewing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dialog systems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Grammar induction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human speechome project</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-2-of-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Internet linguistics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>National Centre for Text Mining</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Natural language processing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>North American Computational Linguistics Olympiad</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quantitative linguistics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Semantic relatedness</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Systemic functional linguistics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Translation memory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ubiquitous Knowledge Processing Lab</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Universal Networking Language</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>WVD</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aclweb.org/'>Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)</link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aclweb.org/anthology'>ACL Anthology of research papers</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://aclweb.org/aclwiki/'>ACL Wiki for Computational Linguistics</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.CICLing.org/'>CICLing annual conferences on Computational Linguistics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://CLA.imcsit.org'>Computational Linguistics&amp;nbsp; Applications workshop</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20080125103030<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.gelbukh.com/clbook/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Free online introductory book on Computational Linguistics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lt-world.org/'>Language Technology World</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cs.technion.ac.il/~gabr/resources/resources.html'>Resources for Text, Speech and Language Processing</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/'>The Research Group in Computational Linguistics</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Computer science</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Computational Linguistics</target></template><link><target>Category:Computational linguistics</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Applied linguistics</target></link><link><target>Category:Linguistics</target></link><link><target>Category:Formal sciences</target></link><link><target>Category:Cognitive science</target></link></paragraph></article>