<article title='Drum'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><link><target>File:TalkingDrum.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Talking drum</target></link>.</part></link>The<space/><bold>drum</bold><space/>is a member of the<space/><link><target>percussion instrument</target><part>percussion</part></link><space/>group of musical instruments. In the<space/><link><target>Hornbostel-Sachs</target></link><space/>classification system, it is a<space/><link><target>membranophones</target><part>membranophone</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">[[Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians|The New Grove Encyclopædia of Music and Musicians]]</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="first">George</arg><arg name="last">Grove</arg><arg name="authorlink">George Grove</arg><arg name="editor">[[Stanley Sadie]]</arg><arg name="date">January 2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Grove's Dictionaries of Music</arg><arg name="pages">Volume 5, pp638–649</arg><arg name="isbn">1-56159-239-0</arg></template></extension><space/>Drums consist of at least one<space/><link><target>Acoustic membrane</target><part>membrane</part></link>, called a<space/><link><target>drumhead</target></link><space/>or drum skin, that is stretched over a shell and struck, either directly with the player's hands, or with a<space/><link><target>drum stick</target></link>, to produce<space/><link><target>sound</target></link>. There is usually a<space/><italics>resonance head</italics><space/>on the underside of the drum, typically tuned to a slightly lower pitch than the top drumhead. Other techniques have been used to cause drums to make sound, such as the<space/><link><target>thumb roll</target></link>. Drums are the world's oldest and most ubiquitous musical instruments, and the basic design has remained virtually unchanged for thousands of years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">[[Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians|The New Grove Encyclopædia of Music and Musicians]]</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="first">George</arg><arg name="last">Grove</arg><arg name="authorlink">George Grove</arg><arg name="editor">[[Stanley Sadie]]</arg><arg name="date">January 2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Grove's Dictionaries of Music</arg><arg name="pages">Volume 4, pp638–649</arg><arg name="isbn">1-56159-239-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Drums may be played individually, with the player using a single drum, and some drums such as the<space/><link><target>djembe</target></link><space/>are almost always played in this way. Others are normally played in a set of two or more, all played by the one player, such as<space/><link><target>bongo drums</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>timpani</target></link>. A number of different drums together with<space/><link><target>cymbal</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>form the basic modern<space/><link><target>drum kit</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Uses</heading><paragraph>Drums are usually played by striking with the hand, or with one or two sticks. In many traditional cultures, drums have a symbolic function and are used in religious ceremonies. Drums are often used in<space/><link><target>music therapy</target></link>, especially hand drums, because of their tactile nature and easy use by a wide variety of people.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last">Weiss
<space/></arg><arg name="first">Rick
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Music Therapy
<space/></arg><arg name="periodical"><space/>The Washington Post
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>Jul 5,1994
<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/72257976.html?dids</arg><arg name="date">July 5, 1994
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>popular music</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>jazz</target></link>, &quot;drums&quot; usually refers to a<space/><link><target>drum kit</target></link><space/>or a set of drums (with some<space/><link><target>cymbals</target></link>), and &quot;<link><target>drummer</target></link>&quot; to the person who plays them.</paragraph><paragraph>Drums acquired even divine status in places such as<space/><link><target>Burundi</target></link>, where the<space/><italics><link><target>karyenda</target></link></italics><space/>was a symbol of the power of the king.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Construction</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:DrumMozartRegiment.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Drum carried by John Unger, Company B, 40th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Infantry Mozart Regiment, December 20, 1863</part></link>The shell almost invariably has a circular opening over which the drumhead is stretched, but the shape of the remainder of the shell varies widely. In the western musical tradition, the most usual shape is a<space/><link><target>cylinder (geometry)</target><part>cylinder</part></link>, although<space/><link><target>timpani</target></link>, for example, use<space/><link><target>bowl (vessel)</target><part>bowl</part></link>-shaped shells.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"></extension><space/>Other shapes include a frame design (<link><target>tar (drum)</target><part>tar</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bodhrn</target></link>), truncated cones (<link><target>bongo drum</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Ashiko</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Goblet drum</target><part>goblet shaped</part></link><space/>(<link><target>djembe</target></link>), and joined truncated cones (<link><target>talking drum</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>Drums with cylindrical shells can be open at one end (as is the case with<space/><link><target>timbales</target></link>), or can have two drum heads. Single-headed drums typically consist of a skin stretched over an enclosed space, or over one of the ends of a hollow vessel. Drums with two heads covering both ends of a cylindrical shell often have a small hole somewhat halfway between the two heads; the shell forms a<space/><link><target>resonance</target><part>resonating</part></link><space/>chamber for the resulting sound. Exceptions include the African<space/><link><target>slit drum</target></link>, also known as a log drum as it is made from a hollowed-out tree trunk, and the<space/><link><target>steel drum</target><part>Caribbean steel drum</part></link>, made from a metal barrel. Drums with two heads can also have a set of wires, called snares, held across the bottom head, top head, or both heads, hence the name<space/><link><target>snare drum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On modern<space/><link><target>band (music)</target><part>band</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>orchestral</target></link><space/>drums, the drumhead is placed over the opening of the drum, which in turn is held onto the shell by a &quot;counterhoop&quot; (or &quot;rim&quot;), which is then held by means of a number of tuning screws called &quot;tension rods&quot; that screw into lugs placed evenly around the circumference. The head's tension can be adjusted by loosening or tightening the rods. Many such drums have six to ten tension rods. The sound of a drum depends on many variablesincluding shape, shell size and thickness, shell materials, counterhoop material, drumhead material, drumhead tension, drum position, location, and striking velocity and angle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the invention of tension rods, drum skins were attached and tuned by rope systemsas on the<space/><link><target>Djembe</target></link>or pegs and ropes such as on<space/><link><target>Ewe music</target><part>Ewe Drums</part></link>. These methods are rarely used today, though sometimes appear on regimental marching band snare drums.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"></extension><space/>The head of a talking drum, for example, can be temporarily tightened by squeezing the ropes that connect the top and bottom heads. Similarly, the tabla is tuned by hammering a disc held in place around the drum by ropes stretching from the top to bottom head. Orchestral timpani can be quickly tuned to precise pitches by using a foot pedal.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Sound of a drum</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Drums for sale at the National Museum of the American Indian.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Several<space/><link><target>Amerindians</target><part>American Indian</part></link>-style drums for sale at the<space/><link><target>National Museum of the American Indian</target></link>.</part></link>Several factors determine the sound a drum produces, including the type, shape and construction of the drum shell, the type of<space/><link><target>drum head</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>it has, and the tension of these drumheads. Different drum sounds have different uses in music. Take, for example, the modern<space/><link><target>Tom-tom drum</target></link>. A<space/><link><target>jazz</target></link><space/>drummer may want drums that are high pitched, resonant and quiet whereas a<space/><link><target>Rock music</target><part>rock</part></link><space/>drummer may prefer drums that are loud, dry and low-pitched. Since these drummers want different sounds, their drums are constructed a little differently.</paragraph><paragraph>The drum head has the most effect on how a drum sounds. Each type of drum head serves its own musical purpose and has its own unique sound. Double-ply drumheads dampen high frequency harmonics because they are heavier and they are suited to heavy playing.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.drumbook.org'>Drum Lessons</link><space/>- Drumbook.org</extension><space/>Drum heads with a white, textured coating on them muffle the<space/><link><target>overtone</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the drum head slightly, producing a less diverse<space/><link><target>Pitch (music)</target><part>pitch</part></link>. Drum heads with central silver or black dots tend to muffle the overtones even more. And drum heads with<space/><link><target>perimeter</target></link><space/>sound rings mostly eliminate overtones (Howie 2005). Some jazz drummers avoid using thick drum heads, preferring single ply drum heads or drum heads with no muffling. Rock drummers often prefer the thicker or coated drum heads.</paragraph><paragraph>The second biggest factor that affects drum sound is head tension against the shell. When the hoop is placed around the drum head and shell and tightened down with tension rods, the tension of the head can be adjusted. When the tension is increased, the<space/><link><target>amplitude</target></link><space/>of the sound is reduced and the<space/><link><target>frequency</target></link><space/>is increased, making the pitch higher and the volume lower.</paragraph><paragraph>The type of shell also affects the sound of a drum. Because the vibrations<space/><link><target>Resonance</target><part>resonate</part></link><space/>in the shell of the drum, the shell can be used to increase the volume and to manipulate the type of sound produced. The larger the diameter of the shell, the lower the pitch. The larger the depth of the drum, the louder the volume. Shell thickness also determines the volume of drums. Thicker shells produce louder drums.<space/><link><target>Mahogany</target></link><space/>raises the frequency of low pitches and keeps higher frequencies at about the same speed. When choosing a set of shells, a jazz drummer may want smaller maple shells, while a rock drummer may want larger birch shells. For more information about<space/><link><target>Musical tuning</target><part>tuning</part></link><space/>drums or the physics of a drum, visit the external links listed below.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:MocheDrum.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Moche (culture)</target><part>Moche</part></link><space/>ceramic vessel depicting a drummer.<space/><link><target>Larco Museum</target></link><space/>Collection. Lima-Peru</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The drum is the oldest known instrument in the world dating back to 4000 BC in<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>(Sowande, 1969)</extension><space/><link><target>Alligator drum</target><part>Drums made with alligator skins</part></link><space/>have been found in<space/><link><target>Neolithic China</target><part>Neolithic cultures</part></link><space/>located in China, dating to a period of 55002350 BC. In literary records, drums manifested shamanistic characteristics and were often used in ritual ceremonies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Liu, Li (2007).<space/><italics>The Chinese Neolithic: Trajectories to Early States</italics>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-01064-0, p. 123</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bronze<space/><link><target>Dong Son drums</target></link><space/>are were fabricated by the<space/><link><target>Bronze Age</target></link><space/><link><target>Dong Son culture</target></link><space/>of northern<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>. They include the ornate<space/><link><target>Ngoc Lu drum</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Animal drumming</heading><paragraph><link><target>Macaque monkey</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>drum objects in a rhythmic way to show<space/><link><target>Social Dominance Theory</target><part>social dominance</part></link><space/>and this has been shown to be processed in a similar way in their brains to vocalizations suggesting an evolutionary origin to drumming as part of social communication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Remedios<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>R<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Logothetis<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>NK<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Kayser<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>C<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Monkey drumming reveals common networks for perceiving vocal and nonvocal communication sounds<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>106<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>42<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>18010–5<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>19805199<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>2755465<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1073/pnas.0909756106<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Other<space/><link><target>primate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>make drumming sounds by chest beating or hand clapping,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Clark Arcadi<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>A<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Robert<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>D<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Mugurusi<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>F<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A comparison of buttress drumming by male chimpanzees from two populations<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Primates; journal of primatology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>45<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>135–9<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>14735390<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/s10329-003-0070-8<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/s10329-009-0130-9<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Kalan<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>AK<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Rainey<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>HJ.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Hand-clapping as a communicative gesture by wild female swamp gorillas<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Primates<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>50<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>273–5<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>19221858<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>rodent</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>kangaroo rat</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>also make similar sounds using their paws on the ground.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Randall<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>JA.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Evolution and Function of Drumming as Communication in Mammals<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://intl-icb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/41/5/1143<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>American Zoologist<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>41<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1143–1156<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1668/0003-1569(2001)041[1143:EAFODA]2.0.CO;2<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Talking drums</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Talking drum</arg></template>Drums are used not only for their musical qualities, but also as a means of<space/><link><target>drum (communication)</target><part>communication</part></link><space/>over great distances. The talking drums of Africa are used to imitate the tone patterns of spoken language. Throughout<space/><link><target>History of Sri Lanka</target><part>Sri Lankan history</part></link><space/>drums have been used for communication between the state and the community, and Sri Lankan drums have a history stretching back over 2500 years.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Drums in art</heading><paragraph>Drumming may be a purposeful expression of emotion for entertainment, spiritualism and communication. Many cultures practice drumming as a spiritual or religious passage and interpret drummed rhythm similarly to spoken language or prayer. Drumming has developed over millennia to be a powerful art form. Drumming is commonly viewed as the root of music and is sometimes performed as a kinesthetic dance. As a discipline, drumming concentrates on training the body to punctuate, convey and interpret musical rhythmic intention to an audience and to the performer.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Military uses</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Military drums</arg></template>Chinese troops used<space/><link><target>tig</target></link><space/>drums to motivate troops, to help set a marching pace, and to call out orders or announcements. For example, during a war between Qi and Lu in 684 BC, the effect of drum on soldier's morale is employed to change the result of a major battle. Fife-and-drum corps of<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target><part>Swiss</part></link><space/>mercenary foot soldiers also used drums. They used an early version of the<space/><link><target>snare drum</target></link><space/>carried over the player's right shoulder, suspended by a strap (typically played with one hand using<space/><link><target>traditional grip</target></link>). It is to this instrument that the English word &quot;drum&quot; was first used. Similarly, during the<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link><space/>rope-tension drums would be carried by junior officers as a means to relay commands from senior officers over the noise of battle. These were also hung over the shoulder of the drummer and typically played with two drum sticks. Different<space/><link><target>regiment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and companies would have distinctive and unique drum beats only they recognized. In the mid-19th century, the Scottish military started incorporating<space/><link><target>pipe band</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>into their Highland Regiments.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chatto, Allan. (1996).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cadre-online.ca/drumhistory.html'>Brief History of Drumming.</link></extension><template><target>listen</target><arg name="filename">Drum - Cadence A.ogg
</arg><arg name="title">Drum - Cadence A
</arg><arg name="filename2">Drum - Cadence B.ogg
</arg><arg name="title2">Drum - Cadence B
</arg><arg name="filename3">Drums - Four Flams.ogg
</arg><arg name="title3">Drum - Four Flams
</arg><arg name="description3">[[Snare drum]] [[drum cadence|cadences]] performed by the [[United States Navy Band]]
</arg></template>During pre-Columbian warfare, Aztec nations were known to have used drums to send signals to the battling warriors. The Nahuatl word for drum is roughly translated as huehuetl.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aguilar-Moreno, Manuel. (2006). [Handbook to Life In the Aztec World]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Rig Veda</target></link>, one of the oldest religious scriptures in the world, contain several references to the use of Dundhubi (war drum). Arya tribes charged into battle to the beating of the war drum and chanting of a hymn that appears in Book VI of the Rig Veda and also the Atharva Veda where it is referred to as the &quot;Hymn to the battle drum&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Types of drum</heading><paragraph><template><target>Col-begin</target></template><template><target>Col-1-of-4</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aburukuwa</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ashiko</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bass drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bat drum</target><part>Bat</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bedug</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bodhrn</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bongo drum</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bougarabou</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cajn</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Candombe drums</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Goblet drum</target><part>Chalice drum</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chenda</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cocktail drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conga</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Crowdy-crawn</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-2-of-4</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Goblet drum</target><part>Darbuka</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Damphu drum</target><part>Damphu</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Davul</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dayereh</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dhak (instrument)</target><part>Dhak</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dhimay</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dhol</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dholak</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Djembe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dong Son drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Doumbek</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dunun</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ewe music</target><part>Ewe Drums</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Frame drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Goblet drum</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-3-of-4</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Hand drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ilimba drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Karyenda</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kpanlogo (drum)</target><part>Kpanlogo</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lambeg drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Log drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Madal</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mridangam</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Repinique</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Snare drum</target><part>Side drum</part></link><space/>(Marching snare drum)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Slit drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Snare drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Steelpan</target></link><space/>(Steel drum)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Surdo</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-4-of-5</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Tabor (instrument)</target><part>Tabor</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tamborim</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tambourine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taiko</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tabla</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Talking drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Davul</target><part>Tapan</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tar (drum)</target><part>Tar</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tavil</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tenor drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timbales</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timpani</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tombak</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tom-tom drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tongue drum</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-5-of-5</target></template><link><target>Image:Gu Hongzhong's Night Revels, Detail 6.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Handscroll detail of a<space/><link><target>China</target><part>Chinese</part></link><space/>percussionist playing a drum for a dancing woman, from a 12th-century remake of<space/><link><target>Gu Hongzhong</target></link>'s 10th-century originals,<space/><link><target>Song dynasty</target></link>.</part></link><template><target>Col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Col-begin</target></template><template><target>Col-1-of-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Blast beat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Double drumming</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drum beat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drum circle</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drum kit</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drumline</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drum machine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drummer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drum replacement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Percussion mallet</target><part>Drumsticks</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-2-of-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Drum tracks</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electronic drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gallop (drumming)</target><part>Gallop</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hearing the shape of a drum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of drummers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Musical instrument</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Practice pad</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vibrations of a circular drum</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-3-of-3</target></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Drums</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target></template><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Music</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nosii.com'>folk workshop for drums and another folk-instruments</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Spoken Wikipedia</target><arg>Drum.ogg</arg><arg>2005-04-13</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Arts/Music/Instruments/Percussion/Drums</arg><arg>Drum resources</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Percussion</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Drums</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Membranophones</target></link></paragraph></article>