<article title='European_Convention_on_Human_Rights'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>ECHR</arg><arg>the Court which enforces the Convention</arg><arg>European Court of Human Rights</arg></template><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>European Convention (1999-2000)</arg><arg>Convention on the Future of Europe</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox Treaty</target><arg name="name"><space/>European Convention on Human Rights
</arg><arg name="long_name"><space/>The Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms
</arg><arg name="image">Council of Europe (orthographic projection).svg
</arg><arg name="image_width"><space/>220px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Parties to the convention
</arg><arg name="date_signed"><space/>4 November 1950 
</arg><arg name="location_signed"><space/>Rome
</arg><arg name="date_effective"><space/>3 September 1953
</arg><arg name="parties">47 (all [[Council of Europe]] [[Member states of the Council of Europe|member states]])
</arg><arg name="depositor"><space/>Secretary General of the Council of Europe
</arg><arg name="languages"><space/>[[English language|English]] and [[French language|French]]
</arg><arg name="wikisource"><space/>European Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>European Convention on Human Rights</bold><space/>(<bold>ECHR</bold>) (formally the<space/><italics>Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms</italics>) is an international treaty to protect<space/><link><target>human rights</target></link><space/>and fundamental<space/><link><target>political freedom</target><part>freedoms</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>. Drafted in 1950 by the then newly formed<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Council of Europe">The<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link><space/>should not be confused with the<space/><link><target>Council of the European Union</target></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>European Council</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>is not a party to the Convention and has no role in the administration of the<space/><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link>.</extension><space/>the convention entered into force on 3 September 1953. All<space/><link><target>Member states of the Council of Europe</target><part>Council of Europe member states</part></link><space/>are party to the Convention and new members are expected to ratify the convention at the earliest opportunity.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://assembly.coe.int/Documents/AdoptedText/TA94/ERES1031.HTM'>Resolution 1031 (1994) on the honouring of commitments entered into by member states when joining the Council of Europe</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Convention established the<space/><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link><space/>(ECtHR). Any person who feels his or her rights have been violated under the Convention by a state party can take a case to the Court. Judgments finding violations are binding on the States concerned and they are obliged to execute them. The<space/><link><target>Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe</target></link><space/>monitors the execution of judgements, particularly to ensure payment of the amounts awarded by the Court to the applicants in compensation for the damage they have sustained. The establishment of a Court to protect individuals from human rights violations is an innovative feature for an international convention on human rights, as it gives the individual an active role on the international arena (traditionally, only states are considered actors in<space/><link><target>international law</target></link>). The European Convention is still the only international human rights agreement providing such a high degree of individual protection.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>State parties can also take cases against other state parties to the Court, although this power is rarely used.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/></paragraph><paragraph>The Convention has several<space/><link><target>protocol (treaty)</target><part>protocol</part><trail>s</trail></link>, which amend the convention framework.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Stamp 2010 HR Convention-60 (1).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Ukrainian stamp, commemorating 60 years of European Convention on Human Rights</part></link><space/><template><target>see also</target><arg>European Court of Human Rights</arg></template>The European Convention on Human Rights has played an important role in the development and awareness of Human Rights in Europe.The development of a regional system of human rights protection operating across Europe can be seen as a direct response to twin concerns. First, in the aftermath of the<space/><link><target>World War II</target><part>Second World War</part></link>, the convention, drawing on the inspiration of the<space/><link><target>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</target></link><space/>can be seen as part of a wider response of the Allied Powers in delivering a human rights agenda through which it was believed that the most serious human rights violations which had occurred during the Second World War could be avoided in the future. Second, the Convention was a response to the growth of Communism in Central and Eastern Europe and designed to protect the member states of the<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link><space/>from communist subversion. This, in part, explains the constant references to values and principles that are &quot;necessary in a democratic society&quot; throughout the Convention, despite the fact that such principles are not in any way defined within the convention itself.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ovey</arg><arg name="first">Clare</arg><arg name="title">The European Convention on Human Rights</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-01-992881-0-6</arg><arg name="pages">1–3</arg><arg name="author2">Robin C.A. White</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Convention was drafted by the<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>World War II</target><part>Second World War</part></link><space/>in response to a call issued by Europeans from all walks of life who had gathered at the<space/><link><target>Hague Congress (1948)</target><part>Hague Congress</part></link>. Over 100 parliamentarians from the twelve member states of the Council of Europe gathered in Strasbourg in the summer of 1949 for the first ever meeting of the Council's Consultative Assembly to draft a &quot;charter of human rights&quot; and to establish a court to enforce it. British MP and lawyer Sir<space/><link><target>David Maxwell-Fyfe</target></link>, the Chair of the Assembly's Committee on Legal and Administrative Questions, was one of its leading members and guided the drafting of the Convention. As a prosecutor at the<space/><link><target>Nuremberg Trials</target></link>, he had seen first-hand how international justice could be effectively applied. With his help, the French former minister and Resistance fighter<space/><link><target>Pierre-Henri Teitgen</target></link><space/>submitted a report<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://assembly.coe.int/Conferences/2009Anniversaire49/DocRef/Teitgen6.pdf'>Report by Pierre-Henri Teitgen of France, submitted to the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe</link></extension><space/>to the Assembly proposing a list of rights to be protected, selecting a number from the<space/><link><target>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</target></link><space/>just agreed to in New York, and defining how the enforcing judicial mechanism might operate. After extensive debates,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://assembly.coe.int/Conferences/2009Anniversaire49/DocRef/Teitgen7E.pdf'>Verbatim of the speech given by Pierre-Henri Teitgen when he presented his report to the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe</link></extension><space/>the Assembly sent its final proposal<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://assembly.coe.int/Conferences/2009Anniversaire49/DocRef/Rec38_9.pdf'>Recommendation 38 of the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe on 'Human rights and fundamental freedoms'</link></extension><space/>to the Council's Committee of Ministers, which convened a group of experts to draft the Convention itself.</paragraph><paragraph>The Convention was designed to incorporate a traditional<space/><link><target>civil liberties</target></link><space/>approach to securing &quot;effective political democracy&quot;, from the strongest traditions in the United Kingdom, France and other member states of the fledgling<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link>. The Convention was opened for signature on 4 November 1950 in Rome. It was ratified and entered into force on 3 September 1953. It is overseen and enforced by the<space/><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link><space/>in Strasbourg, and the<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link>. Until procedural reforms in the late 1990s, the Convention was also overseen by a European Commission on Human Rights.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Drafting</heading><paragraph>The Convention is drafted in broad terms, in a similar (albeit more modern) manner to the<space/><link><target>English Bill of Rights</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>U.S. Bill of Rights</target></link>, the French<space/><link><target>Declaration of the Rights of Man</target></link><space/>or the first part of the German<space/><link><target>Grundgesetz</target><part>Basic law</part></link>. Statements of principle are, from a legal point of view, not determinative and require extensive interpretation by courts to bring out meaning in particular factual situations.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Convention articles</heading><paragraph>As amended by Protocol 11, the Convention consists of three parts. The main rights and freedoms are contained in Section I, which consists of Articles 2 to 18. Section II (Articles 19 to 51) sets up the Court and its rules of operation. Section III contains various concluding provisions.</paragraph><paragraph>Before the entry into force of Protocol 11, Section II (Article 19) set up the Commission and the Court, Sections III (Articles 20 to 37) and IV (Articles 38 to 59) included the high-level machinery for the operation of, respectively, the Commission and the Court, and Section V contained various concluding provisions.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of the Articles in Section I are structured in two paragraphs: the first sets out a basic right or freedom (such as Article 2(1) the right to life) but the second contains various exclusions, exceptions or limitations on the basic right (such as Article 2(2) which excepts certain uses of force leading to death).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 1 - respecting rights</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 1 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Article 1 simply binds the signatory parties to secure the rights under the other Articles of the Convention &quot;within their jurisdiction&quot;. In exceptional cases, &quot;jurisdiction&quot; may not be confined to a Contracting State's own national territory; the obligation to secure Convention rights then also extends to foreign territory, such as occupied land in which the State exercises effective control.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Loizidou v Turkey</target></link></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'>(Preliminary Objections) (1995) 20 EHRR 99</extension><space/>the<space/><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link><space/>ruled that jurisdiction of member states to the convention extended to areas under that state's effective control as a result of military action.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 2 - life</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 2 protects the right of every person to his or her life. The right to life extends only to human beings, not to non-human animals,<extension extension_name='ref' name="korff">Korff, Douwe,<space/><italics>The Right to Life: A Guide to the Implementation of Article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights (Council of Europe - Human Rights Handbook No. 8, November 2006 )</italics>, p. 10</extension><space/>or to &quot;legal persons&quot; such as corporations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="korff"></extension><space/>In<space/><italics><link><target>Evans v United Kingdom</target></link></italics>, the Court ruled that the right to life does not extend to a human embryo. In<space/><italics>Vo v France</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://echr.ketse.com/doc/53924.00-en-20040708/view/'>Vo V. France</link>. Echr.ketse.com. Retrieved on 2013-07-12.</extension><space/>the Court declined to extend the right to life to an unborn child, while stating that &quot;it is neither desirable, nor even possible as matters stand, to answer in the abstract the question whether the unborn child is a person for the purposes of Article 2 of the Convention&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Vo v. France</italics>, section 85 of the judgment</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Article 2 - The right for life - The right to preserve life, - Take life to Preserve life.</paragraph><paragraph>The Court has ruled that states have three main duties under Article 2:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>a duty to refrain from unlawful killing,</listitem><listitem>a duty to investigate suspicious deaths and,</listitem><listitem>in certain circumstances, a positive duty to prevent foreseeable loss of life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jacobs &amp; White, p. 56</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The first paragraph of the article contains an exception for<space/><link><target>Capital punishment</target><part>lawful execution</part><trail>s</trail></link>, although this exception has largely been superseded by Protocols 6 and 13. Protocol 6 prohibits the imposition of the death penalty in peacetime, while Protocol 13 extends the prohibition to all circumstances. (For more on Protocols 6 and 13, see<space/><link><target>#Protocol 13 - complete abolition of death penalty</target><part>below</part></link>.)</paragraph><paragraph>The second paragraph of Article 2 provides that death resulting from defending oneself or others, arresting a suspect or fugitive, or suppressing riots or insurrections, will not contravene the Article when the use of force involved is &quot;no more than absolutely necessary&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Signatory states to the Convention can only derogate from the rights contained in Article 2 for deaths which result from lawful acts of war.</paragraph><paragraph>The European Court of Human Rights did not rule upon the right to life until 1995, when in<space/><italics><link><target>McCann v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'>(1995) 21 EHRR 97</extension><space/>it ruled that the exception contained in the second paragraph does not constitute situations when it is permitted to kill, but situations where it is permitted to use force which might result in the deprivation of life.<extension extension_name='ref'>(1995) 21 EHRR 97 at para. 148</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 3 - torture</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 3 prohibits<space/><link><target>torture</target></link>, and &quot;inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment&quot;. There are no exceptions or limitations on this right. This provision usually applies, apart from torture, to cases of severe police violence and poor conditions in detention.</paragraph><paragraph>The Court have emphasised the fundamental nature of Article 3 in holding that the prohibition is made in &quot;absolute terms ... irrespective of a victim's conduct&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Chahal v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1997) 23 EHRR 413.</extension><space/>The Court has also held that states cannot deport or<space/><link><target>extradition</target><part>extradite</part></link><space/>individuals who might be subjected to torture, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment, in the recipient state.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Chahal v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1997) 23 EHRR 413;<space/><italics><link><target>Soering v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1989) 11 EHRR 439.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Initially the Court took a restrictive view on what consisted of torture, preferring to find that states had inflicted inhuman and degrading treatment. Thus the court held that practices such as sleep deprivation, subjecting individual to intense noise and requiring them to stand against a wall with their limbs outstretched for extended periods of time, did not constitute torture.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Ireland v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1979-80) 2 EHRR 25 at para 167.</extension><space/>In fact the Court only found a state guilty of torture in 1996 in the case of a detainee who was suspended by his arms while his hands were tied behind his back.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Aksoy v. Turkey</italics><space/>(1997) 23 EHRR 553. The process was referred to by the Court as &quot;Palestinian hanging&quot; but more commonly known as<space/><link><target>Strappado</target></link>.</extension><space/>Since then the Court has appeared to be more open to finding states guilty of torture and has even ruled that since the Convention is a &quot;living instrument&quot;, treatment which it had previously characterised as inhuman or degrading treatment might in future be regarded as torture.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Selmouni v. France</italics><space/>(2000) 29 EHRR 403 at para. 101.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 4 - servitude</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 4 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 4 prohibits<space/><link><target>slavery</target></link>, servitude and<space/><link><target>forced labour</target></link><space/>but exempts labour:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>done as a normal part of imprisonment,</listitem><listitem>in the form of<space/><link><target>conscription</target><part>compulsory military service</part></link><space/>or work done as an alternative by conscientious objectors,</listitem><listitem>required to be done during a<space/><link><target>state of emergency</target></link>, and</listitem><listitem>considered to be a part of a person's normal &quot;civic obligations&quot;.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 5 - liberty and security</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 5 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 5 provides that everyone has the right to liberty and security of person. Liberty and security of the person are taken as a &quot;compound&quot; concept - security of the person has not been subject to separate interpretation by the Court.</paragraph><paragraph>Article 5 provides the right to<space/><link><target>liberty</target></link>, subject only to lawful arrest or detention under certain other circumstances, such as arrest on reasonable suspicion of a crime or imprisonment in fulfilment of a sentence. The article also provides those arrested with the right to be informed, in a language they understand, of the reasons for the arrest and any charge they face, the right of prompt access to judicial proceedings to determine the legality of the arrest or detention, to trial within a reasonable time or release pending trial, and the right to compensation in the case of arrest or detention in violation of this article.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 6 - fair trial</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 6 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 6 provides a detailed<space/><link><target>right to a fair trial</target></link>, including the right to a<space/><link><target>hearing (law)</target><part>public hearing</part></link><space/>before an independent and impartial tribunal within reasonable time, the<space/><link><target>presumption of innocence</target></link>, and other minimum rights for those charged with a criminal offence (adequate time and facilities to prepare their defence, access to legal representation, right to examine witnesses against them or have them examined, right to the free assistance of an interpreter).</paragraph><paragraph>The majority of Convention violations that the Court finds today are excessive delays, in violation of the &quot;reasonable time&quot; requirement, in civil and criminal proceedings before national courts, mostly in<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>France</target></link>. Under the &quot;independent tribunal&quot; requirement, the Court has ruled that military judges in Turkish state security courts are incompatible with Article 6. In compliance with this Article, Turkey has now adopted a law abolishing these courts.</paragraph><paragraph>Another significant set of violations concerns the &quot;confrontation clause&quot; of Article 6 (i.e. the right to examine witnesses or have them examined). In this respect, problems of compliance with Article 6 may arise when national laws allow the use in evidence of the testimonies of absent, anonymous and vulnerable witnesses.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>McLibel Case</target><part>Steel v. United Kingdom</part></link></italics><space/>(1998) 28 EHRR 603</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Othman (Abu Qatada) v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(2012) -<space/><link><target>Abu Qatada</target></link><space/>could not be deported to Jordan as that would be a violation of Article 6 &quot;given the real risk of the admission of evidence obtained by torture&quot;. This was the first time the court ruled that such an expulsion would be a violation of Article 6.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tele 17.01.2012"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/terrorism-in-the-uk/9019823/Abu-Qatada-cannot-be-deported-to-Jordan-European-judges-rule.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Abu Qatada cannot be deported to Jordan, European judges rule<space/></arg><arg name="author">Duncan Gardham<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">The Daily Telegraph<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 February 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 7 - retroactivity</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 7 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 7 prohibits the retroactive criminalisation of acts and omissions. No person may be punished for an act that was not a criminal offence at the time of its commission. The article states that a criminal offence is one under either national or international law, which would permit a party to prosecute someone for a crime which was not illegal under domestic law at the time, so long as it was prohibited by<space/><link><target>public international law</target><part>international law</part></link>. The Article also prohibits a heavier penalty being imposed than was applicable at the time when the criminal act was committed.</paragraph><paragraph>Article 7 incorporates the legal principle<space/><italics><link><target>nullum crimen, nulla poena sine lege</target></link></italics><space/>into the convention.</paragraph><paragraph>Relevant cases are:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Kokkinakis v. Greece</target></link></italics><space/>[1993] ECHR 20<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>S.A.S. v. France</target></link></italics><space/>[2014] ECHR 695</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 8 - privacy</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 8 provides a right to respect for one's &quot;private and family life, his home and his<space/><link><target>privacy of correspondence</target><part>correspondence</part></link>&quot;, subject to certain restrictions that are &quot;in accordance with law&quot; and &quot;necessary in a democratic society&quot;. This article clearly provides a right to be free of unlawful searches, but the Court has given the protection for &quot;private and family life&quot; that this article provides a broad interpretation, taking for instance that prohibition of private consensual homosexual acts violates this article. This may be compared to the jurisprudence of the United States Supreme Court, which has also adopted a somewhat broad interpretation of the right to privacy. Furthermore, Article 8 sometimes comprises<space/><link><target>positive obligations</target></link>:<extension extension_name='ref'>Von Hannover v Germany [2004] ECHR 294 (24 June 2004), European Court of Human Rights, para 57</extension><space/>whereas classical human rights are formulated as prohibiting a State from interfering with rights, and thus<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>to do something (e.g. not to separate a family under family life protection), the effective enjoyment of such rights may also include an obligation for the State to become active, and to<space/><italics>do</italics><space/>something (e.g. to enforce access for a divorced parent to his/her child).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 9 - conscience and religion</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 9 provides a right to<space/><link><target>freedom of thought</target></link>, conscience and<space/><link><target>freedom of religion</target><part>religion</part></link>. This includes the freedom to change a religion or belief, and to manifest a religion or belief in worship, teaching, practice and observance, subject to certain restrictions that are &quot;in accordance with law&quot; and &quot;necessary in a democratic society&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Relevant cases are:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Kokkinakis v. Greece</target></link></italics><space/>[1993] ECHR 20<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Universelles Leben e.V. v. Germany</target></link></italics><space/>[1996] (app. no. 29745/96)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Buscarini and Others v. San Marino</target></link></italics><space/>[1999] ECHR 7<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Pichon and Sajous v. France</target></link></italics><space/>[2001] ECHR 898<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Leyla ahin v. Turkey</target></link></italics><space/>[2004] ECHR 299<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Leela Frderkreis E.V. and Others v. Germany</target></link></italics><space/>[2008] ECHR<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Lautsi v. Italy</target></link></italics><space/>[2011] ECHR 2412</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>S.A.S. v. France</target></link></italics><space/>[2014] ECHR 695</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 10 - expression</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 10 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 10 provides the right to<space/><link><target>freedom of expression</target></link>, subject to certain restrictions that are &quot;in accordance with law&quot; and &quot;necessary in a democratic society&quot;. This right includes the freedom to hold opinions, and to receive and impart information and ideas, but allows restrictions for:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>interests of national security</listitem><listitem>territorial integrity or public safety</listitem><listitem>prevention of disorder or crime</listitem><listitem>protection of health or morals</listitem><listitem>protection of the reputation or the rights of others</listitem><listitem>preventing the disclosure of information received in confidence</listitem><listitem>maintaining the authority and impartiality of the judiciary</listitem></list><paragraph>Relevant cases are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Lingens v Austria</target></link></italics><space/>(1986) 8 EHRR 407</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Observer and The Guardian v United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1991) 14 EHRR 153, the &quot;<link><target>Spycatcher</target></link>&quot; case.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Bowman v United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>[1998]<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bailii.org/eu/cases/ECHR/1998/4.html'>ECHR 4</link>, (1998) 26 EHRR 1, distributing vast quantities of anti-abortion material in contravention to election spending laws</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Communist Party v Turkey</target></link></italics><space/>(1998) 26 EHRR 1211</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Appleby v United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(2003) 37 EHRR 38, protests in a private shopping mall</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 11 - association</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 11 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 11 protects the right to<space/><link><target>freedom of assembly</target></link><space/>and association, including the right to form<space/><link><target>trade union</target><trail>s</trail></link>, subject to certain restrictions that are &quot;in accordance with law&quot; and &quot;necessary in a democratic society&quot;.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Vogt v Germany</target></link></italics><space/>(1995)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Yazar, Karatas, Aksoy and Hep v Turkey</target></link></italics><space/>(2003) 36 EHRR 59</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 12 - marriage</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Article 12 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 12 provides a right for women and men of<space/><link><target>marriageable age</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>marry</target></link><space/>and establish a family.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Despite a number of invitations, the Court has so far refused to apply the protections of this article to<space/><link><target>same-sex marriage</target></link>. The Court has defended this on the grounds that the article was intended to apply only to different-sex marriage, and that a wide margin of appreciation must be granted to parties in this area.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Goodwin v United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>the Court ruled that a law which still classified post-operative<space/><link><target>transsexual</target></link><space/>persons under their pre-operative sex, violated article 12 as it meant that transsexual persons were unable to marry individuals of their post-operative opposite sex. This reversed an earlier ruling in<space/><italics><link><target>Rees v United Kingdom</target></link></italics>. This did not, however, alter the Court's understanding that Article 12 protects only different-sex couples.</paragraph><paragraph>The European Court of Justice ruled in<space/><link><target>Schalk and Kopf v Austria</target></link><space/>that countries are not required to provide marriage licenses for same-sex couples, however if a country allows same-sex couple marriage it must be done so under the same conditions that opposite-sex couples marriage face: in order to prevent a breach of article 14 - the prohibition of discrimination. Additionally, the court ruled in the 2015 case of Oliari and others v Italy, that states have a positive obligation to ensure there is specific legal framework for the recognition and protection of same-sex couples.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 13 - effective remedy</heading><paragraph>Article 13 provides for the right for an effective<space/><link><target>legal remedy</target><part>remedy</part></link><space/>before national authorities for violations of rights under the Convention. The inability to obtain a remedy before a national court for an infringement of a Convention right is thus a free-standing and separately actionable infringement of the Convention.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 14 - discrimination</heading><paragraph>Article 14 contains a prohibition of<space/><link><target>discrimination</target></link>. This prohibition is broad in some ways, and narrow in others. It is broad in that it prohibits discrimination under a potentially unlimited number of grounds. While the article specifically prohibits discrimination based on &quot;sex, race, colour, language, religion, political or other opinion, national or social origin, association with a national minority, property, birth or other status&quot;, the last of these allows the court to extend to Article 14 protection to other grounds not specifically mentioned such as has been done regarding discrimination based on a person's sexual orientation.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>At the same time the article's protection is limited in that it only prohibits discrimination with respect to rights under the Convention. Thus, an applicant must prove discrimination in the enjoyment of a specific right that is guaranteed elsewhere in the Convention (e.g. discrimination based on sex - Article 14 - in the enjoyment of the right to freedom of expression - Article 10).</paragraph><paragraph>Protocol 12 extends this prohibition to cover discrimination in any legal right, even when that legal right is not protected under the Convention, so long as it is provided for in national law.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 15 - derogations</heading><paragraph>Article 15 allows contracting states to<space/><link><target>Derogation</target><part>derogate</part></link><space/>from certain rights guaranteed by the Convention in time of &quot;war or other public emergency threatening the life of the nation&quot;. Permissible derogations under article 15 must meet three substantive conditions:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>there must be a public emergency threatening the life of the nation;</listitem><listitem>any measures taken in response must be &quot;strictly required by the exigencies of the situation&quot;, and</listitem><listitem>the measures taken in response to it, must be in compliance with a state's other obligations under international law</listitem></list><paragraph>In addition to these substantive requirements the derogation must be procedurally sound. There must be some formal announcement of the derogation and notice of the derogation, any measures adopted under it, and the ending of the derogation must be communicated to the Secretary-General of the<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Article 15(3).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Court is quite permissive in accepting a state's derogations from the Convention but applies a higher degree of scrutiny in deciding whether measures taken by states under a derogation are, in the words of Article 15, &quot;strictly required by the exigencies of the situation&quot;. Thus in<space/><italics>A v United Kingdom</italics>, the Court dismissed a claim that a derogation lodged by the British government in response to the<space/><link><target>September 11 attacks</target></link><space/>was invalid, but went on to find that measures taken by the United Kingdom under that derogation were disproportionate.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/sites/eng/pages/search.aspx?i=002-1647'>&lt;nowiki&gt;[2009</link>&lt;/nowiki&gt; ECHR 301] paras. 181 and 190.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In order for a derogation itself to be valid, the emergency giving rise to it must be:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>actual or imminent, although states do not have to wait for disasters to strike before taking preventive measures,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>A v United Kingdom</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/sites/eng/pages/search.aspx?i=002-1647'>&lt;nowiki&gt;[2009</link>&lt;/nowiki&gt; ECHR 301] para. 177.</extension></listitem><listitem>involve the whole nation, although a threat confined to a particular region may be treated as &quot;threatening the life of the nation&quot; in that particular region,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Aksoy v. Turkey</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/view.asp?action=html&amp;amp;documentId=695880&amp;amp;portal=hbkm&amp;amp;source=externalbydocnumber&amp;amp;table=F69A27FD8FB86142BF01C1166DEA398649'>(1997) 23 EHRR 553</link><space/>para 70.</extension></listitem><listitem>threaten the continuance of the organised life of the community,<extension extension_name='ref' name="greekcase"><italics>Greek case</italics><space/>(1969) 12 YB 1 at 71-72, paras. 152-154.</extension></listitem><listitem>exceptional such that measures and restriction permitted by the Convention would be &quot;plainly inadequate&quot; to deal with the emergency.<extension extension_name='ref' name="greekcase"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Examples of such derogations include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Operation Demetrius</target></link>Internees arrested without trial pursuant to &quot;Operation Demetrius&quot; could not complain to the<space/><link><target>European Commission of Human Rights</target></link><space/>about breaches of Article 5 because on 27 June 1975, the UK lodged a notice with the Council of Europe declaring that there was a &quot;public emergency within the meaning of Article 15(1) of the Convention.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Detention of Suspected Terrorists in Northern Ireland and Great Britain</arg><arg name="first">Brice</arg><arg name="last">Dickson</arg><arg name="journal">[[University of Richmond Law Review]]</arg><arg name="volume">43</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="date">March 2009</arg><arg name="url">http://lawreview.richmond.edu/the-detention-of-suspected-terrorists-in-northern-ireland-and-great-britain/</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Article 16 - aliens</heading><paragraph>Article 16 allows states to restrict the political activity of foreigners. The Court has ruled that European Union member states cannot consider the nationals of other member states to be aliens.<extension extension_name='ref'>In<space/><italics>Piermont v. France</italics><space/>27 April 1995,<space/><link type='external' href='http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/view.asp?action=html&amp;amp;documentId=695802&amp;amp;portal=hbkm&amp;amp;source=externalbydocnumber&amp;amp;table=F69A27FD8FB86142BF01C1166DEA398649'>314 ECHR (series A)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 17 - abuse of rights</heading><paragraph>Article 17 provides that no one may use the rights guaranteed by the Convention to seek the abolition or limitation of rights guaranteed in the Convention. This addresses instances where states seek to restrict a human right in the name of another human right, or where individuals rely on a human right to undermine other human rights (for example where an individual issues a death threat).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Article 18 - permitted restrictions</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Article 18 of the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Article 18 provides that any limitations on the rights provided for in the Convention may be used only for the purpose for which they are provided. For example, Article 5, which guarantees the right to personal freedom, may be explicitly limited in order to bring a suspect before a judge. To use pre-trial detention as a means of intimidation of a person under a false pretext is therefore a limitation of right (to freedom) which does not serve an explicitly provided purpose (to be brought before a judge), and is therefore contrary to Article 18.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Convention protocols</heading><paragraph><template><target>As of</target><arg>January 2010</arg></template>, fifteen protocols to the Convention have been opened for signature. These can be divided into two main groups: those amending the framework of the convention system, and those expanding the rights that can be protected. The former require unanimous ratification by member states before coming into force, while the latter require a certain number of states to sign before coming into force.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Protocol 1</heading><paragraph>This Protocol contains three different rights in which the signatories could not agree to place in the Convention itself.<space/><link><target>Monaco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target></link><space/>have signed but never ratified Protocol 1.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=009&amp;amp;CM=8&amp;amp;DF=21/02/2011&amp;amp;CL=ENG1st'>protocol signatory and ratification info</link>, Council of Europe treaties office.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Article 1 - property</heading><paragraph>Article 1 provides for the<space/><link><target>Right to property</target><part>right to the peaceful enjoyment of one's possessions</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Article 2 - education</heading><paragraph>Article 2 provides for the right not to be denied an education and the right for parents to have their children educated in accordance with their religious and other views. It does not however guarantee any particular level of education of any particular quality.<extension extension_name='ref'>See the<space/><italics><link><target>Belgian linguistic case</target></link></italics>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although phrased in the Protocol as a negative right, in<space/><italics><link><target>Leyla ahin v. Turkey</target><part>ahin v. Turkey</part></link></italics><space/>the Court ruled that:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="it would be hard to imagine that institutions of higher education existing at a given time do not come within the scope of the first sentence of Article 2 of Protocol No 1. Although that Article does not impose a duty on the Contracting States to set up institutions of higher education, any State doing so will be under an obligation to afford an effective right of access to them. In a democratic society, the right to education, which is indispensable to the furtherance of human rights, plays such a fundamental role that a restrictive interpretation of the first sentence of Article 2 of Protocol No. 1 would not be consistent with the aim or purpose of that provision.<ref>''[http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/view.asp?action">html&documentId</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Article 3 - elections</heading><paragraph>Article 3 provides for the right to regular, free and fair elections.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Matthews v. United Kingdom</target></link></italics><space/>(1999) 28 EHRR 361</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Protocol 4 - civil imprisonment, free movement, expulsion</heading><paragraph>Article 1 prohibits the imprisonment of people for inability to fulfil a contract. Article 2 provides for a<space/><link><target>freedom of movement</target><part>right to freely move</part></link><space/>within a country once lawfully there and for a right to leave any country. Article 3 prohibits the expulsion of nationals and provides for the right of an individual to enter a country of his or her nationality. Article 4 prohibits the collective expulsion of foreigners.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>have signed but never ratified Protocol 4.<link><target>Greece</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target></link><space/>have neither signed nor ratified this protocol.</paragraph><paragraph>The United Kingdom's failure to ratify this protocol is due to concerns over the interaction of Article 2 and Article 3 with<space/><link><target>British nationality law</target></link>. Specifically, several classes of &quot;British national&quot; (such as<space/><link><target>British National (Overseas)</target></link>) do not have the right of abode in the United Kingdom and are subject to immigration control there. In 2009, the UK government stated that it had no plans to ratify Protocol 4 because of concerns that those articles could be taken as conferring that right.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200809/ldhansrd/text/90115w0003.htm'>Lords Hansard text for 15 Jan 200915 Jan 2009 (pt 0003)</link>. Publications.parliament.uk. Retrieved on 2013-07-12.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Protocol 6 - restriction of death penalty</heading><paragraph>Requires parties to restrict the application of the<space/><link><target>Capital punishment</target><part>death penalty</part></link><space/>to times of war or &quot;imminent threat of war&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Every Council of Europe member state has signed and ratified Protocol 6, except<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>, which has signed but not ratified.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8367831.stm'>Russia enshrines ban on death penalty</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Protocol 7 - crime and family</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Article 1 provides for a<space/><link><target>right to fair trial</target><part>right to fair procedures</part></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>permanent residency</target><part>lawfully resident</part></link><space/>foreigners facing expulsion.</listitem><listitem>Article 2 provides for the right to<space/><link><target>appeal</target></link><space/>in criminal matters.</listitem><listitem>Article 3 provides for compensation for the victims of miscarriages of justice.</listitem><listitem>Article 4 prohibits the re-trial of anyone who has already been finally acquitted or convicted of a particular offence (<link><target>Double jeopardy</target></link>).</listitem><listitem>Article 5 provides for equality between<space/><link><target>spouse</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Despite having signed the protocol more than twenty years ago, Germany, the Netherlands and Turkey have never ratified it. Belgium, which signed the protocol in 2005, ratified it in 2012, becoming the latest member state to do so. The United Kingdom has neither signed nor ratified the protocol.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Protocol No. 7 to the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms CETS No.: 117</arg><arg name="url">http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT</arg><arg name="work">conventions.coe.int</arg><arg name="publisher">Council of Europe Treaty Office</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 November 2012</arg><arg name="date">16 November 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Protocol 12 - discrimination</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Protocol 12 to the European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template>Applies the current expansive and indefinite grounds of prohibited discrimination in<space/><link><target>#Article 14 - prohibition of discrimination</target><part>Article 14</part></link><space/>to the exercise of any legal right and to the actions (including the obligations) of public authorities.</paragraph><paragraph>The Protocol entered into force on 1 April 2005 and has (<template><target>as of</target><arg>July 2009</arg></template>) been ratified by 17 member states. Several member states<link><target>Bulgaria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lithuania</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Malta</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Monaco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Poland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sweden</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>have not signed the protocol.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=177&amp;amp;CM=8&amp;amp;DF=7/6/2009&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Information on the current state of the protocol</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The United Kingdom Government has declined to sign Protocol 12 on the basis that they believe the wording of protocol is too wide and would result in a flood of new cases testing the extent of the new provision. They believe that the phrase &quot;rights set forth by law&quot; might include international conventions to which the UK is not a party, and would result in incorporation of these instruments by stealth. It has been suggested that the protocol is therefore in a<space/><link><target>catch-22 (logic)</target><part>catch-22</part></link>, since the UK will decline to either sign or ratify the protocol until the<space/><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link><space/>has addressed the meaning of the provision, while the court is hindered in doing so by the lack of applications to the court concerning the protocol caused by the decisions of Europe's most populous statesincluding the UKnot to ratify the protocol. The UK Government, nevertheless, &quot;agrees in principle that the ECHR should contain a provision against discrimination that is free-standing and not parasitic on the other Convention rights&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="UK position"><link type='external' href='http://www.humanrights.gov.uk/ngo/reviews/appendix6.pdf'>2004 UK Government's position</link></extension><space/>The first judgment that found a violation of Protocol No. 12,<space/><italics><link><target>Sejdi and Finci v. Bosnia and Herzegovina</target></link></italics>, was delivered in 2009.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Protocol 13 - complete abolition of death penalty</heading><paragraph>Protocol 13 provides for the total abolition of the death penalty.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/en/Treaties/Html/187.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Protocol No. 13 to the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms, concerning the abolition of the death penalty in all circumstances<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Council of Europe<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>Currently all Council of Europe member states bar three, have ratified Protocol 13.<space/><link><target>Armenia</target></link><space/>has signed but not ratified the protocol.<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Azerbaijan</target></link><space/>have not signed it.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=187&amp;amp;CM=8&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Treaty Office Website</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Procedural and institutional protocols</heading><paragraph>The Convention's provisions affecting institutional and procedural matters have been altered several times by means of protocols. These amendments have, with the exception of Protocol 2, amended the text of the convention. Protocol 2 did not amend the text of the convention as such, but stipulated that it was to be treated as an integral part of the text. All of these protocols have required the unanimous ratification of all the member states of the Council of Europe to enter into force.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Protocol 11</heading><paragraph>Protocols 2, 3, 5, 8, 9 and 10 have now been superseded by Protocol 11 which entered into force on 1 November 1998.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">List of the treaties coming from the subject-matter: Human Rights (Convention and Protocols only)<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ListeTraites.asp?MA</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>It established a fundamental change in the machinery of the convention. It abolished the Commission, allowing individuals to apply directly to the Court, which was given compulsory jurisdiction and altered the latter's structure. Previously states could ratify the Convention without accepting the jurisdiction of the Court of Human Rights. The protocol also abolished the judicial functions of the Committee of Ministers.<space/></paragraph><heading level='4'>Protocol 14</heading><paragraph>Protocol 14 follows on from Protocol 11 in proposing to further improve the efficiency of the Court. It seeks to &quot;filter&quot; out cases that have less chance of succeeding along with those that are broadly similar to cases brought previously against the same member state. Furthermore, a case will not be considered admissible where an applicant has not suffered a &quot;significant disadvantage&quot;. This latter ground can only be used when an examination of the application on the merits is not considered necessary and where the subject-matter of the application had already been considered by a national court.</paragraph><paragraph>A new mechanism was introduced by Protocol 14 to assist enforcement of judgements by the Committee of Ministers. The Committee can ask the Court for an interpretation of a judgement and can even bring a member state before the Court for non-compliance of a previous judgement against that state. Protocol 14 also allows for<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/><link><target>Relationship between the European Court of Justice and European Court of Human Rights#EU accession to ECHR</target><part>accession to the Convention</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Article 17 of the<space/><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/EN/Treaties/Html/194.htm'>Protocol No. 14</link><space/>amending Article 59 of the Convention.</extension><space/>The protocol has been ratified by every Council of Europe member state, Russia being last in February 2010. It entered into force on 1 June 2010.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=194&amp;amp;CM=2&amp;amp;DF=19/02/2010&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Protocol No. 14 to the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A provisional<space/><bold>Protocol 14bis</bold><space/>had been opened for signature in 2009.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/QueVoulezVous.asp?NT=204&amp;amp;CM=2&amp;amp;DF=5/30/2009&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Protocol No. 14bis to the ECHR</link></extension><space/>Pending the ratification of Protocol 14 itself, 14bis was devised to allow the Court to implement revised procedures in respect of the states which have ratified it. It allowed single judges to reject manifestly inadmissible applications made against the states that have ratified the protocol. It also extended the competence of three-judge chambers to declare applications made against those states admissible and to decide on their merits where there already is a well-established case law of the Court. Now that all Council of Europe member states have ratified Protocol 14, Protocol 14bis has lost its<space/><italics>raison d'tre</italics><space/>and according to its own terms ceased to have any effect when Protocol 14 entered into force on 1 June 2010.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Capital punishment in Europe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European Court of Human Rights</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European Social Charter</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human Rights Act 1998</target></link><space/>for how the Convention has been incorporated into the law of the United Kingdom.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Human rights in Europe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Territorial scope of European Convention on Human Rights</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European Convention on Human Rights Act 2003</target></link><space/>Irish Act similar to the British<space/><link><target>Human Rights Act 1998</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Jacobs & White: The European Convention on Human Rights<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Clare<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Ovey<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Robin C. A.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">White<space/></arg><arg name="edition">4th<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-928810-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The European Convention on Human Rights: Achievements, Problems and Prospects<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Steven</arg><arg name="last1">Greer<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0521608596</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Positive Obligations of the State under the European Convention of Human Rights<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Dimitris</arg><arg name="last1">Xenos<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-66812-5</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category-inline</target><arg>European Convention on Human Rights</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ListeTraites.asp?MA=3&amp;amp;CM=7&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>List of the ECHR and all Protocols</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/treaty/en/Treaties/Html/005.htm'>Text of the ECHR</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/search.asp?skin=hudoc-en'>Database of European Human Rights Court (Strasbourg) judgments</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>official website</target><arg>http://human-rights-convention.org/</arg><arg>European Convention of Human Rights official website</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ListeTraites.asp?CM=8&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>List of all European treaties and protocols</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/3534274.stm'>Terror detention law 'must go'</link>; BBC; 4 August 2004</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=177&amp;amp;CM=8&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Current Status of Protocol 12</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ChercheSig.asp?NT=194&amp;amp;CM=8&amp;amp;CL=ENG'>Current Status of Protocol 14</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.humanrights.gov.uk/ngo/reviews/appendix6.pdf'>UK Government's position on Protocol 12</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://indexoncensorship.org'>Index on Censorship</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Articles of the European Convention on Human Rights</target></template><template><target>International human rights legal instruments</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:European Convention On Human Rights</target></template><link><target>Category:European Convention on Human Rights</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Human rights instruments</target></link><link><target>Category:Council of Europe treaties</target><part>Convention on Human Rights</part></link><link><target>Category:Treaties concluded in 1950</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties entered into force in 1953</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Albania</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Andorra</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Armenia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Austria</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Azerbaijan</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Belgium</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Bosnia and Herzegovina</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Bulgaria</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Croatia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Cyprus</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of the Czech Republic</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Denmark</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Estonia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Finland</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of France</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Georgia (country)</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of West Germany</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Hungary</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Iceland</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Ireland</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Italy</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Latvia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Liechtenstein</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Lithuania</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Luxembourg</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Malta</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Moldova</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Monaco</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Montenegro</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of the Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Norway</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Poland</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Portugal</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Romania</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Russia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of San Marino</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Serbia and Montenegro</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Slovakia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Slovenia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Spain</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Sweden</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Switzerland</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of the Republic of Macedonia</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Turkey</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of Ukraine</target></link><link><target>Category:Treaties of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:1950 in Italy</target></link></paragraph></article>