<article title='Eocene'><paragraph><template><target>paleogene</target></template>The<space/><bold>Eocene</bold><space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>ɵ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>n</arg></template><space/>(symbol<space/><xhtml:span style="letter-spacing:-1px">E<template><target>font</target><arg>'''o'''</arg><arg name="size">75%</arg></template></xhtml:span>&amp;thinsp;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1999/of99-430/of99-430_sec38.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-06-22<space/></arg><arg name="title">Geologic Age Symbol Font (StratagemAge)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">USGS<space/></arg><arg name="id">99-430</arg></template></extension>) Epoch, lasting from<space/><template><target>ma</target><arg>Eocene</arg><arg>Oligocene</arg><arg>million years ago</arg></template>, is a major division of the<space/><link><target>geologic timescale</target></link><space/>and the second epoch of the<space/><link><target>Paleogene</target></link><space/>Period in the<space/><link><target>Cenozoic</target></link><space/>Era. The Eocene spans the time from the end of the<space/><link><target>Palaeocene</target></link><space/>Epoch to the beginning of the<space/><link><target>Oligocene</target></link><space/>Epoch. The start of the Eocene is marked by a brief period in which the concentration of the<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/><link><target>isotope</target></link><space/><link><target>Carbon-13</target><part><xhtml:sup>13</xhtml:sup>C</part></link><space/>in the atmosphere was exceptionally low in comparison with the more common isotope<space/><link><target>Carbon-12</target><part><xhtml:sup>12</xhtml:sup>C</part></link>. The end is set at a major<space/><link><target>extinction event</target></link><space/>called the<space/><italics>Grande Coupure</italics><space/>(the &quot;Great Break&quot; in continuity) or the<space/><link><target>EoceneOligocene extinction event</target></link>, which may be related to the impact of one or more large<space/><link><target>bolide</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Popigai crater</target><part>Siberia</part></link><space/>and in what is now<space/><link><target>Chesapeake Bay impact crater</target><part>Chesapeake Bay</part></link>. As with other<space/><link><target>geologic period</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>Stratum</target><part>strata</part></link><space/>that define the start and end of the epoch are well identified,<extension extension_name='ref'>The extinction of the Hantkeninidae, a planktonic family of<space/><link><target>foraminifera</target></link><space/>became generally accepted as marking the Eocene-Oligocene boundary; in 1998<space/><link><target>Massignano</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Umbria</target></link>, central Italy, was designated the<space/><link><target>Global Boundary Stratotype Section and Point</target></link><space/>(GSSP).</extension><space/>though their exact dates are slightly uncertain.</paragraph><paragraph>The name<space/><italics>Eocene</italics><space/>comes from the<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>ἠώς</arg></template><space/>(<italics>eos</italics>,<space/><link><target>dawn</target></link>) and<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>καινός</arg></template><space/>(<italics>kainos</italics>, new) and refers to the &quot;dawn&quot; of modern ('new')<space/><link><target>fauna</target></link><space/>that appeared during the epoch.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OnlineEtDict"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eocene</arg><arg name="url">http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Online Etymology Dictionary]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Subdivisions</heading><paragraph>The Eocene epoch is usually divided into early, middle, and late subdivisions. The corresponding<space/><link><target>rocks</target></link><space/>are referred to as lower, middle, and upper Eocene. The<space/><link><target>Ypresian</target></link><space/>stage constitutes the lower, the<space/><link><target>Priabonian</target></link><space/>stage the upper; and the<space/><link><target>Lutetian</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bartonian</target></link><space/>stages are united as the middle Eocene.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Climate</heading><paragraph>The Eocene Epoch contained a wide variety of different climate conditions that includes the warmest climate in the<space/><link><target>Cenozoic Era</target></link><space/>and ends in an icehouse climate. The evolution of the Eocene climate began with warming after the end of the<space/><link><target>Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum</target></link><space/>(PETM) at 56 million years ago to a maximum during the Eocene Optimum at around 49 million years ago. During this period of time, little to no ice was present on Earth with a smaller difference in temperature from the equator to the poles. Following the maximum was a descent into an icehouse climate from the Eocene Optimum to the Eocene-Oligocene transition at 34 million years ago. During this decrease ice began to reappear at the poles, and the Eocene-Oligocene transition is the period of time where the<space/><link><target>Antarctic ice sheet</target></link><space/>began to rapidly expand.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Atmospheric greenhouse gas evolution</heading><paragraph>Greenhouse gases, in particular<space/><link><target>carbon dioxide</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>methane</target></link>, played a significant role during the Eocene in controlling the surface temperature. The end of the PETM was met with a very large sequestration of carbon dioxide in the form of<space/><link><target>methane clathrate</target></link>,<space/><link><target>coal</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>crude oil</target></link><space/>at the bottom of the<space/><link><target>Arctic Ocean</target></link>, that reduced the atmospheric carbon dioxide.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bowen3"></extension><space/>This event was similar in magnitude to the massive release of greenhouse gasses at the beginning of the PETM, and it is hypothesized that the sequestration was mainly due to organic carbon burial and<space/><link><target>weathering</target></link><space/>of silicates. For the early Eocene there is much discussion on how much carbon dioxide is in the atmosphere. This is due to numerous proxies representing different atmospheric carbon dioxide content. For example, diverse geochemical and paleontological proxies indicate that at the maximum of global warmth the atmospheric carbon dioxide values were at 700 900 ppm<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson4"></extension><space/>while other proxies such as pedogenic (soil building) carbonate and marine boron isotopes indicate large changes of carbon dioxide of over 2,000 ppm over periods of time of less than 1 million years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Royer5"></extension><space/>Sources for this large influx of carbon dioxide could be attributed to volcanic out-gassing due to North Atlantic rifting or oxidation of methane stored in large reservoirs deposited from the PETM event in the sea floor or wetland environments.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson4"></extension><space/>For contrast, today the<space/><link><target>Atmosphere of Earth</target><part>carbon dioxide levels</part></link><space/>are at 400 ppm or 0.04%.</paragraph><paragraph>At about the beginning of the Eocene Epoch (55.8-33.9 million years ago) the amount of oxygen in the earth's atmosphere more or less doubled.<extension extension_name='ref' name="anthro.palomar.edu">http://anthro.palomar.edu/earlyprimates/early_2.htm</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the early Eocene, methane was another greenhouse gas that had a drastic effect on the climate. In comparison to carbon dioxide, methane has much higher consequences with regards to temperature as methane has ~34 times more effect per molecule than carbon dioxide on a 100-year scale (it has a higher<space/><link><target>global warming potential</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph>Myhre, G., D. Shindell, F.-M. Bron, W. Collins, J. Fuglestvedt, J. Huang, D. Koch, J.-F. Lamarque, D. Lee, B. Mendoza, T. Nakajima, A. Robock, G. Stephens, T. Takemura and H. Zhang (2013)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.climatechange2013.org/images/report/WG1AR5_Chapter08_FINAL.pdf'>&quot;Anthropogenic and Natural Radiative Forcing&quot;</link>. In:<space/><italics>Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italics>. Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.). Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA.</paragraph><paragraph><link type='external' href='http://www.climatechange2013.org/images/report/WG1AR5_Chapter08_FINAL.pdf'>Anthropogenic and Natural Radiative Forcing</link></paragraph></extension><space/>The majority of the methane released to the atmosphere during this period of time would have been from wetlands, swamps, and forests.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan6"></extension><space/>The atmospheric methane<space/><link><target>Atmosphere of Earth</target><part>concentration today</part></link><space/>is 0.000179% or 1.79 ppmv. Due to the warmer climate and sea level rise associated with the early Eocene, more wetlands, more forests, and more coal deposits would be available for methane release. Comparing the early Eocene production of methane to current levels of atmospheric methane, the early Eocene would be able to produce triple the amount of current methane production. The warm temperatures during the early Eocene could have increased methane production rates, and methane that is released into the atmosphere would in turn warm the troposphere, cool the stratosphere, and produce water vapor and carbon dioxide through oxidation. Biogenic production of methane produces carbon dioxide and water vapor along with the methane, as well as yielding infrared radiation. The breakdown of methane in an oxygen atmosphere produces carbon monoxide, water vapor and infrared radiation. The carbon monoxide is not stable so it eventually becomes carbon dioxide and in doing so releases yet more infrared radiation. Water vapor traps more infrared than does carbon dioxide.</paragraph><paragraph>The middle to late Eocene marks not only the switch from warming to cooling, but also the change in carbon dioxide from increasing to decreasing. At the end of the Eocene Optimum, carbon dioxide began decreasing due to increased siliceous plankton productivity and marine carbon burial.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson4"></extension><space/>At the beginning of the middle Eocene an event that may have triggered or helped with the draw down of carbon dioxide was the<space/><link><target>Azolla event</target></link><space/>at around 49 million years ago.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Speelman7"></extension><space/>With the equable climate during the early Eocene, warm temperatures in the arctic allowed for the growth of<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link>, which is a floating aquatic fern, on the<space/><link><target>Arctic Ocean</target></link>. Compared to current carbon dioxide levels, these azolla grew rapidly in the enhanced carbon dioxide levels found in the early Eocene. As these<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link><space/>sank into the Arctic Ocean, they became buried and sequestered their carbon into the seabed. This event could have led to a draw down of atmospheric carbon dioxide of up to 470 ppm.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Speelman7"></extension><space/>Assuming the carbon dioxide concentrations were at 900 ppmv prior to the<space/><link><target>Azolla Event</target></link><space/>they would have dropped to 430 ppmv, or 40 ppmv more than they are today, after the Azolla Event. Another event during the middle Eocene that was a sudden and temporary reversal of the cooling conditions was the<space/><link><target>Middle Eocene Climatic Optimum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension><space/>At around 41.5 million years ago, stable isotopic analysis of samples from Southern Ocean drilling sites indicated a warming event for 600 thousand years. A sharp increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide was observed with a maximum of 4000 ppm: the highest amount of atmospheric carbon dioxide detected during the Eocene.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson9"></extension><space/>The main hypothesis for such a radical transition was due to the continental drift and collision of the India continent with the Asia continent and the resulting formation of the<space/><link><target>Himalayas</target></link>. Another hypothesis involves extensive sea floor rifting and metamorphic decarbonation reactions releasing considerable amounts of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the end of the Middle Eocene Climatic Optimum, cooling and the carbon dioxide drawdown continued through the late Eocene and into the Eocene-Oligocene transition around 34 million years ago. Multiple proxies, such as oxygen isotopes and alkenones, indicate that at the Eocene-Oligocene transition, the atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration had decreased to around 750-800 ppm, approximately twice that of<space/><link><target>Atmosphere of Earth</target><part>present levels</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pagani10"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Lear11"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early Eocene and the equable climate problem</heading><paragraph>One of the unique features of the Eocenes climate as mentioned before was the equable and homogeneous climate that existed in the early parts of the Eocene. A multitude of<space/><link><target>Proxy (climate)</target><part>proxies</part></link><space/>support the presence of a warmer equable climate being present during this period of time. A few of these proxies include the presence of fossils native to warm climates, such as<space/><link><target>crocodile</target><trail>s</trail></link>, located in the higher latitudes,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan12"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber13"></extension><space/>the presence in the high-latitudes of frost-intolerant flora such as<space/><link><target>palm trees</target></link><space/>which cannot survive during sustained freezes,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber13"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber14"></extension><space/>and fossils of<space/><link><target>snakes</target></link><space/>found in the tropics that would require much higher average temperatures to sustain them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber13"></extension><space/>Using isotope proxies to determine ocean temperatures indicates sea surface temperatures in the tropics as high as 35&amp;nbsp;C (95&amp;nbsp;F) and, relative to present day values, bottom water temperatures that are 10&amp;nbsp;C (18&amp;nbsp;F) higher.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber14"></extension><space/>With these bottom water temperatures, temperatures in areas where deep-water forms near the poles are unable to be much cooler than the bottom water temperatures.</paragraph><paragraph>An issue arises, however, when trying to model the Eocene and reproduce the results that are found with the<space/><link><target>Proxy (climate)</target><part>proxy data</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan15"></extension><space/>Using all different ranges of greenhouse gasses that occurred during the early Eocene, models were unable to produce the warming that was found at the poles and the reduced seasonality that occurs with winters at the poles being substantially warmer. The models, while accurately predicting the tropics, tend to produce significantly cooler temperatures of up to 20&amp;nbsp;C (36&amp;nbsp;F) colder than the actual determined temperature at the poles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber14"></extension><space/>This error has been classified as the equable climate problem. To solve this problem, the solution would involve finding a process to warm the poles without warming the tropics. Some hypotheses and tests which attempt to find the process are listed below.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Large lakes</heading><paragraph>Due to the nature of water as opposed to land, less temperature variability would be present if a large body of water is also present. In an attempt to try to mitigate the cooling polar temperatures, large lakes were proposed to mitigate seasonal climate changes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan16"></extension><space/>To replicate this case, a lake was inserted into North America and a climate model was run using varying carbon dioxide levels. The model runs concluded that while the lake did reduce the seasonality of the region greater than just an increase in carbon dioxide, the addition of a large lake was unable to reduce the seasonality to the levels shown by the floral and faunal data.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Ocean heat transport</heading><paragraph>The transport of heat from the tropics to the poles, much like how ocean heat transport functions in modern times, was considered a possibility for the increased temperature and reduced seasonality for the poles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber17"></extension><space/>With the increased sea surface temperatures and the increased temperature of the deep ocean water during the early Eocene, one common hypothesis was that due to these increases there would be a greater transport of heat from the tropics to the poles. Simulating these differences, the models produced lower heat transport due to the lower temperature gradients and were unsuccessful in producing an equable climate from only ocean heat transport.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Orbital parameters</heading><paragraph>While typically seen as a control on ice growth and seasonality, the orbital parameters were theorized as a possible control on continental temperatures and seasonality.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan18"></extension><space/>Simulating the Eocene by using an ice free planet,<space/><link><target>Orbital eccentricity</target><part>eccentricity</part></link>,<space/><link><target>obliquity</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>precession</target></link><space/>were modified in different model runs to determine all the possible different scenarios that could occur and their effects on temperature. One particular case led to warmer winters and cooler summer by up to 30% in the North American continent, and it reduced the seasonal variation of temperature by up to 75%. While orbital parameters did not produce the warming at the poles, the parameters did show a great effect on seasonality and needed to be considered.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Polar stratospheric clouds</heading><paragraph>Another method considered for producing the warm polar temperatures were<space/><link><target>polar stratospheric clouds</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan19"></extension><space/>Polar stratospheric clouds are clouds that occur in the lower stratosphere at very low temperatures. Polar stratospheric clouds have a great impact on radiative forcing. Due to their minimal albedo properties and their optical thickness, polar stratospheric clouds act similar to a greenhouse gas and traps outgoing longwave radiation. Different types of polar stratospheric clouds occur in the atmosphere: polar stratospheric clouds that are created due to interactions with nitric or sulfuric acid and water (Type I) or polar stratospheric clouds that are created with only water ice (Type II).</paragraph><paragraph>Methane is an important factor in the creation of the primary Type II polar stratospheric clouds that were created in the early Eocene.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan20"></extension><space/>Since water vapor is the only supporting substance used in Type II polar stratospheric clouds, the presence of water vapor in the lower stratosphere is necessary where in most situations the presence of water vapor in the lower stratosphere is rare. When methane is oxidized, a significant amount of water vapor is released. Another requirement for polar stratospheric clouds is cold temperatures to ensure condensation and cloud production. Polar stratospheric cloud production, since it requires the cold temperatures, is usually limited to nighttime and winter conditions. With this combination of wetter and colder conditions in the lower stratosphere, polar stratospheric clouds could have formed over wide areas in Polar Regions.</paragraph><paragraph>To test the polar stratospheric clouds effects on the Eocene climate, models were run comparing the effects of polar stratospheric clouds at the poles to an increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sloan19"></extension><space/>The polar stratospheric clouds had a warming effect on the poles, increasing temperatures by up to 20&amp;nbsp;C in the winter months. A multitude of feedbacks also occurred in the models due to the polar stratospheric clouds presence. Any ice growth was slowed immensely and would lead to any present ice melting. Only the poles were affected with the change in temperature and the tropics were unaffected, which with an increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide would also cause the tropics to increase in temperature. Due to the warming of the troposphere from the increased greenhouse effect of the polar stratospheric clouds, the stratosphere would cool and would potentially increase the amount of polar stratospheric clouds.</paragraph><paragraph>While the polar stratospheric clouds could explain the reduction of the equator to pole temperature gradient and the increased temperatures at the poles during the early Eocene, there are a few drawbacks to maintaining polar stratospheric clouds for an extended period of time. Separate model runs were used to determine the sustainability of the polar stratospheric clouds.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirk21"></extension><space/>Methane would need to be continually released and sustained to maintain the lower stratospheric water vapor. Increasing amounts of ice and condensation nuclei would be need to be high for the polar stratospheric cloud to sustain itself and eventually expand.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hyperthermals through the Early Eocene</heading><paragraph>During the warming in the Early Eocene between 52 and 55 million years ago, there were a series of short-term changes of<space/><link><target>carbon isotope</target></link><space/>composition in the ocean.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Galeotti22"></extension><space/>These isotope changes occurred due to the release of carbon from the ocean into the atmosphere that led to a temperature increase of 4-8&amp;nbsp;C (7.2-14.4&amp;nbsp;F) at the surface of the ocean. These hyperthermals led to increased perturbations in planktonic and benthic<space/><link><target>foraminifera</target></link>, with a higher rate of sedimentation as a consequence of the warmer temperatures. Recent analysis of and research into these hyperthermals in the early Eocene has led to hypotheses that the hyperthermals are based on orbital parameters, in particular eccentricity and obliquity. The hyperthermals in the early Eocene, notably the<space/><link><target>Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum</target></link><space/>(PETM), the<space/><link><target>Eocene Thermal Maximum 2</target></link><space/>(ETM2), and the Eocene Thermal Maximum 3 (ETM3), were analyzed and found that orbital control may have had a role in triggering the ETM2 and ETM3.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Greenhouse to icehouse climate</heading><paragraph>The Eocene is not only known for containing the warmest period during the Cenozoic, but it also marked the decline into an icehouse climate and the rapid expansion of the<space/><link><target>Antarctic ice sheet</target></link>. The transition from a warming climate into a cooling climate began at ~49 million years ago. Isotopes of carbon and oxygen indicate a shift to a global cooling climate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Speelman7"></extension><space/>The cause of the cooling has been attributed to a significant decrease of &gt;2000&amp;nbsp;ppm in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson4"></extension><space/>One proposed cause of the reduction in carbon dioxide during the warming to cooling transition was the<space/><link><target>Azolla event</target></link>. The increased warmth at the poles, the isolated Arctic basin during the early Eocene, and the significantly high amounts of carbon dioxide possibly led to<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link><space/>blooms across the Arctic Ocean.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Speelman7"></extension><space/>The isolation of the Arctic Ocean led to stagnant waters and as the<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link><space/>sank to the sea floor, they became part of the sediments and effectively sequestered the carbon. The ability for the<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link><space/>to sequester carbon is exceptional, and the enhanced burial of<space/><link><target>azolla</target></link><space/>could have had a significant effect on the world atmospheric carbon content and may have been the event to begin the transition into an ice house climate. Cooling after this event continued due to continual decrease in atmospheric carbon dioxide from organic productivity and<space/><link><target>weathering</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>mountain building</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Global cooling continued until there was a major reversal from cooling to warming indicated in the<space/><link><target>Southern Ocean</target></link><space/>at around 42-41 million years ago.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension><space/><link><target>Oxygen isotope</target></link><space/>analysis showed a large negative change in the proportion of heavier oxygen isotopes to lighter oxygen isotopes, which indicates an increase in global temperatures. This warming event is known as the Middle Eocene Climatic Optimum. The cause of the warming is considered to primarily be due to carbon dioxide increases, since carbon isotope signatures rule out major methane release during this short term warming.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension><space/>The increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide is considered to be due to increased<space/><link><target>seafloor spreading</target></link><space/>rates between Australia and Antarctica and increased amounts of<space/><link><target>volcanism</target></link><space/>in the region. Another possible atmospheric carbon dioxide increase could be during a sudden increase with metamorphic release during the<space/><link><target>Himalayan orogeny</target></link>, however data on the exact timing of metamorphic release of atmospheric carbon dioxide is not well resolved in the data.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bohaty8"></extension><space/>Recent studies have mentioned, however, that the removal of the ocean between Asia and India could release significant amounts of carbon dioxide.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson9"></extension><space/>This warming is short lived, as benthic oxygen isotope records indicate a return to cooling at ~40 million years ago.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pagani10"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Cooling continued throughout the rest of the late Eocene into the Eocene-Oligocene transition. During the cooling period, benthic oxygen isotopes show the possibility of ice creation and ice increase during this later cooling.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pearson4"></extension><space/>The end of the Eocene and beginning of the Oligocene is marked with the massive expansion of area of the Antarctic ice sheet that was a major step into the icehouse climate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lear11"></extension><space/>Along with the decrease of atmospheric carbon dioxide reducing the global temperature, orbital factors in ice creation can be seen with 100,000 year and 400,000 year fluctuations in benthic oxygen isotope records.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Diester23"></extension><space/>Another major contribution to the expansion of the ice sheet was the creation of the<space/><link><target>Antarctic circumpolar current</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barker24"></extension><space/>The creation of the Antarctic circumpolar current would isolate the cold water around the Antarctic, which would reduce heat transport to the Antarctic<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huber25"></extension><space/>along with create<space/><link><target>ocean gyre</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that result in the<space/><link><target>upwelling</target></link><space/>of colder bottom waters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barker24"></extension><space/>The issue with this hypothesis of the consideration of this being a factor for the Eocene-Oligocene transition is the timing of the creation of the circulation is uncertain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barker26"></extension><space/>For<space/><link><target>Drake Passage</target></link>, sediments indicate the opening occurred ~41 million years ago while tectonics indicate that this occurred ~32 million years ago.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Palaeogeography</heading><paragraph>During the Eocene, the<space/><link><target>continent</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>continued to<space/><link><target>plate tectonics</target><part>drift</part></link><space/>toward their present positions.</paragraph><paragraph>At the beginning of the period,<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Antarctica</target></link><space/>remained connected, and warm equatorial currents mixed with colder Antarctic waters, distributing the<space/><link><target>heat</target></link><space/>around the<space/><link><target>planet</target></link><space/>and keeping global temperatures high, but when Australia split from the southern continent around 45 Ma, the warm equatorial currents were routed away from Antarctica. An isolated cold water channel developed between the two continents. The Antarctic region cooled down, and the ocean surrounding Antarctica began to freeze, sending cold water and<space/><link><target>icefloe</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>north, reinforcing the cooling.</paragraph><paragraph>The northern<space/><link><target>supercontinent</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Laurasia</target></link><space/>began to break up, as<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Greenland</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>drifted apart.</paragraph><paragraph>In western North America,<space/><link><target>Orogeny</target><part>mountain building</part></link><space/>started in the Eocene, and huge lakes formed in the high flat basins among uplifts, resulting in the deposition of the<space/><link><target>Green River Formation</target></link><space/><link><target>lagersttte</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>At about 35 Ma, an asteroid impact on the eastern coast of North America formed the<space/><link><target>Chesapeake Bay impact crater</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In Europe, the<space/><link><target>Tethys Ocean</target><part>Tethys Sea</part></link><space/>finally vanished, while the uplift of the<space/><link><target>Alps</target></link><space/>isolated its final remnant, the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Sea</target><part>Mediterranean</part></link>, and created another shallow sea with island<space/><link><target>archipelago</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to the north. Though the North<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target><part>Atlantic</part></link><space/>was opening, a land connection appears to have remained between North America and Europe since the faunas of the two regions are very similar.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>India</target></link><space/>continued its journey away from<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link><space/>and began its collision with<space/><link><target>Asia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>fold (geology)</target><part>fold</part><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Himalaya</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>into existence.</paragraph><paragraph>It is hypothesized that the Eocene hothouse world was caused by runaway global warming from released<space/><link><target>methane clathrate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>deep in the<space/><link><target>ocean</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The<space/><link><target>clathrate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were buried beneath<space/><link><target>mud</target></link><space/>that was disturbed as the oceans warmed.<space/><link><target>Methane</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Carbon</target><part>C</part></link><link><target>Hydrogen</target><part>H</part></link><xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>) has ten to twenty times the<space/><link><target>greenhouse gas</target></link><space/>effect of<space/><link><target>carbon dioxide</target></link><space/>(CO<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Flora</heading><paragraph>At the beginning of the Eocene, the high<space/><link><target>temperature</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and warm oceans created a moist, balmy environment, with<space/><link><target>forest</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>spreading throughout the Earth from pole to pole. Apart from the driest<space/><link><target>desert</target><trail>s</trail></link>, Earth must have been entirely covered in forests.</paragraph><paragraph>Polar forests were quite extensive.<space/><link><target>Fossil</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and even preserved remains of trees such as<space/><link><target>Cupressaceae</target><part>swamp cypress</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>dawn redwood</target></link><space/>from the Eocene have been found on<space/><link><target>Ellesmere Island</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Arctic</target></link>. Even at that time, Ellesmere Island was only a few degrees in latitude further south than it is today. Fossils of<space/><link><target>subtropical</target></link><space/>and even tropical trees and plants from the Eocene have also been found in Greenland and<space/><link><target>Alaska</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Tropical rainforest</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>grew as far north as northern<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Palm tree</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were growing as far north as Alaska and<space/><link><target>northern Europe</target></link><space/>during the early Eocene, although they became less abundant as the climate cooled.<space/><link><target>Dawn redwood</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were far more extensive as well.</paragraph><paragraph>Cooling began mid-period, and by the end of the Eocene continental interiors had begun to dry out, with forests thinning out considerably in some areas. The newly evolved<space/><link><target>grasses</target></link><space/>were still confined to<space/><link><target>river</target></link><space/>banks and<space/><link><target>lake</target></link><space/>shores, and had not yet expanded into<space/><link><target>plain</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>savanna</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The cooling also brought<space/><link><target>season</target><trail>al</trail></link><space/>changes.<space/><link><target>Deciduous</target></link><space/>trees, better able to cope with large temperature changes, began to overtake<space/><link><target>evergreen</target></link><space/>tropical species. By the end of the period, deciduous forests covered large parts of the northern continents, including North America,<space/><link><target>Eurasia</target></link><space/>and the Arctic, and rainforests held on only in equatorial<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>India</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Antarctica</target></link>, which began the Eocene fringed with a warm temperate to sub-tropical<space/><link><target>rainforest</target></link>, became much colder as the period progressed; the heat-loving tropical<space/><link><target>flora (plants)</target><part>flora</part></link><space/>was wiped out, and by the beginning of the Oligocene, the continent hosted deciduous forests and vast stretches of<space/><link><target>tundra</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Fauna</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Eocene.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Eocene fauna of North America</part></link><link><target>Image:Crassostrea gigantissima (Finch, 1824).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Crassostrea gigantissima'' (Finch, 1824), a giant oyster from the Eocene of<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>Image:Nummulitids.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Fossil nummulitid<space/><link><target>foraminifera</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>showing microspheric and megalospheric individuals; Eocene of the<space/><link><target>United Arab Emirates</target></link>; scale in mm.</part></link>The oldest known<space/><link><target>fossil</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of most of the modern mammal orders appear within a brief period during the early Eocene. At the beginning of the Eocene, several new mammal groups arrived in North America. These modern mammals, like<space/><link><target>artiodactyl</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>perissodactyls</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>primate</target><trail>s</trail></link>, had features like long, thin<space/><link><target>leg</target><trail>s</trail></link>, feet and<space/><link><target>hand</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>capable of grasping, as well as differentiated<space/><link><target>teeth</target></link><space/>adapted for chewing.<space/><link><target>Insular dwarfism</target><part>Dwarf</part></link><space/>forms reigned. All the members of the new mammal orders were small, under 10&amp;nbsp;kg; based on comparisons of tooth size, Eocene mammals were only 60% of the size of the primitive Palaeocene mammals that preceded them. They were also smaller than the mammals that followed them. It is assumed that the hot Eocene temperatures favored smaller animals that were better able to manage the heat.</paragraph><paragraph>Both groups of modern<space/><link><target>ungulate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(hoofed animals) became prevalent because of a major radiation between Europe and North America, along with carnivorous ungulates like<space/><italics><link><target>Mesonyx</target></link></italics>. Early forms of many other modern mammalian orders appeared, including<space/><link><target>bat</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>proboscidea</target><part>proboscidian</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(elephants), primates,<space/><link><target>rodent</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>marsupials</target></link>. Older primitive forms of mammals declined in variety and importance. Important Eocene land fauna fossil remains have been found in western North America, Europe,<space/><link><target>Patagonia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>southeast Asia</target></link>. Marine fauna are best known from<space/><link><target>South Asia</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>southeast United States</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Reptile fossils from this time, such as fossils of<space/><link><target>Pythonidae</target><part>python</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>turtle</target><trail>s</trail></link>, are abundant. The remains of<space/><italics><link><target>Titanoboa</target></link></italics>, a snake the length of a school bus, was discovered in South America along with other large reptilian megafauna.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Head, Jj; Bloch, Ji; Hastings, Ak; Bourque, Jr; Cadena, Ea; Herrera, Fa; Polly, Pd; Jaramillo, Ca 2009 7157"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1038/nature07671<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 2009<space/></arg><arg name="author">Head, Jj; Bloch, Ji; Hastings, Ak; Bourque, Jr; Cadena, Ea; Herrera, Fa; Polly, Pd; Jaramillo, Ca<space/></arg><arg name="title">Giant boid snake from the Palaeocene neotropics reveals hotter past equatorial temperatures<space/></arg><arg name="volume">457<space/></arg><arg name="issue">7230<space/></arg><arg name="pages">715–7<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0028-0836<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">19194448<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Nature</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2009Natur.457..715H<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>During the Eocene, plants and marine faunas became quite modern. Many modern<space/><link><target>Aves</target><part>bird</part></link><space/>orders first appeared in the Eocene.</paragraph><paragraph>Several rich fossil insect faunas are known from the Eocene, notably the<space/><link><target>Baltic amber</target></link><space/>found mainly along the south coast of the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target></link>, amber from the<space/><link><target>Paris Basin (geology)</target><part>Paris Basin</part></link>, France, the<space/><link><target>Fur Formation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Bembridge Marls</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Isle of Wight</target></link>, England. Insects found in Eocene deposits are mostly assignable to modern genera, though frequently these genera do not occur in the area at present. For instance the<space/><link><target>Bibionidae</target><part>bibionid</part></link><space/>genus<space/><italics><link><target>Plecia</target></link></italics><space/>is common in fossil faunas from presently temperate areas, but only lives in the tropics and subtropics today.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Oceans</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Basilosaurus BW.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>''Basilosaurus''</part></link><link><target>Image:Prorastomus BW.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>''<link><target>Prorastomus</target></link>'', an early<space/><link><target>sirenian</target></link></part></link>The Eocene oceans were warm and teeming with<space/><link><target>fish</target></link><space/>and other sea life. The first<space/><link><target>Carcharhiniformes</target><part>carcharinid sharks</part></link><space/>evolved, as did early marine mammals, including<space/><italics><link><target>Basilosaurus</target></link></italics>, an early species of<space/><link><target>whale</target></link><space/>that is thought to be descended from land animals that existed earlier in the Eocene, the<space/><link><target>hoof</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/><link><target>predator</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>called<space/><link><target>mesonychid</target><trail>s</trail></link>, of which<space/><italics><link><target>Mesonyx</target></link></italics><space/>was a member. The first<space/><link><target>sirenian</target><trail>s</trail></link>, relatives of the<space/><link><target>elephant</target><trail>s</trail></link>, also evolved at this time.</paragraph><heading level='2'>EoceneOligocene extinction</heading><paragraph>The end of the Eocene was marked by the<space/><link><target>EoceneOligocene extinction event</target></link>, also known as the<space/><italics>Grande Coupure</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>-</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>PaleoceneEocene Thermal Maximum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Green River Formation</target></link><space/>in western North America</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of fossil sites</target></link><space/><italics>(with link directory)</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>London Clay</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fur Formation</target></link><space/>in Denmark</listitem><listitem><link><target>Messel Pit</target></link><space/>in Germany</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bolca</target></link><space/>in Italy</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wadi Al-Hitan</target></link><space/>in Egypt</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg><arg name="refs">
<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ogg, Jim; June, 2004,<space/><italics>Overview of Global Boundary Stratotype Sections and Points (GSSP's)</italics><space/>http://www.stratigraphy.org/gssp.htm Accessed April 30, 2006.</listitem><listitem>Stanley, Steven M.<space/><italics>Earth System History.</italics><space/><link><target>New York</target></link>: W.H. Freeman and Company, 1999. ISBN 0-7167-2882-6</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Eocene</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource portal</target><arg>Cenozoic#Paleogene</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scotese.com/'>PaleoMap Project</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.palaeos.com/Cenozoic/Eocene/Eocene.htm'>Paleos Eocene page</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/change/deeptime/eocene.html'>PBS Deep Time: Eocene</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dmap.co.uk/fossils/'>Eocene and Oligocene Fossils</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sas.upenn.edu/earth/arctic/'>The UPenn Fossil Forest Project, focusing on the Eocene polar forests in Ellesmere Island, Canada</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://members.cox.net/pyrophyllite/Basilosaurus1.html'>Basilosaurus Primitive Eocene Whales</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oceansofkansas.com/Harlan1834b.html'>Basilosaurus - The plesiosaur that wasn't....</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jan.ucc.nau.edu/~rcb7/terpaleo.html'>Detailed maps of Tertiary Western North America</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scotese.com/newpage9.htm'>Map of Eocene Earth</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.foraminifera.eu/querydb.php?age=Eocene&amp;amp;aktion=suche'>Eocene Microfossils: 60+ images of Foraminifera</link></listitem><listitem>Eocene Epoch. (2011). In Encyclopdia Britannica. Retrieved from http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/189322/Eocene-Epoch</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Paleogene Footer</target></template><template><target>Geological history</target><arg>p</arg><arg>c</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Eocene</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Geological epochs</target></link><link><target>Category:Paleogene geochronology</target></link></paragraph></article>