<article title='Backplane'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><link><target>Image:PICMG-Backplane-Details.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>Major components on a PICMG 1.3 active backplane</part></link><link><target>File:PDP-8I-backplane.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Wire-wrapped backplane from a 1960s<space/><link><target>PDP-8</target></link><space/>minicomputer</part></link>A<space/><bold>backplane</bold><space/>(or &quot;backplane system&quot;) is a group of<space/><link><target>electrical connector</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in parallel with each other, so that each pin of each connector is linked to the same relative pin of all the other connectors, forming a<space/><link><target>computer bus</target></link>. It is used as a backbone to connect several printed circuit boards together to make up a complete<space/><link><target>computer system</target></link>. Backplanes commonly use a<space/><link><target>printed circuit board</target></link>, but<space/><link><target>wire-wrap</target><trail>ped</trail></link><space/>backplanes have also been used in<space/><link><target>minicomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and high-reliability applications.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Usage</heading><paragraph>Early microcomputer systems like the<space/><link><target>Altair 8800</target></link><space/>used a backplane for the processor and<space/><link><target>expansion card</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A backplane is generally differentiated from a motherboard by the lack of on-board processing and storage elements. A backplane uses plug-in cards for storage and processing.</paragraph><paragraph>Backplanes are normally used in preference to cables because of their greater<space/><link><target>Reliability engineering</target><part>reliability</part></link>. In a cabled system, the cables need to be flexed every time that a card is added or removed from the system; this flexing eventually causes mechanical failures. A backplane does not suffer from this problem, so its service life is limited only by the longevity of its connectors. For example, the<space/><link><target>DIN 41612</target></link><space/>connectors used in the<space/><link><target>VMEbus</target></link><space/>system can withstand 50 to 500 insertions and removals (called<space/><italics>mating cycles</italics>), depending on their quality. To transmit information, Serial Back-Plane technology uses a<space/><link><target>low voltage differential signaling</target></link><space/>transmission method for sending information.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Varnarvas</arg><arg name="first">Kosta</arg><arg name="title">Serial Back-Plane Technologies in Advanced Avionics Architectures</arg><arg name="url">http://hdl.handle.net/2060/20050215620</arg><arg name="work">NASA Technical Reports Server</arg><arg name="publisher">Marshall Space Flight Center</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 October 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In addition, there are bus expansion cables which will extend a computer bus to an external backplane, usually located in an enclosure, to provide more or different slots than the host computer provides. These cable sets have a transmitter board located in the computer, an expansion board in the remote backplane, and a cable between the two.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Active versus passive backplanes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:ISA-Backplane.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>ISA Passive Backplane showing connectors and parallel signal traces on back side. Only components are connectors, capacitors, resistors and voltage indicator LEDs.</part></link>Backplanes have grown in complexity from the simple<space/><link><target>Industry Standard Architecture</target></link><space/>(ISA) (used in the original<space/><link><target>IBM PC</target></link>) or<space/><link><target>S-100 bus</target><part>S-100</part></link><space/>style where all the connectors were connected to a common bus. Due to limitations inherent in the<space/><link><target>Peripheral Component Interconnect</target></link><space/>(PCI) specification for driving slots, backplanes are now offered as<space/><bold>passive</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>active</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>True passive backplanes offer no active bus driving circuitry. Any desired arbitration logic is placed on the daughter cards. Active backplanes include chips which<space/><link><target>Buffer (computer science)</target><part>buffer</part></link><space/>the various signals to the slots.</paragraph><paragraph>The distinction between the two isn't always clear, but may become an important issue if a whole system is expected to not have a<space/><link><target>single point of failure</target></link><space/>(SPOF). A passive backplane, even if it<space/><italics>is</italics><space/>single, is not usually considered a SPOF. Active backplanes are more complicated and thus have a non-zero risk of malfunction.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Backplanes versus motherboards</heading><paragraph>When a backplane is used with a plug-in<space/><link><target>single board computer</target></link><space/>(SBC) or<space/><link><target>System Host Board</target><part>system host board</part></link><space/>(SHB), the combination provides the same functionality as a<space/><link><target>motherboard</target></link>, providing processing power, memory, I/O and slots for plug-in cards. While there are a few motherboards that offer more than 8 slots, that is the traditional limit. In addition, as technology progresses, the availability and number of a particular slot type may be limited in terms of what is currently offered by motherboard manufacturers.</paragraph><paragraph>However, backplane architecture is somewhat unrelated to the SBC technology plugged into it. There are some limitations to what can be constructed, in that the SBC chip set and processor have to provide the capability of supporting the slot types. In addition, virtually an unlimited number of slots can be provided with 20, including the SBC slot, as a practical though not an absolute limit. Thus, a PICMG backplane can provide any number and any mix of ISA, PCI, PCI-X, and PCI-e slots, limited only by the ability of the SBC to interface to and drive those slots. For example, an SBC with the latest i7 processor could interface with a backplane providing up to 19 ISA slots to drive legacy I/O cards.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Butterfly backplanes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Butterfly-backplane-annotated.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>PICMG 1.3 Butterfly Backplane Showing Both Sides</part></link>Some backplanes are constructed with slots on both sides. These are not the same as midplane backplanes. A butterfly backplane is typically constructed to maximize the number of slots for the least vertical height. The backplane would be mounted vertically in a chassis oriented front to back and the plug-in SBC and cards would lay flat, protruding out both sides of the backplane. This, for example, allows the use of up to four full height boards in a 2U chassis.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Midplane</heading><paragraph>Some backplanes are constructed with slots for connecting to devices on both sides, and are referred to as midplanes. This ability to plug cards into either side of a midplane is often useful in larger systems made up primarily of modules attached to the midplane.</paragraph><paragraph>Midplanes are often used in computers, mostly in<space/><link><target>blade server</target><trail>s</trail></link>, where server blades reside on one side and the peripheral (power, networking, and other I/O) and service modules reside on the other.Midplanes are also popular in networking and telecommunications equipment where one side of the chassis accepts system processing cards and the other side of the chassis accepts network interface cards.</paragraph><paragraph>Orthogonal midplanes connect vertical cards on one side to horizontal boards on the other side.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kevin OConnor.<link type='external' href='http://www.ecnmag.com/articles/2010/12/orthogonal-backplane-connector-technology-offers-design-flexibility'>&quot;Orthogonal Backplane Connector Technology Offers Design Flexibility&quot;</link>.2010.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Pete.<link type='external' href='http://www.connector.com/2011/02/high-speed-orthogonal-connectors-optimize-signal-integrity/'>&quot;High-Speed Orthogonal Connectors Optimize Signal Integrity&quot;</link>.2011.</extension>One common orthogonal midplane connects many vertical telephone<space/><link><target>line card</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on one side, each one connected to copper telephone wires, to a horizontal communications card on the other side.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fci.com/en/products/backplane-connectors/airmax-vs-backplane/airmax-vs-orthogonal.html'>&quot;AirMax VS Orthogonal&quot;</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A &quot;virtual midplane&quot; is an imaginary plane between vertical cards on one side that directly connect to horizontal boards on the other side; the card-slot aligners of the card cage and self-aligning connectors on the cards hold the cards in position.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Fowler.<link type='external' href='http://electronicdesign.com/boards/virtual-midplane-realizes-ultrafast-card-interconnects'>&quot;Virtual Midplane Realizes Ultrafast Card Interconnects&quot;</link>.Electronic Design.2002.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some people use the term &quot;midplane&quot; to describe a board that sits between and connects a hard drive hot-swap backplane and redundant power supplies.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://h20000.www2.hp.com/bizsupport/TechSupport/Document.jsp?lang=en&amp;amp;cc=us&amp;amp;objectID=c00881823&amp;amp;jumpid=reg_r1002_usen_c-001_title_r0001'>&quot;HP StorageWorks Modular Smart Array 70 Enclosure - Replacing the Backplane&quot;</link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://download.intel.com/support/motherboards/server/s5520ur/sb/r2612ur_service_guide_14.pdf'>&quot;Intel Server System SR2612UR Service Guide&quot;</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>STORAGE</arg><arg>Backplanes in storage</arg></template>Backplanes in storage</heading><paragraph>Servers commonly have a backplane to attach hot swappable hard drives; backplane pins pass directly into hard drive sockets without cables. They may have single connector to connect one<space/><link><target>disk array controller</target></link><space/>or multiple connectors that can be connected to one or more controllers in arbitrary way. Backplanes are commonly found in<space/><link><target>disk enclosure</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>disk array</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>Server (computing)</target><part>server</part><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Backplanes for SAS and SATA HDDs most commonly use the<space/><link><target>SGPIO</target></link><space/>protocol as means of communication between the<space/><link><target>host adapter</target></link><space/>and the backplane. Alternatively<space/><link><target>SCSI Enclosure Services</target></link><space/>can be used. With<space/><link><target>Parallel SCSI</target></link><space/>subsystems,<space/><link><target>SAF-TE</target></link><space/>is used.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Platforms</heading><heading level='3'>PICMG</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:SBC-Backplane.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>A<space/><link><target>single-board computer</target></link><space/>installed into a<space/><link><target>#Active versus passive backplanes</target><part>passive</part></link><space/>backplane</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>PICMG<space/></arg></template>A single-board computer meeting the PICMG 1.3 specification and compatible with a PICMG 1.3 backplane is referred to as a<space/><link><target>system host board</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Intel Single Board Computer world,<space/><link><target>PICMG</target></link><space/>provides standards for the backplane interface:<link><target>PICMG 1.0</target></link>, 1.1 and 1.2<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.picmgeu.org/specs/available_specifications.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">PICMG 1.0, 1.1 and 1.2<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Picmgeu.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-09-20</arg></template></extension><space/>provide ISA and PCI support, with 1.2 adding PCIX support.PICMG 1.3<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.picmgeu.org/specs/available_specifications.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">PICMG 1.3<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Picmgeu.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-09-20</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.picmg.org/v2internal/SHB_Express.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">PICMG 1.3 SHB Express Resources<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Picmg.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-09-20</arg></template></extension><space/>provides PCI-Express support.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Motherboard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Switched fabric</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Daughterboard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>M-Module</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>SS-50 Bus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>STD Bus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>STEbus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Eurocard (printed circuit board)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>VXI</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Backplanes</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Computer buses</target></link></paragraph></article>