<article title='Caravaggio'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Infobox artist ii</target><arg name="name"><space/>Caravaggio
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Bild-Ottavio Leoni, Caravaggio.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Chalk portrait of Caravaggio by [[Ottavio Leoni]], circa 1621.
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Michelangelo Merisi or Amerighi
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1571|09|29|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Milan]], [[Lombardy]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1610|07|18|1571|09|29|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Porto Ercole]], [[Tuscany]]
</arg><arg name="field"><space/>[[Painting]]
</arg><arg name="training">
</arg><arg name="movement"><space/>[[Baroque]]
</arg><arg name="works"><space/>See [[Chronology of works by Caravaggio]]
</arg><arg name="patrons"><space/>Cardinal [[Francesco Maria del Monte]]<br>[[Alof de Wignacourt]]
</arg><arg name="awards">
</arg></template><bold>Michelangelo Merisi</bold><space/>(<bold>Michael Angelo Merigi</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Amerighi</bold>)<space/><bold>da Caravaggio</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>karaˈvaddʒo</arg></template>; 29 September 1571 in<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>18 July? 1610) was an<space/><link><target>list of Italian painters</target><part>Italian painter</part></link><space/>active in<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Naples</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Malta</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Sicily</target></link><space/>between 1592 (1595?) and 1610. His paintings, which combine a realistic observation of the human state, both physical and emotional, with a dramatic use of lighting, had a formative influence on<space/><link><target>Baroque painting</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Vincenzio Fanti</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Descrizzione Completa di Tutto Ciò che Ritrovasi nella Galleria di Sua Altezza Giuseppe Wenceslao del S.R.I. Principe Regnante della Casa di Lichtenstein<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1767<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Trattner<space/></arg><arg name="page">21<space/></arg><arg name="language">Italian</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gettyimages.it/detail/fotografie-di-cronaca/italian-painter-michelangelo-amerighi-da-fotografie-di-cronaca/2636291<space/></arg><arg name="title">Italian Painter Michelangelo Amerighi da Caravaggio<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Gettyimages.it<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-20</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.getty.edu/vow/ULANFullDisplay?find</arg><arg name="title">Caravaggio, Michelangelo Merisi da (Italian painter, 1571-1610)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Getty.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio trained as a painter in<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Simone Peterzano</target></link><space/>who had himself trained under<space/><link><target>Titian</target></link>. In his twenties Caravaggio moved to Rome where there was a demand for paintings to fill the many huge new churches and<space/><link><target>palazzo</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>being built at the time. It was also a period when the Church was searching for a stylistic alternative to<space/><link><target>Mannerism</target></link><space/>in religious art that was tasked to<space/><link><target>Counter-Reformation</target><part>counter the threat of Protestantism</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harris, Ann Sutherland, Seventeenth-century Art &amp; Architecture (Upper Saddle River: Pearson/Prentice Hall, 2008).</extension><space/>Caravaggio's innovation was a radical<space/><link><target>Naturalism (art)</target><part>naturalism</part></link><space/>that combined close physical observation with a dramatic, even theatrical, use of<space/><link><target>chiaroscuro</target></link><space/>which came to be known as<space/><link><target>tenebrism</target></link><space/>(the shift from light to dark with little intermediate value).</paragraph><paragraph>He burst upon the Rome art scene in 1600 with the success of his first public commissions, the<space/><italics><link><target>The Martyrdom of Saint Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>Martyrdom of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Calling of St Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>Calling of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics>. Thereafter he never lacked commissions or patrons, yet he handled his success poorly. He was jailed on several occasions, vandalized his own apartment, and ultimately had a death warrant issued for him by the Pope after killing a young man, possibly unintentionally, on May 29, 1606.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Watkins<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ally<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.artinfo.com/news/story/37059/caravaggios-rap-sheet-reveals-him-to-have-been-a-lawless-sword-obsessed-wildman-and-a-terrible-renter/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Caravaggio's Rap Sheet Reveals Him to Have Been a Lawless Sword-Obsessed Wildman, and a Terrible Renter<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Artinfo<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-02-24<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An early published notice on him, dating from 1604 and describing his lifestyle three years previously, recounts that &quot;after a fortnight's work he will swagger about for a month or two with a sword at his side and a servant following him, from one ball-court to the next, ever ready to engage in a fight or an argument, so that it is most awkward to get along with him.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Floris Claes van Dijk, a contemporary of Caravaggio in Rome in 1601, quoted in John Gash, &quot;Caravaggio&quot;, p.13. The quotation originates in<space/><link><target>Karel van Mander</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Het Schilder-Boek</italics><space/>of 1604, translated in full in Howard Hibbard, &quot;Caravaggio&quot;. The first reference to Caravaggio in a contemporary document from Rome is the listing of his name, with that of Prospero Orsi as his partner, as an 'assistente' in a procession in October 1594 in honour of St. Luke (see H. Waga &quot;Vita nota e ignota dei virtuosi al Pantheon&quot; Rome 1992, Appendix I, pp.219 and 220ff). The earliest informative account of his life in the city is a court transcript dated 11 July 1597, when Caravaggio and Prospero Orsi were witnesses to a crime near San Luigi de' Francesi. (See &quot;The earliest account of Caravaggio in Rome&quot; Sandro Corradini and Maurizio Marini,<space/><link><target>The Burlington Magazine</target></link>, pp.2528).</extension><space/>In 1606 he killed a young man in a brawl and fled from Rome with a price on his head. He was involved in a brawl in Malta in 1608, and another in Naples in 1609, possibly a deliberate attempt on his life by unidentified enemies. This encounter left him severely injured. A year later, at the age of 38, he died under mysterious circumstances in<space/><link><target>Porto Ercole</target></link><space/>in Tuscany, reportedly from a fever while on his way to Rome to receive a pardon.</paragraph><paragraph>Famous while he lived, Caravaggio was forgotten almost immediately after his death, and it was only in the 20th century that his importance to the development of Western art was rediscovered. Despite this, his influence on the new Baroque style that eventually emerged from the ruins of Mannerism was profound. It can be seen directly or indirectly in the work of<space/><link><target>Rubens</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jusepe de Ribera</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bernini</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Rembrandt</target></link>, and artists in the following generation heavily under his influence were called the &quot;Caravaggisti&quot; or &quot;Caravagesques&quot;, as well as tenebrists or<space/><italics>tenebrosi</italics><space/>(&quot;shadowists&quot;). The 20th-century art historian Andr Berne-Joffroy claimed: &quot;What begins in the work of Caravaggio is, quite simply, modern painting.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Gilles Lambert, &quot;Caravaggio&quot;, p.8.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Early life (15711592)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy-Caravaggio (c.1595).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy'' (c.1595)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio (Michelangelo Merisi or Amerighi) was born in<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>where his father, Fermo (Fermo Merixio), was a household administrator and architect-decorator to the Marchese of<space/><link><target>Caravaggio, Lombardy</target><part>Caravaggio</part></link>, a town not far from the city of<space/><link><target>Bergamo</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Confirmed by the finding of the baptism certificate from the Milanese parish of Santo Stefano in Brolo</arg><arg name="url">http://www.italica.rai.it/index.php?categoria</arg><arg name="publisher">Italica.rai.it</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension><space/>His mother, Lucia Aratori (Lutia de Oratoribus), came from a propertied family of the same district.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">That Terrible Shadowing: The Quest Across Time for Caravaggio's Killer<space/></arg><arg name="author">David Stedman<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">books.google.com<space/></arg><arg name="pages">183, 447<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1848761315<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1576 the family moved to Caravaggio (Caravaggius) to escape a plague which ravaged Milan, and Caravaggio's father died there in 1577.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ParisArtStudies"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.parisartstudies.com/index2.php?option</arg><arg name="title">Paris Art Studies Caravaggio<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">parisartstudies.com<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009</arg></template></extension><space/>It is assumed that the artist grew up in Caravaggio, but his family kept up connections with the<space/><link><target>Sforza</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and with the powerful<space/><link><target>Colonna family</target></link>, who were allied by marriage with the Sforzas and destined to play a major role later in Caravaggio's life.</paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio's mother died in 1584, the same year he began his four-year apprenticeship to the Milanese painter<space/><link><target>Simone Peterzano</target></link>, described in the contract of apprenticeship as a pupil of<space/><link><target>Titian</target></link>. Caravaggio appears to have stayed in the Milan-Caravaggio area after his apprenticeship ended, but it is possible that he visited<space/><link><target>Venice</target></link><space/>and saw the works of<space/><link><target>Giorgione</target></link>, whom<space/><link><target>Federico Zuccari</target></link><space/>later accused him of imitating, and<space/><link><target>Titian</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harris, p. 21.</extension><space/>He would also have become familiar with the art treasures of Milan, including<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Last Supper (Leonardo)</target><part>Last Supper</part></link></italics>, and with the regional Lombard art, a style which valued simplicity and attention to<space/><link><target>Naturalism (visual art)</target><part>naturalistic</part></link><space/>detail and was closer to the naturalism of Germany than to the stylised formality and grandeur of Roman<space/><link><target>Mannerism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rosa Giorgi, &quot;Caravaggio: Master of light and dark his life in paintings&quot;, p.12.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Rome (1592/951600)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio - I Musici.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>The Musicians (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Musicians</part></link>'', 15951596,<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New York</target></link>.</part></link>Caravaggio left Milan for Rome in 1592, in flight after &quot;certain quarrels&quot; and the wounding of a police officer. He arrived in Rome &quot;naked and extremely needy ... without fixed address and without provision ... short of money.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted without attribution in Robb, p.35, apparently based on the three primary sources, Mancini, Baglione and Bellori, all of whom depict Caravaggio's early Roman years as a period of extreme poverty (see references below).</extension><space/>A few months later he was performing hack-work for the highly successful<space/><link><target>Giuseppe Cesari</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pope Clement VIII</target></link>'s favourite artist, &quot;painting flowers and fruit&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Giovanni Pietro Bellori,<space/><italics>Le Vite de' pittori, scultori, et architetti moderni</italics>, 1672: &quot;Michele was forced by necessity to enter the services of Cavalier Giuseppe d'Arpino, by whom he was employed to paint flowers and fruits so realistically that they began to attain the higher beauty that we love so much today.&quot;</extension><space/>in his factory-like workshop. Known works from this period include a small<space/><italics><link><target>Boy Peeling Fruit (Caravaggio)</target><part>Boy Peeling a Fruit</part></link></italics><space/>(his earliest known painting), a<space/><italics><link><target>Boy with a Basket of Fruit</target></link></italics>, and the<space/><italics><link><target>Young Sick Bacchus</target></link></italics>, supposedly a self-portrait done during convalescence from a serious illness that ended his employment with Cesari. All three demonstrate the physical particularity for which Caravaggio was to become renowned: the fruit-basket-boy's produce has been analysed by a professor of horticulture, who was able to identify individual cultivars right down to &quot;... a large fig leaf with a prominent fungal scorch lesion resembling<space/><link><target>anthracnose</target></link><space/>(<italics>Glomerella cingulata</italics>).&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hort.purdue.edu/newcrop/caravaggio/caravaggio_l.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Caravaggio<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hort.purdue.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension><link><target>File:Canestra di frutta (Caravaggio).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>Basket of Fruit (Caravaggio)</target><part>Basket of Fruit</part></link>,'' c. 15951596, oil on canvas,<space/><link><target>Pinacoteca Ambrosiana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio left Cesari, determined to make his own way. At this point he forged some extremely important friendships, with the painter<space/><link><target>Prospero Orsi</target></link>, the architect<space/><link><target>Onorio Longhi</target></link>, and the sixteen-year-old<space/><link><target>Sicily</target><part>Sicilian</part></link><space/>artist<space/><link><target>Mario Minniti</target></link>. Orsi, established in the profession, introduced him to influential collectors; Longhi, more balefully, introduced him to the world of Roman street-brawls; and Minniti served as a model and, years later, would be instrumental in helping Caravaggio to important commissions in Sicily.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catherine Puglisi, &quot;Caravaggio&quot;, p.79. Longhi was with Caravaggio on the night of the fatal brawl with Tomassoni; Robb, &quot;M&quot;, p.341, believes that Minniti was as well.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>The Fortune Teller (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Fortune Teller</part></link></italics>, his first composition with more than one figure, shows Mario being cheated by a gypsy girl. The theme was quite new for Rome, and proved immensely influential over the next century and beyond. This, however, was in the future: at the time, Caravaggio sold it for practically nothing.<space/><italics><link><target>Cardsharps</target><part>The Cardsharps</part></link></italics><space/>showing another nave youth of privilege falling the victim of card cheats is even more psychologically complex, and perhaps Caravaggio's first true masterpiece. Like the<space/><italics><link><target>The Fortune Teller (Caravaggio)</target><part>Fortune Teller</part></link></italics>, it was immensely popular, and over 50 copies survive. More importantly, it attracted the patronage of<space/><link><target>cardinal (Catholicism)</target><part>Cardinal</part></link><space/><link><target>Francesco Maria del Monte</target></link>, one of the leading connoisseurs in Rome. For Del Monte and his wealthy art-loving circle, Caravaggio executed a number of intimate chamber-pieces<space/><italics><link><target>The Musicians (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Musicians</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Lute Player (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Lute Player</part></link></italics>, a tipsy<space/><italics><link><target>Bacchus (Caravaggio)</target><part>Bacchus</part></link></italics>, an allegorical but realistic<space/><italics><link><target>Boy Bitten by a Lizard (Caravaggio)</target><part>Boy Bitten by a Lizard</part></link></italics><space/>featuring Minniti and other adolescent models.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio Judith Beheading Holofernes.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''<link><target>Judith Beheading Holofernes (Caravaggio)</target><part>Judith Beheading Holofernes</part></link>'' 15981599.<space/><link><target>Galleria Nazionale d'Arte Antica</target></link>, Rome.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The realism returned with Caravaggio's first paintings on religious themes, and the emergence of remarkable spirituality. The first of these was the<space/><italics><link><target>Penitent Magdalene (Caravaggio)</target><part>Penitent Magdalene</part></link></italics>, showing<space/><link><target>Mary Magdalene</target></link><space/>at the moment when she has turned from her life as a courtesan and sits weeping on the floor, her jewels scattered around her. &quot;It seemed not a religious painting at all ... a girl sitting on a low wooden stool drying her hair ... Where was the repentance ... suffering ... promise of salvation?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Robb, p.79. Robb is drawing on Bellori, who praises Caravaggio's &quot;true&quot; colours but finds the naturalism offensive: &quot;He (Caravaggio) was satisfied with [the] invention of nature without further exercising his brain.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It was understated, in the Lombard manner, not histrionic in the Roman manner of the time. It was followed by others in the same style:<space/><italics><link><target>Saint Catherine (Caravaggio)</target><part>Saint Catherine</part></link></italics>;<space/><italics><link><target>Martha and Mary Magdalene (Caravaggio)</target><part>Martha and Mary Magdalene</part></link></italics>;<space/><italics><link><target>Judith Beheading Holofernes (Caravaggio)</target><part>Judith Beheading Holofernes</part></link></italics>; a<space/><italics><link><target>Sacrifice of Isaac (Caravaggio)</target><part>Sacrifice of Isaac</part></link></italics>; a<space/><italics><link><target>Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy (Caravaggio)</target><part>Saint Francis of Assisi in Ecstasy</part></link></italics>; and a<space/><italics><link><target>Rest on the Flight into Egypt (Caravaggio)</target><part>Rest on the Flight into Egypt</part></link></italics>. The works, while viewed by a comparatively limited circle, increased Caravaggio's fame with both connoisseurs and his fellow artists. But a true reputation would depend on public commissions, and for these it was necessary to look to the Church.</paragraph><paragraph>Already evident was the intense realism or naturalism for which Caravaggio is now famous. He preferred to paint his subjects as the eye sees them, with all their natural flaws and defects instead of as idealised creations. This allowed a full display of Caravaggio's virtuosic talents. This shift from accepted standard practice and the classical idealism of<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link><space/>was very controversial at the time. Not only was his realism a noteworthy feature of his paintings during this period, he turned away from the lengthy preparations traditional in central Italy at the time. Instead, he preferred the Venetian practice of working in oils directly from the subject half-length figures and still life. One of the characteristic paintings by Caravaggio at this time which gives a good demonstration of his virtuoso talent was his work<space/><italics><link><target>Supper at Emmaus (Caravaggio), London</target><part>Supper at Emmaus</part></link></italics><space/>from c.16001601.</paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Most famous painter in Rome&quot; (16001606)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Calling of Saint Matthew-Caravaggo (1599-1600).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>The Calling of St Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Calling of Saint Matthew</part></link>'' (15991600).<space/><link><target>Contarelli Chapel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>San Luigi dei Francesi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>. The beam of light, which enters the picture from the direction of a real window, expresses in the blink of an eye the conversion of St Matthew, the hinge on which his destiny will turn, with no flying angels, parting clouds or other artifacts.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1599, presumably through the influence of Del Monte, Caravaggio was contracted to decorate the<space/><link><target>Contarelli Chapel</target></link><space/>in the church of<space/><link><target>San Luigi dei Francesi</target></link>. The two works making up the commission, the<space/><italics><link><target>The Martyrdom of Saint Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>Martyrdom of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Calling of St Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>Calling of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics>, delivered in 1600, were an immediate sensation. Caravaggio's<space/><link><target>tenebrism</target></link><space/>(a heightened<space/><link><target>chiaroscuro</target></link>) brought high drama to his subjects, while his acutely observed realism brought a new level of emotional intensity. Opinion among Caravaggio's artist peers was polarized. Some denounced him for various perceived failings, notably his insistence on painting from life, without drawings, but for the most part he was hailed as a great artistic visionary: &quot;The painters then in Rome were greatly taken by this novelty, and the young ones particularly gathered around him, praised him as the unique imitator of nature, and looked on his work as miracles.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Bellori. The passage continues: &quot;[The younger painters] outdid each other in copying him, undressing their models and raising their lights; and rather than setting out to learn from study and instruction, each readily found in the streets or squares of Rome both masters and models for copying nature.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio went on to secure a string of prestigious commissions for religious works featuring violent struggles, grotesque decapitations, torture and death, most notable and most technically masterful among them<space/><italics><link><target>The Taking of Christ (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Taking of Christ</part></link></italics><space/>of circa 1602 for the Mattei Family, recently rediscovered in Ireland after two centuries. For the most part each new painting increased his fame, but a few were rejected by the various bodies for whom they were intended, at least in their original forms, and had to be re-painted or find new buyers. The essence of the problem was that while Caravaggio's dramatic intensity was appreciated, his realism was seen by some as unacceptably vulgar.<extension extension_name='ref'>For an outline of the Counter-Reformation Church's policy on decorum in art, see Giorgi, p.80. For a more detailed discussion, see Gash, p.8ff; and for a discussion of the part played by notions of decorum in the rejection of &quot;St Matthew and the Angel&quot; and &quot;Death of the Virgin&quot;, see Puglisi, pp.179188.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>His first version of<space/><italics><link><target>Saint Matthew and the Angel (Caravaggio)</target><part>Saint Matthew and the Angel</part></link></italics>, featured the saint as a bald peasant with dirty legs attended by a lightly clad over-familiar boy-angel, was rejected and a second version had to be painted as<space/><italics><link><target>The Inspiration of Saint Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Inspiration of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics>. Similarly,<space/><italics><link><target>The Conversion of Saint Paul (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Conversion of Saint Paul</part></link></italics><space/>was rejected, and while another version of the same subject, the<space/><italics><link><target>Conversion on the Way to Damascus</target></link></italics>, was accepted, it featured the saint's horse's haunches far more prominently than the saint himself, prompting this exchange between the artist and an exasperated official of<space/><link><target>Santa Maria del Popolo</target></link>: &quot;Why have you put a horse in the middle, and<space/><link><target>Paul of Tarsus</target><part>Saint Paul</part></link><space/>on the ground?&quot; &quot;Because!&quot; &quot;Is the horse God?&quot; &quot;No, but he stands in God's light!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted without attribution in Lambert, p.66.</extension><link><target>File:Martirio di San Pietro September 2015-1a.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''<link><target>Crucifixion of St. Peter (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Crucifixion of Saint Peter</part></link>'', 1601.<space/><link><target>Cerasi Chapel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Santa Maria del Popolo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Other works included<space/><italics><link><target>The Entombment of Christ (Caravaggio)</target><part>Entombment</part></link></italics>, the<space/><italics><link><target>Madonna di Loreto (Caravaggio)</target><part>Madonna di Loreto</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>Madonna of the Pilgrims</italics>), the<space/><italics><link><target>Madonna and Child with St. Anne (Dei Palafrenieri) (Caravaggio)</target><part>Grooms' Madonna</part></link></italics>, and the<space/><italics><link><target>Death of the Virgin (Caravaggio)</target><part>Death of the Virgin</part></link></italics>. The history of these last two paintings illustrates the reception given to some of Caravaggio's art, and the times in which he lived. The<space/><italics><link><target>Madonna and Child with St. Anne (Dei Palafrenieri) (Caravaggio)</target><part>Grooms' Madonna</part></link></italics>, also known as<space/><italics>Madonna dei palafrenieri</italics>, painted for a small altar in Saint Peter's Basilica in Rome, remained there for just two days, and was then taken off. A cardinal's secretary wrote: &quot;In this painting there are but vulgarity, sacrilege, impiousness and disgust...One would say it is a work made by a painter that can paint well, but of a dark spirit, and who has been for a lot of time far from God, from His adoration, and from any good thought...&quot;The<space/><italics><link><target>Death of the Virgin (Caravaggio)</target><part>Death of the Virgin</part></link></italics>, then, commissioned in 1601 by a wealthy jurist for his private chapel in the new Carmelite church of Santa Maria della Scala, was rejected by the Carmelites in 1606. Caravaggio's contemporary<space/><link><target>Giulio Mancini</target></link><space/>records that it was rejected because Caravaggio had used a well-known prostitute as his model for the Virgin.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mancini: &quot;Thus one can understand how badly some modern artists paint, such as those who, wishing to portray the Virgin Our Lady, depict some dirty prostitute from the Ortaccio, as Michelangelo da Caravaggio did in the Death of the Virgin in that painting for the Madonna della Scala, which for that very reason those good fathers rejected it, and perhaps that poor man suffered so much trouble in his lifetime.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Giovanni Baglione</target></link>, another contemporary, tells us it was due to Mary's bare legs<extension extension_name='ref'>Baglione: &quot;For the [church of] Madonna della Scala in Trastevere he painted the death of the Madonna, but because he had portrayed the Madonna with little decorum, swollen and with bare legs, it was taken away, and the Duke of Mantua bought it and placed it in his most noble gallery.&quot;</extension><space/>a matter of decorum in either case. Caravaggio scholar John Gash suggests that the problem for the Carmelites may have been theological rather than aesthetic, in that Caravaggio's version fails to assert the doctrine of the<space/><link><target>Assumption of Mary</target></link>, the idea that the Mother of God did not die in any ordinary sense but was assumed into Heaven. The replacement altarpiece commissioned (from one of Caravaggio's most able followers,<space/><link><target>Carlo Saraceni</target></link>), showed the Virgin not dead, as Caravaggio had painted her, but seated and dying; and even this was rejected, and replaced with a work which showed the Virgin not dying, but ascending into Heaven with choirs of angels. In any case, the rejection did not mean that Caravaggio or his paintings were out of favour. The<space/><italics>Death of the Virgin</italics><space/>was no sooner taken out of the church than it was purchased by the Duke of Mantua, on the advice of<space/><link><target>Peter Paul Rubens</target><part>Rubens</part></link>, and later acquired by<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target></link><space/>before entering the French royal collection in 1671.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Amor Vincet Omnia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>Amor Vincit Omnia (Caravaggio)</target><part>Amor Vincit Omnia</part></link>''. 16011602.<space/><link><target>Gemldegalerie (Berlin)</target><part>Gemldegalerie</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Berlin</target></link>. Caravaggio shows<space/><link><target>Cupid</target></link><space/>prevailing over all human endeavors: war, music, science, government.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>One secular piece from these years is<space/><italics><link><target>Amor Vincit Omnia (Caravaggio)</target><part>Amor Victorious</part></link></italics>, painted in 1602 for<space/><link><target>Vincenzo Giustiniani</target></link>, a member of Del Monte's circle. The model was named in a memoir of the early 17th century as &quot;Cecco&quot;, the diminutive for Francesco. He is possibly Francesco Boneri, identified with an artist active in the period 16101625 and known as<space/><link><target>Cecco del Caravaggio</target></link><space/>('Caravaggio's Cecco'),<extension extension_name='ref'>While Gianni Papi's identification of Cecco del Caravaggio as Francesco Boneri is widely accepted, the evidence connecting Boneri to Caravaggio's servant and model in the early 17th century is circumstantial. See Robb, pp193196.</extension><space/>carrying a bow and arrows and trampling symbols of the warlike and peaceful arts and sciences underfoot. He is unclothed, and it is difficult to accept this grinning urchin as the Roman god<space/><link><target>Cupid</target></link><space/>as difficult as it was to accept Caravaggio's other semi-clad adolescents as the various angels he painted in his canvases, wearing much the same stage-prop wings. The point, however, is the intense yet ambiguous reality of the work: it is simultaneously Cupid and Cecco, as Caravaggio's Virgins were simultaneously the Mother of Christ and the Roman courtesans who modeled for them.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:San Gerolamo (Caravaggio) September 2015-1a.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''St. Jerome'', 16051606,<space/><link><target>Galleria Borghese</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Exile and death (16061610)</heading><paragraph>Caravaggio led a tumultuous life. He was notorious for brawling, even in a time and place when such behavior was commonplace, and the transcripts of his police records and trial proceedings fill several pages. On 29 May 1606, he killed, possibly unintentionally, a young man named Ranuccio Tomassoni from<space/><link><target>Terni</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Umbria</target></link>). The circumstances of the brawl and the death of Ranuccio Tomassoni remain mysterious. Several contemporary<space/><italics>avvisi</italics><space/>referred to a quarrel over a gambling debt and a tennis game, and this explanation has become established in the popular imagination.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Life of Caravaggio"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Baglione</arg><arg name="first">Giovanni<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Giovanni Baglione</arg><arg name="title">Life of Caravaggio</arg><arg name="year">1642</arg><arg name="location">Italy</arg><arg name="url">http://caravaggio.com/preview/attach/data01/D000001.htm</arg></template><space/>Because of the excessive ardour of his spirit Michelangelo was a little wild and he sometimes looked for the chance to break his neck or to risk the lives of others. People as quarrelsome as he were often to be found in his company: and having in the end confronted Ranuccio Tomassoni a well-mannered young man over some disagreement about a tennis match they challenged one another to a duel. After Ranuccio fell to the ground Michelangelo struck him with the point of his sword and having wounded him in the thigh killed him.</extension><space/>But recent scholarship has made it clear that more was involved. Good modern accounts are to be found in<space/><link><target>Peter Robb</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>M (Peter Robb book)</target><part>M</part></link></italics><space/>and Helen Langdon's<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A Life</italics>. An interesting theory relating the death to Renaissance notions of honour and symbolic wounding has been advanced by art historian<space/><link><target>Andrew Graham-Dixon</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Milner<space/></arg><arg name="first">Catherine<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/italy/1396127/Red-blooded-Caravaggio-killed-love-rival-in-bungled-castration-attempt.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">'Red-blooded Caravaggio killed love rival in bungled castration attempt'<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Telegraph.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">2002-06-02<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-03-17<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>Previously his high-placed patrons had protected him from the consequences of his escapades, but this time they could do nothing. Caravaggio, outlawed, fled to<space/><link><target>Naples</target></link>. There, outside the jurisdiction of the Roman authorities and protected by the Colonna family, the most famous painter in Rome became the most famous in Naples. His connections with the<space/><link><target>Colonna family</target><part>Colonnas</part></link><space/>led to a stream of important church commissions, including the<space/><italics><link><target>Madonna of the Rosary (Caravaggio)</target><part>Madonna of the Rosary</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>The Seven Works of Mercy (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Seven Works of Mercy</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>In 1606, following the death of Tomassoni, he fled first to the Colonna estates south of Rome, then on to Naples where Costanza Colonna Sforza, widow of Francesco Sforza, in whose husband's household Caravaggio's father had held a position, maintained a palace. Costanza's brother Ascanio was Cardinal-Protector of the Kingdom of Naples, another brother, Marzio, was an advisor to the Spanish Viceroy, and a sister was married into the important Neapolitan Carafa familyconnections which might help explain the cornucopia of major commissions which fell into Caravaggio's lap in that city. Costanza's son Fabrizio Sforza Colonna, Knight of Malta and general of the Order's galleys, appears to have facilitated his arrival in the island in 1607 and his escape the next year, and he stayed in Costanza's Neapolitan palazzo on his return there in 1609. These connections are treated in most biographies and studiessee, for example, Catherine Puglisi, &quot;Caravaggio&quot;, p.258, for a brief outline. Helen Langdon, &quot;Caravaggio: A Life&quot;, ch.12 and 15, and Peter Robb, &quot;M&quot;, pp.398ff and 459ff, give a fuller account.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite his success in Naples, after only a few months in the city Caravaggio left for<space/><link><target>Malta</target></link>, the headquarters of the<space/><link><target>Knights Hospitaller</target><part>Knights of Malta</part></link>, presumably hoping that the patronage of<space/><link><target>Alof de Wignacourt</target></link>, Grand Master of the Knights, could help him secure a pardon for Tomassoni's death. De Wignacourt proved so impressed at having the famous artist as official painter to the Order that he inducted him as a knight, and the early biographer Bellori records that the artist was well pleased with his success. Major works from his Malta period include a huge<space/><italics><link><target>The Beheading of Saint John the Baptist (Caravaggio)</target><part>Beheading of Saint John the Baptist</part></link></italics><space/>(the only painting to which he put his signature) and a<space/><italics><link><target>Portrait of Alof de Wignacourt and his Page</target></link></italics>, as well as portraits of other leading knights. Yet by late August 1608 he was arrested and imprisoned. The circumstances surrounding this abrupt change of fortune have long been a matter of speculation, but recent investigation has revealed it to have been the result of yet another brawl, during which the door of a house was battered down and a knight seriously wounded.<extension extension_name='ref'>The discovery of the evidence for this brawl was reported by Dr Keith Sciberras of the University of Malta, in &quot;Frater Michael Angelus in tumultu: the cause of Caravaggio's imprisonment in Malta&quot;,<space/><italics>The Burlington Magazine</italics>, CXLV, April 2002, pp.229232, and &quot;Riflessioni su Malta al tempo del Caravaggio&quot;,<space/><italics>Paragone Arte</italics>, Anno LII N.629, July 2002, pp.320. Sciberras' findings are summarised online at<space/><link type='external' href='http://caravaggio.com/preview/attach/data01/D000199.htm'>Caravaggio.com</link>.</extension><space/>He was imprisoned by the knights and managed to escape. By December he had been expelled from the Order &quot;as a foul and rotten member.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>This was the formal phrase used in all such cases. The senior knights of the Order convened on 1 December 1608 and, after verifying that the accused had failed to appear although summoned four times, voted unanimously to expel their<space/><italics>putridum et foetidum</italics><space/>ex-brother. Caravaggio was expelled, not for his crime, but for having left Malta without permission (i.e., escaping).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio - Sette opere di Misericordia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>The Seven Works of Mercy (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Seven Works of Mercy</part></link>'', 16061607,<space/><link><target>Pio Monte della Misericordia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Naples</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio made his way to<space/><link><target>Sicily</target></link><space/>where he met his old friend Mario Minniti, who was now married and living in<space/><link><target>Syracuse, Italy</target><part>Syracuse</part></link>. Together they set off on what amounted to a triumphal tour from Syracuse to<space/><link><target>Messina</target></link><space/>and, maybe, on to the island capital,<space/><link><target>Palermo</target></link>. In Syracuse and Messina Caravaggio continued to win prestigious and well-paid commissions. Among other works from this period are<space/><italics><link><target>Burial of St. Lucy (Caravaggio)</target><part>Burial of St. Lucy</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Raising of Lazarus - Messina (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Raising of Lazarus</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Adoration of the Shepherds (Caravaggio)</target><part>Adoration of the Shepherds</part></link></italics>. His style continued to evolve, showing now friezes of figures isolated against vast empty backgrounds. &quot;His great Sicilian altarpieces isolate their shadowy, pitifully poor figures in vast areas of darkness; they suggest the desperate fears and frailty of man, and at the same time convey, with a new yet desolate tenderness, the beauty of humility and of the meek, who shall inherit the earth.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Langdon, p.365.</extension><space/>Contemporary reports depict a man whose behaviour was becoming increasingly bizarre, sleeping fully armed and in his clothes, ripping up a painting at a slight word of criticism, mocking the local painters.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caravaggio displayed bizarre behaviour from very early in his career. Mancini describes him as &quot;extremely crazy&quot;, a letter of Del Monte notes his strangeness, and Mario Minniti's 1724 biographer says that Mario left Caravaggio because of his behaviour. The strangeness seems to have increased after Malta. Susinno's early 18th century<space/><italics>Le vite de' pittori Messinesi</italics>, &quot;Lives of the Painters of Messina&quot;, provides several colourful anecdotes of Caravaggio's erratic behaviour in Sicily, and these are reproduced in modern full-length biographies such as Langdon and Robb. Bellori writes of Caravaggio's &quot;fear&quot; driving him from city to city across the island and finally, &quot;feeling that it was no longer safe to remain&quot;, to Naples. Baglione says Caravaggio was being &quot;chased by his enemy&quot;, but like Bellori does not say who this enemy was.</extension><link><target>File:CaravaggioSalomeMadrid.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''<link><target>Salome with the Head of John the Baptist (Caravaggio), Madrid</target><part>Salome with the Head of John the Baptist''</part></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Caravaggio - David con la testa di Golia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''David with the Head of Goliath'', 16091610,<space/><link><target>Galleria Borghese</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link>After only nine months in Sicily, Caravaggio returned to Naples. According to his earliest biographer he was being pursued by enemies while in Sicily and felt it safest to place himself under the protection of the Colonnas until he could secure his pardon from the pope (now<space/><link><target>Paul V</target></link>) and return to Rome.<extension extension_name='ref'>Baglione says that Caravaggio in Naples had &quot;given up all hope of revenge&quot; against his unnamed enemy.</extension><space/>In Naples he painted<space/><italics><link><target>The Denial of Saint Peter (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Denial of Saint Peter</part></link></italics>, a final<space/><italics><link><target>John the Baptist (Caravaggio)</target><part>John the Baptist (Borghese)</part></link></italics>, and his last picture,<space/><italics><link><target>The Martyrdom of Saint Ursula (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Martyrdom of Saint Ursula</part></link></italics>. His style continued to evolve<space/><link><target>Saint Ursula</target></link><space/>is caught in a moment of highest action and drama, as the arrow fired by the king of the<space/><link><target>Huns</target></link><space/>strikes her in the breast, unlike earlier paintings which had all the immobility of the posed models. The brushwork was much freer and more impressionistic.</paragraph><paragraph>In Naples an attempt was made on his life, by persons unknown. At first it was reported in Rome that the &quot;famous artist&quot; Caravaggio was dead, but then it was learned that he was alive, but seriously disfigured in the face. He painted a<space/><italics><link><target>Salome with the Head of John the Baptist (Madrid) (Caravaggio)</target><part>Salome with the Head of John the Baptist (Madrid)</part></link></italics>, showing his own head on a platter, and sent it to de Wignacourt as a plea for forgiveness. Perhaps at this time he painted also a<space/><italics><link><target>David with the Head of Goliath</target></link></italics>, showing the young David with a strangely sorrowful expression gazing on the severed head of the giant, which is again Caravaggio's. This painting he may have sent to his patron the unscrupulous art-loving Cardinal<space/><link><target>Scipione Borghese</target></link>, nephew of the pope, who had the power to grant or withhold pardons.<extension extension_name='ref'>According to a 17th-century writer the painting the head of Goliath is a self-portrait of the artist, while David is<space/><italics>il suo Caravaggino</italics>, &quot;his little Caravaggio&quot;. This phrase is obscure, but it has been interpreted as meaning either that the boy is a youthful self-portrait, or, more commonly, that this is the Cecco who modelled for the<space/><italics>Amor Vincit</italics>. The sword-blade carries an abbreviated inscription which has been interpreted as meaning Humility Conquers Pride. Attributed to a date in Caravaggio's late Roman period by Bellori, the recent tendency is to see it as a product on Caravaggio's second Neapolitan period. (See Gash, p.125).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the summer of 1610 he took a boat northwards to receive the pardon, which seemed imminent thanks to his powerful Roman friends. With him were three last paintings, gifts for Cardinal Scipione.<extension extension_name='ref'>A letter from the<space/><link><target>Bishop of Caserta</target></link><space/>in Naples to Cardinal Scipione Borghese in Rome, dated 29 July 1610, informs the Cardinal that the Marchesa of Caravaggio is holding two John the Baptists and a Magdalene which were intended for Borghese. These were presumably the price of Caravaggio's pardon from Borghese's uncle, the pope.</extension><space/>What happened next is the subject of much confusion and conjecture. The bare facts are that on 28 July an anonymous<space/><italics>avviso</italics><space/>(private newsletter) from Rome to the ducal court of Urbino reported that Caravaggio was dead. Three days later another<space/><italics>avviso</italics><space/>said that he had died of fever on his way from Naples to Rome. A poet friend of the artist later gave 18 July as the date of death, and a recent researcher claims to have discovered a death notice showing that the artist died on that day of a fever in<space/><link><target>Porto Ercole</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Grosseto</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Tuscany</target></link>. Human remains found in a church in Porto Ercole in 2010 are believed to almost certainly belong to Caravaggio.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-10682743<space/></arg><arg name="title">BBC News - Vatican reveals Caravaggio painting 'found' in Rome<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bbc.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-07-19<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension><space/>The findings come after a year-long investigation using DNA, carbon dating and other analyses.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10333158<space/></arg><arg name="title">BBC News - Church bones 'belong to Caravaggio', researchers say<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bbc.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-06-16<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some scholars argue that Caravaggio was murdered by the same &quot;enemies&quot; that had been pursuing him since he fled Malta, possibly<space/><link><target>Alof de Wignacourt</target><part>Wignacourt</part></link><space/>and/or factions in the<space/><link><target>Knights Hospitaller</target><part>Order of St. John</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Robb argues this in<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>beginning in chapter 20.</extension><space/>Caravaggio might have died of<space/><link><target>lead poisoning</target></link>. Bones with high lead levels were recently found in a grave likely to be Caravaggio's.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Tom Kington in Rome<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2010/jun/16/caravaggio-italy-remains-ravenna-art<space/></arg><arg name="title">The mystery of Caravaggio's death solved at last – painting killed him &#124; Art and design<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Guardian<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010-06-16</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>Paints used at the time contained high amounts of lead salts. Caravaggio is known to have indulged in violent behavior, as caused by lead poisoning.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sexuality</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Boy with a Basket of Fruit-Caravaggio (1593).jpg</target><part></part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>Boy with a Basket of Fruit (Caravaggio)</target><part>Boy with a Basket of Fruit</part></link>'', 15931594. Oil on canvas,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>67</arg><arg>x</arg><arg>53</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="lk">out</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<space/><link><target>Galleria Borghese</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio never married and had no known children, and Howard Hibbard notes the absence of erotic female figures from the artist's oeuvre: &quot;In his entire career he did not paint a single female nude.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hibbard, p.97</extension><space/>On the other hand, the cabinet-pieces from the Del Monte period are replete with &quot;full-lipped, languorous boys ... who seem to solicit the onlooker with their offers of fruit, wine, flowers - and themselves.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Louis Crompton, &quot;Homosexuality and Civilization&quot; (Harvard, 2006) p.288</extension><space/>Nevertheless, a connection with a certain Lena is mentioned in a 1605 court deposition by Pasqualone, where she is described as &quot;Michelangelo's girl&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bertolotti, &quot;Artisti Lombardi&quot;. pp.71-72</extension><space/>According to G.B.Passeri this 'Lena' was Caravaggio's model for the<space/><italics>Madonna di Loreto</italics>. According to Catherine Puglisi 'Lena' may have been the same as the courtesan Maddalena di Paolo Antognetti, who named Caravaggio as an<space/><italics>intimate friend</italics><space/>by her own testimony in 1604.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catheine Puglisi, &quot;Caravaggio&quot; Phaidon 1998, p.199</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Riccardo Bassani and Fiora Bellini, &quot;Caravaggio assassino&quot;, 1994, pp.205-214</extension><space/>Caravaggio also probably enjoyed close relationships with other &quot;whores and courtesans&quot; such as<space/><link><target>Portrait of a Courtesan (Caravaggio)</target><part>Fillide Melandroni</part></link>, of whom he painted a portrait.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA">Andrew Graham-Dixon,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A life sacred and profane</italics>, Penguin, 2011</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since the 1970s art scholars and historians have debated the inferences of<space/><link><target>homoeroticism</target></link><space/>in Caravaggio's works.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/10/arts/design/10abroad.html?hp Herwarth Roettgen, Il Caravaggio, ricerche e interpretazione, Rome 1975; R. Longhi, Novelletta del Caravaggio invertito, Paragone, March 1952, 62-4; Calvesi, Caravaggio, Art &amp; Dossier, April 1986; Christopher Frommer, Caravaggios frhwerk und der cardinal del Monte, Storia dellarte, 9-10 (1971): 5-29; Margaret Walters, The Male Nude, Harmondsworth, 1978: 188-189; Helen Langdon, Caravaggio; Robb, M</extension><space/>The model of &quot;Omnia vincit amor&quot; is known as Cecco di Caravaggio. Cecco stayed with him even after he was obliged to leave Rome in 1606, and the two may have been lovers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrew Graham-Dixon 2011, p.4">Andrew Graham-Dixon,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A life sacred and profane</italics>, Penguin, 2011, p.4</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Aside from the paintings, evidence also comes from the libel trial brought against Caravaggio by<space/><link><target>Giovanni Baglione</target></link><space/>in 1603. Baglione accused Caravaggio and his friends of writing and distributing scurrilous doggerel attacking him; the pamphlets, according to Baglione's friend and witness Mao Salini, had been distributed by a certain Giovanni Battista, a<space/><italics>bardassa,</italics><space/>or boy prostitute, shared by Caravaggio and his friend Onorio Longhi. Caravaggio denied knowing any young boy of that name, and the allegation was not followed up.<extension extension_name='ref'>The transcript of the trial is given in Walter Friedlander, &quot;Caravaggio Studies&quot; (Princeton, 1955, revised edn. 1969)</extension><space/>Baglione's painting of &quot;Divine Love&quot; has also been seen as a visual accusation of sodomy against Caravaggio.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>Such accusations were damaging and dangerous as sodomy was a capital crime at the time. Even though the authorities were unlikely to investigate such a well-connected person as Caravaggio: &quot;Once an artist had been smeared as a pederast, his work was smeared too.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrew Graham-Dixon 2011, p.4"></extension><space/>Francesco Susinoo in his later biography relates the story of how the artist was chased by a school-master in Sicily for spending too long gazing at the boys in his care. Susino presents it as a misunderstanding, but Caravaggio may indeed have been seeking sexual solace; and the incident could explain one of his most homoerotic paintings: his last depiction of St John the Baptist.<extension extension_name='ref'>Andrew Graham-Dixon,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A life sacred and profane</italics>, Penguin, 2011, p.412</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The art historian, Andrew Graham-Dixon has summarised the debate:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>A lot has been made of Caravaggio's presumed homosexuality, which has in more than one previous account of his life been presented as the single key that explains everything, both the power of his art and the misfortunes of his life. There is no absolute proof of it, only strong circumstantial evidence and much rumour. The balance of probability suggests that Caravaggio did indeed have sexual relations with men. But certainly had female lovers. Throughout the years that he spent in Rome he kept close company with a number of prostitutes. The truth is that Caravaggio was as uneasy in his relationships as he was in most other aspects of life. He likely slept with men. He did sleep with women. He settled with no one... [but] the idea that he was an early martyr to the drives of an unconventional sexuality is an anachronistic fiction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrew Graham-Dixon 2011, p.4"></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>As an artist</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio - Taking of Christ - Dublin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>The Taking of Christ</target></link>'', 1602.<space/><link><target>National Gallery of Ireland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dublin</target></link>. Caravaggio's application of the<space/><link><target>chiaroscuro</target></link><space/>technique shows through on the faces and armour notwithstanding the lack of a visible shaft of light. The figure on the extreme right is a self-portrait.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>The birth of Baroque</heading><paragraph>Caravaggio &quot;put the oscuro (shadows) into<space/><link><target>chiaroscuro</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Lambert, p.11.</extension><space/>Chiaroscuro was practiced long before he came on the scene, but it was Caravaggio who made the technique a dominant stylistic element, darkening the shadows and transfixing the subject in a blinding shaft of light. With this came the acute observation of physical and psychological reality which formed the ground both for his immense popularity and for his frequent problems with his religious commissions. He worked at great speed, from live models, scoring basic guides directly onto the canvas with the end of the brush handle; very few of Caravaggio's drawings appear to have survived, and it is likely that he preferred to work directly on the canvas. The approach was<space/><link><target>anathema</target></link><space/>to the skilled artists of his day, who decried his refusal to work from drawings and to idealise his figures. Yet the models were basic to his realism. Some have been identified, including<space/><link><target>Mario Minniti</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Francesco Boneri</target></link>, both fellow artists, Mario appearing as various figures in the early secular works, the young Francesco as a succession of angels, Baptists and Davids in the later canvasses. His female models include<space/><link><target>Portrait of a Courtesan (Caravaggio)</target><part>Fillide Melandroni</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Martha and Mary Magdalene (Caravaggio)</target><part>Anna Bianchini</part></link>, and Maddalena Antognetti (the &quot;Lena&quot; mentioned in court documents of the &quot;artichoke&quot; case<extension extension_name='ref'>Much of the documentary evidence for Caravaggio's life in Rome comes from court records; the &quot;artichoke&quot; case refers to an occasion when the artist threw a dish of hot artichokes at a waiter.</extension><space/>as Caravaggio's concubine), all well-known prostitutes, who appear as female religious figures including the Virgin and various saints.<extension extension_name='ref'>Robb,<space/><italics>passim</italics>, makes a fairly exhaustive attempt to identify models and relate them to individual canvases.</extension><space/>Caravaggio himself appears in several paintings, his final self-portrait being as the witness on the far right to the<space/><italics><link><target>The Martyrdom of Saint Ursula (Caravaggio)</target><part>Martyrdom of Saint Ursula</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caravaggio's self-portraits run from the<space/><italics>Sick Bacchus</italics><space/>at the beginning of his career to the head of Goliath in the<space/><italics>David with the Head of Goliath</italics><space/>in Rome's Borghese Gallery. Previous artists had included self-portraits as onlookers to the action, but Caravaggio's innovation was to include himself as a participant.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio - Cena in Emmaus.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>Supper at Emmaus (London) (Caravaggio)</target><part>Supper at Emmaus</part></link>'', 1601. Oil on canvas,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>139</arg><arg>x</arg><arg>195</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<space/><link><target>National Gallery, London</target></link>. Caravaggio included himself as the figure on the top left.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio had a noteworthy ability to express in one scene of unsurpassed vividness the passing of a crucial moment.<space/><italics><link><target>Supper at Emmaus (London) (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Supper at Emmaus</part></link></italics><space/>depicts the recognition of Christ by his disciples: a moment before he is a fellow traveler, mourning the passing of the Messiah, as he never ceases to be to the inn-keeper's eyes, the second after, he is the Saviour. In<space/><italics><link><target>The Calling of St Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Calling of St Matthew</part></link></italics>, the hand of the Saint points to himself as if he were saying &quot;who, me?&quot;, while his eyes, fixed upon the figure of Christ, have already said, &quot;Yes, I will follow you&quot;. With<space/><italics><link><target>The Raising of Lazarus (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Resurrection of Lazarus</part></link></italics>, he goes a step further, giving us a glimpse of the actual physical process of resurrection. The body of Lazarus is still in the throes of rigor mortis, but his hand, facing and recognizing that of Christ, is alive. Other major<space/><link><target>Baroque</target></link><space/>artists would travel the same path, for example<space/><link><target>Bernini</target></link>, fascinated with themes from Ovid's<space/><italics><link><target>Metamorphoses</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Death of the Virgin-Caravaggio (1606).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''<link><target>Death of the Virgin (Caravaggio)</target><part>Death of the Virgin</part></link>''. 16011606.<space/><link><target>Louvre</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>The<space/><italics>Caravaggisti</italics></heading><paragraph>The installation of the St. Matthew paintings in the Contarelli Chapel had an immediate impact among the younger artists in Rome, and Caravaggism became the cutting edge for every ambitious young painter. The first Caravaggisti included<space/><link><target>Orazio Gentileschi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Giovanni Baglione</target></link>. Baglione's Caravaggio phase was short-lived; Caravaggio later accused him of plagiarism and the two were involved in a long feud. Baglione went on to write the first biography of Caravaggio. In the next generation of Caravaggisti there were<space/><link><target>Carlo Saraceni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bartolomeo Manfredi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Orazio Borgianni</target></link>. Gentileschi, despite being considerably older, was the only one of these artists to live much beyond 1620, and ended up as court painter to<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target></link>. His daughter<space/><link><target>Artemisia Gentileschi</target></link><space/>was also close to Caravaggio, and one of the most gifted of the movement. Yet in Rome and in Italy it was not Caravaggio, but the influence of<space/><link><target>Annibale Carracci</target></link>, blending elements from the<space/><link><target>High Renaissance</target></link><space/>and Lombard realism, which ultimately triumphed.</paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio's brief stay in Naples produced a notable school of Neapolitan Caravaggisti, including<space/><link><target>Battistello Caracciolo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carlo Sellitto</target></link>. The Caravaggisti movement there ended with a terrible outbreak of plague in 1656, but the Spanish connection Naples was a possession of Spain was instrumental in forming the important Spanish branch of his influence.</paragraph><paragraph>A group of Catholic artists from<space/><link><target>Utrecht</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Utrecht School</target><part>&quot;Utrecht Caravaggisti&quot;</part></link>, travelled to Rome as students in the first years of the 17th century and were profoundly influenced by the work of Caravaggio, as Bellori describes. On their return to the north this trend had a short-lived but influential flowering in the 1620s among painters like<space/><link><target>Hendrick ter Brugghen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gerrit van Honthorst</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andries Both</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dirck van Baburen</target></link>. In the following generation the effects of Caravaggio, although attenuated, are to be seen in the work of<space/><link><target>Peter Paul Rubens</target><part>Rubens</part></link><space/>(who purchased one of his paintings for the Gonzaga of Mantua and painted a copy of the<space/><italics><link><target>The Entombment of Christ (Caravaggio)</target><part>Entombment of Christ</part></link></italics>),<space/><link><target>Vermeer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rembrandt Harmenszoon van Rijn</target><part>Rembrandt</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Diego Velzquez</target><part>Velzquez</part></link>, the last of whom presumably saw his work during his various sojourns in Italy.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Death and rebirth of a reputation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Caravaggio - La Deposizione di Cristo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>''<link><target>The Entombment of Christ (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Entombment of Christ</part></link>'', (16021603),<space/><link><target>Pinacoteca Vaticana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio's innovations inspired the Baroque, but the Baroque took the drama of his chiaroscuro without the psychological realism. While he directly influenced the style of the artists mentioned above, and, at a distance, the Frenchmen<space/><link><target>Georges de La Tour</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Simon Vouet</target></link>, and the Spaniard<space/><link><target>Giuseppe Ribera</target></link>, within a few decades his works were being ascribed to less scandalous artists, or simply overlooked. The Baroque, to which he contributed so much, had evolved, and fashions had changed, but perhaps more pertinently Caravaggio never established a workshop as the Carracci did, and thus had no school to spread his techniques. Nor did he ever set out his underlying philosophical approach to art, the psychological realism which can only be deduced from his surviving work.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus his reputation was doubly vulnerable to the critical demolition-jobs done by two of his earliest biographers,<space/><link><target>Giovanni Baglione</target></link>, a rival painter with a personal vendetta, and the influential 17th century critic<space/><link><target>Gian Pietro Bellori</target></link>, who had not known him but was under the influence of the earlier<space/><link><target>Giovanni Battista Agucchi</target></link><space/>and Bellori's friend<space/><link><target>Poussin</target></link>, in preferring the &quot;classical-idealistic&quot; tradition of the<space/><link><target>Bolognese school (painting)</target><part>Bolognese school</part></link><space/>led by the Carracci.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wikkkower, p. 266; also see criticism by fellow Italian<space/><link><target>Vincenzo Carducci</target></link><space/>(living in Spain), who calls Caravaggio an &quot;Antichrist&quot; of painting with &quot;monstrous&quot; talents of deception.</extension><space/>Baglione, his first biographer, played a considerable part in creating the legend of Caravaggio's unstable and violent character, as well as his inability to draw.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ostrow, 608</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1920s, art critic<space/><link><target>Fondazione Roberto Longhi</target><part>Roberto Longhi</part></link><space/>brought Caravaggio's name once more to the foreground, and placed him in the European tradition: &quot;<link><target>Jusepe de Ribera</target><part>Ribera</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Vermeer</target></link>, La Tour and Rembrandt could never have existed without him. And the art of<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target><part>Delacroix</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Gustave Courbet</target><part>Courbet</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>douard Manet</target><part>Manet</part></link><space/>would have been utterly different&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberto Longhi, quoted in Lambert, op. cit., p.15</extension><space/>The influential<space/><link><target>Bernard Berenson</target></link><space/>agreed: &quot;With the exception of<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link>, no other Italian painter exercised so great an influence.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Bernard Berenson, in Lambert, op. cit., p.8</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Oeuvre</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Conversion on the Way to Damascus-Caravaggio (c.1600-1).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''<link><target>Conversion on the Way to Damascus</target></link>'', 1601,<space/><link><target>Cerasi Chapel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Santa Maria del Popolo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>.</part></link>Only about 80 paintings by Caravaggio have survived, but some lost works have been found from time to time. One,<space/><italics><link><target>The Calling of Saints Peter and Andrew</target></link></italics>, was recently authenticated and restored; it had been in storage in<space/><link><target>Hampton Court</target></link>, mislabeled as a copy.<space/><link><target>Richard Francis Burton</target></link><space/>writes of a &quot;picture of St. Rosario (in the museum of the Grand Duke of Tuscany), showing a circle of thirty men<space/><italics>turpiter ligati</italics>&quot; which is not known to have survived. The rejected version of<space/><italics><link><target>The Inspiration of Saint Matthew (Caravaggio)</target><part>The Inspiration of Saint Matthew</part></link></italics><space/>intended for the<space/><link><target>Contarelli Chapel</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>San Luigi dei Francesi</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link><space/>was destroyed during the<space/><link><target>Bombing of Dresden in World War II</target><part>bombing of Dresden</part></link>, though black and white photographs of the work exist. In June 2011 it was announced that a previously unknown Caravaggio painting of<space/><link><target>Saint Augustine</target></link><space/>dating to about 1600 had been discovered in a private collection in Britain. Called a &quot;significant discovery&quot;, the painting had never been published and is thought to have been commissioned by<space/><link><target>Vincenzo Giustiniani</target></link>, a patron of the painter in Rome.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Unknown Caravaggio painting unearthed in Britain</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2011/jun/19/unknown-caravaggio-painting-unearthed-britain</arg><arg name="author"></arg><arg name="last">Alberge</arg><arg name="first">Dalya</arg><arg name="work">[[The Guardian]]</arg><arg name="date">19 June 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-06-20</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Epitaph</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Denial of Saint Peter-Caravaggio (1610).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>The Denial of Saint Peter (Caravaggio)</target><part>Denial of Saint Peter (1610)</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Caravaggio's epitaph was composed by his friend Marzio Milesi. It reads:</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Michelangelo Merisi, son of Fermo di Caravaggio in painting not equal to a painter, but to Nature itself died in Port' Ercole betaking himself hither from Naples returning to Rome 15th calend of August In the year of our Lord 1610 He lived thirty-six years nine months and twenty days Marzio Milesi, Jurisconsult Dedicated this to a friend of extraordinary genius.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Inscriptiones et Elogia (Cod.Vat.7927)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>He was commemorated on the front of the<space/><link><target>:File:Lire 100000 (Caravaggio).JPG</target><part>Banca d'Italia 100,000 lire banknote in the 1980s and 90s</part></link><space/>(before Italy switched to the Euro) with the back showing his<space/><italics>Basket of Fruit</italics>.<template><target>-</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Theft of his Nativity</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio - Nativity with St Francis and St Lawrence - WGA04193.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''Nativity with San Lorenzo and San Francesco''</part></link>In October 1969, two thieves entered the Oratory of San Lorenzo in Palermo, Italy and removed the Caravaggio<space/><italics><link><target>Nativity with St. Francis and St. Lawrence</target></link></italics><space/>from its frame. Experts estimate its value at $20 million.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fbi.gov/about-us/investigate/vc_majorthefts/arttheft/caravaggio<space/></arg><arg name="title">FBI — Caravaggio<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fbi.gov<space/></arg><arg name="date">2012-09-17<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-18</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Sooke<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alastair<space/></arg><arg name="title">Caravaggio's Nativity: Hunting a stolen masterpiece<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 December 2013<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC website<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20131219-hunting-a-stolen-masterpiece<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 December 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Italian neorealism</target></link>, a 194452 movement characterized by stories set amongst the disadvantaged</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>category see also</target><arg>Paintings by Caravaggio</arg></template><template><target>-</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Primary sources</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>The main primary sources for Caravaggio's life are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Giulio Mancini's comments on Caravaggio in<space/><italics>Considerazioni sulla pittura</italics>, c.16171621</listitem><listitem>Giovanni Baglione's<space/><italics>Le vite de' pittori</italics>, 1642</listitem><listitem>Giovanni Pietro Bellori's<space/><italics>Le Vite de' pittori, scultori et architetti moderni</italics>, 1672</listitem></list><paragraph>All have been reprinted in Howard Hibbard's &quot;Caravaggio&quot; and in the appendices to Catherine Puglisi's &quot;Caravaggio&quot;.</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Secondary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Andrea Bayer<space/></arg><arg name="title">[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/96665 ''Painters of reality : the legacy of Leonardo and Caravaggio in Lombardy'']<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Metropolitan Museum of Art<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9781588391162</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Maurizio Calvesi,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics>, Art Dossier 1986, Giunti Editori (1986) (ISBN not available)</listitem><listitem><link><target>John Denison Champlin</target></link><space/>and Charles Callahan Perkins, Ed.,<space/><italics>Cyclopedia of Painters and Paintings</italics>, Charles Scribner's Sons, New York (1885), p.&amp;nbsp;241 (available at the Harvard's Fogg Museum Library and scanned on Google Books)</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Keith Christiansen.<space/></arg><arg name="title">[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/42365/rec/5 ''A Caravaggio Rediscovered, The Lute Player'']<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Metropolitan Museum of Art<space/></arg><arg name="year">1990<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780870995750</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Andrea Dusio,<space/><italics>Caravaggio White Album</italics>, Cooper Arte, Roma 2009, ISBN 978-88-7394-128-6</listitem><listitem>Walter Friedlaender, Caravaggio Studies, Princeton: Princeton University Press 1955</listitem><listitem>John Gash,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics>, Chaucer Press, (2004) ISBN 1-904449-22-0)</listitem><listitem>Rosa Giorgi,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: Master of light and dark his life in paintings</italics>, Dorling Kindersley (1999) ISBN 978-0-7894-4138-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>Andrew Graham-Dixon</target></link>,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A Life Sacred and Profane</italics>, London, Allen Lane, 2009. ISBN 978-0-7139-9674-6</listitem><listitem>Howard Hibbard,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics><space/>(1983) ISBN 978-0-06-433322-1</listitem><listitem>Harris, Ann Sutherland.<space/><italics>Seventeenth-century Art &amp; Architecture</italics>, Laurence King Publishing (2004), ISBN 1-85669-415-1.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Michael Kitson</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Complete Paintings of Caravaggio</italics><space/>London, Abrams, 1967. New edition: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicholson, 1969 and 1986, ISBN 978-0-297-76108-2</listitem><listitem>Pietro Koch,<space/><italics>Caravaggio The Painter of Blood and Darkness</italics>, Gunther Edition, (Rome 2004)</listitem><listitem>Gilles Lambert,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics>, Taschen, (2000) ISBN 978-3-8228-6305-3</listitem><listitem>Helen Langdon,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: A Life</italics>, Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1999 (original UK edition 1998) ISBN 978-0-374-11894-5</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alfred Moir</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Italian Followers of Caravaggio</italics>, Harvard University Press (1967) ISBN 978-0674469006</listitem><listitem>Ostrow, Steven F., review of<space/><italics>Giovanni Baglione: Artistic Reputation in Baroque Rome</italics><space/>by Maryvelma Smith O'Neil,<space/><italics><link><target>The Art Bulletin</target></link></italics>, Vol. 85, No. 3 (Sep., 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;608611,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.mutualart.com/OpenArticle/Giovanni-Baglione--Artistic-Reputation-i/119746C99929E2DE'>online text</link></listitem><listitem>Catherine Puglisi,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics>, Phaidon (1998) ISBN 978-0-7148-3966-0</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter Robb</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>M (Peter Robb book)</target><part>M</part></link></italics>, Duffy &amp; Snellgrove, 2003 amended edition (original edition 1998) ISBN 978-1-876631-79-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>John Spike</target></link>, with assistance from<space/><link><target>Michle Kahn Spike</target></link>,<space/><italics>Caravaggio</italics><space/>with Catalogue of Paintings on CD-ROM, Abbeville Press, New York (2001) ISBN 978-0-7892-0639-8</listitem><listitem>John L. Varriano,<space/><italics>Caravaggio: The Art of Realism</italics>, Pennsylvania State University Press (University Park, PA 2006) ISBN 978-0271027180</listitem><listitem><link><target>Rudolf Wittkower</target></link>,<space/><italics>Art and Architecture in Italy, 1600-1750</italics>, Penguin/Yale History of Art, 3rd edition, 1973, ISBN 978-0300079395</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alberto Macchi</target></link>, &quot;L'uomo Caravaggio&quot; - Atto unico (pref. Stefania Macioce), AETAS, Roma 1995, ISBN 88-851-72-19-9</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><bold>Biography</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.artble.com/artists/caravaggio'>Caravaggio Biography, Style and Technique</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bergerfoundation.ch/Caravage/E/'>Caravaggio, The Prince of the Night</link></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Articles and essays</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fbi.gov/hq/cid/arttheft/europe/italy/italyart.htm'>FBI Art Theft Notice for Caravaggio's Nativity</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://vecchiaforma.com/uploads/3/3/3/5/3335127/e21-passion-cvgg.pdf'>The Passion of Caravaggio</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://vecchiaforma.com/uploads/3/3/3/5/3335127/e4-cvgg-velz.pdf'>Deconstructing Caravaggio and Velzquez</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.duffyandsnellgrove.com.au/extracts/m_interview.htm'>Interview with Peter Robb, author of ''M''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rijksmuseum.nl/formats/container_remcar_en.html'>Compare</link><space/>Rembrandt with Caravaggio.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.webexhibits.org/hockneyoptics/post/grundy7.html'>Caravaggio and the Camera Obscura</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vandewerken.nl/teksten/caravaggio%20english.html'>Caravaggio's incisions by Ramon van de Werken</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.physorg.com/news155889108.html'>Caravaggio's use of the Camera Obscura: Lapucci</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://painterpatrickswift.blogspot.co.uk/1970/03/some-notes-on-caravaggio-nimbus-1956.html'>Some notes on Caravaggio - Patrick Swift</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.robertalapucci.com'>Roberta Lapucci's website and most of her publications on Caravaggio as freely downloadable PDF</link></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Art works</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.caravaggio.org'>Caravaggio.org</link><space/>Famous Caravagio Paintings at Caravaggio.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.caravaggio-foundation.org'>caravaggio-foundation.org</link><space/>175 works by Caravaggio</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ibiblio.org/wm/paint/auth/caravaggio/'>Caravaggio, Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio WebMuseum, Paris webpage</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eyegate.com/showgal.php?id=33'>Caravaggio's EyeGate Gallery</link></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Music</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.answers.com/topic/jordi-savall-dominique-fernandez-lachrimae-caravaggio'>Lachrimae Caravaggio, by Jordi Savall, performed by Le Concert des Nations &amp; Hesperion XXI (Article at Answers.com)<space/></link></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Video</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/caravaggio-matthew.html'>Caravaggio's Calling of Saint Matthew</link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Smarthistory</target></link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/crucifixion-of-st.-peter.html'>Caravaggio's Crucifixion of Saint Peter</link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/caravaggios-death-of-the-virgin.html'>Caravaggio's Death of the Virgin</link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/narcissus-at-the-source.html'>Caravaggio's Narcissus at the Source</link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/contarelli-chapel.html'>Caravaggio's paintings in the Contarelli Chapel, San Luigi dei Francesi</link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/supper-at-emmaus.html'>Caravaggio's Supper at Emmaus</link>, accessed February 13, 2013</listitem><listitem>A music video from British-Canadian band Velcro Hooks stages a number of &quot;live&quot; reproductions of Caravaggio's paintings in their<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-mmJiNGh_mk'>&quot;A Love Song to T. S. Eliot.&quot;</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Caravaggio</target></template><template><target>Caravaggisti</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME">Caravaggio
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Caravaggio, Michelangelo Merisi or Amerighi da
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>[[Painting]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>September 29, 1571
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Milan]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>July 18, 1610
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Porto Ercole, near [[Grosseto]] in [[Tuscany]]
</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Caravaggio</target></template><link><target>Category:Caravaggio</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1571 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1610 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian Baroque painters</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century Italian painters</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Italian painters</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian Roman Catholics</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of Malta</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Milan</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Catholic Church painters</target></link><link><target>Category:LGBT Roman Catholics</target></link></paragraph></article>