<article title='Claudius'><paragraph><template><target>other people</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="name"><space/>Claudius
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Claudius crop.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Bust of Claudius at the [[Naples National Archaeological Museum]]
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[Roman Emperor|4th Emperor]] of the [[Roman Empire]]
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>24 January 41 – 13 October 54<br/>(13 years)
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Caligula]], nephew by elder brother (Germanicus)
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Nero]], grand nephew by elder brother (Germanicus) and stepson by 4th wife (Agrippina)
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>{{plainlist|
* [[Plautia Urgulanilla]]
* [[Aelia Paetina]]
* [[Valeria Messalina]]
* [[Agrippina the Younger]] (niece)
}}
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>{{plainlist|
* [[Claudius Drusus]]
* [[Claudia Antonia]] 
* [[Claudia Octavia]] 
* [[Britannicus]]
* [[Nero]] (adoptive)
}}
</arg><arg name="full name"><space/>''(at birth)''<br>Tiberius Claudius Nero<br>''(by death)''<br>{{nowrap|[[Tiberius (praenomen)|Ti.]] Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus}}
</arg><arg name="royal house"><space/>[[Julio-Claudian dynasty|Julio-Claudian]]
</arg><arg name="house-type"><space/>Imperial Dynasty
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Nero Claudius Drusus]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>[[Antonia Minor]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>1 August 10 BC
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Lugdunum]], [[Roman Gaul|Gaul]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>13 October 54 AD (aged 63)
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Rome]], [[Italy (Roman Empire)|Italy]]
</arg><arg name="place of burial"><space/>[[Mausoleum of Augustus]]
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Roman Paganism]]
</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Claudius</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>ɔː</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>i</arg><arg>ə</arg><arg>s</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>lang-la</target><arg>Tiberius Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph>Classical Latin spelling and<space/><link><target>Latin spelling and pronunciation</target><part>reconstructed Classical Latin pronunciation</part></link><space/>of the name of Claudius:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><template><target>sqc</target><arg>TIBERIVS CLAVDIVS CAESAR AVGVSTVS GERMANICVS</arg></template><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>IPA-la</target><arg>tɪ'bɛ.ri.ʊs 'klau̯.di.ʊs 'kae̯.sar au̯'gʊs.tus gɛr'maː.nɪ.kʊs</arg><arg>IPA</arg></template></listitem></list></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Claudius' regal name has an equivalent English meaning of &quot;Tiberius Claudius Caesar, the Majestic Ruler, Conqueror of the Germans&quot;.</extension><space/>1 August 10 BC 13 October 54 AD) was<space/><link><target>Roman emperor</target></link><space/>from 41 to 54. A member of the<space/><link><target>Julio-Claudian dynasty</target></link>, he was the son of<space/><link><target>Nero Claudius Drusus</target><part>Drusus</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Antonia Minor</target></link>. He was born at<space/><link><target>Lugdunum</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Gaul</target></link>, the first Roman Emperor to be born outside<space/><link><target>Italia (Roman Empire)</target><part>Italy</part></link>. Because he was afflicted with a limp and slight deafness due to sickness at a young age, his family ostracized him and excluded him from public office until his<space/><link><target>Roman consul</target><part>consulship</part></link>, shared with his nephew<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link><space/>in 37.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius' infirmity probably saved him from the fate of many other nobles during the purges of<space/><link><target>Tiberius</target></link><space/>and Caligula's reigns; potential enemies did not see him as a serious threat. His survival led to his being declared Emperor by the<space/><link><target>Praetorian Guard</target></link><space/>after Caligula's assassination, at which point he was the last man of his family.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite his lack of experience, Claudius proved to be an able and efficient administrator. He was also an ambitious builder, constructing many new roads, aqueducts, and canals across the Empire. During his reign the Empire began the<space/><link><target>Roman conquest of Britain</target><part>conquest of Britain</part></link><space/>(if the earlier<space/><link><target>Caesar's invasions of Britain</target><part>invasions of Britain by Caesar</part></link><space/>and Caligula's aborted attempt are not counted). Having a personal interest in law, he presided at public trials, and issued up to twenty edicts a day.</paragraph><paragraph>He was seen as vulnerable throughout his reign, particularly by elements of the nobility. Claudius was constantly forced to shore up his position; this resulted in the deaths of many<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target><part>senators</part></link>. These events damaged his reputation among the ancient writers, though more recent historians have revised this opinion. Many authors contend that he was murdered by his own wife. After his death in 54 AD (at age of 63), his grand-nephew and adopted son<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link><space/>succeeded him as Emperor.</paragraph><paragraph>He was a descendant of the<space/><link><target>Octavii Rufi</target></link><space/>(through<space/><link><target>Gaius Octavius</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Julii Caesares</target></link><space/>(through<space/><link><target>Julia Caesaris (youngest sister of Julius Caesar)</target><part>Julia Atii</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Julia Antonia</target><part>Julia Antonii</part></link>) and the<space/><link><target>Claudii Nerones</target></link><space/>(through<space/><link><target>Nero Claudius Drusus</target></link>); he was a great-nephew of<space/><link><target>Augustus</target></link><space/>through his full sister<space/><link><target>Octavia the Younger</target><part>Octavia Minor</part></link>, an uncle of<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link><space/>and finally a great-uncle of<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link><space/>through Caligula's father and Nero's grandfather<space/><link><target>Germanicus</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Family and early life</heading><paragraph><template><target>Julio-Claudian dynasty</target></template>Claudius was born on 1 August 10 BC at the<space/><link><target>Sanctuary of the Three Gauls</target></link><space/>in what is now<space/><link><target>Lyon, France</target><part>Lyon</part></link>, France. He had two older siblings,<space/><link><target>Germanicus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Livilla</target></link>. His mother, Antonia, may have had two other children who died young.</paragraph><paragraph>His maternal grandparents were<space/><link><target>Mark Antony</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Octavia Minor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Augustus</target></link>' sister, and he was therefore the great-great grandnephew of<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target><part>Gaius Julius Caesar</part></link>. His paternal grandparents were<space/><link><target>Livia</target></link>, Augustus' third wife, and<space/><link><target>Tiberius Claudius Nero (praetor 42 BC)</target><part>Tiberius Claudius Nero</part></link>. During his reign, Claudius revived the rumor that his father Drusus was actually the illegitimate son of Augustus, to give the false appearance that Augustus was Claudius' paternal grandfather.</paragraph><paragraph>In 9 BC, his father Drusus unexpectedly died on campaign in Germania, possibly from illness. Claudius was then left to be raised by his mother, who never remarried. When Claudius' disability became evident, the relationship with his family turned sour. Antonia referred to him as a monster, and used him as a standard for stupidity. She seems to have passed her son off on his grandmother Livia for a number of years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dio<space/><italics>Hist.</italics><space/>LX 2</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Livia was a little kinder, but nevertheless often sent him short, angry letters of reproof. He was put under the care of a &quot;former mule-driver&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>2. Suet<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>4 indicates the reasons for choosing this tutor, as outlined in Leon (1948).</extension><space/>to keep him disciplined, under the logic that his condition was due to laziness and a lack of will-power. However, by the time he reached his teenage years his symptoms apparently waned and his family took some notice of his scholarly interests.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet4">Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>4.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 7 AD,<space/><link><target>Livy</target></link><space/>was hired to tutor him in history, with the assistance of Sulpicius Flavus. He spent a lot of his time with the latter and the philosopher<space/><link><target>Athenodoros Cananites</target><part>Athenodorus</part></link>. Augustus, according to a letter, was surprised at the clarity of Claudius' oratory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet4"></extension><space/>Expectations about his future began to increase.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Public life</heading><paragraph>His work as a budding historian damaged his prospects for advancement in public life. According to Vincent Scramuzza and others, Claudius began work on a history of the<space/><link><target>Roman civil wars</target><part>Civil Wars</part></link><space/>that was either too truthful or too critical of<space/><link><target>Octavian</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940) p.&amp;nbsp;39.</extension>then reigning as<space/><link><target>Augustus Caesar</target></link>. In either case, it was far too early for such an account, and may have only served to remind Augustus that Claudius was Antony's descendant. His mother and grandmother quickly put a stop to it, and this may have convinced them that Claudius was not fit for public office. He could not be trusted to toe the existing party line.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stuart">Stuart (1936).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When he returned to the narrative later in life, Claudius skipped over the wars of the second triumvirate altogether. But the damage was done, and his family pushed him to the background. When the<space/><link><target>Triumphal arch</target><part>Arch</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Pavia</target></link><space/>was erected to honor the Imperial clan in 8 BC, Claudius' name (now Tiberius Claudius Nero Germanicus after his elevation to<space/><link><target>paterfamilias</target></link><space/>of Claudii Nerones on the adoption of his brother) was inscribed on the edgepast the deceased princes,<space/><link><target>Gaius Caesar</target><part>Gaius</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lucius Caesar</target><part>Lucius</part></link>, and Germanicus' children. There is some speculation that the inscription was added by Claudius himself decades later, and that he originally did not appear at all.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stuart"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:A Roman Emperor AD41 detail.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Gratus</target></link><space/>proclaims Claudius emperor. Detail from ''A Roman Emperor 41AD'', by<space/><link><target>Lawrence Alma-Tadema</target></link>. Oil on canvas, c. 1871.</part></link>When Augustus died in 14 AD, Claudius then 23 appealed to his uncle<space/><link><target>Tiberius</target></link><space/>to allow him to begin the<space/><italics><link><target>cursus honorum</target></link></italics>. Tiberius, the new Emperor, responded by granting Claudius consular ornaments. Claudius requested office once more and was snubbed. Since the new Emperor was no more generous than the old, Claudius gave up hope of public office and retired to a scholarly, private life.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite the disdain of the Imperial family, it seems that from very early on the general public respected Claudius. At Augustus' death, the<space/><italics><link><target>Equestrian (Roman)</target><part>equites</part></link></italics>, or knights, chose Claudius to head their delegation. When his house burned down, the Senate demanded it be rebuilt at public expense. They also requested that Claudius be allowed to debate in the Senate. Tiberius turned down both motions, but the sentiment remained.</paragraph><paragraph>During the period immediately after the death of Tiberius' son,<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar Drusus</target><part>Drusus</part></link>, Claudius was pushed by some quarters as a potential heir. This again suggests the political nature of his exclusion from public life. However, as this was also the period during which the power and terror of the commander of the<space/><link><target>Praetorian Guard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sejanus</target></link>, was at its peak, Claudius chose to downplay this possibility.</paragraph><paragraph>After the death of Tiberius the new emperor<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link><space/>(the son of Claudius' brother<space/><link><target>Germanicus</target></link>) recognized Claudius to be of some use. He appointed Claudius his co-consul in 37 in order to emphasize the memory of Caligula's deceased father Germanicus. Despite this, Caligula relentlessly tormented his uncle: playing practical jokes, charging him enormous sums of money, humiliating him before the Senate, and the like. According to<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>Claudius became very sickly and thin by the end of Caligula's reign, most likely due to stress.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LX 2. Suhr (1955) suggests that this must refer to before Claudius came to power.</extension><space/>A possible surviving portrait of Claudius from this period may support this.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Assassination of Caligula (41 AD)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Herold of Chalcis coin showing Herod of Chalcis with brother Agrippa of Judaea crowning Roman Emperor Claudius I.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A coin of<space/><link><target>Herod of Chalcis</target></link>, showing him with his brother<space/><link><target>Herod Agrippa I</target><part>Agrippa of Judaea</part></link><space/>crowning Claudius.<space/><link><target>British Museum</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On 24 January 41, Caligula was assassinated in a broad-based<space/><link><target>conspiracy (political)</target><part>conspiracy</part></link><space/>involving the Praetorian commander<space/><link><target>Cassius Chaerea</target></link><space/>and several<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target><part>senators</part></link>. There is no evidence that Claudius had a direct hand in the<space/><link><target>assassination</target></link>, although it has been argued that he knew about the plot particularly since he left the scene of the crime shortly before his nephew was murdered.<extension extension_name='ref'>Major (1992)</extension><space/>However, after the deaths of<space/><link><target>Milonia Caesonia</target><part>Caligula's wife</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Julia Drusilla (daughter of Caligula)</target><part>daughter</part></link>, it became apparent that Cassius intended to go beyond the terms of the conspiracy and wipe out the Imperial family.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Josephus">Josephus<space/><italics>Antiquitates Iudiacae</italics><space/>XIX. Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/60*.html#1'>LX 1.3</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the chaos following the murder, Claudius witnessed the<space/><link><target>Germania</target><part>German</part></link><space/>guard cut down several uninvolved noblemen, including many of his friends. He fled to the palace to hide. According to tradition, a Praetorian named<space/><link><target>Gratus</target></link><space/>found him hiding behind a curtain and suddenly declared him<space/><italics><link><target>princeps</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Josephus"></extension><space/>A section of the guard may have planned in advance to seek out Claudius, perhaps with his approval. They reassured him that they were not one of the battalions looking for revenge. He was spirited away to the<space/><link><target>Castra Praetoria</target><part>Praetorian camp</part></link><space/>and put under their protection.</paragraph><paragraph>The Senate quickly met and began debating a change of government, but this eventually devolved into an argument over which of them would be the new<space/><italics>princeps</italics>. When they heard of the Praetorians' claim, they demanded that Claudius be delivered to them for approval, but he refused, sensing the danger that would come with complying. Some historians, particularly<space/><link><target>Josephus</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Josephus<space/><italics>Ant. Iud.</italics><space/>XIX.</extension><space/>claim that Claudius was directed in his actions by the<space/><link><target>Iudaea Province</target><part>Judaean</part></link><space/>King<space/><link><target>Herod Agrippa</target></link>. However, an earlier version of events by the same ancient author downplays Agrippa's role<extension extension_name='ref'>Josephus<space/><italics>Bellum Iudiacum</italics><space/>II, 204233.</extension><space/>so it remains uncertain. Eventually the Senate was forced to give in and, in return, Claudius pardoned nearly all the assassins.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Claudiuspax.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Claudius issued this ''<link><target>denarius</target></link>'' type to emphasize his<space/><link><target>clemency</target></link><space/>after Caligula's assassination. The depiction of the goddess<space/><link><target>Pax-Nemesis</target></link>, representing subdued vengeance, would be used on the coins of many later emperors.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>As Emperor</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove-section</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template>Claudius took several steps to legitimize his rule against potential usurpers, most of them emphasizing his place within the Julio-Claudian family. He adopted the name &quot;Caesar&quot; as a<space/><link><target>cognomen</target></link>, as the name still carried great weight with the populace. In order to do so, he dropped the cognomen &quot;Nero&quot; which he had adopted as<space/><italics>paterfamilias</italics><space/>of the Claudii Nerones when his brother Germanicus was adopted out.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While Claudius had never been formally adopted either by Augustus or his successors, he was nevertheless the grandson of his sister Octavia, and so he felt that he had the right of family. He also adopted the name &quot;Augustus&quot; as the two previous emperors had done at their accessions. He kept the honorific &quot;Germanicus&quot; to display the connection with his heroic brother. He deified his paternal grandmother Livia to highlight her position as wife of the divine Augustus. Claudius frequently used the term &quot;filius Drusi&quot; (son of Drusus) in his titles, in order to remind the people of his legendary father and lay claim to his reputation.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Since Claudius was the first Emperor proclaimed on the initiative of the Praetorian Guard instead of the Senate, his repute suffered at the hands of commentators (such as<space/><link><target>Seneca the Younger</target><part>Seneca</part></link>). Moreover, he was the first Emperor who resorted to bribery as a means to secure army loyalty and rewarded the soldiers of the Praetorian Guard that had elevated him with 15,000 sesterces.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suetonius,<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>10</extension><space/>Tiberius and Augustus had both left gifts to the army and guard in their<space/><link><target>will (law)</target><part>wills</part></link>, and upon Caligula's death the same would have been expected, even if no will existed. Claudius remained grateful to the guard, however, issuing coins with tributes to the Praetorians in the early part of his reign.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Expansion of the Empire</heading><paragraph>Under Claudius, the Empire underwent its first major expansion since the reign of Augustus. The provinces of<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Noricum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pamphylia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lycia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Judea</target></link><space/>were<space/><link><target>annexation</target><part>annexed</part></link><space/>(or put under direct rule) under various circumstances during his term. The annexation of<space/><link><target>Mauretania</target></link>, begun under Caligula, was completed after the defeat of rebel forces, and the official division of the former client kingdom into two Imperial provinces.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pliny 5.15.2, Cassius Dio, 60.8, 60.9</extension><space/>The most far-reaching conquest was the<space/><link><target>Roman conquest of Britain</target><part>conquest of Britannia</part></link>''.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza, Chap. 9</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Roman emperor head.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Bronze head of Claudius found in the<space/><link><target>River Alde</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Rendham</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Saxmundham</target></link>, Suffolk (<link><target>British Museum</target></link>). Potentially taken from the<space/><link><target>Temple of Claudius, Colchester</target><part>Temple of Claudius</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Colonia Victricensis</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Sack of Camulodunum</target><part>Boudican revolt</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/pe_prb/b/bronze_head_of_claudius.aspx</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Head of the Emperor Claudius</arg><arg name="publisher">British Museum</arg></template></extension></part></link>In 43 AD, Claudius sent<space/><link><target>Aulus Plautius</target></link><space/>with four<space/><link><target>Roman legion</target><part>legions</part></link><space/>to Britain (<italics>Britannia</italics>) after an appeal from an ousted tribal ally. Britain was an attractive target for Rome because of its material wealth&amp;nbsp; particularly mines and slaves. It was also a haven for<space/><link><target>Gaul</target><part>Gallic</part></link><space/>rebels and the like, and so could not be left alone much longer. Claudius himself travelled to the island after the completion of initial offensives, bringing with him reinforcements and elephants. The latter must have made an impression on the<space/><link><target>British people</target><part>Britons</part></link><space/>when they were displayed in the large tribal centre of<space/><link><target>Camulodunum</target></link>, modern day<space/><link><target>Colchester</target></link>. The Roman<space/><italics><link><target>Colonia (Roman)</target><part>colonia</part></link></italics><space/>of<space/><italics>Colonia Claudia Victricensis</italics><space/>was established as the provincial capital of the newly established<space/><link><target>Roman Britain</target><part>province of Britannia</part></link><space/>at Camulodunum,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crummy 97">Crummy, Philip (1997) City of Victory; the story of Colchester - Britain's first Roman town. Published by Colchester Archaeological Trust (ISBN 1 897719 04 3)</extension><space/>where a large<space/><link><target>Temple of Claudius, Colchester</target><part>Temple was dedicated in his honour</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crummy 97"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He left after 16 days, but remained in the provinces for some time. The Senate granted him a<space/><link><target>Roman triumph</target><part>triumph</part></link><space/>for his efforts. Only members of the Imperial family were allowed such honours, but Claudius subsequently lifted this restriction for some of his conquering generals. He was granted the honorific &quot;Britannicus&quot; but only accepted it on behalf of his son, never using the title himself. When the Briton general<space/><link><target>Caractacus</target></link><space/>was captured in 50 AD, Claudius granted him clemency. Caractacus lived out his days on land provided by the Roman state, an unusual end for an enemy commander.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius conducted a census in 48 that found 5,984,072 Roman citizens<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza, Chap. 7, p. 142</extension><space/>(adult males with<space/><link><target>Roman citizenship</target></link>; women, children, slaves, and free adult males without Roman citizenship were not counted), an increase of around a million since the census conducted at Augustus' death. He had helped increase this number through the foundation of Roman colonies that were granted blanket<space/><link><target>Roman citizenship</target><part>citizenship</part></link>. These colonies were often made out of existing communities, especially those with elites who could rally the populace to the Roman cause. Several colonies were placed in new provinces or on the border of the Empire to secure Roman holdings as quickly as possible.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Judicial and legislative affairs</heading><paragraph>Claudius personally judged many of the legal cases tried during his reign. Ancient historians have many complaints about this, stating that his judgments were variable and sometimes did not follow the law.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>15. Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LXI 33.</extension><space/>He was also easily swayed. Nevertheless, Claudius paid detailed attention to the operation of the judicial system.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Scramuzza ch6"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He extended the summer court session, as well as the winter term, by shortening the traditional breaks. Claudius also made a law requiring plaintiffs to remain in the city while their cases were pending, as defendants had previously been required to do. These measures had the effect of clearing out the docket. The minimum age for jurors was also raised to 25 in order to ensure a more experienced jury pool.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Scramuzza ch6">Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 6</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Claudius also settled disputes in the provinces. He freed the island of<space/><link><target>Rhodes</target></link><space/>from Roman rule for their good faith and exempted<space/><link><target>Troy</target></link><space/>from taxes. Early in his reign, the<space/><link><target>Greeks</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jews</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link><space/>sent him two embassies at once after riots broke out between the two communities. This resulted in the famous &quot;Letter to the Alexandrians&quot;, which reaffirmed Jewish rights in the city but also forbade them to move in more families en masse. According to<space/><link><target>Josephus</target></link>, he then reaffirmed the rights and freedoms of all the Jews in the Empire.<extension extension_name='ref'>Josephus<space/><italics>Ant. Iud.</italics><space/>XIX.5.3 (287).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of Claudius's investigators discovered that many old Roman citizens based in the modern city of<space/><link><target>Trento</target></link><space/>were not in fact citizens.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 7, p.129</extension><space/>The Emperor issued a declaration, contained in the<space/><italics><link><target>Tabula clesiana</target></link></italics>, that they would be considered to hold citizenship from then on, since to strip them of their status would cause major problems. However, in individual cases, Claudius punished false assumption of citizenship harshly, making it a capital offense. Similarly, any freedmen found to be laying false claim to membership of the<space/><link><target>Roman equestrian order</target></link><space/>were sold back into slavery.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 7</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Numerous edicts were issued throughout Claudius' reign. These were on a number of topics, everything from medical advice to moral judgments. A famous medical examples is one promoting<space/><link><target>Taxus baccata</target><part>yew</part></link><space/>juice as a cure for snakebite.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suetonius,<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>16</extension><space/>Suetonius wrote that he is even said to have thought of an edict allowing public flatulence for good health.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suetonius,<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>32 http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Claudius*.html#32</extension><space/>One of the more famous edicts concerned the status of sick slaves. Masters had been abandoning ailing slaves at the<space/><link><target>Tiber Island</target><part>temple of Aesculapius</part></link><space/>on Tiber Island to die instead of providing them with medical assistance and care, and then reclaiming them if they lived. Claudius ruled that slaves who were thus abandoned and recovered after such treatment would be free. Furthermore, masters who chose to kill slaves rather than take care of them were liable to be charged with murder.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Claudius*.html#25'>Suetonius, ''Claud.'' 51<space/></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Public works</heading><paragraph>Claudius embarked on many public works throughout his reign, both in the capital and in the provinces. He built two<space/><link><target>Aqueduct (Roman)</target><part>aqueducts</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Aqua Claudia</target></link>, begun by<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Anio Novus</target></link>. These entered the city in 52 and met at the famous<space/><link><target>Porta Maggiore</target></link>. He also restored a third, the<space/><link><target>Aqua Virgo</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Esquilino - Porta Maggiore - st1.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Porta Maggiore</target></link><space/>aqueduct in Rome</part></link>He paid special attention to transportation. Throughout<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>and the provinces he built roads and canals. Among these was a large canal leading from the<space/><link><target>Rhine</target></link><space/>to the sea, as well as a road from Italy to Germany&amp;nbsp; both begun by his father, Drusus. Closer to Rome, he built a navigable canal on the<space/><link><target>Tiber</target></link>, leading to<space/><link><target>Portus</target></link>, his new port just north of<space/><link><target>Ostia Antica (archaeological site)</target><part>Ostia</part></link>. This port was constructed in a semicircle with two<space/><link><target>Mole (architecture)</target><part>moles</part></link><space/>and a lighthouse at its mouth. The construction also had the effect of reducing flooding in Rome.</paragraph><paragraph>The port at Ostia was part of Claudius' solution to the constant grain shortages that occurred in winter, after the Roman shipping season. The other part of his solution was to insure the ships of grain merchants who were willing to risk travelling to Egypt in the off-season. He also granted their sailors special privileges, including citizenship and exemption from the<space/><link><target>Lex Papia Poppaea</target><part>Lex Papia-Poppaea</part></link>, a law that regulated marriage. In addition, he repealed the taxes that<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link><space/>had instituted on food, and further reduced taxes on communities suffering<space/><link><target>drought</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>famine</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The last part of Claudius' plan was to increase the amount of arable land in Italy. This was to be achieved by draining the<space/><link><target>Fucine lake</target></link>, which would have the added benefit of making the nearby river navigable year-round.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tacitus<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 57</extension><space/>A tunnel was dug through the lake bed, but the plan was a failure. The tunnel was crooked and not large enough to carry the water, which caused it to back up when opened. The resultant flood washed out a large gladiatorial exhibition held to commemorate the opening, causing Claudius to run for his life along with the other spectators. The draining of the lake was revisited many times in history, including by Emperors<space/><link><target>Trajan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hadrian</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Emperor</target></link><space/><link><target>Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Frederick II</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>. It was finally achieved by the Prince<space/><link><target>Torlonia</target></link><space/>in the 19th century, producing over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>160000</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>km2</arg></template><space/>of new arable land.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940), Chap. 9, pp. 1734</extension><space/>He expanded the Claudian tunnel to three times its original size.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Claudius and the Senate</heading><paragraph>Because of the circumstances of his accession, Claudius took great pains to please the Senate. During regular sessions, the Emperor sat among the Senate body, speaking in turn. When introducing a law, he sat on a bench between the consuls in his position as Holder of the Power of<space/><link><target>Tribune</target></link><space/>(The Emperor could not officially serve as a Tribune of the Plebes as he was a<space/><link><target>Patrician (ancient Rome)</target><part>Patrician</part></link>, but it was a power taken by previous rulers). He refused to accept all his predecessors' titles (including<space/><link><target>Imperator</target></link>) at the beginning of his reign, preferring to earn them in due course. He allowed the Senate to issue its own bronze coinage for the first time since Augustus. He also put the Imperial provinces of<space/><link><target>Macedonia (Roman province)</target><part>Macedonia</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Achaea (Roman province)</target><part>Achaea</part></link><space/>back under Senate control.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius set about remodeling the Senate into a more efficient, representative body. He chided the senators about their reluctance to debate bills introduced by himself, as noted in the fragments of a surviving speech:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>If you accept these proposals, Conscript Fathers, say so at once and simply, in accordance with your convictions. If you do not accept them, find alternatives, but do so here and now; or if you wish to take time for consideration, take it, provided you do not forget that you must be ready to pronounce your opinion whenever you may be summoned to meet. It ill befits the dignity of the Senate that the consul designate should repeat the phrases of the consuls word for word as his opinion, and that every one else should merely say 'I approve', and that then, after leaving, the assembly should announce 'We debated'.<ref>English translation of Berlin papyrus by W.D. Hogarth, in Momigliano (1934).</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 47 he assumed the office of<space/><italics><link><target>Roman censor</target><part>Censor</part></link></italics><space/>with<space/><link><target>Lucius Vitellius</target></link>, which had been allowed to lapse for some time. He struck the names of many senators and equites who no longer met qualifications, but showed respect by allowing them to resign in advance. At the same time, he sought to admit eligible men from the provinces. The<space/><link><target>Lyon Tablet</target></link><space/>preserves his speech on the admittance of Gallic senators, in which he addresses the Senate with reverence but also with criticism for their disdain of these men. (He even jokes about how the Senate had admitted members from beyond<space/><link><target>Gallia Narbonensis</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Lyons, France</target></link>), i.e. himself). He also increased the number of<space/><link><target>Patrician (ancient Rome)</target><part>Patricians</part></link><space/>by adding new families to the dwindling number of noble lines. Here he followed the precedent of<space/><link><target>Lucius Junius Brutus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, many in the Senate remained hostile to Claudius, and many plots were made on his life. This hostility carried over into the historical accounts. As a result, Claudius was forced to reduce the Senate's power for efficiency. The administration of Ostia was turned over to an Imperial<space/><link><target>Promagistrate</target><part>Procurator</part></link><space/>after construction of the port. Administration of many of the empire's financial concerns was turned over to Imperial appointees and freedmen. This led to further resentment and suggestions that these same freedmen were ruling the Emperor.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Plots and coup attempts</heading><paragraph>Several<space/><link><target>coup</target></link><space/>attempts were made during Claudius' reign, resulting in the deaths of many senators.<space/><link><target>Appius Silanus</target></link><space/>was executed early in Claudius' reign under questionable circumstances. Shortly after, a large rebellion was undertaken by the Senator Vinicianus and<space/><link><target>Lucius Arruntius Camillus Scribonianus</target><part>Scribonianus</part></link>, the governor of<space/><link><target>Dalmatia (Roman province)</target><part>Dalmatia</part></link><space/>and gained quite a few senatorial supporters. It ultimately failed because of the reluctance of Scribonianus' troops, and the<space/><link><target>suicide</target></link><space/>of the main conspirators.</paragraph><paragraph>Many other senators tried different conspiracies and were condemned. Claudius' son-in-law<space/><link><target>Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus (Claudia Antonia's first husband)</target><part>Pompeius Magnus</part></link><space/>was executed for his part in a conspiracy with his father Crassus Frugi. Another plot involved the consulars Lusiius Saturninus, Cornelius Lupus, and Pompeius Pedo.</paragraph><paragraph>In 46,<space/><link><target>Asinius Gallus</target></link>, the grandson of<space/><link><target>Gaius Asinius Pollio (consul 40 BC)</target><part>Asinius Pollio</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Titus Statilius Taurus Corvinus</target></link><space/>were exiled for a plot hatched with several of Claudius' own freedmen.<space/><link><target>Valerius Asiaticus</target></link><space/>was executed without public trial for unknown reasons. The ancient sources say the charge was<space/><link><target>adultery</target></link>, and that Claudius was tricked into issuing the punishment. However, Claudius singles out Asiaticus for special damnation in his speech on the Gauls, which dates over a year later, suggesting that the charge must have been much more serious.</paragraph><paragraph>Asiaticus had been a claimant to the throne in the chaos following Caligula's death and a co-consul with the Titus Statilius Taurus Corvinus mentioned above. Most of these conspiracies took place before Claudius' term as<space/><link><target>Roman censor</target><part>Censor</part></link>, and may have induced him to review the Senatorial rolls. The conspiracy of<space/><link><target>Gaius Silius</target></link><space/>in the year after his Censorship, 48, is detailed in the section discussing Claudius' third wife,<space/><link><target>Messalina</target></link>. Suetonius states that a total of 35 senators and 300 knights were executed for offenses during Claudius' reign.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>29.</extension><space/>Needless to say, the responses to these conspiracies could not have helped Senate-emperor relations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Secretariat and centralization of powers</heading><paragraph>Claudius was hardly the first emperor to use<space/><link><target>Freedman</target><part>freedmen</part></link><space/>to help with the day-to-day running of the Empire. He was, however, forced to increase their role as the powers of the<space/><italics>princeps</italics><space/>became more centralized and the burden larger. This was partly due to the ongoing hostility of the Senate, as mentioned above, but also due to his respect for the senators. Claudius did not want free-born magistrates to have to serve under him, as if they were not peers.</paragraph><paragraph>The secretariat was divided into bureaus, with each being placed under the leadership of one freedman.<space/><link><target>Tiberius Claudius Narcissus</target><part>Narcissus</part></link><space/>was the secretary of correspondence.<space/><link><target>Pallas (freedman)</target><part>Pallas</part></link><space/>became the secretary of the treasury.<space/><link><target>Gaius Julius Callistus</target><part>Callistus</part></link><space/>became secretary of justice. There was a fourth bureau for miscellaneous issues, which was put under<space/><link><target>Polybius (freedman)</target><part>Polybius</part></link><space/>until his execution for treason. The freedmen could also officially speak for the Emperor, as when Narcissus addressed the troops in Claudius' stead before the conquest of Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tac">Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 65. Seneca<space/><italics>Ad Polybium.</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since these were important positions, the senators were aghast at their being placed in the hands of former slaves. If freedmen had total control of money, letters, and law, it seemed it would not be hard for them to manipulate the Emperor. This is exactly the accusation put forth by the ancient sources. However, these same sources admit that the freedmen were loyal to Claudius.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tac"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He was similarly appreciative of them and gave them due credit for policies where he had used their advice. However, if they showed treasonous inclinations, the Emperor did punish them with just force, as in the case of Polybius and Pallas' brother,<space/><link><target>Antonius Felix</target><part>Felix</part></link>. There is no evidence that the character of Claudius' policies and edicts changed with the rise and fall of the various freedmen, suggesting that he was firmly in control throughout.</paragraph><paragraph>Regardless of the extent of their political power, the freedmen did manage to amass wealth through their positions.<space/><link><target>Pliny the Elder</target></link><space/>notes that several of them were richer than<space/><link><target>Crassus</target></link>, the richest man of the<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target><part>Republican era</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pliny<space/><italics>Natural History</italics><space/>134.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Religious reforms</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Claudius (M.A.N. Madrid) 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Portrait of Claudius,<space/><link><target>National Archaeological Museum of Spain</target></link></part></link>Claudius, as the author of a treatise on Augustus' religious reforms, felt himself in a good position to institute some of his own. He had strong opinions about the proper form for state religion. He refused the request of Alexandrian Greeks to dedicate a temple to his divinity, saying that only gods may choose new gods. He restored lost days to festivals and got rid of many extraneous celebrations added by Caligula. He re-instituted old observances and archaic language.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius was concerned with the spread of eastern mysteries within the city and searched for more Roman replacements. He emphasized the<space/><link><target>Eleusinian mysteries</target></link><space/>which had been practiced by so many during the Republic. He expelled foreign astrologers, and at the same time rehabilitated the old Roman soothsayers (known as<space/><link><target>haruspices</target></link>) as a replacement. He was especially hard on<space/><link><target>Druidism</target></link>, because of its incompatibility with the Roman state religion and its<space/><link><target>Proselytism</target><part>proselytizing</part></link><space/>activities.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It is also reported that at one time he expelled the Jews from Rome, probably because the Jews within the city caused continuous disturbances at the instigation of<space/><link><target>Chrestus</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>There is some debate about what actually happened. It is reported by Suetonius and in Acts (18:2), Cassius Dio minimizes the event and Josephuswho was reporting on Jewish eventsdoes not mention it at all. Some scholars hold that it didn't happen, while others have only a few missionaries expelled for the short term.</extension><space/>Claudius opposed proselytizing in any religion, even in those regions where he allowed natives to worship freely. The results of all these efforts were recognized even by Seneca, who has an ancient Latin god defend Claudius in his satire.<extension extension_name='ref'>Seneca<space/><italics>Apocolo.</italics><space/>9.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Public games and entertainments</heading><paragraph>According to Suetonius, Claudius was extraordinarily fond of games. He is said to have risen with the crowd after gladiatorial matches and given unrestrained praise to the fighters.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet. Claud. 12</extension><space/>Claudius also presided over many new and original events. Soon after coming into power, Claudius instituted games to be held in honor of his father on the latter's birthday.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet. Claud. 11</extension><space/>Annual games were also held in honour of his accession, and took place at the Praetorian camp where Claudius had first been proclaimed Emperor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet">Suet. Claud. 21</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Claudius organised a performance of the<space/><link><target>Secular Games</target></link>, marking the 800th anniversary of the founding of Rome. Augustus had performed the same games less than a century prior. Augustus' excuse was that the interval for the games was 110 years, not 100, but his date actually did not qualify under either reasoning.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet"></extension><space/>Claudius also presented naval battles to mark the attempted draining of the<space/><link><target>Fucine Lake</target></link>, as well as many other public games and shows.</paragraph><paragraph>At Ostia, in front of a crowd of spectators, Claudius fought a<space/><link><target>killer whale</target></link><space/>which was trapped in the harbour. The event was witnessed by<space/><link><target>Pliny the Elder</target></link>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>A killer whale was actually seen in the harbour of Ostia, locked in combat with the emperor Claudius. She had come when he was completing the construction of the harbour, drawn there by the wreck of a ship bringing leather hides from Gaul, and feeding there over a number of days, had made a furrow in the shallows: the waves had raised up such a mound of sand that she couldn't turn around at all, and while she was pursuing her banquet as the waves moved it shorewards, her back stuck up out of the water like the overturned keel of a boat. The Emperor ordered that a large array of nets be stretched across the mouths of the harbour, and setting out in person with the Praetorian cohorts gave a show to the Roman people, soldiers showering lances from attacking ships, one of which I saw swamped by the beast's waterspout and sunk. — "''Historia Naturalis''" IX.14–15.<ref>[http://www.ostia-antica.org/~atexts/plinsen.htm Translation of] Pliny's ''Historia Naturalis''</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Claudius also restored and adorned many of the venues around Rome. The old wooden barriers of the<space/><link><target>Circus Maximus</target></link><space/>were replaced with ones made of gold-ornamented marble.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet"></extension><space/>A new section of the Circus was designated for seating the senators, who previously had sat among the general public.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet"></extension><space/>Claudius rebuilt<space/><link><target>Pompey's Theatre</target></link><space/>after it had been destroyed by fire, organising special fights at the re-dedication which he observed from a special platform in the orchestra box.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Marriages and personal life</heading><paragraph>Suetonius and the other ancient authors accused Claudius of being dominated by women and wives, of being<space/><link><target>wikt:uxorious</target><part>uxorious</part></link>, and of being a<space/><link><target>Womanizing</target><part>womanizer</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius married four times, after two failed betrothals. The first betrothal was to his distant cousin<space/><link><target>Aemilia Lepida (fiancee of Claudius)</target><part>Aemilia Lepida</part></link>, but was broken for political reasons. The second was to<space/><link><target>Livia Medullina</target></link>, which ended with Medullina's sudden death on their wedding day.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Plautia Urgulanilla</heading><paragraph><link><target>Plautia Urgulanilla</target></link><space/>was the granddaughter of Livia's confidant<space/><link><target>Urgulania</target></link>. During their marriage she gave birth to a son, Claudius Drusus. Drusus died of asphyxiation in his early teens, shortly after becoming engaged to Junilla, the daughter of<space/><link><target>Sejanus</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius later divorced Urgulanilla for adultery and on suspicion of murdering her sister-in-law Apronia. When Urgulanilla gave birth after the divorce, Claudius<space/><link><target>repudiate</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>the baby girl, Claudia, as the father was allegedly one of his own freedmen. This action made him later the target of criticism by his enemies.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aelia Paetina</heading><paragraph>Soon after (possibly in 28), Claudius married<space/><link><target>Aelia Paetina</target></link>, a relative of Sejanus, if not Sejanus's adoptive sister. During their marriage, Claudius and Paetina had a daughter,<space/><link><target>Claudia Antonia</target></link>. He later divorced her after the marriage became a political liability, although Leon (1948) suggests it may have been due to emotional and mental abuse by Paetina.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Valeria Messalina</heading><paragraph>Some years after divorcing Aelia Paetina, in 38 or early 39, Claudius married<space/><link><target>Valeria Messalina</target></link>, who was his first cousin once removed and closely allied with Caligula's circle. Shortly thereafter, she gave birth to a daughter<space/><link><target>Claudia Octavia</target></link>. A son, first named Tiberius Claudius Germanicus, and later known as<space/><link><target>Britannicus</target></link>, was born just after Claudius' accession.</paragraph><paragraph>This marriage ended in tragedy. The ancient historians allege that Messalina was a<space/><link><target>Hypersexuality</target><part>nymphomaniac</part></link><space/>who was regularly unfaithful to Claudius<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link><space/>states she went so far as to compete with a<space/><link><target>prostitute</target></link><space/>to see who could have the most sexual partners in a night<extension extension_name='ref'>Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XI 10. Also Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LXI 31, and Pliny<space/><italics>Nat. Hist.</italics><space/>X 172.</extension><space/>and manipulated his policies in order to amass wealth. In 48, Messalina married her lover<space/><link><target>Gaius Silius (consul designatus 49 AD)</target><part>Gaius Silius</part></link><space/>in a public ceremony while Claudius was at<space/><link><target>Ostia Antica (archaeological site)</target><part>Ostia</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Sources disagree as to whether or not she divorced the Emperor first, and whether the intention was to usurp the throne. Scramuzza, in his biography, suggests that Silius may have convinced Messalina that Claudius was doomed, and the union was her only hope of retaining rank and protecting her children.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940) p.&amp;nbsp;90. Momigliano (1934) pp.&amp;nbsp;67. Levick (1990) p.&amp;nbsp;19.</extension><space/>The historian<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link><space/>suggests that Claudius's ongoing term as Censor may have prevented him from noticing the affair before it reached such a critical point.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XI. 25, 8.</extension><space/>Whatever the case, the result was the execution of Silius, Messalina, and most of her circle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Farquhar, Michael (2001).<space/><italics>A Treasure of Royal Scandals</italics>, p.212. Penguin Books, New York. ISBN 0-7394-2025-9.</extension><space/>Claudius made the<space/><link><target>Praetorians</target></link><space/>promise to kill him if he ever married again.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Agrippina the Younger</heading><paragraph>Claudius did marry once more. The ancient sources tell that his freedmen pushed three candidates,<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link>'s third wife<space/><link><target>Lollia Paulina</target></link>, Claudius's divorced second wife<space/><link><target>Aelia Paetina</target></link><space/>and Claudius's niece<space/><link><target>Agrippina the Younger</target></link>. According to Suetonius, Agrippina won out through her feminine wiles.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>26.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The truth is likely more political. The attempted<space/><link><target>coup d'etat</target></link><space/>by Silius and Messalina had probably made Claudius realize the weakness of his position as a member of the Claudian but not the Julian family. This weakness was compounded by the fact that he did not have an obvious adult heir, Britannicus being just a boy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Scramuzza91-92">Scramuzza (1940) pp.&amp;nbsp;9192. See also Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 6, 7; Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>26.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Agrippina was one of the few remaining descendants of Augustus, and her son Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus (the future Emperor<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link>) was one of the last males of the Imperial family. Coup attempts could rally around the pair and Agrippina was already showing such ambition. It has been suggested in recent times that the Senate may have pushed for the marriage, to end the feud between the Julian and Claudian branches.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Scramuzza91-92"></extension><space/>This feud dated back to Agrippina's<space/><link><target>Agrippina the Elder</target><part>mother's</part></link><space/>actions against Tiberius after the death of her husband<space/><link><target>Germanicus</target></link><space/>(Claudius's brother), actions which Tiberius had gladly punished. In any case, Claudius accepted Agrippina and later adopted the newly mature Nero as his son.</paragraph><paragraph>Nero was made joint heir with the underage<space/><link><target>Britannicus</target></link>, married to Octavia and promoted. This was not as unusual as it seems, to people acquainted with hereditary monarchies.<space/><link><target>Barbara Levick</target></link><space/>notes that Augustus had named his grandson<space/><link><target>Postumus Agrippa</target></link><space/>and his stepson<space/><link><target>Tiberius</target></link><space/>as joint heirs.<extension extension_name='ref'>Levick (1990) p.&amp;nbsp;70. See also Scramuzza (1940) p.&amp;nbsp;92.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Tiberius named<space/><link><target>Caligula</target></link><space/>joint heir with his grandson<space/><link><target>Tiberius Gemellus</target></link>. Adoption of adults or near adults was an old tradition in Rome, when a suitable natural adult heir was unavailable as was the case during Britannicus' minority. S.V. Oost suggests that Claudius had previously looked to adopt one of his sons-in-law to protect his own reign.<extension extension_name='ref'>Oost (1958).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Faustus Cornelius Sulla Felix</target></link>, married to his daughter<space/><link><target>Claudia Antonia</target></link>, was only descended from Octavia and Antony on one side&amp;nbsp; not close enough to the Imperial family to prevent doubts (that did not stop others from making him the object of a coup attempt against Nero a few years later). Besides which, he was the half-brother of<space/><link><target>Valeria Messalina</target></link><space/>and at this time those wounds were still fresh.<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link><space/>was more popular with the general public as the grandson of Germanicus and the direct descendant of Augustus.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Claudius' affliction and personality</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Statue Claudius Vatikanische Museen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Claudius depicted as the<space/><link><target>Jupiter (mythology)</target><part>Roman god Jupiter</part></link></part></link>The historian<space/><link><target>Lives of the Twelve Caesars</target><part>Suetonius</part></link><space/>describes the physical manifestations of Claudius' affliction in relatively good detail.<extension extension_name='ref' name="boyjnt">Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>30.</extension><space/>His knees were weak and gave way under him and his head shook. He stammered and his speech was confused. He slobbered and his nose ran when he was excited. The<space/><link><target>Stoicism</target><part>Stoic</part></link><space/><link><target>Seneca the Younger</target><part>Seneca</part></link><space/>states in his<space/><italics><link><target>Apocolocyntosis</target></link></italics><space/>that Claudius' voice belonged to no land animal, and that his hands were weak as well.<extension extension_name='ref'>Seneca<space/><italics>Apocolo.</italics><space/>5, 6.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, he showed no physical deformity, as Suetonius notes that when calm and seated he was a tall, well-built figure of<space/><italics><link><target>Dignitas (Roman concept)</target><part>dignitas</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="boyjnt"></extension><space/>When angered or stressed, his symptoms became worse. Historians agree that this condition improved upon his accession to the throne.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>31.</extension><space/>Claudius himself claimed that he had exaggerated his ailments to save his life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>38.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Modern assessments of his health have changed several times in the past century. Prior to<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>,<space/><link><target>infantile paralysis</target></link><space/>(or polio) was widely accepted as the cause. This is the diagnosis used in<space/><link><target>Robert Graves</target></link>'<space/><link><target>Claudius (novel)</target><part>Claudius novels</part></link>, first published in the 1930s. Polio does not explain many of the described symptoms, however, and a more recent theory implicates<space/><link><target>cerebral palsy</target></link><space/>as the cause, as outlined by Ernestine Leon.<extension extension_name='ref'>Leon (1948).</extension><space/><link><target>Tourette syndrome</target></link><space/>has also been considered a possibility.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burden, George.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.mentalhealth.com/mag1/p5m-tor1.html'>The Imperial Gene</link>,<space/><italics>The Medical Post</italics>, 16 July 1996. Retrieved 24 June 2007.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1080/09647040902872775</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>20628951</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Neurological Mystery from History: The Case of Claudius Caesar</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010</arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Murad</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Ali</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of the History of the Neurosciences</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>19</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>221–7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As a person, ancient historians described Claudius as generous and lowbrow, a man who sometimes lunched with the<space/><link><target>plebeians</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>5, 21, 40; Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LX 2, 5, 12, 31.</extension><space/>They also paint him as bloodthirsty and cruel, overly fond of<space/><link><target>gladiator</target><trail>ial</trail></link><space/>combat and executions, and very quick to anger; Claudius himself acknowledged the latter trait, and apologized publicly for his temper.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>34, 38. Tacitus<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 20.</extension><space/>According to the ancient historians he was also overly trusting, and easily manipulated by his wives and freedmen.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>29. Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LX 2, 8.</extension><space/>But at the same time they portray him as paranoid and apathetic, dull and easily confused.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>35, 36, 37, 39, 40. Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LX 2, 3.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The extant works of Claudius present a different view, painting a picture of an intelligent, scholarly, well-read, and conscientious administrator with an eye to detail and justice. Thus, Claudius becomes an enigma. Since the discovery of his &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.csun.edu/~hcfll004/claualex.html'>Letter to the Alexandrians</link>&quot; in the last century, much work has been done to rehabilitate Claudius and determine where the truth lies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Scholarly works and their impact</heading><paragraph>Claudius wrote copiously throughout his life.<space/><link><target>Arnaldo Momigliano</target></link><space/>states that during the reign of Tiberius&amp;nbsp; which covers the peak of Claudius' literary career&amp;nbsp; it became impolitic to speak of republican Rome. The trend among the young historians was to either write about the new empire or obscure antiquarian subjects. Claudius was the rare scholar who covered both.<extension extension_name='ref'>Momigliano (1934) pp.&amp;nbsp;46.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Besides the history of Augustus' reign that caused him so much grief, his major works included an<space/><link><target>Etruscan civilization</target><part>Etruscan</part></link><space/>history and eight volumes on<space/><link><target>Carthage</target><part>Carthaginian</part></link><space/>history, as well as an<space/><link><target>Etruscan language</target><part>Etruscan</part></link><space/>dictionary and a book on dice playing. (Claudius is actually the last person known to have been able to read Etruscan.)<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>Despite the general avoidance of the Republican era, he penned a defense of<space/><link><target>Cicero</target></link><space/>against the charges of<space/><link><target>Gaius Asinius Gallus Saloninus</target><part>Asinius Gallus</part></link>. Modern historians have used this to determine the nature of his politics and of the aborted chapters of his civil war history.</paragraph><paragraph>He proposed a reform of the<space/><link><target>Latin alphabet</target></link><space/>by the addition of<space/><link><target>Claudian letters</target><part>three new letters</part></link>, two of which served the function of the modern letters<space/><italics>W</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Y</italics>. He officially instituted the change during his censorship but they did not survive his reign. Claudius also tried to revive the old custom of putting dots between successive words (Classical Latin was written with no spacing). Finally, he wrote an eight-volume autobiography, that Suetonius describes as lacking in taste.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>41.</extension><space/>Since Claudius (like most of the members of his dynasty) harshly criticized his predecessors and relatives in surviving speeches,<extension extension_name='ref'>See Claudius' letter to the people of Trent (linked below), in which he refers to the &quot;obstinate retirement&quot; of Tiberius. See also Josephus<space/><italics>Ant Iud.</italics><space/>XIX, where an edict of Claudius refers to Caligula's &quot;madness and lack of understanding.&quot;</extension><space/>it is not hard to imagine the nature of Suetonius' charge.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Claudian letters.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Claudian letters</target></link></part></link>None of the works survive but live on as sources for the surviving histories of the Julio-Claudian dynasty. Suetonius quotes Claudius' autobiography once and must have used it as a source numerous times. Tacitus uses Claudius' arguments for the orthographical innovations mentioned above and may have used him for some of the more antiquarian passages in his annals. Claudius is the source for numerous passages of<space/><link><target>Pliny the Elder</target><part>Pliny's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Natural History (Pliny)</target><part>Natural History</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Momigliano (1934) Chap.&amp;nbsp;1, note&amp;nbsp;20 (p.&amp;nbsp;83). Pliny credits him by name in Book VII 35.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The influence of historical study on Claudius is obvious. In his speech on Gallic senators, he uses a version of the founding of Rome identical to that of Livy, his tutor in adolescence. The detail of his speech borders on the pedantic, a common mark of all his extant works and he goes into long digressions on related matters. This indicates a deep knowledge of a variety of historical subjects, that he could not help but share. Many of the public works instituted in his reign were based on plans first suggested by<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link>. Levick believes this emulation of Caesar may have spread to all aspects of his policies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Levick (1978).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>His censorship seems to have been based on those of his ancestors, particularly<space/><link><target>Appius Claudius Caecus</target></link><space/>and he used the office to put into place many policies based on those of Republican times. This is when many of his religious reforms took effect and his building efforts greatly increased during his tenure. In fact, his assumption of the office of Censor may have been motivated by a desire to see his academic labors bear fruit. For example, he believed (as most Romans) that his ancestor<space/><link><target>Appius Claudius Caecus</target></link><space/>had used the censorship to introduce<space/><link><target>R</target><part>the letter &quot;R&quot;</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Ryan (1993) refers to the historian<space/><link><target>Varro</target></link>'s account of the introduction</extension><space/>and so used his own term to introduce his new letters.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Death</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Togato con tesa dell'imperatore claudio, inv. 2221.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>A statue of Claudius in the<space/><link><target>Vatican Museums</target><part>Vatican museum</part></link>.</part></link>The consensus of ancient historians was that Claudius was murdered by poison&amp;nbsp; possibly contained in mushrooms or on a feather&amp;nbsp; and died in the early hours of 13 October 54 CE. Accounts vary greatly. Some claim Claudius was in Rome<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet44">Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>44</extension><space/>while others claim he was in<space/><link><target>Sinuessa</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 66</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nearly all implicate his final wife,<space/><link><target>Agrippina the Younger</target><part>Agrippina</part></link>, as the instigator. Agrippina and Claudius had become more combative in the months leading up to his death. This carried on to the point where Claudius openly lamented his bad wives, and he began to comment on Britannicus' approaching manhood with an eye towards restoring his status within the imperial family.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>43</extension><space/>Agrippina had motive in ensuring the succession of Nero before Britannicus could gain power.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some implicate either his taster<space/><link><target>Halotus</target></link>, his doctor<space/><link><target>Gaius Stertinius Xenophon</target><part>Xenophon</part></link>, or the infamous poisoner<space/><link><target>Locusta</target></link><space/>as the administrator of the fatal substance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Accounts of his death: Suet.<space/><italics>Claud.</italics><space/>43, 44. Tac.<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XII 64, 6667. Josephus<space/><italics>Ant. Iud.</italics><space/>XX 148, 151. Dio<space/><italics>Rom. Hist.</italics><space/>LX 34. Pliny<space/><italics>Natural History</italics><space/>II xxiii 92, XI lxxiii 189, XXII xlvi 92.</extension><space/>Some say he died after prolonged suffering following a single dose at dinner, and some have him recovering only to be poisoned again.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suet44"></extension><space/>Among contemporary sources, Seneca the younger ascribed the emperor's death to natural causes, while Josephus only spoke of rumors on his poisoning.<extension extension_name='ref'>Flavius Josephus Antiquities of the Jews 19:67; 20:148</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In modern times, some authors have cast doubt on whether Claudius was actually murdered or merely succumbed to illness or old age.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza (1940) pp. 9293 says that tradition makes every emperor the victim of foul play, so we can't know if Claudius was truly murdered. Indeed, the Emperor appears to have been seriously ill since at least 53 CE. Levick (1990) pp.&amp;nbsp;7677. raises the possibility that Claudius was killed by the stress of fighting with Agrippina over the succession, but concludes that the timing makes murder the most likely cause.</extension><space/>Some modern scholars claim the near universality of the accusations in ancient texts lends credence to the crime.<extension extension_name='ref'>Levick (1990); also as opposed to the murder of Augustus, which is only found in Tacitus and Dio where he quotes Tacitus. Suetonius, an inveterate gossip, doesn't mention it at all.</extension><space/>Claudius' ashes were interred in the<space/><link><target>Mausoleum of Augustus</target></link><space/>on 24 October 54 CE, after a funeral in the manner of Augustus.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>After death</heading><heading level='3'>Divine honours</heading><paragraph>Already, while alive, he received the widespread private worship of a living<space/><link><target>Princeps</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Gradel I. Emperor worship and Roman religion. Clarendon Press, Oxford, 2002. ISBN 978-0-19-927548-9</extension><space/>and was worshipped in<space/><link><target>Britannia</target></link><space/>in his own<space/><link><target>Temple of Claudius, Colchester</target><part>temple in Camulodunum</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Claudius was deified by Nero and the Senate almost immediately.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Nero</italics><space/>9</extension><space/>Those who regard this homage as cynical should note that, cynical or not, such a move would hardly have benefited those involved, had Claudius been &quot;hated&quot;, as some commentators, both modern and historic, characterize him. Many of Claudius' less solid supporters quickly became Nero's men. Claudius' will had been changed shortly before his death to either recommend Nero and Britannicus jointly or perhaps just Britannicus, who would have been considered an adult man according to Roman law only a few months later.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Views of the new regime</heading><paragraph>Agrippina had sent away<space/><link><target>Tiberius Claudius Narcissus</target><part>Narcissus</part></link><space/>shortly before Claudius' death, and now murdered the freedman. The last act of this secretary of letters was to burn all of Claudius' correspondence most likely so it could not be used against him and others in an already hostile new regime. Thus Claudius' private words about his own policies and motives were lost to history. Just as Claudius had criticized his predecessors in official edicts (see below), Nero often criticized the deceased Emperor and many of Claudius' laws and edicts were disregarded under the reasoning that he was too stupid and senile to have meant them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suet.<space/><italics>Nero</italics><space/>33</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Seneca's<space/><link><target>Apocolocyntosis</target></link><space/>reinforces the view of Claudius as an unpleasant fool and this remained the official view for the duration of Nero's reign. Eventually Nero stopped referring to his deified adoptive father at all, and realigned with his birth family. Claudius' temple was left unfinished after only some of the foundation had been laid down. Eventually the site was overtaken by Nero's<space/><link><target>Domus Aurea</target><part>Golden House</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="iiovah">Levick (1990)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Flavian and later perspectives</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Flavians</target></link>, who had risen to prominence under Claudius, took a different tack. They were in a position where they needed to shore up their legitimacy, but also justify the fall of the Julio-Claudians. They reached back to Claudius in contrast with Nero, to show that they were good associated with good. Commemorative coins were issued of Claudius and his son<space/><link><target>Britannicus</target></link>, who had been a friend of the Emperor<space/><link><target>Titus</target></link><space/>(Titus was born in 39, Britannicus was born in 41). When Nero's<space/><link><target>Domus Aurea</target><part>Golden House</part></link><space/>was burned, the<space/><link><target>Temple of Claudius</target></link><space/>was finally completed on the Caelian Hill.<extension extension_name='ref' name="iiovah"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, as the Flavians became established, they needed to emphasize their own credentials more, and their references to Claudius ceased. Instead, he was lumped with the other emperors of the fallen dynasty. His state cult in Rome probably continued until the abolition of all such cults of dead Emperors by<space/><link><target>Maximinus Thrax</target></link><space/>in 237238.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gradel I. Emperor worship and Roman religion. Clarendon Press, Oxford, 2002. ISBN 978-0-19-927548-9 p.&amp;nbsp;356341</extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Feriale Duranum</target></link></italics>, probably identical to the festival calendars of every regular army unit, assigns him a sacrifice of a<space/><link><target>Cattle#Terminology</target><part>steer</part></link><space/>on his birthday, the<space/><link><target>Kalends</target></link><space/>of August.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rome and Its Empire, AD 193-284<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7486-2304-4<space/></arg><arg name="author1"><space/>Hekster<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Olivier<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008</arg></template></extension><space/>And such commemoration (and consequent feasting) probably continued until the Christianization and disintegration of the army in the late 4th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gradel I. Emperor worship and Roman religion. Clarendon Press, Oxford, 2002. ISBN 978-0-19-927548-9 p.367</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Views of ancient historians</heading><paragraph>The main ancient historians<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lives of the Twelve Caesars</target><part>Suetonius</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>all wrote after the last of the Flavians had gone. All three were senators or<space/><italics>equites</italics>. They took the side of the Senate in most conflicts with the Princeps, invariably viewing him as being in the wrong. This resulted in biases, both conscious and unconscious. Suetonius lost access to the official archives shortly after beginning his work. He was forced to rely on second-hand accounts when it came to Claudius (with the exception of Augustus' letters, which had been gathered earlier). Suetonius painted Claudius as a ridiculous figure, belittling many of his acts and attributing the objectively good works to his retinue.<extension extension_name='ref'>Scramuzza, p.&amp;nbsp;29</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Tacitus wrote a narrative for his fellow senators and fitted each of the emperors into a simple mold of his choosing.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vessey (1971)</extension><space/>He wrote of Claudius as a passive pawn and an idiot in affairs relating to the palace and often in public life. During his censorship of 47-8 Tacitus allows the reader a glimpse of a Claudius who is more statesmanlike (XI.23-25), but it is a mere glimpse. Tacitus is usually held to have 'hidden' his use of Claudius' writings and to have omitted Claudius' character from his works.<extension extension_name='ref'>Griffin (1990).<space/><italics>Ann.</italics><space/>XI 14 is often thought to be a good example: the digression on the history of writing is actually Claudius' own argument for his new letters, and fits in with his personality and extant writings. Tacitus makes no explicit attribution - and so there exists the possibility that the digression is Tacitus' own work or derivative of another source</extension><space/>Even his version of Claudius' Lyons tablet speech is edited to be devoid of the Emperor's personality. Dio was less biased, but seems to have used Suetonius and Tacitus as sources. Thus the conception of Claudius as the weak fool, controlled by those he supposedly ruled, was preserved for the ages.</paragraph><paragraph>As time passed, Claudius was mostly forgotten outside of the historians' accounts. His books were lost first, as their antiquarian subjects became unfashionable. In the 2nd century,<space/><link><target>Pertinax</target></link>, who shared his birthday, became emperor, overshadowing commemoration of Claudius.<extension extension_name='ref'>Levick.<space/><italics>Claudius</italics><space/>p. 194</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In modern literature, film and radio</heading><paragraph>The best known fictional representation of the Emperor Claudius were the books<space/><italics><link><target>I, Claudius</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Claudius the God</target></link></italics><space/>(published in 1934 and 1935) by<space/><link><target>Robert Graves</target></link>, both written in the<space/><link><target>Grammatical person</target><part>first-person</part></link><space/>to give the reader the impression that they are Claudius'<space/><link><target>autobiography</target></link>. Graves employed a fictive artifice to suggest that they were recently discovered, genuine translations of Claudius' writings. Claudius' extant letters, speeches, and sayings were incorporated into the text (mostly in the second book,<space/><italics>Claudius the God</italics>), to add authenticity.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1937, director<space/><link><target>Josef von Sternberg</target></link><space/>attempted a film version of<space/><italics><link><target>I, Claudius (film)</target><part>I, Claudius</part></link></italics>, with<space/><link><target>Charles Laughton</target></link><space/>as Claudius. However, the lead actress<space/><link><target>Merle Oberon</target></link><space/>suffered a near-fatal accident and the movie was never finished. The surviving reels were featured in the BBC documentary<space/><italics>The Epic That Never Was</italics><space/>(1965). The motion picture rights for a new film eventually passed to producer<space/><link><target>Scott Rudin</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://movies.msn.com/movies/movie-synopsis/i-claudius.1/</arg><arg name="title">I, Claudius (2009)&nbsp;– Synopsis</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 January 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Graves's two books were the basis for a British television adaptation<space/><italics><link><target>I, Claudius (TV series)</target><part>I, Claudius</part></link></italics>, produced by the<space/><link><target>British Broadcasting Corporation</target><part>BBC</part></link>. The series starred<space/><link><target>Derek Jacobi</target></link><space/>as Claudius and was broadcast in 1976 on<space/><link><target>BBC Two</target><part>BBC2</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0074006/</extension><space/>It was a substantial critical success, and won several<space/><link><target>British Academy of Film and Television Arts</target><part>BAFTA</part></link><space/>awards. The series was later broadcast in the United States on<space/><italics><link><target>Masterpiece Theatre</target></link></italics><space/>in 1977. The 1996 7-VHS release and the later DVD release of the television series, include the<space/><italics>The Epic That Never Was</italics><space/>documentary.</paragraph><paragraph>A radio adaptation of the Graves novels by<space/><link><target>Robin Brooks</target></link><space/>and directed by<space/><link><target>Jonquil Panting</target></link>, was broadcast in six one-hour episodes on<space/><link><target>BBC Radio 4</target></link><space/>beginning 4 December 2010. The cast featured<space/><link><target>Tom Goodman-Hill</target></link><space/>as Claudius,<space/><link><target>Derek Jacobi</target></link><space/>as Augustus,<space/><link><target>Harriet Walter</target></link><space/>as Livia,<space/><link><target>Tim McInnerny</target></link><space/>as Tiberius and<space/><link><target>Samuel Barnett (actor)</target><part>Samuel Barnett</part></link><space/>as Caligula.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2011, it was announced rights for a miniseries adaptation passed to HBO and BBC2. Anne Thomopoulos and Jane Tranter, producers of the popular HBOBBC2<space/><italics><link><target>Rome (TV Series)</target><part>Rome</part></link></italics><space/>miniseries, are attached to the new<space/><italics>I, Claudius</italics><space/>project.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1954 film<space/><italics><link><target>Demetrius and the Gladiators</target></link></italics><space/>also portrayed him sympathetically, played by<space/><link><target>Barry Jones (actor)</target><part>Barry Jones</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>On television,<space/><link><target>Freddie Jones</target></link><space/>portrayed Claudius in the 1968 British<space/><link><target>television</target></link><space/>series<space/><italics><link><target>The Caesars (TV series)</target><part>The Caesars</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1975 TV Special<space/><italics>Further Up Pompeii!</italics><space/>(based on the<space/><link><target>Frankie Howerd</target></link><space/>sit-com<space/><italics><link><target>Up Pompeii!</target></link></italics>) featured<space/><link><target>Cyril Appleton</target></link><space/>as Claudius.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1979 motion picture<space/><italics><link><target>Caligula (film)</target><part>Caligula</part></link></italics>, where the role was performed by<space/><link><target>Giancarlo Badessi</target></link>, Claudius is depicted as an idiot, in contrast to<space/><link><target>Robert Graves</target></link>' portrait of Claudius as a cunning and deeply intelligent man, who is perceived by others to be an idiot.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1985 made-for-television<space/><link><target>miniseries</target></link><space/><italics>A.D.</italics><space/>features actor<space/><link><target>Richard Kiley</target></link><space/>as Claudius. Kiley portrays him as thoughtful, but willing to cater to public opinion as well as being under the influence of Agrippina.</paragraph><paragraph>There is also a reference to Claudius' suppression of a coup in the movie<space/><italics><link><target>Gladiator (2000 film)</target><part>Gladiator</part></link></italics>, though the incident is entirely fictional.</paragraph><paragraph>In literature, Claudius and his contemporaries appear in the historical novel<space/><italics>The Roman</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Mika Waltari</target></link>. Canadian-born science fiction writer<space/><link><target>A. E. van Vogt</target></link><space/>reimagined Robert Graves' Claudius story, in his two novels<space/><italics><link><target>Empire of the Atom</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Wizard of Linn</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ancestry</heading><paragraph><template><target>Ahnentafel top</target><arg name="width">100%</arg></template><template><target>Ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Claudius'''
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. [[Nero Claudius Drusus]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. [[Antonia Minor]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[Tiberius Claudius Nero (praetor 42 BC)|Tiberius Claudius Nero]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. [[Livia Drusilla]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3"><space/>6. [[Mark Antony]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4"><space/>7. [[Octavia Minor]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[Drusus Claudius Nero I]]
</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. Claudia
</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[Marcus Livius Drusus Claudianus]]
</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. [[Aufidia]]
</arg><arg name="4"><space/>12. [[Marcus Antonius Creticus]]
</arg><arg name="5"><space/>13. [[Julia Antonia]]
</arg><arg name="6"><space/>14. [[Gaius Octavius]]
</arg><arg name="7"><space/>15. [[Atia Balba Caesonia]]
</arg><arg name="8">
</arg><arg name="9">
</arg><arg name="10">
</arg><arg name="11">
</arg><arg name="12">
</arg><arg name="13">
</arg><arg name="14"><space/>22. [[Aufidius Lurco]]
</arg><arg name="15">
</arg><arg name="16"><space/>24. Marcus Antonius Orator
</arg><arg name="17">
</arg><arg name="18"><space/>26. [[Lucius Julius Caesar III]]
</arg><arg name="19">
</arg><arg name="20"><space/>28. Gaius Octavius
</arg><arg name="21">
</arg><arg name="22"><space/>30. [[Marcus Atius]]
</arg><arg name="23"><space/>31. [[Julia Caesaris (sister of Julius Caesar)|Julia Caesaris]]
</arg><arg name="24"><space/>24. Marcus Antonius Orator
</arg><arg name="25">
</arg><arg name="26"><space/>26. [[Lucius Julius Caesar III]]
</arg><arg name="27">
</arg><arg name="28"><space/>28. Gaius Octavius
</arg><arg name="29">
</arg><arg name="30"><space/>30. [[Marcus Atius]]
</arg><arg name="31"><space/>31. [[Julia Caesaris (sister of Julius Caesar)|Julia Caesaris]]
</arg></template>&lt;/center&gt;<template><target>Ahnentafel bottom</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Julio-Claudian family tree</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Temple of Claudius, Colchester</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Temple of Claudius</target></link>, Rome</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Baldwin, B. (1964). &quot;Executions under Claudius: Seneca's Ludus de Morte Claudii&quot;.<space/><italics>Phoenix</italics><space/><bold>18</bold><space/>(1): 3948.<space/><template><target>jstor</target><arg>1086911</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Griffin, M. (1990). &quot;Claudius in Tacitus&quot;.<space/><italics>Classical Quarterly</italics><space/><bold>40</bold><space/>(2): 482501.<space/><template><target>jstor</target><arg>639107</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Levick, B.M. (1978). &quot;Claudius: Antiquarian or Revolutionary?&quot;<space/><italics>American Journal of Philology</italics>,<space/><bold>99</bold><space/>(1): 79105.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>293870</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Levick, Barbara (1990).<space/><italics>Claudius</italics>. New Haven: Yale University Press.</listitem><listitem>Leon, E.F. (1948). &quot;The Imbecillitas of the Emperor Claudius&quot;,<space/><italics>Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association</italics>,<space/><bold>79</bold><space/>7986.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>283354</arg></template></listitem><listitem>McAlindon, D. (1957). &quot;Claudius and the Senators&quot;,<space/><italics>American Journal of Philology</italics>,<space/><bold>78</bold><space/>(3): 279286.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>292122</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Major, A. (1992). &quot;Was He Pushed or Did He Leap? Claudius' Ascent to Power&quot;,<space/><italics>Ancient History</italics>, 22 2531.</listitem><listitem>Malloch, S. J. V. (2013).<space/><italics>The Annals of Tacitus, book 11</italics>. Cambridge University Press.</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Minaud, Grard,<space/><italics>Les vies de 12 femmes d'empereur romain - Devoirs, Intrigues &amp; Volupts</italics>, Paris, L'Harmattan, 2012, ch. 2,<space/><italics><space/>La vie de Messaline, femme de Claude</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;3964 ; ch. 3,<space/><italics><space/>La vie d'Agrippine, femme de Claude</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;6596. ISBN 978-2-336-00291-0.</listitem><listitem>Momigliano, Arnaldo (1934).<space/><italics>Claudius: the Emperor and His Achievement</italics><space/>Trans. W.D. Hogarth. Cambridge: W. Heffer and Sons.</listitem><listitem>Oost, S.V. (1958). &quot;The Career of M. Antonius Pallas&quot;,<space/><italics>American Journal of Philology</italics>, 79 (2): 113139.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>292103</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Osgood</arg><arg name="first">Josiah</arg><arg name="title">Claudius Caesar : image and power in the early Roman empire</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-88181-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Johns Hopkins University</arg><arg name="title">The problem of Claudius: Some aspects of a character study</arg><arg name="year">1916</arg><arg name="last">Ruth</arg><arg name="first">Thomas De Coursey<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Ryan, F.X. (1993). &quot;Some Observations on the Censorship of Claudius and Vitellius, AD 4748&quot;,<space/><italics>American Journal of Philology</italics>,<space/><bold>114</bold><space/>(4): 611618.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>295428</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Scramuzza, Vincent (1940).<space/><italics>The Emperor Claudius</italics><space/>Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</listitem><listitem>Stuart, M. (1936). &quot;The Date of the Inscription of Claudius on the Arch of Ticinum&quot;<space/><italics>American Journal of Archaeology</italics><space/><bold>40</bold><space/>(3): 314322.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>498692</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Suetonius</arg><arg name="title">The Twelve Caesars</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-044072-0</arg><arg name="others">Robert Graves, trans</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Suhr</arg><arg name="first">Elmer G.</arg><arg name="title">A Portrait of Claudius</arg><arg name="journal">American Journal of Archaeology</arg><arg name="year">1955</arg><arg name="volume">59</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pages">319–322</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/500799</arg><arg name="jstor">500799</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Vessey, D.W.T.C. (1971). &quot;Thoughts on Tacitus' Portrayal of Claudius&quot;<space/><italics>American Journal of Philology</italics><space/><bold>92</bold><space/>(3) 385409.<template><target>jstor</target><arg>292801</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Claudius</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Ancient Sources</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Suetonius<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Claudius*.html'>Life of Claudius</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Tacitus<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/txt/ah/tacitus/TacitusAnnals11.html'>Tacitus on the second half of Claudius' reign, book 11</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/txt/ah/tacitus/TacitusAnnals12.html'>Tacitus on Claudius' last years, book 12</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Dio<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/60*.html'>Cassius Dio's account of Claudius' reign, part I</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/61*.html'>Cassius Dio's account, part II</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Josephus<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/j/josephus/works/JOSEPHUS.HTM'>The works of Josephus</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Seneca<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.forumromanum.org/literature/apocolocyntosis.html'>The Apocolocyntosis of the Divine Claudius</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Claudius<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.csun.edu/~hcfll004/claualex.html'>Claudius' Letter to the Alexandrians</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lyon Tablet</target><part>Lyons tablet</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lugdunum Tablet</target><part>Extract from first half of the Lyons Tablet</part></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/48claudius.html'>Second half of the Lyons Tablet</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/tacitus-ann11a.html'>Tacitus' version of the Lyons Tablet speech</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tabula clesiana</target><part>Edict confirming the rights of the people of Trent</part></link>. Full Latin text<space/><link><target>:it:Tabula clesiana</target><part>here</part></link>.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Modern Biographies</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.roman-emperors.org/claudius.htm'>Biography from De Imperatoribus Romanis</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/Athens/Parthenon/7094/claudius.html&amp;amp;date=2009-10-25+06:19:08'>Claudius Page</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/claudius.shtml'>Claudius I</link><space/>at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/'>BBC History</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Julio-Claudian dynasty]]</arg><arg>1 August</arg><arg>10 BC</arg><arg>13 October</arg><arg>54</arg></template><template><target>S-roy</target><arg>rm</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">Gaius ([[Caligula]])</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Roman Emperors|Roman Emperor]]</arg><arg name="years">41–54</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Nero]]</arg></template><template><target>s-off</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Gnaeus Acerronius Proculus]] and [[Gaius Petronius Pontius Nigrinus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[List of early imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] together with [[Caligula]]</arg><arg name="years"><space/>37 (suffect)</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Marcus Aquila Julianus]] and [[Gaius Nonius Asprenas]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Caligula]] and [[Gnaeus Sentius Saturninus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[List of early imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] together with [[Gaius Caecina Largus]] (42) and [[Lucius Vitellius]] (43)</arg><arg name="years"><space/>42–43</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Titus Statilius Taurus]] and [[Gaius Sallustius Crispus Passienus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Decimus Valerius Asiaticus]] and [[Marcus Junius Silanus Torquatus (consul AD 46)|Marcus Junius Silanus Torquatus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[List of early imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] together with [[Lucius Vitellius]]</arg><arg name="years"><space/>47</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Vitellius]] and [[Lucius Vipstanus Publicola Messalla]]</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Gaius Antistius Vetus (consul 50)|Gaius Antistius Vetus]] and [[Marcus Suillius Nerullinus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[List of early imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] together with [[Servius Cornelius Scipio Salvidienus Orfitus (consul 51)|Servius Cornelius Scipio Salvidienus Orfitus]]</arg><arg name="years"><space/>51</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Faustus Cornelius Sulla Felix]] and [[Lucius Salvius Otho Titianus]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Roman Emperors</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:10 BC</target></link><link><target>Category:54 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century crimes</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century historians</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Romans in Britain</target></link><link><target>Category:Characters in works by Geoffrey of Monmouth</target></link><link><target>Category:Claudii</target></link><link><target>Category:Deified Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Creators of writing systems</target></link><link><target>Category:Julio-Claudian dynasty</target></link><link><target>Category:Latin historians</target></link><link><target>Category:Murdered Roman emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Lugdunum</target></link><link><target>Category:People with cerebral palsy</target></link><link><target>Category:Poisoned Romans</target></link><link><target>Category:Royalty and nobility with disabilities</target></link><link><target>Category:10s BC births</target></link></paragraph></article>