<article title='Eli_Whitney'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>pp-vandalism</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox engineer</target><arg name="image"><space/>Eli Whitney by Samuel Finley Breese Morse 1822.jpeg
</arg><arg name="image_width">
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Eli Whitney, painted by [[Samuel F. B. Morse]], 1822. [[Yale University Art Gallery]]
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Eli Whitney
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>American
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>December 8, 1765
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Westborough, Massachusetts|Westborough]], [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts]], [[British America]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>January 8, 1825 (aged 59)
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[New Haven, Connecticut|New Haven]], [[Connecticut]], U.S.
</arg><arg name="education"><space/>[[Yale College]]
</arg><arg name="spouse">
</arg><arg name="parents"><space/>Eli Whitney, Elizabeth Fay
</arg><arg name="children"><space/>4
</arg><arg name="practice_name">
</arg><arg name="significant_projects"><space/>[[Interchangeable parts]], [[cotton gin]]
</arg><arg name="significant_design">
</arg><arg name="significant_advance">
</arg><arg name="significant_awards">
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>Eli Whitney signature from 1846 memoir.svg
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Eli Whitney</bold><space/>(December 8, 1765 January 8, 1825) was an American inventor best known for inventing the<space/><link><target>cotton gin</target></link>. This was one of the key inventions of the<space/><link><target>Industrial Revolution</target></link><space/>and shaped the economy of the<space/><link><target>Antebellum South</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mssa"></extension><space/>Whitney's invention made upland short cotton into a profitable crop, which strengthened the economic foundation of<space/><link><target>slavery in the United States</target></link>. Despite the social and economic impact of his invention, Whitney lost many profits in legal battles over patent infringement for the cotton gin. Thereafter, he turned his attention into securing contracts with the government in the manufacture of muskets for the newly formed United States Army. He continued making arms and inventing until his death in 1825.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life and education</heading><paragraph>Whitney was born in<space/><link><target>Westborough, Massachusetts</target><part>Westborough</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Province of Massachusetts Bay</target><part>Massachusetts</part></link>, on December 8, 1765, the eldest child of Eli Whitney Sr., a prosperous farmer, and his wife Elizabeth Fay, also of Westborough.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the younger Eli, born in 1765, could technically be called a &quot;Junior&quot;, history has never known him as such. He was famous during his lifetime and afterward by the name &quot;Eli Whitney&quot;. His son, born in 1820, also named Eli, was well known during his lifetime and afterward by the name &quot;Eli Whitney, Jr.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Whitney's mother, Elizabeth Fay, died in 1777, when he was 11.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.newenglandancestors.org/database_search/Vital_records.asp</arg><arg name="title">Westborough Deaths</arg><arg name="date">2001–2008</arg><arg name="work">Massachusetts Vital Records to 1850</arg><arg name="publisher">New England Historic Genealogical Society</arg><arg name="page">275</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 17, 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>At age 14 he operated a profitable nail manufacturing operation in his father's workshop during the<space/><link><target>American Revolutionary War</target><part>Revolutionary War</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MIT"><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/whitney.html'>MIT Inventor of the Week archive profile</link>. From a website funded and administered by<space/><link><target>Lemelson-MIT Program</target></link>. Accessed March 18, 2008.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Because his stepmother opposed his wish to attend college, Whitney worked as a farm laborer and school teacher to save money. He prepared for Yale at<space/><link><target>Leicester Academy</target></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>Becker College</target></link>) and under the tutelage of Rev. Elizur Goodrich of<space/><link><target>Durham, Connecticut</target></link>, he entered the class of 1789 and graduated<space/><link><target>Phi Beta Kappa</target></link><space/>in 1792.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mssa"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.library.yale.edu/mssa/exhibits/elms/18th_item01.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Elms and Magnolias: The 18th century<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">March 19, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 16, 1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pbk.org/infoview/PBK_InfoView.aspx?t=&amp;amp;id=59'>Who Belongs To Phi Beta Kappa</link>, Phi Beta Kappa website, accessed October 4, 2009</extension><space/>Whitney expected to study law but, finding himself short of funds, accepted an offer to go to South Carolina as a private tutor.<link><target>File:Petition of Eli Whitney to Selectmen of Westborough Massachusetts.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Petition by Whitney to the<space/><link><target>selectmen</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Westborough, Massachusetts</target><part>Westborough</part></link><space/>to run a public school, with sample of his penmanship</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Instead of reaching his destination, he was convinced to visit Georgia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MIT"></extension><space/>In the closing years of the 18th century, Georgia was a magnet for New Englanders seeking their fortunes (its Revolutionary-era governor had been<space/><link><target>Lyman Hall</target></link>, a migrant from Connecticut). When he initially sailed for South Carolina, among his shipmates were the widow and family of the Revolutionary hero Gen.<space/><link><target>Nathanael Greene</target></link><space/>of Rhode Island.<space/><link><target>Catherine Littlefield Greene</target><part>Mrs. Greene</part></link><space/>invited Whitney to visit her Georgia plantation,<space/><link><target>Mulberry Grove Plantation</target><part>Mulberry Grove</part></link>. Her plantation manager and husband-to-be was Phineas Miller, another Connecticut migrant and Yale graduate (class of 1785), who would become Whitney's business partner.</paragraph><paragraph>Whitney is most famous for two innovations which later divided the United States in the mid-19th century: the<space/><link><target>cotton gin</target></link><space/>(1793) and his advocacy of<space/><link><target>interchangeable parts</target></link>. In the South, the cotton gin revolutionized the way cotton was<space/><link><target>harvest</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>and reinvigorated slavery. In the North the adoption of interchangeable parts revolutionized the manufacturing industry, and contributed greatly to the U.S. victory in the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target><part>Civil War</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-3497'>New Georgia Encyclopedia: Eli Whitney in Georgia</link>. Accessed March 19, 2008.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Career</heading><heading level='3'>Interchangeable parts</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Interchangeable parts</arg></template><link><target>File:Eli Whitney's first contract as a gunfounder signed by Oliver Ellsworth 1786.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>First contract of Eli Whitney as a firearms manufacturer, 1798. Signed by<space/><link><target>Oliver Wolcott, Jr.</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Secretary of the Treasury</target></link>.</part></link>Eli Whitney has often been incorrectly credited with inventing the idea of interchangeable parts, which he championed for years as a maker of<space/><link><target>musket</target><trail>s</trail></link>; however, the idea predated Whitney, and Whitney's role in it was one of promotion and popularizing, not invention.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><space/>Successful implementation of the idea eluded Whitney until near the end of his life, occurring first in others' armories.</paragraph><paragraph>Attempts at interchangeability of parts can be traced back as far as the<space/><link><target>Punic Wars</target></link><space/>through both archaeological remains of boats now in Museo Archeologico Baglio Anselmi and contemporary written accounts.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template><space/>In modern times the idea developed over decades among many people. An early leader was<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Vaquette de Gribeauval</target></link>, an 18th-century French<space/><link><target>artillery</target><part>artillerist</part></link><space/>who created a fair amount of<space/><link><target>standardization</target></link><space/>of artillery pieces, although not true interchangeability of parts. He inspired others, including<space/><link><target>Honor Blanc</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Louis de Tousard</target></link>, to work further on the idea, and on shoulder weapons as well as artillery. In the 19th century these efforts produced the &quot;armory system,&quot; or<space/><link><target>American system of manufacturing</target></link>. Certain other New Englanders, including<space/><link><target>Captain John H. Hall</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Simeon North</target></link>, arrived at successful interchangeability before Whitney's armory did. The Whitney armory finally succeeded not long after his death in 1825.</paragraph><paragraph>The motives behind Whitney's acceptance of a contract to manufacture muskets in 1798 were mostly monetary. By the late 1790s, Whitney was on the verge of bankruptcy and the cotton gin litigation had left him deeply in<space/><link><target>debt</target></link>. His<space/><link><target>New Haven</target></link><space/>cotton gin factory had burned to the ground, and litigation sapped his remaining resources. The<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>had ignited new conflicts between Great Britain, France, and the United States. The new American government, realizing the need to prepare for war, began to rearm. The<space/><link><target>United States Department of War</target><part>War Department</part></link><space/>issued contracts for the manufacture of 10,000 muskets. Whitney, who had never made a gun in his life, obtained a contract in January 1798 to deliver 10,000 to 15,000 muskets in 1800. He had not mentioned interchangeable parts at that time. Ten months later, the Treasury Secretary,<space/><link><target>Oliver Wolcott, Jr.</target></link>, sent him a &quot;foreign pamphlet on arms manufacturing techniques,&quot; possibly one of Honor Blanc's reports, after which Whitney first began to talk about interchangeability.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eli Whitney Gun Factory William Giles Munson 1827.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Whitney's gun factory in 1827</part></link>In May 1798, Congress voted for legislation that would use eight hundred thousand dollars in order to pay for small arms and cannons in case war with France erupted. They offered a 5,000 dollar incentive with an additional 5,000 dollars once that money was exhausted for the person that was able to accurately produce arms for the government. Because the cotton gin had not brought Whitney the rewards he believed he would get, he accepted the contract. Although the contract was for one year, Whitney did not deliver the arms until eight years later in 1809 using multiple excuses for the delay of such. Recently, historians have found that during 18011806, Whitney took the money and headed into South Carolina in order to profit from the cotton gin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baida1987"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Whitney's demonstration of 1801 appeared to show the ingenuity of interchangeable parts,<space/><link><target>Merritt Roe Smith</target></link><space/>concludes that Whitney's demonstration was &quot;staged&quot; and &quot;duped government authorities&quot; into believing that he had created interchangeable parts. The charade was only useful in order to gain more time and resources for the project but not to create interchangeable parts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baida1987"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When the government complained that Whitney's price per musket compared unfavorably with those produced in government armories, Whitney was able to calculate an actual price per musket by including<space/><link><target>fixed cost</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as insurance and<space/><link><target>machinery</target></link>, which the government had not included. He thus made early contributions to both the concept of<space/><link><target>cost accounting</target></link>, and the concept of the<space/><link><target>efficiency (economics)</target><part>efficiency</part></link><space/>of private industry.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cotton gin</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Cotton gin</arg></template><link><target>File:Cotton gin harpers.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;First cotton gin&quot; from Harpers Weekly. 1869 illustration depicting event of some 70 years earlier.</part></link><link><target>File:Whitney Gin.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Cotton Gin Patent. It shows sawtooth gin blades, which were not part of Whitney's original patent.</part></link><link><target>File:Cotton gin EWM 2007.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A cotton gin on display at the<space/><link><target>Eli Whitney Museum</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The cotton gin is a mechanical device that removes the seeds from cotton, a process that had previously been extremely labor-intensive. The word<space/><italics>gin</italics><space/>is short for<space/><italics>engine.</italics><space/>The cotton gin was a wooden drum stuck with hooks that pulled the cotton fibers through a mesh. The cotton seeds would not fit through the mesh and fell outside. Whitney occasionally told a story wherein he was pondering an improved method of seeding the cotton when he was inspired by observing a cat attempting to pull a chicken through a fence, and could only pull through some of the feathers.</paragraph><paragraph>A single cotton gin could generate up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>55</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>of cleaned cotton daily. This contributed to the economic development of the<space/><link><target>Southern United States</target><part>Southern states</part></link><space/>of the United States, a prime cotton growing area; some historians believe that this invention allowed for the<space/><link><target>History of slavery in the United States</target><part>African slavery system</part></link><space/>in the Southern United States to become more sustainable at a critical point in its development.</paragraph><paragraph>Whitney received a patent (later numbered as X72) for his cotton gin on March 14, 1794, but it was not validated until 1807. Whitney and his partner, Miller, did not intend to sell the gins. Rather, like the proprietors of<space/><link><target>gristmill</target><part>grist</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sawmill</target><trail>s</trail></link>, they expected to charge farmers for cleaning their cotton two-fifths of the value, paid in cotton. Resentment at this scheme, the mechanical simplicity of the device and the primitive state of<space/><link><target>History of patent law</target><part>patent law</part></link>, made<space/><link><target>Patent infringement</target><part>infringement</part></link><space/>inevitable. Whitney and Miller could not build enough gins to meet demand, so gins from other makers found ready sale. Ultimately, patent infringement lawsuits consumed the profits and their cotton gin company went out of business in 1797.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MIT"></extension><space/>One oft-overlooked point is that there were drawbacks to Whitney's first design. There is significant evidence that the design flaws were solved by a plantation owner,<space/><link><target>Catherine Littlefield Greene</target></link>, wife of the<space/><link><target>American Revolutionary War</target></link><space/>general<space/><link><target>Nathanael Greene</target></link>; Whitney gave her no public credit or recognition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EWnameProject"><link type='external' href='http://peoplenamedeliwhitney.blogspot.com/2009/10/eli-whitney-really-famous-one.html'>Eli Whitney Project</link><space/>A website for The Eli Whitney Project</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the cotton gin did not earn Whitney the fortune he had hoped for, it did give him fame.</paragraph><paragraph>It has been argued by some historians that Whitney's cotton gin was an important if unintended cause of the American Civil War. Before the invention of the cotton gin, slavery had been on the<space/><link><target>decline</target></link>; in fact many slaveholders had even given away their slaves.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2012</arg></template><space/>After Whitney's invention, the<space/><link><target>Plantations in the American South</target><part>plantation slavery</part></link><space/>industry was rejuvenated, eventually culminating in the Civil War.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://americanhistory.about.com/od/civilwarmenu/a/cause_civil_war.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Top Five Causes of the Civil War<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Americanhistory.about.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2012-01-26<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-14</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>And the cotton gin transformed Southern agriculture and the national economy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EWmuseum"><link type='external' href='http://www.eliwhitney.org/'>The Eli Whitney Museum and Workshop</link><space/>A website for The Eli Whitney Museum in<space/><link><target>Hamden, Connecticut</target><part>Hamden, CT.</part></link></extension><space/>Southern cotton found ready markets in Europe and in the burgeoning<space/><link><target>cotton mill</target><part>textile mill</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>New England</target></link>. Cotton exports from the U.S. boomed after the cotton gin's appearance from less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500000</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>in 1793 to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>93</arg><arg>e6lb</arg><arg>kg</arg></template><space/>by 1810.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="journal"><space/>Monthly Summary of Commerce and Finance
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Monthly Summary of Commerce and Finance of the United States, Issues 1-3
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1895–1896
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>290
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>U.S. Department of the Treasury
<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Cotton was a staple that could be stored for long periods and shipped long distances, unlike most agricultural products. It became the U.S.'s chief export, representing over half the value of U.S. exports from 1820 to 1860.</paragraph><paragraph>Paradoxically, the cotton gin, a labor-saving device, helped preserve<space/><link><target>slavery</target></link><space/>in the U.S. Before the 1790s, slave labor was primarily employed in growing rice, tobacco, and<space/><link><target>indigo</target></link>, none of which were especially profitable any more. Neither was cotton, due to the difficulty of seed removal. But with the gin, growing cotton with slave labor became highly profitable the chief source of wealth in the American South, and the basis of frontier settlement from<space/><link><target>Georgia (U.S. state)</target><part>Georgia</part></link><space/>to Texas. &quot;<link><target>King Cotton</target></link>&quot; became a dominant economic force, and slavery was sustained as a key institution of Southern society.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Milling machine</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Milling machine</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Machine tool historian Joseph W. Roe credited Whitney with inventing the first<space/><link><target>milling machine</target></link><space/>circa 1818. Subsequent work by other historians (Woodbury; Smith; Muir; Battison [cited by Baida<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baida1987"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baida<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter<space/></arg><arg name="date">May–June 1987<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Eli Whitney's Other Talent<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>American Heritage<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>38<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.americanheritage.com/content/eli-whitney%E2%80%99s-other-talent?page</arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 30, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="postscript">.<space/></arg></template></extension>]) suggests that Whitney was among a group of contemporaries all developing milling machines at about the same time (1814 to 1818), and that the others were more important to the innovation than Whitney was. (The machine that excited Roe may not have been built until 1825, after Whitney's death.) Therefore, no one person can properly be described as the inventor of the milling machine.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later life and legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Eli Whitney 1940 Issue-1c.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Eli Whitney on US Postage<space/><link><target>Postage stamps and postal history of the United States#Famous Americans Series of 1940</target><part>Issue of 1940</part></link>, 1c</part></link><link><target>File:EliWhitneyGraveSouthSideGroveStCemeteryNewHavenCT04152008.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>South side of Eli Whitney monument in the<space/><link><target>Grove Street Cemetery</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Haven, Connecticut</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Despite his humble origins, Whitney was keenly aware of the value of social and political connections. In building his arms business, he took full advantage of the access that his status as a Yale alumnus gave him to other well-placed graduates, such as<space/><link><target>Oliver Wolcott, Jr.</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United States Secretary of the Treasury</target><part>Secretary of the Treasury</part></link><space/>(class of 1778), and<space/><link><target>James Hillhouse</target></link>, a New Haven developer and political leader.</paragraph><paragraph>His 1817 marriage to Henrietta Edwards, granddaughter of the famed<space/><link><target>Evangelism</target><part>evangelist</part></link><space/><link><target>Jonathan Edwards (theologian)</target><part>Jonathan Edwards</part></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Pierpont Edwards</target></link>, head of the Democratic Party in Connecticut, and first cousin of Yale's president,<space/><link><target>Timothy Dwight IV</target><part>Timothy Dwight</part></link>, the state's leading<space/><link><target>Federalist</target></link>, further tied him to Connecticut's<space/><link><target>ruling elite</target></link>. In a business dependent on government contracts, such connections were essential to success.</paragraph><paragraph>Whitney died of<space/><link><target>prostate cancer</target></link><space/>on January 8, 1825, in New Haven, Connecticut, just a month after his 59th birthday. He left a widow and his four children behind. During the course of his illness, he invented and constructed several devices to mechanically ease his pain. These devices, drawings of which are in his collected papers, were effective but were never manufactured for use of others due to his heirs' reluctance to trade in &quot;indelicate&quot; items.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Eli Whitney Students Program</target></link>, Yale University's admissions program for non-traditional students, is named after Whitney who matriculated into Yale when he was 23.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yale Admissions"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://admissions.yale.edu/eli-whitney<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eli Whitney Students Program – A Program for Non-Traditional Students<space/></arg><arg name="work">Yale College Admissions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Yale University]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">New Haven, CT<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 21, 2011<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Whitney family</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Battison, Edwin. (1960). &quot;Eli Whitney and the Milling Machine.&quot; Smithsonian Journal of History I.</listitem><listitem>Cooper, Carolyn, &amp; Lindsay, Merrill K. (1980). Eli Whitney and the Whitney Armory.</listitem><listitem>Whitneyville, CT: Eli Whitney Museum.</listitem><listitem>Dexter, Franklin B. (1911). &quot;Eli Whitney.&quot; Yale Biographies and Annals, 17921805. New York, NY: Henry Holt &amp; Company.</listitem><listitem>Hall, Karyl Lee Kibler, &amp; Cooper, Carolyn. (1984). Windows on the Works: Industry on the Eli Whitney Site, 17981979.</listitem><listitem>Hamden, CT: Eli Whitney Museum</listitem><listitem><template><target>Hounshell1984</target></template></listitem><listitem>Lakwete, Angela. (2004). Inventing the Cotton Gin: Machine and Myth in Antebellum America. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.</listitem><listitem>Smith, Merritt Roe. 1973. &quot;John H. Hall, Simeon North, and the Milling Machine: The Nature of Innovation among Antebellum Arms Makers.&quot; Technology &amp; Culture 14.</listitem><listitem>Woodbury, Robert S. (1960). &quot;The Legend of Eli Whitney and Interchangeable Parts.&quot; Technology &amp; Culture 1.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Iles</arg><arg name="first"><space/>George</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1912</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Leading American Inventors</arg><arg name="place">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Henry Holt and Company</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.archive.org/details/leadingamericani00ilesrich</arg><arg name="pages">75–103</arg></template></listitem><listitem>McL. Green, Constance Edited by Oscar Handlin. (1956). Eli Whitney &amp; The Birth of American Technology. Library of American Biography series.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Roe<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joseph Wickham<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>English and American Tool Builders<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Yale University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1916<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New Haven, Connecticut<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="lccn"><space/>16011753</arg></template>. Reprinted by McGraw-Hill, New York and London, 1926 (<template><target>LCCN</target><arg>27024075</arg></template>); and by Lindsay Publications, Inc., Bradley, Illinois, (ISBN 978-0-917914-73-7).</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eliwhitney.org/'>The Eli Whitney Museum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.whitneygen.org/archives/biography/eli.html'>Eli Whitney Biography on at Whitney Research Group</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/whitney.html'>Inventor of the Week: Eli Whitney (MIT)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-3497'>Entry in New Georgia Encyclopedia</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wikisource-inline</target><arg name="list">
**{{Cite Collier's|wstitle</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.teachingushistory.org/tTrove/Whitney11Sept1793.htm'>Letter from Eli Whitney to his Father regarding his invention of the cotton gin, September 11, 1793</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.teachingushistory.org/lessons/JefftoWhit.htm'>Letter from Thomas Jefferson to Eli Whitney, Jr. regarding his cotton gin patent, November 16, 1793</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.teachingushistory.org/tTrove/whitneyobit.html'>Obituary for Eli Whitney, in Niles Weekly Register, January 25, 1825</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Hall of Fame for Great Americans</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Whitney, Eli</target></template><link><target>Category:1765 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1825 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:American business theorists</target></link><link><target>Category:American business pioneers</target></link><link><target>Category:American engineers</target></link><link><target>Category:American inventors</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Grove Street Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in Connecticut</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from prostate cancer</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of English descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Firearm designers</target></link><link><target>Category:Textile workers</target></link><link><target>Category:Machine tool builders</target></link><link><target>Category:People from New Haven, Connecticut</target></link><link><target>Category:People of the Industrial Revolution</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Westborough, Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:Whitney family</target></link><link><target>Category:Leicester Academy alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Yale University alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Hall of Fame for Great Americans inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:Cotton gin</target></link></paragraph></article>