<article title='Citizenship'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>being a member of a country</arg><arg></arg><arg>Citizen (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>redirects here</target><arg>Nationalities</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Nationality</arg></template><template><target>legal status</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Citizenship</bold><space/>is the status of a person recognized under the<space/><link><target>custom (law)</target><part>custom</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>law</target></link><space/>as being a member of a<space/><link><target>State (polity)</target><part>state</part></link>. A person may have<space/><link><target>multiple citizenship</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and a person who does not have citizenship of any state is said to be<space/><link><target>Stateless person</target><part>stateless</part></link>. Other words used to describe statelessness are countryless or exile.</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Nationality</target></link></bold><space/>is often used as a synonym for citizenship in English<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.pitt.edu/~votruba/qsonhist/slovaknationalityethnicityenglishtranslation.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nationality, ethnicity in Slovakia.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Votruba<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Martin<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Slovak Studies Program<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Pittsburgh</arg></template></extension><space/>notably in<space/><link><target>public international law</target><part>international law</part></link><space/>although the term is sometimes understood as denoting a person's membership of a<space/><link><target>nation</target></link><space/>(a large<space/><link><target>Ethnicity</target><part>ethnic group</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Nationality and Statelessness in International Law<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Paul<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Weis<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9789028603295<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sijthoff & Noordhoff<space/></arg><arg name="page">[http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>In some countries, e.g. the United States,<space/><link><target>British nationality law#Classes of British nationality</target><part>the United Kingdom</part></link>,<space/><italics>nationality</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>citizenship</italics><space/>can have different meanings (for more information, see<space/><link><target>Nationality#Nationality versus citizenship</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Determining factors</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><template><target>further</target><arg>Nationality law</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A person can be a citizen for several reasons. Usually citizenship of the place of birth is automatic; in other cases an application may be required. Each country has their own policies and regulations which change the criteria of who is issued citizenship.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Parents are citizens</bold><space/>(<italics><link><target>jus sanguinis</target></link></italics>). If one or both of a person's parents are citizens of a given state, then the person may have the right to be a citizen of that state as well.<space/><template><target>efn</target><arg>Examples: [[Philippine nationality law|Philippines]],<ref>[http://www.chanrobles.com/article4.htm Article IV of the Philippine Constitution].</ref><space/>[[Title 8 of the United States Code|United States]]<ref>[http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/8/chapter-12/subchapter-III/part-I 8 USC Part I - Nationality at Birth and Collective Naturalization8 USC Part I - Nationality at Birth and Collective Naturalization]</ref></arg></template><space/>Formerly this might only have applied through the paternal line, but<space/><link><target>sex equality</target></link><space/>became common since the late twentieth century. Citizenship is granted based on ancestry or<space/><link><target>ethnicity</target></link>, and is related to the concept of a<space/><link><target>nation state</target></link><space/>common in China. Where<space/><italics>jus sanguinis</italics><space/>holds, a person born outside a country, one or both of whose parents are citizens of the country, is also a citizen. States normally<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><space/>limit the right to citizenship by descent to a certain number of generations born outside the state.<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><space/>This form of citizenship is not common in<space/><link><target>civil law (legal system)</target><part>civil law</part></link><space/>countries.</listitem><listitem><bold>Born within a country</bold><space/>(<italics><link><target>jus soli</target></link></italics>). Some people are automatically citizens of the state in which they are born. This form of citizenship originated in<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>where those who were born within the realm were<space/><link><target>British subject#Prior to 1949</target><part>subjects of the monarch</part></link><space/>(a concept pre-dating citizenship), and is common in<space/><link><target>common law</target></link><space/>countries.</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>In many cases both<space/><italics>jus solis</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>jus sanguinis</italics><space/>hold; citizenship either by place or parentage (or of course both).</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Marriage to a citizen</bold><space/>(<italics><link><target>jure matrimonii</target></link></italics>). Many countries fast-track naturalization based on the marriage of a person to a citizen. Countries which are destinations for such immigration often have regulations to try to detect<space/><link><target>sham marriage</target><trail>s</trail></link>, where a citizen marries a non-citizen typically for payment, without them having the intention of living as man and wife.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/media-centre/news/sham-marriage-bishops'>UK government Web site: Bishops act to tackle sham marriages - New UK Border Agency approved guidance for clergy should help prevent weddings for visas, 11 April 2011</link></extension></listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Naturalization</target></link></bold>. States normally grant citizenship to people who have entered the country legally and been granted permit to stay, or been granted<space/><link><target>political asylum</target></link>, and also lived there for a specified period. In some countries, naturalization is subject to conditions which may include passing a test demonstrating reasonable knowledge of the language or way of life of the host country, good conduct (no serious criminal record) and moral character (such as drunkenness, or gambling), vowing allegiance to their new state or its ruler and renouncing their prior citizenship. Some states allow<space/><link><target>dual citizenship</target></link><space/>and do not require naturalized citizens to formally renounce any other citizenship.</listitem><listitem><bold>Excluded categories</bold>. In the past there have been exclusions on entitlement to citizenship on grounds such as skin color, ethnicity, sex, and free status (not being a<space/><link><target>slave</target></link>). Most of these exclusions no longer apply in most places. Modern examples include some<space/><link><target>Arab countries</target></link><space/>which rarely grant citizenship to non-Muslims, e.g.<space/><link><target>Qatar</target></link><space/>is known for granting citizenship to foreign athletes, but they all have to profess the<space/><link><target>Islamic</target></link><space/>faith in order to receive citizenship. The United States grants citizenship to those born as a result of reproductive technologies, and internationally adopted children born after Feb 27, 1983. Some exclusions still persist for internationally adopted children born before Feb 27, 1983 even though their parents meet citizenship criteria.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of citizenship</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Polis</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Polis</arg></template>Many thinkers point to the concept of citizenship beginning in the early<space/><link><target>city-state</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>ancient Greece</target></link>, although others see it as primarily a modern phenomenon dating back only a few hundred years and, for mankind, that the concept of citizenship arose with the first<space/><link><target>law</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><italics>Polis</italics><space/>meant both the political assembly of the city-state as well as the entire society.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">32</arg></template><space/>Citizenship has generally been identified as a western phenomenon.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zarrow</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template><space/>There is a general view that citizenship in ancient times was a simpler relation than modern forms of citizenship, although this view has come under scrutiny.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y17"></extension><space/>The relation of citizenship has not been a fixed or static relation, but constantly changed within each society, and that according to one view, citizenship might &quot;really have worked&quot; only at select periods during certain times, such as when the Athenian politician<space/><link><target>Solon</target></link><space/>made reforms in the early Athenian state.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Heater
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Derek 
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Brief History of Citizenship
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New York University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York City
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>157
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8147-3671-8<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Hosking</target></link><space/>in his 2005<space/><italics>Modern Scholar</italics><space/>lecture course suggested that citizenship in<space/><link><target>ancient Greece</target></link><space/>arose from an appreciation for the importance of<space/><link><target>Political freedom</target><part>freedom</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsfjiui"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hosking
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Geoffrey
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Epochs of European Civilization: Antiquity to Renaissance
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Modern Scholar via [[Recorded Books]]
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Lecture 3: Ancient Greece
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>United Kingdom
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1, 2 (tracks)
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4025-8360-5</arg></template></extension><space/>Hosking explained:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg>It can be argued that this growth of slavery was what made Greeks particularly conscious of the value of freedom. After all, any Greek farmer might fall into debt and therefore might become a slave, at almost any time ... When the Greeks fought together, they fought in order to avoid being enslaved by warfare, to avoid being defeated by those who might take them into slavery. And they also arranged their political institutions so as to remain free men.</arg><arg name="Geoffrey Hosking, 2005<ref name">twsfjiui/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Arte greca, pietra tombale di donna con la sua assistente, 100 ac. circa.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Geoffrey Hosking suggests that fear of being enslaved was a central motivating force for the development of the Greek sense of citizenship. Sculpture: a Greek woman being served by a slave-child.</part></link>Slavery permitted slaveowners to have substantial free time, and enabled participation in public life.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsfjiui"></extension><space/>Polis citizenship was marked by exclusivity. Inequality of status was widespread; citizens had a higher status than non-citizens, such as women, slaves or<space/><link><target>barbarians</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y16"></extension><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">33</arg></template><space/>The first form of citizenship was based on the way people lived in the<space/><link><target>ancient Greek</target></link><space/>times, in small-scale organic communities of the polis. Citizenship was not seen as a separate activity from the private life of the individual person, in the sense that there was not a distinction between<space/><link><target>public sphere</target><part>public</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Private sphere</target><part>private</part></link><space/>life. The obligations of citizenship were deeply connected into one's everyday life in the polis. These small-scale organic communities were generally seen as a new development in world history, in contrast to the established ancient civilizations of Egypt or Persia, or the hunter-gatherer bands elsewhere. From the viewpoint of the ancient Greeks, a person's public life was not separated from their private life, and Greeks did not distinguish between the two worlds according to the modern western conception. The obligations of citizenship were deeply connected with everyday life. To be truly human, one had to be an active citizen to the community, which Aristotle famously expressed: &quot;To take no part in the running of the community's affairs is to be either a beast or a god!&quot; This form of citizenship was based on obligations of citizens towards the community, rather than rights given to the citizens of the community. This was not a problem because they all had a strong affinity with the polis; their own destiny and the destiny of the community were strongly linked. Also, citizens of the polis saw obligations to the community as an opportunity to be virtuous, it was a source of honour and respect. In Athens, citizens were both ruler and ruled, important political and judicial offices were rotated and all citizens had the right to speak and vote in the political assembly.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman ideas</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>, citizenship expanded from small-scale communities to the entire empire. Romans realized that granting citizenship to people from all over the empire legitimized Roman rule over conquered areas. Roman citizenship was no longer a status of political agency; it had been reduced to a judicial safeguard and the expression of rule and law.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><link><target>Civis romanus sum</target></link>.</extension><space/>Rome carried forth Greek ideas of citizenship such as the principles of<space/><link><target>equality under the law</target></link>, civic participation in government, and notions that &quot;no one citizen should have too much power for too long&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsffujfk"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hosking
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Geoffrey
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Epochs of European Civilization: Antiquity to Renaissance
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Modern Scholar via Recorded Books
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Lecture 5: Rome as a city-state
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>United Kingdom
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>tracks 1 through 9
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4025-8360-5</arg></template></extension><space/>but Rome offered relatively generous terms to its captives, including chances for lesser forms of citizenship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsffujfk"></extension><space/>If Greek citizenship was an &quot;emancipation from the world of things&quot;,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template><space/>the Roman sense increasingly reflected the fact that citizens could act upon material things as well as other citizens, in the sense of buying or selling property, possessions, titles, goods. One historian explained:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg>The person was defined and represented through his actions upon things; in the course of time, the term property came to mean, first, the defining characteristic of a human or other being; second, the relation which a person had with a thing; and third, the thing defined as the possession of some person.</arg><arg name="[[J. G. A. Pocock]], 1988{{sfn|Pocock|1998|p">36}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Roman citizenship reflected a struggle between the upper-class<space/><link><target>Patrician (ancient Rome)</target><part>patrician</part></link><space/>interests against the lower-order working groups known as the<space/><link><target>plebs</target><part>plebeian</part></link><space/>class.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsffujfk"></extension><space/>A citizen came to be understood as a person &quot;free to act by law, free to ask and expect the law's protection, a citizen of such and such a legal community, of such and such a legal standing in that community&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/>Citizenship meant having rights to have possessions, immunities, expectations, which were &quot;available in many kinds and degrees, available or unavailable to many kinds of person for many kinds of reason&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/>And the law, itself, was a kind of bond uniting people.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">38</arg></template><space/>Roman citizenship was more impersonal, universal, multiform, having different degrees and applications.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pocock</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">38</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Middle Ages</heading><paragraph>During the European<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>, citizenship was usually associated with cities and towns, and applied mainly to middle class folk. Titles such as<space/><link><target>bourgeoisie</target><part>burgher</part></link>,<space/><link><target>grand burgher</target></link><space/>(German<space/><italics>Grobrger</italics>) and<space/><link><target>bourgeoisie</target></link><space/>denoted political affiliation and identity in relation to a particular locality, as well as membership in a mercantile or trading class; thus, individuals of respectable means and socioeconomic status were interchangeable with citizens.</paragraph><paragraph>During this era, members of the<space/><link><target>nobility</target></link><space/>had a range of<space/><link><target>Privilege (legal ethics)</target><part>privilege</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>above<space/><link><target>commoner</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>aristocracy</target></link>), though political upheavals and reforms, beginning most prominently with the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>, abolished privileges and created an egalitarian concept of citizenship.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Renaissance</heading><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Renaissance</target></link>, people transitioned from being subjects of a king or queen to being citizens of a city and later to a nation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.161</arg></template><space/>Each city had its own law, courts, and independent administration.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">44</arg></template><space/>And being a citizen often meant being subject to the city's law in addition to having power in some instances to help choose officials.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">44</arg></template><space/>City dwellers who had fought alongside nobles in battles to defend their cities were no longer content with having a subordinate social status, but demanded a greater role in the form of citizenship.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">46</arg></template><space/>Membership in<space/><link><target>guild</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>was an indirect form of citizenship in that it helped their members succeed financially.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">46-47</arg></template><space/>The rise of citizenship was linked to the rise of republicanism, according to one account, since independent citizens meant that kings had less power.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zarrow</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">3</arg></template><space/>Citizenship became an idealized, almost abstract, concept,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>and did not signify a submissive relation with a lord or count, but rather indicated the bond between a person and the state in the rather abstract sense of having<space/><link><target>rights</target></link><space/>and duties.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern times</heading><paragraph>The modern idea of citizenship still respects the idea of political participation, but it is usually done through &quot;elaborate systems of political representation at a distance&quot; such as<space/><link><target>representative democracy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y17"></extension><space/>Modern citizenship is much more passive; action is delegated to others; citizenship is often a constraint on acting, not an impetus to act.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y17"></extension><space/>Nevertheless, citizens are usually aware of their obligations to authorities, and are aware that these bonds often limit what they can do.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y17"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>further2</target><arg>[[History of citizenship]]</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Different senses</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Citizenship contrasting views.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>Many theorists suggest that there are two opposing conceptions of citizenship: an economic one, and a political one. For further information, see<space/><link><target>History of citizenship#Competing senses of citizenship</target><part>History of citizenship</part></link>.</part></link>Citizenship status, under<space/><link><target>social contract</target></link><space/>theory, carries with it both<space/><link><target>Social rights (social contract theory)</target><part>rights</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>duties</target></link>. In this sense, citizenship was described as &quot;a bundle of rights -- primarily, political participation in the life of the community, the right to vote, and the right to receive certain protection from the community, as well as obligations.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsJun16"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Virginia Leary</arg><arg name="editors">Alan C. Cairns, John C. Courtney, Peter MacKinnon, Hans J. Michelmann, David E. Smith</arg><arg name="title">Citizenship, Diversity, and Pluralism: Canadian and Comparative Perspectives</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7735-1893-3</arg><arg name="pages">247–264</arg><arg name="chapter">Citizenship. Human rights, and Diversity</arg><arg name="chapterurl">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="quote">... The concept of 'citizenship' has long acquired the connotation of a bundle of rights... .</arg></template></extension><space/>Citizenship is seen by most scholars as culture-specific, in the sense that the meaning of the term varies considerably from culture to culture, and over time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y17"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Isin
<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Engin F.
<space/></arg><arg name="editor2">Bryan S. Turner
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Handbook of Citizenship Studies
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sage
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Chapter 5 -- David Burchell -- Ancient Citizenship and its Inheritors; Chapter 6 -- Rogers M. Smith -- Modern Citizenship
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>89–104, 105
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7619-6858-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>How citizenship is understood depends on the person making the determination. The relation of citizenship has never been fixed or static, but constantly changes within each society. While citizenship has varied considerably throughout history, and within societies over time, there are some common elements but they vary considerably as well. As a bond, citizenship extends beyond basic kinship ties to unite people of different genetic backgrounds. It usually signifies membership in a political body. It is often based on, or was a result of, some form of military service or expectation of future service. It usually involves some form of political participation, but this can vary from token acts to active service in government. Citizenship is a status in society. It is an ideal state as well. It generally describes a person with legal rights within a given political order. It almost always has an element of exclusion, meaning that some people are not citizens, and that this distinction can sometimes be very important, or not important, depending on a particular society. Citizenship as a concept is generally hard to isolate intellectually and compare with related political notions, since it relates to many other aspects of society such as the<space/><link><target>family</target></link>,<space/><link><target>military service</target></link>, the individual,<space/><link><target>political freedom</target><part>freedom</part></link>,<space/><link><target>religion</target></link>, ideas of<space/><link><target>ethics</target><part>right and wrong</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ethnicity</target></link>, and patterns for how a person should behave in society.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14"></extension><space/>When there are many different groups within a nation, citizenship may be the only real bond which unites everybody as equals without discriminationit is a &quot;broad bond&quot; linking &quot;a person with the state&quot; and gives people a universal identity as a legal member of a specific nation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y15"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gross
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Feliks 
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship and ethnicity: the growth and development of a democratic multiethnic institution
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Greenwood Press
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1999
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Westport, Connecticut
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>xi, xii, xiii,4
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-313-30932-9
<space/></arg><arg name="jfm"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Modern citizenship has often been looked at as two competing underlying ideas:<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y18"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Beiner (editor)
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ronald
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Theorizing Citizenship
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>State University of New York, Albany
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>J. G. A. Pocock, Michael Ignatieff
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>USA
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>29, 54
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7914-2335-2<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold>liberal-individualist</bold><space/>or sometimes<space/><italics>liberal</italics><space/>conception of citizenship suggests that citizens should have entitlements necessary for<space/><link><target>human dignity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14qwea"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Oldfield
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Adrian
</arg><arg name="editor">Bryan Turner<space/></arg><arg name="editor2">Peter Hamilton
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship: Critical Concepts
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>United States and Canada
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>476 pages total; source: ''The Political Quarterly'', 1990 vol.61, pp. 177–187; in the book, pages 188+
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></extension><space/>It assumes people act for the purpose of<space/><link><target>enlightened self-interest</target></link>. According to this viewpoint, citizens are sovereign, morally autonomous beings with duties to pay taxes, obey the law, engage in business transactions, and defend the nation if it comes under attack,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14qwea"></extension><space/>but are essentially passive politically,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y18"></extension><space/>and their primary focus is on economic betterment. This idea began to appear around the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, and became stronger over time, according to one view.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>According to this formulation, the state exists for the benefit of citizens and has an obligation to respect and protect the rights of citizens, including civil rights and political rights.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>It was later that so-called social rights became part of the obligation for the state.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold>civic-republican</bold><space/>or sometimes<space/><italics>classical</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>civic humanist</italics><space/>conception of citizenship emphasizes man's political nature, and sees citizenship as an active process, not a passive state or legal marker.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y18"></extension><space/>It is relatively more concerned that government will interfere with popular places to practice citizenship in the<space/><link><target>public sphere</target></link>. Citizenship means being active in government affairs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14qwea"></extension><space/>According to one view, most people today live as citizens according to the liberal-individualist conception but wished they lived more according to the civic-republican ideal.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y18"></extension><space/>An ideal citizen is one who exhibits &quot;good civic behavior&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Free citizens and a republic government are &quot;mutually interrelated.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Citizenship suggested a commitment to &quot;duty and civic virtue&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Scholars suggest that the concept of citizenship contains many unresolved issues, sometimes called tensions, existing within the relation, that continue to reflect uncertainty about what citizenship is supposed to mean.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Some unresolved issues regarding citizenship include questions about what is the proper balance between<space/><link><target>duties</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>rights</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Another is a question about what is the proper balance between<space/><italics>political citizenship</italics><space/>versus<space/><italics>social citizenship</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Some thinkers see benefits with people being absent from public affairs, since too much participation such as revolution can be destructive, yet too little participation such as total apathy can be problematic as well.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>Citizenship can be seen as a special elite status, and it can also be seen as a democratizing force and something that everybody has; the concept can include both senses.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y12"></extension><space/>According to<space/><link><target>sociology</target><part>sociologist</part></link><space/><link><target>Arthur Stinchcombe</target></link>, citizenship is based on the extent that a person can control one's own destiny within the group in the sense of being able to influence the government of the group.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y14"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Taylor
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David
<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Bryan Turner<space/></arg><arg name="editor2">Peter Hamilton
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship: Critical Concepts
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>United States and Canada
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>476 pages total; 
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-415-07036-8</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.150</arg></template><space/>One last distinction within citizenship is the so-called<space/><italics>consent descent</italics><space/>distinction, and this issue addresses whether citizenship is a fundamental matter determined by a person<space/><italics>choosing</italics><space/>to belong to a particular nation&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;by his or her<space/><italics>consent</italics>&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;or is citizenship a matter of where a person was born&amp;ndash;&amp;ndash;that is, by his or her<space/><italics>descent</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws2Y16"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hebert (editor)
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Yvonne M.
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship in transformation in Canada
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Toronto Press
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>chapters by Veronica Strong-Boag, Yvonne Hebert, Lori Wilkinson
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Toronto
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>3, 4, 5
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8020-0850-X</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>International</heading><paragraph>Some<space/><link><target>intergovernmental organization</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have extended the concept and terminology associated with citizenship to the international level,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Daniele Archibugi</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://press.princeton.edu/titles/8737.html'>''&quot;The Global Commonwealth of Citizens. Toward Cosmopolitan Democracy&quot;''</link>,<space/><link><target>Princeton University Press</target></link>, Princeton, 2008</extension><space/>where it is applied to the totality of the citizens of their constituent countries combined. Citizenship at this level is a secondary concept, with rights deriving from national citizenship.</paragraph><heading level='3'>European Union</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Citizenship of the European Union</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Maastricht Treaty</target></link><space/>introduced the concept of<space/><link><target>citizenship of the European Union</target></link>. Article 17 (1) of the<space/><link><target>Treaties of the European Union#Treaty on European Union</target><part>Treaty on European Union</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Note: the consolidated version.</extension><space/>stated that:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Citizenship of the Union is hereby established. Every person holding the nationality of a Member State shall be a citizen of the Union. Citizenship of the Union shall be additional to and not replace national citizenship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rome"><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2008:115:0001:01:EN:HTML'>Consolidated versions of the Treaty on European Union</link></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An agreement known as the amended<space/><link><target>EC Treaty</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="Rome"></extension><space/>established certain minimal rights for European Union citizens. Article 12 of the amended EC Treaty guaranteed a general right of non-discrimination within the scope of the Treaty. Article 18 provided a limited right to free movement and residence in Member States other than that of which the European Union citizen is a national. Articles 18-21 and 225 provide certain political rights.</paragraph><paragraph>Union citizens have also extensive<space/><link><target>Four Freedoms (European Union)</target><part>rights to move in order to exercise economic activity</part></link><space/>in any of the Member States<extension extension_name='ref'>Note: Articles 39, 43, 49 EC.</extension><space/>which predate the introduction of Union citizenship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Violaine Hacker, Citoyennet culturelle et politique europenne des mdias : entre comptitivit et promotion des valeurs , NATIONS, CULTURES ET ENTREPRISES EN EUROPE, sous la direction de Gilles Rouet, Collection Local et Global, L'Harmattan, Paris, pp. 163-184</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Commonwealth</heading><paragraph>The concept of &quot;<link><target>Commonwealth citizen</target><part>Commonwealth Citizenship</part></link>&quot; has been in place ever since the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of Nations</target></link>. As with the EU, one holds Commonwealth citizenship only by being a citizen of a Commonwealth member state. This form of citizenship offers certain privileges within some Commonwealth countries:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Some such countries do not require tourist<space/><link><target>visa (document)</target><part>visas</part></link><space/>of citizens of other Commonwealth countries.</listitem><listitem>In some Commonwealth countries<space/><link><target>permanent resident</target><part>resident</part></link><space/>citizens of other Commonwealth countries are entitled to political rights, e.g., the<space/><link><target>right to vote</target></link><space/>in local and national elections and in some cases even the right to stand for election.</listitem><listitem>In some instances the right to work in any position (including the<space/><link><target>civil service</target></link>) is granted, except for certain specific positions, such as in the defense departments,<space/><link><target>Governor-General</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>President</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Prime Minister</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>Republic of Ireland</target><part>Ireland</part></link><space/>was excluded from the Commonwealth in 1949 because it declared itself a republic, Ireland is generally treated as if it were still a member. Legislation often specifically provides for equal treatment between Commonwealth countries and Ireland and refers to &quot;Commonwealth countries and Ireland&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2005/246/pdfs/uksi_20050246_en.pdf'>The Commonwealth Countries and Ireland (Immunities and Privileges) (Amendment) Order 2005</link></extension><space/>Ireland's citizens are not classified as foreign nationals in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Canada departed from the principle of nationality being defined in terms of allegiance in 1921. In 1935 the<space/><link><target>Irish Free State</target></link><space/>was the first to introduce its own citizenship. However,<space/><link><target>Irish citizen</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were still treated as<space/><link><target>British subject</target><part>subjects of the Crown</part></link>, and they are still not regarded as foreign, even though Ireland is not a member of the Commonwealth.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Murray v Parkes</italics><space/>[1942] All ER 123.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Canadian Citizenship Act 1946</target><part>Canadian Citizenship Act</part></link><space/>of 1947 provided for a distinct Canadian Citizenship, automatically conferred upon most individuals born in Canada, with some exceptions, and defined the conditions under which one could become a naturalized citizen. The concept of Commonwealth citizenship was introduced in 1948 in the<space/><link><target>History of British nationality law#British Nationality Act 1948</target><part>British Nationality Act 1948</part></link>. Other<space/><link><target>dominion</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>adopted this principle such as<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link>, by way of the British Nationality and New Zealand Citizenship Act of 1948.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Subnational</heading><paragraph>Citizenship most usually relates to membership of the nation state, but the term can also apply at the subnational level.<space/><link><target>Subnational entity</target><part>Subnational entities</part></link><space/>may impose requirements, of<space/><link><target>Residency (domicile)</target><part>residency</part></link><space/>or otherwise, which permit citizens to participate in the political life of that entity, or to enjoy benefits provided by the government of that entity. But in such cases, those eligible are also sometimes seen as &quot;citizens&quot; of the relevant state, province, or region. An example of this is how the fundamental basis of<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target><part>Swiss</part></link><space/>citizenship is citizenship of an individual<space/><link><target>Commune (administrative division)</target><part>commune</part></link>, from which follows citizenship of a<space/><link><target>Canton (country subdivision)</target><part>canton</part></link><space/>and of the Confederation. Another example is<space/><link><target>land</target></link><space/>where the residents enjoy a special provincial citizenship within<space/><link><target>Finland</target></link>,<space/><italics>hembygdsrtt</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>has a federal system in which a person is a citizen of their specific state of residence, such as<space/><link><target>New Jersey</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>California</target></link>, as well as a<space/><link><target>Citizenship in the United States</target><part>citizen of the United States</part></link>. State<space/><link><target>constitution</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>may grant certain rights above and beyond what are granted under the<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target></link><space/>and may impose their own obligations including the sovereign right of taxation and military service; each state maintains at least one military force subject to national militia transfer service, the state's national guard, and some states maintain a second military force not subject to nationalization.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Diagram of citizenship.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Diagram of relationship between; Citizens, Politicians + Laws</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Education</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Citizenship education (subject)</arg></template>&quot;<link><target>Active citizenship</target></link>&quot; is the philosophy that citizens should work towards the betterment of their community through economic participation, public, volunteer work, and other such efforts to improve life for all citizens. In this vein,<space/><link><target>school</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in some countries provide<space/><link><target>citizenship education (subject)</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph>Citizenship is offered as a<space/><link><target>General Certificate of Secondary Education</target></link><space/>(GCSE) course in many schools in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>. As well as teaching knowledge about<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link>, parliament, government, the justice system,<space/><link><target>human rights</target></link><space/>and the UK's relations with the wider world, students participate in active citizenship, often involving a social action or social enterprise in their local community.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Citizenship is a compulsory subject of the National Curriculum in state schools in<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>for all pupils aged 1116. Some schools offer a qualification in this subject at<space/><link><target>GCSE</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>A level</target></link>. All state schools have a statutory requirement to teach the subject, assess pupil attainment and report student's progress in citizenship to parents.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dfes"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dfes.gov.uk/citizenship/
</arg><arg name="title">National curriculum
</arg><arg name="publisher">British Government, Department for Children, Schools and Families
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-02-02</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In<space/><link><target>Wales</target></link><space/>the model used is<space/><link><target>Personal and Social Education</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://new.wales.gov.uk/publications/circular/circulars03/NAFWC132003?lang</arg><arg name="title"><space/>NAFWC 13/2003 Personal and Social Education (PSE) and Work-Related Education (WRE) in the Basic Curriculum. Education (WRE) in the Basic Curriculum.
</arg><arg name="date">15 June 2003
</arg><arg name="publisher">Welsh Assembly Government
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-06-09</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://new.wales.gov.uk/topics/educationandskills/policy_strategy_and_planning/schools/339214-wag/key_documents/supporting_specific_groups/personal_social_education?lang</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Personal and Social Education Framework: Key Stages 1 to 4 in Wales
</arg><arg name="publisher">Welsh Assembly Government
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-06-09</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Citizenship is not taught as a discrete subject in<space/><link><target>Scotland</target><part>Scottish</part></link><space/>schools, but is a cross-curricular strand of the Curriculum for Excellence. However they do teach a subject called &quot;Modern Studies&quot; which covers the social, political and economic study of local, national and international issues.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.msa-scotland.co.uk/
</arg><arg name="title">Modern Studies Association
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-08-09</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Ireland</heading><paragraph>It is taught in<space/><link><target>Republic of Ireland</target><part>Ireland</part></link><space/>as an exam subject for the Junior Certificate. It is known as Civic, Social and Political Education (CSPE). A new Leaving Certificate exam subject with the working title 'Politics &amp; Society' is being developed by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment (NCCA) and is expected to be introduced to the curriculum sometime after 2012.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.ncca.ie/en/Publications/Reports/Senior_Cycle_Politics_and_Society_Report_on_the_consultation.pdf</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nationalism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Non-citizens (Latvia)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Citizenship in the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Citizenship in Canada</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Global citizenship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of citizenship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Transnational citizenship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Spatial Citizenship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Honorary citizenship</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Honorary citizen of the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Honorary Canadian citizenship</target></link></listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Notelist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Weber
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Max
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship in Ancient and Medieval Cities
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The University of Minnesota
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Chapter 3
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Minneapolis, MN
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>43–49
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8166-2880-7
</arg><arg name="ref">harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Peter
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Zarrow
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Imagining the People: Chinese Intellectuals and the Concept of Citizenship, 1890-1920
<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Fogel
<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Joshua A.
<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Zarrow
<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Peter G.
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>3
<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Armonk, NY
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>M. E. Sharpe
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7656-0098-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pocock
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>J. G. A.
</arg><arg name="editor-last">Shafir
</arg><arg name="editor-first">Gershon
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Citizenship Debates
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The University of Minnesota
<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Chapter 2 -- The Ideal of Citizenship since Classical Times (originally published in ''Queen's Quarterly'' 99, no. 1)
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Minneapolis, MN
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>31
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8166-2880-7
</arg><arg name="ref">harv
</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>[[Daniele Archibugi|Archibugi, Daniele]]
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Global Commonwealth of Citizens. Toward Cosmopolitan Democracy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Princeton University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-4008-2976-7
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Beaven, Brad, and John Griffiths. &quot;Creating the Exemplary Citizen: The Changing Notion of Citizenship in Britain 18701939,&quot;<space/><italics>Contemporary British History</italics><space/>(2008) 22#2 pp 203225<space/><template><target>doi</target><arg>10.1080/13619460701189559</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>[[Joseph Carens|Carens, Joseph]]
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Culture, Citizenship, and Community: A Contextual Exploration of Justice as Evenhandedness
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-829768-0
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Heater
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Derek
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Brief History of Citizenship
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>NYU Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8147-3672-2
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Kymlicka
<space/></arg><arg name="first">Will
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Will Kymlicka
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Multicultural Citizenship: A Liberal Theory of Minority Rights
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-829091-9
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Maas
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Willem
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Creating European Citizens
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Rowman & Littlefield
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7425-5486-3
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Marshall
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>T.H.
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1950
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship and Social Class and Other Essays
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shue
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Henry
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1950
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Basic Rights
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">
<space/></arg><arg name="id">
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smith
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rogers
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Stories of Peoplehood: The Politics and Morals of Political Membership
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-521-52003-4
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Somers
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Margaret
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Genealogies of Citizenship: Markets, Statelessness, and the Right to Have Rights
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-521-79394-0
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Soysal
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Yasemin
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Limits of Citizenship. Migrants and Postnational Membership in Europe
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Chicago Press
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Turner
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bryan S.
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship and Social Theory
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sage
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8039-8611-4
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Young<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Iris Marion<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Iris Marion Young<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Polity and group difference: A critique of the ideal of universal citizenship<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Ethics (journal)]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>99<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>250–274<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[University of Chicago Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>2381434<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>January 1989<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/2381434<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>.</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">no</arg><arg name="about">yes</arg><arg name="wikititle">citizenship</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/schools/pshe_and_citizenship/'>BBC PSHE &amp; Citizenship</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2280329'>The Life in the UK Citizenship Test Report by Thom Brooks</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>citizenship</arg><arg>Citizenship</arg><arg>Dominique Leydet</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://opm.gov/extra/investigate/IS-01.pdf
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Citizenship Laws of the World
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2007-03-07
</arg><arg name="date">March 2001
</arg><arg name="format"><space/>pdf
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>United States Office of Personnel Management Investigations Service
</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20060404042127/http://www.opm.gov/extra/investigate/IS-01.pdf
</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2006-04-04
</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Citizenship</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Human migration</target></link><link><target>Category:Nationality</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Government</target></link><link><target>Category:Political concepts</target></link><link><target>Category:Immigration law</target></link></paragraph></article>