<article title='Alfonso_XII_of_Spain'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the ship</arg><arg>Spanish cruiser Alfonso XII</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg>monarch
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Alfonso XII
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[King of Spain]] ''([[List of titles and honours of the Spanish Crown|more]])''
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>King Alfonso XII.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>1884 photograph
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>29 December 1874 –<space/><br><space/>25 November 1885
</arg><arg name="coronation"><space/>
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Amadeo I of Spain|Amadeo I]]<space/><br><space/>{{small|''as King of Spain''}}<space/><br><space/>[[Francisco Serrano, 1st Duke of la Torre|Francisco Serrano]]<space/><br><space/>{{small|''as President of the Republic''}}
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Alfonso XIII of Spain|Alfonso XIII]]
</arg><arg name="reg-type"><space/>{{nowrap|[[Prime Minister of Spain|Prime Ministers]]}}
</arg><arg name="regent"><space/>{{List collapsed|title</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Mercedes of Orléans]]<br/>[[Maria Christina of Austria]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>[[Mercedes, Princess of Asturias|Mercedes]]<br/>[[Infanta Maria Teresa of Spain|Maria Teresa]]<br>[[Fernand Sanz]]<br/>[[Alfonso XIII of Spain|Alfonso XIII]]
</arg><arg name="issue-link"><space/>#Second marriage and rule
</arg><arg name="issue-pipe"><space/>more...
</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[House of Bourbon]]
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Francis, Duke of Cádiz]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>[[Isabella II of Spain|Isabella II, Queen of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{Birth date|1857|11|28|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Madrid]], [[Mid-nineteenth century Spain|Spain]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{Death date and age|1885|11|25|1857|11|28|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Madrid]], [[Restoration (Spain)|Spain]]
</arg><arg name="place of burial"><space/>[[El Escorial]]
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Alfonso XII</bold><space/>(Alfonso Francisco de Ass Fernando Po Juan Mara de la Concepcin Gregorio Pelayo; 28 November 1857 25 November 1885) was<space/><link><target>List of Spanish monarchs</target><part>King of Spain</part></link>, reigning from 1874 to 1885, after a<space/><italics>coup d'tat</italics><space/>restored the monarchy and ended the ephemeral<space/><link><target>First Spanish Republic</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Having been forced into exile after the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution (Spain)</target><part>Glorious Revolution</part></link><space/>deposed his mother<space/><link><target>Isabella II of Spain</target><part>Isabella II</part></link><space/>from the throne in 1868, Alfonso studied in<space/><link><target>Austria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>France</target></link>. His mother abdicated in his favour in 1870, and he returned to Spain as king in 1874 following a military coup. Alfonso died aged 27 in 1885, and was succeeded by his unborn son, who became<space/><link><target>Alfonso XIII of Spain</target><part>Alfonso XIII</part></link><space/>on his birth the following year.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Political background, early life and paternity</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Prncipe Alfonso.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Prince Alfonso.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Alfonso was born in<space/><link><target>Madrid</target></link><space/>as the eldest son of<space/><link><target>Isabella II of Spain</target><part>Queen Isabella II</part></link>. Officially, his father was her husband,<space/><link><target>Francis, Duke of Cdiz</target><part>King Francis</part></link>. Alfonso's biological paternity is uncertain: there is speculation that his biological father may have been Enrique Puigmolt y Mayans (a captain of the guard).<extension extension_name='ref'>Juan Sisinio Prez Garzn, Isabel II: Los Espejos de la Reina (2004)</extension><space/>These rumours were used as political propaganda against Alfonso by the<space/><link><target>Carlism</target><part>Carlists</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>His mother's accession created the second cause of instability, which was the Carlist Wars. The supporters of the<space/><link><target>Infante Carlos, Count of Molina</target><part>Count of Molina</part></link><space/>as king of Spain rose to have him enthroned. In addition, within the context of the post-Napoleonic restorations and revolutions which engulfed the West both in Europe and the Americas, both the Carlistas as well as the Isabelino conservatives were opposed to the new Napoleonic constitutional system. Much like in Britain, who subtracted itself from the liberal constitutional process, Spanish conservatives wanted to continue with the Traditional Spanish Organic Laws such as the<space/><link><target>Fuero Juzgo</target></link>, the Novsima Recopilacin and the<space/><link><target>Siete Partidas</target><part>Partidas of Alfonso X</part></link>. This led to the third cause of instability of worth, the &quot;Independence of the American Kingdoms&quot;, recognized between 1823 and 1850.</paragraph><heading level='2'>A split nation</heading><paragraph>When Queen Isabella and her husband were forced to leave Spain by the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution (Spain)</target><part>Revolution of 1868</part></link>, Alfonso accompanied them to Paris. From there, he was sent to the<space/><link><target>Theresianum</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link><space/>to continue his studies. On 25 June 1870, he was recalled to Paris, where his mother abdicated in his favour, in the presence of a number of Spanish nobles who had tied their fortunes to that of the exiled queen. He assumed the title of Alfonso XII, for although no King of united Spain had borne the name &quot;Alfonso XI&quot;, the Spanish monarchy was regarded as continuous with the more ancient monarchy represented by the 11 kings of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Asturias</target><part>Asturias</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Len</target><part>Len</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Castile</target><part>Castile</part></link><space/>also named<space/><link><target>Alfonso</target></link>.<link><target>File:Royal Monogram of Alfonso XII of Spain.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>120px</part><part>Royal Monogram</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>The Republic</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>First Spanish Republic</arg></template>After Amadeo's abandonment in 1873, Parliament declared the Federal Republic (including Cuba, Puerto Rico and the Pacific Archipelagos), the first act of President Estanislao Figueras was to extend the Abolition Act to Puerto Rico. Cuban slaves would have to wait until 1889.</paragraph><paragraph>But the republicans were not in agreement either, and they had to contend with the War in Cuba, and Muslim uprisings in Spanish Morocco. In the midst of the crisis during and after the First Spanish Republic, the<space/><link><target>Carlism</target><part>Carlist</part></link><space/>party made itself strong in areas with claims over their national and institutional specificity, such as Catalonia or the Basque districts. By 1872, the<space/><link><target>Third Carlist War</target></link><space/>erupted. This unrest led to the creation of a group in favor of the Bourbon restoration, made by some sectors of the conservatives led by Canovas del Castillo.</paragraph><paragraph>The Prince of Asturias, Alfonso, was the person chosen to develop the new road map proposed by Canovas, which led to the June 1870 abdication of Queen Isabel II in favour of her son Prince Alfonso. The new road map which indeed ended the eternal crisis begun in 1810 was called 'Alfonsismo' and the moderate centrist Cnovas del Castillo became the spokesman. As having Alfonso in Spain, would be a problem Cnovas became responsible for his education. So, he sent Alfonso to the Sandhurst Military Academy in England, where the training Alfonso received was severe but more cosmopolitan than Spain, given the current atmosphere.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1 December 1874, Alfonso issued the Sandhurst Manifesto, where he set the ideological basis of the Bourbon Restoration. It was drafted in reply to a birthday greeting from his followers, a manifesto proclaiming himself the sole representative of the Spanish monarchy. At the end of 1874, Brigadier<space/><link><target>Arsenio Martnez Campos</target><part>Martnez Campos</part></link>, who had long been working more or less openly for the king, led some battalions of the central army to<space/><link><target>Sagunto</target></link>, rallied to his own flag the troops sent against him, and entered<space/><link><target>Valencia</target></link><space/>in the king's name.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template><space/>Thereupon the President resigned, and his power was transferred to the king's plenipotentiary and adviser,<space/><link><target>Antonio Cnovas del Castillo</target><part>Antonio Cnovas</part></link>. The 29 December 1874 military coup of Gen. Martinez Campos in Sagunto ended the failed republic and meant the rise of the young Prince Alfonso.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Return from exile</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Alfonso XII King.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>210px</part><part>Alfonso XII in the uniform of the Supreme Commander of the<space/><link><target>Spanish Navy</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:5 Pesetas l'effigie d'Alphonse XII,1875.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>5 Peseta of Alfonso XII</part></link>Within a few days after Canovas del Castillo took power as Premier, the new king, proclaimed on 29 December 1874, arrived at Madrid, passing through<space/><link><target>Barcelona</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Valencia</target></link><space/>and was acclaimed everywhere (1875). In 1876, a vigorous campaign against the<space/><link><target>Carlists</target></link>, in which the young king took part, resulted in the defeat of<space/><link><target>Carlos, Duke of Madrid</target><part>Don Carlos</part></link><space/>and the Duke's abandonment of the struggle.</paragraph><paragraph>Initially led by Canovas del Castillo as moderate prime minister, what was thought at one time as a coup aimed at placing the military in the political-administrative positions of power, in reality ushered in a permanent civilian regime that lasted until the 1931 Second Republic. Cnovas was the real architect of the new regime of the Restoration.</paragraph><paragraph>In order to eliminate one of the problems of the reign of Isabel II, the single party and its destabilizing consequences, the Liberal Party was allowed to incorporate and participate in national politics, and the 'turnismo' or alternation was to become the new system. Turnismo would be endorsed in the Constitution of 1876 and the Pact of Pardo Palace (1885). It meant that liberal and conservative prime ministers would succeed each other ending thus the troubles.</paragraph><paragraph>This led to the end of the Carlist revolts and the victory over the New York-backed Cuban revolutionaries, and led to a huge backing both by insular and peninsular Spaniards of Alfonso as a wise and able king.</paragraph><paragraph>Alfonso's short reign established the foundations for the final socioeconomic recuperation of Spain after the 18081874 crisis. Both European (the coastal regions, such as the Basque Country, Catalonia, and Asturias) and Overseas Antilles and Pacific were able to grow steadily. Cuba and Puerto Rico prospered to the point that Spain's first train was between Havana and Camaguey, and the world's first telegraph was in Puerto Rico, as Samuel Morse lived there with his daughter, married to a Puerto Rican businessman. Upon the American invasion of Puerto Rico, ten US dollars were needed to buy one Puerto Rican peso.</paragraph><paragraph>On 23 January 1878 at the Basilica of<space/><link><target>Basilica of Nuestra Seora de Atocha</target><part>Atocha</part></link><space/>in Madrid, Alfonso married his first cousin, Princess<space/><link><target>Mercedes of Orlans</target><part>Maria de las Mercedes</part></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Antoine, Duke of Montpensier</target></link>, but she died within six months of the marriage.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Second marriage and rule</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Alfonso XII with his second wife.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Alfonso XII and his second wife<space/><link><target>Maria Christina of Austria</target></link>, 1885.</part></link>On 29 November 1879 at the Basilica of Atocha in<space/><link><target>Madrid</target></link>, Alfonso married a much more distant relative,<space/><link><target>Maria Christina of Austria</target></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Karl Ferdinand, Archduke of Austria</target><part>Archduke Karl Ferdinand</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Archduchess Elisabeth Franziska of Austria</target><part>Archduchess Elisabeth of Austria</part></link>. During the honeymoon, a pastry cook named Otero fired at the young sovereign and his wife as they were driving in Madrid.</paragraph><paragraph>The children of this marriage were:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mercedes, Princess of Asturias</target><part>Mara de las Mercedes</part></link>, Princess of Asturias, (11 September 1880 17 October 1904), married on 14 February 1901 to<space/><link><target>Prince Carlos of Bourbon-Two Sicilies</target></link>, and titular heiress from the death of her father until the posthumous birth of her brother</listitem><listitem><link><target>Infanta Maria Teresa of Spain</target><part>Mara Teresa</part></link>, (12 November 1882 23 September 1912), married to<space/><link><target>Prince Ferdinand of Bavaria</target></link><space/>on 12 January 1906</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alfonso XIII of Spain</target><part>Alfonso XIII</part></link><space/>(17 May 1886 28 February 1941). Born posthumously. He married<space/><link><target>Princess Victoria Eugenie of Battenberg</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Alfonso had two sons by Elena Armanda Nicolasa Sanz y Martnez de Arizala (<link><target>Castelln de la Plana</target></link>, 15 December 1849 Paris, 24 December 1898):</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Alfonso Sanz y Martnez de Arizala (28 January 1880, Madrid 1970), married in 1922 to Mara de Guadalupe de Limantour y Mariscal (d. 1977, Marbella), daughter of Julio de Limantour y Marquet (17 June 1863,<space/><link><target>Mexico City</target></link><space/>11 October 1909, Mexico City) and wife Elena Mariscal y ..., paternal granddaughter of French Joseph Yves de Limantour y Rence de la Pagame (1812,<space/><link><target>Ploemeur</target></link><space/>1885, Mexico City) and wife Adle Marquet y Cabannes<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Real Academia Matritense de Heráldica y Genealogía</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anales de la Real Academia Matritense de Heráldica y Genealogía</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>RAMHG</arg><arg name="page"><space/>273<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fernando Sanz y Martnez de Arizala</target></link><space/>(28 February 1881, Madrid 1922, Nice, France), unmarried and without issue</listitem></list><paragraph>In 1881 Alfonso refused to sanction a law by which the ministers were to remain in office for a fixed term of 18 months. Upon the consequent resignation of Canovas del Castillo, he summoned<space/><link><target>Prxedes Mateo Sagasta</target></link>, the Liberal leader, to form a new cabinet.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Death and impact</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Death of King Alfonso XII of Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Funeral procession of Alfonso XII, from the 5 December 1885, issue of ''<link><target>L'Illustration</target></link>''</part></link><link><target>File:Monumento a Alfonso XII de Espaa en los Jardines del Retiro - 04.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part><link><target>Monument to Alfonso XII</target></link>, erected in 1922 in the<space/><link><target>Parque del Buen Retiro</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Madrid</target></link>.</part></link>In November 1885, Alfonso died, just short of his 28th birthday, at the<space/><link><target>Royal Palace of El Pardo</target></link>. He had been suffering from<space/><link><target>tuberculosis</target></link>, but the immediate cause of his death was a recurrence of<space/><link><target>dysentery</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Death of the King of Spain&quot;,<space/><italics>The Times</italics><space/>(26 November 1885): 7.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1902, his widow Maria Cristina initiated a national contest to build a monument in memory of Alfonso. The winning design, by<space/><link><target>Jos Grases Riera</target></link>, was erected in an artificial lake in Madrid's<space/><link><target>Parque del Buen Retiro</target></link><space/>in 1922.</paragraph><paragraph>Coming to the throne at such an early age, Alfonso had served no apprenticeship in the art of ruling, but he possessed great natural tact and a sound judgment ripened by the trials of exile. Benevolent and sympathetic in disposition, he won the affection of his people by fearlessly visiting districts ravaged by<space/><link><target>cholera</target></link><space/>or devastated by earthquake in 1885. His capacity for dealing with men was considerable, and he never allowed himself to become the instrument of any particular party. During his short reign, peace was established both at home and abroad, finances were well regulated, and the various administrative services were placed on a basis that afterwards enabled Spain to pass through the disastrous<space/><link><target>SpanishAmerican War</target><part>war with the United States</part></link><space/>without the threat of a revolution.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Monument to Alfonso XII</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Alphonso</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Ancestry</heading><paragraph><template><target>ahnentafel top</target><arg name="width">100%</arg></template><xhtml:center><template><target>ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Alfonso XII of Spain'''
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. [[Francis of Spain|Infante Francis of Spain, Duke of Cádiz]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. [[Isabella II of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[Infante Francisco de Paula of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. [[Princess Luisa Carlotta of Bourbon-Two Sicilies|Princess Luisa Carlotta of the Two Sicilies]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3"><space/>6. [[Ferdinand VII of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4"><space/>7. [[Maria Christina of the Two Sicilies|Princess Maria Christina of the Two Sicilies]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[Charles IV of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. [[Maria Luisa of Parma|Princess Maria Luisa of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[Francis I of the Two Sicilies]] (</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. [[Maria Isabella of Spain|Infanta Maria Isabella of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="4"><space/>12. [[Charles IV of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="5"><space/>13. [[Maria Luisa of Parma|Princess Maria Luisa of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="6"><space/>14. [[Francis I of the Two Sicilies]] (</arg><arg name="7"><space/>15. [[Maria Isabella of Spain|Infanta Maria Isabella of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="8"><space/>16. [[Charles III of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="9"><space/>17. [[Maria Amalia of Saxony|Princess Maria Amalia of Saxony]] (</arg><arg name="10"><space/>18. [[Philip, Duke of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="11"><space/>19. [[Princess Louise-Élisabeth of France]] (</arg><arg name="12"><space/>20. [[Ferdinand I of the Two Sicilies]] (</arg><arg name="13"><space/>21. [[Marie Caroline of Austria|Archduchess Marie Caroline of Austria]] (</arg><arg name="14"><space/>22. [[Charles IV of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="15"><space/>23. [[Maria Luisa of Parma|Princess Maria Luisa of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="16"><space/>24. [[Charles III of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="17"><space/>25. [[Maria Amalia of Saxony|Princess Maria Amalia of Saxony]] (</arg><arg name="18"><space/>26. [[Philip, Duke of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="19"><space/>27. [[Princess Louise-Élisabeth of France]] (</arg><arg name="20"><space/>28. [[Ferdinand I of the Two Sicilies]] (</arg><arg name="21"><space/>29. [[Marie Caroline of Austria|Archduchess Marie Caroline of Austria]] (</arg><arg name="22"><space/>30. [[Charles IV of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="23"><space/>31. [[Maria Luisa of Parma|Princess Maria Luisa of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="24"><space/>24. [[Charles III of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="25"><space/>25. [[Maria Amalia of Saxony|Princess Maria Amalia of Saxony]] (</arg><arg name="26"><space/>26. [[Philip, Duke of Parma]] (</arg><arg name="27"><space/>27. [[Princess Louise-Élisabeth of France]] (</arg><arg name="28"><space/>28. [[Ferdinand I of the Two Sicilies]] (</arg><arg name="29"><space/>29. [[Marie Caroline of Austria|Archduchess Marie Caroline of Austria]] (</arg><arg name="30"><space/>30. [[Charles IV of Spain]] (</arg><arg name="31"><space/>31. [[Maria Luisa of Parma|Princess Maria Luisa of Parma]] (</arg></template></xhtml:center><template><target>ahnentafel bottom</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Alfonso XII of Spain</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://historiaantiqua.byethost8.com/paginas/liberalismo.htm#AlfonsoXII'>Historiaantiqua.</link><space/><italics>Alfonso XII; (Spanish)</italics><space/>(2008)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg>[[House of Bourbon]]</arg><arg>28 November</arg><arg>1857</arg><arg>25 November</arg><arg>1885</arg><arg>[[Capetian dynasty]]</arg></template><template><target>S-reg</target></template><template><target>s-break</target></template><template><target>s-vac</target><arg name="reason">[[First Spanish Republic|Republic declared]]</arg><arg name="last">[[Amadeo I of Spain|Amadeo I]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Spanish monarchs|King of Spain]]</arg><arg name="years">1874 – 1885</arg></template><template><target>s-vac</target><arg name="next">[[Alfonso XIII of Spain|Alfonso XIII]]</arg></template><template><target>S-roy</target><arg>es</arg></template><template><target>s-break</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Isabella, Princess of Asturias (1851–1931)|Isabella]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Prince of Asturias]]</arg><arg name="years">1857 – 1868</arg></template><template><target>S-vac</target><arg name="reason">[[Glorious Revolution (Spain)|Glorious Revolution]]</arg><arg name="next">[[Prince Emanuele Filiberto, Duke of Aosta|Emanuele Filiberto]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Monarchs of Spain</target></template><template><target>Infantes of Spain</target></template><template><target>Princes of Asturias</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Alfonso 12 Of Spain</target></template><link><target>Category:1857 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1885 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Nobility from Madrid</target></link><link><target>Category:Spanish monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Bourbon (Spain)</target></link><link><target>Category:Princes of Asturias</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Catholic monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Restoration (Spain)</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of Santiago</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Order of Alcntara</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Golden Fleece</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Garter</target></link><link><target>Category:Recipients of the Royal Order of Kamehameha I</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from tuberculosis</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from dysentery</target></link><link><target>Category:Graduates of the Royal Military College, Sandhurst</target></link><link><target>Category:Infectious disease deaths in Spain</target></link><link><target>Category:Spanish infantes</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials in the Pantheon of Kings at El Escorial</target></link><link><target>Category:Grand Masters of the Order of the Golden Fleece</target></link><link><target>Category:Collge Stanislas de Paris alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century monarchs in Europe</target></link></paragraph></article>