<article title='Cotton_Mather'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the 17th and 18th century Puritan minister</arg><arg>from the rock band</arg><arg>Cotton Mather (band)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="name"><space/>Cotton Mather
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Cotton Mather.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Cotton Mather, circa 1700
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|mf</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Boston]], [[Massachusetts Bay Colony]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|mf</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>[[Minister (religion)|Minister]]
</arg><arg name="parents"><space/>[[Increase Mather]] and Maria Cotton
</arg><arg name="relatives"><space/>[[John Cotton (Puritan)|John Cotton]] and [[Richard Mather]]
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>Appletons' Mather Richard - Cotton signature.png</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Cotton Mather</bold>,<space/><link><target>Fellow of the Royal Society#Fellows</target><part>FRS</part></link><space/>(February 12, 1663&amp;nbsp; February 13, 1728; A.B. 1678,<space/><link><target>Harvard University</target><part>Harvard College</part></link>; A.M. 1681, honorary doctorate 1710,<space/><link><target>University of Glasgow</target></link>) was a socially and politically influential<space/><link><target>History of New England</target><part>New England</part></link><space/><link><target>Puritan</target></link><space/>minister, prolific author, and<space/><link><target>pamphleteer</target></link>. Known for his vigorous support for the<space/><link><target>Salem witch trials</target></link>, he also left a scientific legacy due to his<space/><link><target>Hybrid (biology)</target><part>hybridization</part></link><space/>experiments and his promotion of<space/><link><target>inoculation</target></link><space/>for disease prevention. He was subsequently denied the Presidency of Harvard College which his father, Increase, had held.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Life and work</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Richard Mather.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>100px</part><part>Richard Mather</part></link><link><target>File:JohnCotton.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>100px</part><part>thumb</part><part>John Cotton (15851652)</part></link>Mather was born in Boston, Massachusetts Bay Colony, the son of Maria (ne Cotton) and<space/><link><target>Increase Mather</target></link>, and grandson of both<space/><link><target>John Cotton (Puritan)</target><part>John Cotton</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Richard Mather</target></link>, all also prominent Puritan ministers. Mather was named after his maternal grandfather, John Cotton. He attended<space/><link><target>Boston Latin School</target></link>, where his name was posthumously added to its<space/><link><target>Boston Latin School#Hall of Fame</target><part>Hall of Fame</part></link>, and graduated from Harvard in 1678 at age 15. After completing his post-graduate work, he joined his father as assistant pastor of Boston's original<space/><link><target>Second Church, Boston</target><part>North Church</part></link><space/>(not to be confused with the Anglican/Episcopal<space/><link><target>Old North Church</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Paul Revere</target></link><space/>fame). In 1685 Mather assumed full responsibilities as pastor of the church.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CottonMather house HanoverSt Boston.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Mather lived on<space/><link><target>Hanover Street (Boston, Massachusetts)</target><part>Hanover Street</part></link>, Boston, 16881718<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="publisher">State Street Trust Co</arg><arg name="title">Forty of Boston's historic houses</arg><arg name="year">1912</arg></template>.</extension></part></link>Mather wrote more than 450 books and pamphlets, and his ubiquitous literary works made him one of the most influential religious leaders in America. Mather set the moral tone in the colonies, and sounded the call for second- and third-generation Puritans, whose parents had left<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>New England</target></link><space/>colonies of<space/><link><target>North America</target></link>, to return to the<space/><link><target>Theology</target><part>theological</part></link><space/>roots of<space/><link><target>Puritan</target><trail>ism</trail></link>. The most important of these,<space/><italics><link><target>Magnalia Christi Americana</target></link></italics><space/>(1702), comprises seven distinct books, many of which depict biographical and historical narratives.</paragraph><paragraph>From his religious training, Mather viewed the importance of texts for elaborating meaning and for bridging different moments of historylinking, for instance, the Biblical stories of<space/><link><target>Noah</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Abraham</target></link><space/>with the arrival of such eminent leaders as<space/><link><target>John Eliot (missionary)</target><part>John Eliot</part></link>,<space/><link><target>John Winthrop</target></link>, and his own father, Increase. Highly influential, Mather was a force to be reckoned with in secular, as well as in spiritual, matters. After the fall of<space/><link><target>James II of England</target></link>, in 1688, Mather was among the leaders of the successful<space/><link><target>1689 Boston revolt</target><part>revolt</part></link><space/>against James' governor of the consolidated<space/><link><target>Dominion of New England</target></link>, Sir<space/><link><target>Edmund Andros</target></link>.<link><target>File:Increase Mather grave.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The Mather tomb in<space/><link><target>Copp's Hill Burying Ground</target><part>Copp's Hill Cemetery</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Mather was not known for writing in a neutral, unbiased perspective. Many, if not all, of his writings had bits and pieces of his own personal life in them or were written for personal reasons. According to literary historian Sacvan Bercovitch:<extension extension_name='ref'>Bercovitch 1972, p. 106</extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>Few puritans more loudly decried the bosom serpent of egotism than did Cotton Mather; none more clearly exemplified it. Explicitly or implicitly, he projects himself everywhere in his writings. In the most direct compensatory sense, he does so by using literature as a means of personal redress. He tells us that he composed his discussions of the family to bless his own, his essays on the riches of Christ to repay his benefactors, his tracts on morality to convert his enemies, his funeral discourses to console himself for the loss of a child, wife, or friend.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather influenced early American science. In 1716, because of observations of corn varieties, he conducted one of the first recorded experiments with plant<space/><link><target>Hybrid (biology)</target><part>hybridization</part></link>. This observation was memorialized in a letter to his friend James Petiver:<extension extension_name='ref'>Zirkle 1935, p.<space/><link type='external' href='http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015011424788;seq=129;view=1up;num=104'>104</link></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg name="First: my Friend planted a Row of Indian corn that was Coloured Red and Blue; the rest of the Field being planted with corn of the yellow, which is the most usual color. To the Windward side, this Red and Blue Row, so infected Three or Four whole Rows, as to communicate the same Colour unto them; and part of ye Fifth and some of ye Sixth. But to the Leeward Side, no less than Seven or Eight Rows, had ye same Colour communicated unto them; and some small Impressions were made on those that were yet further off.<ref>Zirkle 1935, p. [http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id">mdp.39015011424788;seq</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In November 1713, Mather's wife, newborn twins, and two-year-old daughter all succumbed during a measles epidemic.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hostetter</arg><arg name="first">Margaret Kendrick</arg><arg name="title">What We Don't See</arg><arg name="journal">The New England Journal of Medicine</arg><arg name="date">April 5, 2012</arg><arg name="volume">366</arg><arg name="pages">1328–34</arg><arg name="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1111421</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nejm.org/doi/pdf/10.1056/NEJMra1111421</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>April 6, 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>Twice widowed, of his 15 children, only two survived Mather, who died on the day after his 65th birthday and was buried on<space/><link><target>Copp's Hill</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Old North Church</target></link>.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Boyle's influence on Mather</heading><paragraph>A huge influence throughout Mather's career was<space/><link><target>Robert Boyle</target></link>. Mather read<space/><italics>The Usefulness of Experimental Natural Philosophy</italics>, which Boyle had written. Mather read Boyle's work closely throughout the 1680s and his early works on science and religion borrowed greatly from it. He used almost identical language to Boyle.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="author-link">Robert Middlekauff</arg><arg name="last">Middlekauff</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="title">The Mathers: Three Generations of Puritan Intellectuals, 1596–1728</arg><arg name="place">Los Angeles, CA</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Increase Mather</heading><paragraph>Mather's relationship with his own father, Increase Mather, is thought by some to have been strained and difficult. Increase was a pastor of the<space/><link><target>Second Church, Boston</target><part>North Square Church</part></link><space/>and president of<space/><link><target>Harvard College</target></link>; he led an accomplished life. Despite Cotton's efforts, he never became quite as well known and successful in politics as his father. He did surpass his father's output as a writer, writing over 400 books. One of the most public displays of their strained relationship emerged during the witch trials, which Increase Mather reportedly did not support.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hovey, pp. 53132</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Yale College</heading><paragraph>Cotton Mather helped convince<space/><link><target>Elihu Yale</target></link><space/>to make a donation to a new college in New Haven that would come to be<space/><link><target>Yale College</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.yale.edu/opa/arc-ybc/v27.n28/story3.html</arg><arg name="title">Profile</arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 25, 2014</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Smallpox inoculation controversy</heading><paragraph>The practice of smallpox<space/><link><target>inoculation</target></link><space/>(as opposed to the later practice of<space/><link><target>vaccination</target></link>) was developed possibly in 8th-century India<extension extension_name='ref'>Hopkins, Donald R. (2002).<space/><italics>The Greatest Killer: Smallpox in History</italics>; ISBN 0-226-35168-8, p. 140.</extension><space/>or 10th-century China.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Needham</arg><arg name="first">Joseph</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="series">Science and Civilization in China</arg><arg name="volume">6. Biology and Biological Technology</arg><arg name="title">Part 6, Medicine</arg><arg name="place"><space/>Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="page">154</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Spreading its reach in seventeenth-century Turkey, inoculation or, rather, variolation, involved infecting a person through a cut in the skin with<space/><link><target>exudate</target></link><space/>from a patient with a relatively mild case of smallpox (<link><target>variola</target></link>), in order to bring about a manageable and recoverable infection that would provide later immunity. By the beginning of the 18th century, the<space/><link><target>Royal Society</target></link><space/>in England was discussing the practice of inoculation, and the smallpox epidemic in 1713 spurred further interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Blake 1952, pp. 48990</extension><space/>It was not until 1721, however, that England recorded its first case of inoculation.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early New England</heading><paragraph>Smallpox was a serious threat in colonial America, most devastating to Native Americans, but also to Anglo-American settlers. New England suffered smallpox epidemics in 1677, 168990, and 1702.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aronson and Newman 2002</extension><space/>It was highly contagious, and mortality could reach as high as 30 percent or more.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gronim 2007, 248">Gronim 2007, p. 248.</extension><space/>Boston had been plagued by smallpox outbreaks in 1690 and 1702. During this era, public authorities in Massachusetts dealt with the threat primarily by means of quarantine. Incoming ships were quarantined in Boston harbor, and any smallpox patients in town were held under guard or in a &quot;pesthouse.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Blake 1952, p. 489</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1706, Mather's slave, Onesimus, explained to Mather how he had been inoculated as a child in<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Niven</arg><arg name="first1">Steven J.</arg><arg name="title">Onesimus (fl. 1706 – 1717), slave and medical pioneer, was born in the...</arg><arg name="url">http://hutchinscenter.fas.harvard.edu/onesimus-fl-1706-1717-slave-and-medical-pioneer-was-born<space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/>Hutchins center<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard College</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2015</arg><arg name="date">2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Mather was fascinated by the idea. By July 1716, Mather had read an endorsement of inoculation by Dr Emanuel Timonius of Constantinople in the<space/><italics><link><target>Philosophical Transactions</target></link></italics>. Mather then declared, in a letter to Dr.<space/><link><target>John Woodward (naturalist)</target><part>John Woodward</part></link><space/>of Gresham College in London, that he planned to press Boston's doctors to adopt the practice of inoculation should smallpox reach the colony again.<extension extension_name='ref'>Blake 1952, pp. 49091</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By 1721, a whole generation of young Bostonians was vulnerable and memories of the last epidemic's horrors had by and large disappeared.<extension extension_name='ref'>Winslow 1974, pp. 2429</extension><space/>On April 22 of that year, the HMS<space/><italics>Seahorse</italics><space/>arrived from the West Indies carrying smallpox on board. Despite attempts to protect the town through quarantine, eight known cases of smallpox appeared in Boston by May 27, and by mid-June, the disease was spreading at an alarming rate. As a new wave of smallpox hit the area and continued to spread, many residents fled to outlying rural settlements. The combination of exodus, quarantine, and outside traders' fears disrupted business in the capital of the Bay Colony for weeks. Guards were stationed at the House of Representatives to keep Bostonians from entering without special permission. The death toll reached 101 in September, and the<space/><link><target>Selectmen</target></link>, powerless to stop it, &quot;severely limited the length of time funeral bells could toll.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blake 1952, 495">Blake 1952, p. 495</extension><space/>As one response, legislators delegated a thousand pounds from the treasury to help the people who, under these conditions, could no longer support their families.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On June 6, 1721, Mather sent an abstract of reports on inoculation by Timonius and Jacobus Pylarinus to local physicians, urging them to consult about the matter. He received no response. Next, Mather pleaded his case to Dr.<space/><link><target>Zabdiel Boylston</target></link>, who tried the procedure on his only son and two slavesone grown and one a boy. All recovered in about a week. Boylston inoculated seven more people by mid-July. The epidemic peaked in October 1721, with 411 deaths; by February 26, 1722, Boston was, once again, free of smallpox. The total number of cases since April 1721 came to 5,889, with 844 deathsmore than three-quarters of all the deaths in Boston during 1721.<extension extension_name='ref'>Blake 1952, 496</extension><space/>Meanwhile, Boylston had inoculated 287 people, with six resulting deaths.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Best</arg><arg name="first1">M</arg><arg name="title">Making the right decision: Benjamin Franklin's son dies of smallpox in 1736</arg><arg name="journal">Qual Saf Health Care</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="volume">16</arg><arg name="issue">6</arg><arg name="pages">478–80</arg><arg name="doi">10.1136/qshc.2007.023465</arg><arg name="pmid">18055894</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18055894</arg><arg name="accessdate">September 13, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Inoculation debate</heading><paragraph>Boylston and Mather's inoculation crusade &quot;raised a horrid Clamour&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Mather</arg><arg>1911–1912</arg><arg name="pp">11, 628</arg></template><space/>among the people of Boston. Both Boylston and Mather were &quot;Object[s] of their Fury; their furious Obloquies and Invectives&quot;, which Mather acknowledges in his diary. Boston's Selectmen, consulting a doctor who claimed that the practice caused many deaths and only spread the infection, forbade Boylston from performing it again.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Blake</arg><arg>1952</arg><arg name="p">493</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>The New-England Courant</target></link></italics><space/>published writers who opposed the practice. The editorial stance was that the Boston populace feared that inoculation spread, rather than prevented, the disease; however, some historians, notably<space/><link><target>H. W. Brands</target></link>, have argued that this position was a result of editor-in-chief<space/><link><target>James Franklin (printer)</target><part>James Franklin</part></link>'s (<link><target>Benjamin Franklin</target></link>'s brother)<space/><link><target>contrarian</target></link><space/>positions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.bl.uk/onlinegallery/features/cowpocklge.html</arg><arg name="title">The Smallpox Inoculation Hospital at St. Pancras</arg><arg name="publisher">BL</arg><arg name="place">[[United Kingdom|UK]]</arg><arg name="date">2003-11-30</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-15</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Public discourse ranged in tone from organized arguments by Reverend John Williams from Boston, who posted that &quot;several arguments proving that inoculating the smallpox is not contained in the law of Physick, either natural or divine, and therefore unlawful&quot;,<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Williams</arg><arg>1721</arg></template><space/>to those put forth in a pamphlet by Dr.<space/><link><target>William Douglass (physician)</target><part>William Douglass</part></link><space/>of Boston, entitled<space/><italics>The Abuses and Scandals of Some Late Pamphlets in Favour of Inoculation of the Small Pox</italics><space/>(1721), on the qualifications of inoculation's proponents. (Douglass was exceptional at the time for holding a medical degree from Europe.) At the extreme, in November 1721, someone hurled a lighted grenade into Mather's home.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Blake</arg><arg>1952</arg><arg name="p">495</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Medical opposition</heading><paragraph>Several opponents of smallpox inoculation, among them Rev. John Williams, stated that there were only two laws of physick (medicine): sympathy and antipathy. In his estimation, inoculation was neither a sympathy toward a wound or a disease, or an antipathy toward one, but the creation of one. For this reason, its practice violated the natural laws of medicine, transforming health care practitioners into those who harm rather than heal.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Williams</arg><arg>1721</arg><arg name="p">13</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As with many colonists, Williams' Puritan beliefs were enmeshed in every aspect of his life, and he used the<space/><link><target>Bible</target></link><space/>to state his case. He quoted<space/><link><target>Matthew 9:12</target></link>, when<space/><link><target>Jesus</target></link><space/>said: &quot;It is not the healthy who need a doctor, but the sick.&quot; Dr.<space/><link><target>William Douglass (physician)</target><part>William Douglass</part></link><space/>proposed a more<space/><link><target>secular</target></link><space/>argument against inoculation, stressing the importance of reason over passion and urging the public to be pragmatic in their choices. In addition, he demanded that ministers leave the practice of medicine to physicians, and not meddle in areas where they lacked expertise. According to Douglass, smallpox inoculation was &quot;a medical experiment of consequence,&quot; one not to be undertaken lightly. He believed that not all learned individuals were qualified to doctor others, and while ministers took on several roles in the early years of the colony, including that of caring for the sick, they were now expected to stay out of state and civil affairs. Douglass also felt that inoculation caused more deaths than it prevented. The only reason Cotton Mather had success in it, he said, was because Mather had used it on children, who are naturally more resilient. Douglass vowed to always speak out against &quot;the wickedness of spreading infection.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Douglass<space/></arg><arg><space/>1722<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>11</arg></template><space/>Speak out he did: &quot;The battle between these two prestigious adversaries [Douglass and Mather] lasted far longer than the epidemic itself, and the literature accompanying the controversy was both vast and venomous.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Van de Wetering<space/></arg><arg><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>46</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Puritan resistance</heading><paragraph>Generally, Puritan pastors favored the inoculation experiments. Increase Mather was joined by prominent pastors Benjamin Colman and William Cooper in openly propagating the use of inoculations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stout,<space/><italics>The New England Soul</italics>, p. 102</extension><space/>&quot;One of the classic assumptions of the Puritan mind was that the will of God was to be discerned in nature as well as in revelation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Alan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Heimert<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Religion and the American Mind<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>5</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Nevertheless Williams questioned whether the smallpox &quot;is not one of the strange works of God; and whether inoculation of it be not a fighting with the most High.&quot; He also asked his readers if the smallpox epidemic may have been given to them by God as &quot;punishment for sin,&quot; and warned that attempting to shield themselves from God's fury (via inoculation), would only serve to &quot;provoke him more.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg><space/>1721<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>4</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Puritans found meaning in affliction, and they did not yet know why God was showing them disfavor through smallpox. Not to address their errant ways before attempting a cure could set them back in their &quot;errand&quot;. Many Puritans believed that creating a wound and inserting poison was doing violence and therefore was antithetical to the healing art. They grappled with adhering to the<space/><link><target>Ten Commandments</target></link>, with being proper church members and good caring neighbors. The apparent contradiction between harming or murdering a neighbor through inoculation and the Sixth Commandment &quot;thou shalt not kill&quot; seemed insoluble and hence stood as one of the main objections against the procedure. Williams maintained that because the subject of inoculation could not be found in the Bible, it was not the will of God, and therefore &quot;unlawful.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Williams 1721, p. 2</extension><space/>He explained that inoculation violated<space/><link><target>The Golden Rule</target></link>, because if one neighbor voluntarily infected another with disease, he was not doing unto others as he would have done to him. With the Bible as the Puritans' source for all decision-making, lack of scriptural evidence concerned many, and Williams vocally scorned Mather for not being able to reference an inoculation edict directly from the Bible.<extension extension_name='ref'>Williams 1721, p. 14</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Inoculation defended</heading><paragraph>With the smallpox epidemic catching speed and racking up a staggering death toll, a solution to the crisis was becoming more urgently needed by the day. The use of quarantine and various other efforts, such as balancing the body's<space/><link><target>humors</target></link>, did not slow the spread of the disease. As news rolled in from town to town and correspondence arrived from overseas, reports of horrific stories of suffering and loss due to smallpox stirred mass panic among the people. &quot;By circa 1700, smallpox had become among the most devastating of epidemic diseases circulating in the Atlantic world.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Gronim</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">248</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather strongly challenged the perception that inoculation was against the will of God and argued that the procedure was not outside of Puritan principles. He wrote that &quot;whether a Christian may not employ this Medicine (let the matter of it be what it will) and humbly give Thanks to God's good Providence in discovering of it to a miserable World; and humbly look up to His Good Providence (as we do in the use of any other Medicine) It may seem strange, that any wise Christian cannot answer it. And how strangely do Men that call themselves Physicians betray their Anatomy, and their Philosophy, as well as their Divinity in their invectives against this Practice?&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Mather</arg><arg>1721</arg><arg name="page">25, n. 15</arg></template><space/>The Puritan minister began to embrace the sentiment that smallpox was an inevitability for anyone, both the good and the wicked, yet God had provided them with the means to save themselves. Mather reported that, from his view, &quot;none that have used it ever died of the Small Pox, tho at the same time, it were so malignant, that at least half the People died, that were infected With it in the Common way.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Mather</arg><arg>1721</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While Mather was experimenting with the procedure, prominent Puritan pastors Benjamin Colman and William Cooper expressed public and theological support for them.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="last">Cooper</arg><arg name="title">A Letter from a Friend in the Country, Attempting a Solution of the Scruples and Objections of a Conscientious or Religious Nature, Commonly Made Against the New Way of Receiving the Small Pox</arg><arg name="place">Boston</arg><arg name="publisher">S. Kneeland</arg><arg name="year">1721</arg><arg name="pages">6–7</arg></template>. Apparently Cooper, also a minister, wrote this in cooperation with Colman because nearly the same response to the objections to inoculation is published under Colman's name as the last chapter to<space/><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Colman</arg><arg name="title">A Narrative of the Method and Success of Inoculating the Small Pox in New England</arg><arg name="year">1722</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The practice of smallpox inoculation was eventually accepted by the general population due to first-hand experiences and personal relationships. Although many were initially wary of the concept, it was because people were able to witness the procedure's consistently positive results, within their own community of ordinary citizens, that it became widely utilized and supported. One important change in the practice after 1721 was regulated quarantine of innoculees.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Van de Wetering</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="page"><space/>66, n. 55</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The aftermath</heading><paragraph>Although Mather and Boylston were able to demonstrate the efficacy of the practice, the debate over inoculation would continue even beyond the epidemic of 172122. After overcoming considerable difficulty and achieving notable success, Boylston traveled to<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>in 1725 where he published his results and was elected to the<space/><link><target>Royal Society</target></link><space/>in 1726.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Salem witch trials of 1692, The Mather Influence</heading><paragraph>Mather's contemporary critic,<space/><link><target>Robert Calef</target></link>, considered him responsible for laying the very groundwork that inspired the<space/><link><target>Salem witch trials</target></link>:<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Calef</arg><arg>1700</arg><arg name="p">152</arg></template><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Mr Cotton Mather was the most active and forward of any Minister in the Country in those matters [the Goodwin children and Goody Glover],{{Sfn|Hansen|1969}}{{Page needed|date">October 2015}} taking home one of the Children, and managing such intrigues with that Child, and after printing such an account of the whole, in his Memorable Provinces [published in 1689], as conduced much to the kindling of those Flames, that in Sir Williams time [i.e. Salem Witch Trials] threatened the devouring of this Country."<ref>{{Citation|last</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>Charles Wentworth Upham</target></link>, writing in 1869 says that both Mathers &quot;are answerable... more than almost any other... for the opinions of their time. It was indeed a superstitious age, but made much more so by their operations, influence, and writings, beginning with Increase Mather's movement at the assembly of Ministers in 1681, and ending with Cotton Mather's dealings with the Goodwin children, and the account thereof which he printed [1689] and circulated far and wide.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="upham"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first">Charles</arg><arg name="last">Upham</arg><arg name="title">Salem Witchcraft</arg><arg name="publisher">Frederick Ungar</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1859</arg><arg name="isbn">0-548-15034-6</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><space/>Upham refers to the afflicted in Salem as the &quot;imitators&quot; of the Goodwin children, whose family's conduct resulted in the hanging of Goodwife Ann Glover.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Upham</arg><arg>1869</arg><arg name="p">603</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather was influential in the construction of the court for the trials from the beginning. Sir<space/><link><target>William Phips</target></link>, governor of the newly chartered<space/><link><target>Province of Massachusetts Bay</target></link>, appointed his lieutenant governor,<space/><link><target>William Stoughton (Massachusetts)</target><part>William Stoughton</part></link>, as head of a special witchcraft tribunal and then as chief justice of the colonial courts, where he presided over the witch trials. According to George Bancroft, Mather had been influential in gaining the politically unpopular Stoughton his appointment as lieutenant governor under Phips through the intervention of Mather's own politically powerful father, Increase. &quot;Intercession had been made by Cotton Mather for the advancement of Stoughton, a man of cold affections, proud, self-willed and covetous of distinction.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Bancroft</arg><arg>1874–1878</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template><space/>Apparently Mather saw in Stoughton an ally for church-related matters. Bancroft quotes Mather's reaction to Stoughton's appointment as follows:<template><target>quote</target><arg name=""The time for a favor is come", exulted Cotton Mather; "Yea, the set time is come."{{Sfn|Bancroft|1874–1878|p">84}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather claimed not to have attended the trials in Salem (although his father attended the trial of<space/><link><target>George Burroughs</target></link>). Two contemporaries, Calef and<space/><link><target>Thomas Brattle</target></link>, place him at the executions (see below). Mather began to publicize and celebrate the trials well before they were put to an end: &quot;If in the midst of the many Dissatisfaction among us, the publication of these Trials may promote such a pious Thankfulness unto God, for Justice being so far executed among us, I shall Re-joyce that God is Glorified...&quot; Mather called himself a historian not an advocate, but his writing largely presumes the guilt of the accused and includes such venomous comments as calling Martha Carrier &quot;a rampant hag&quot;. Mather referred to George Burroughs -- a Harvard alumnus, survivor of Indian attacks in<space/><link><target>Maine</target></link>, and unordained minister hanged the same day as Martha Carrier, John Proctor, George Jacobs and John Willard -- as a &quot;very puny man&quot; whose &quot;tergiversations, contradictions, and falsehoods&quot; made his testimony not &quot;worth considering&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stacy Schiff. &quot;The Witches of Salem: Diabolical doings in a Puritan village&quot;,<space/><italics>The New Yorker</italics>, September 7, 2015, pp. 46-55.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">[[Wonders of the Invisible World]]</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Use of spectral evidence</heading><paragraph>Mather's most fatal influence over the trials was in composing the answer to the question of whether or not to allow<space/><link><target>spectral evidence</target></link>, that is, allowing the afflicted girls to claim that some invisible ghost of the defendant was tormenting them, and for this to be considered evidence of witchcraft by the defendant, even if the defendant denied it and professed their own strongly held Christian beliefs. An opinion on the matter was sought from the most esteemed ministers of the area and Mather took credit for their response when anonymously celebrating himself years later: &quot;drawn up at their desire, by Cotton Mather the younger, as I have been informed.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">The Life of Sir [[William Phips]]</arg><arg name="author">Anonymous</arg><arg name="place">London</arg><arg name="year">1697</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On May 31, 1692, Mather wrote to one of the judges,<space/><link><target>John Richards (colonial judge)</target><part>John Richards</part></link>, a member of his congregation,<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Upham</arg><arg>1869</arg></template><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><space/>expressing his support of the prosecutions, but cautioning; &quot;do not lay more stress on pure<space/><link><target>spectral evidence</target></link><space/>than it will bear ... It is very certain that the Devils have sometimes represented the Shapes of persons not only innocent, but also very virtuous. Though I believe that the just God then ordinarily provides a way for the speedy vindication of the persons thus abused.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="silverman"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Selected Letters</arg><arg name="first">Cotton</arg><arg name="last">Mather</arg><arg name="editor-first">Kenneth</arg><arg name="editor-last">Silverman</arg><arg name="year">1971</arg><arg name="publisher">Louisiana State University Press</arg><arg name="place">Baton Rouge, Louisiana</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8071-0920-7</arg><arg name="pages">35–40</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 24, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Hutchinson (governor)</target><part>Hutchinson</part></link><space/>sums the letter, &quot;The two first and the last sections of this advice took away the force of all the others, and the prosecutions went on with more vigor than before.&quot; (Reprinting the letter years later in<space/><italics>Magnalia</italics>, Mather notably omitted the fateful &quot;two first and the last&quot; sections.) The original full version of the letter, called<space/><italics>Return of the Several Ministers</italics>, was dated June 15, 1692, and had been reprinted in late 1692 in the final two pages of<space/><link><target>Increase Mather</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Cases of Conscience</italics>. It is a curious document and remains a source of confusion and argument. Calef calls it &quot;perfectly Ambidexter, giving as great as greater Encouragement to proceed in those dark methods, then cautions against them... indeed the Advice then given, looks most like a thing of his Composing, as carrying both Fire to increase and Water to quench the Conflagration.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Upham</arg><arg>1859</arg></template><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Regarding spectral evidence, Upham concludes that &quot;Cotton Mather never in any public writing 'denounced the admission' of it, never advised its absolute exclusion; but on the contrary recognized it as a ground of 'presumption' ... [and once admitted] nothing could stand against it. Character, reason, common sense, were swept away.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="upham"></extension><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>The S.G. [Salem Gentlemen] will by no means allow, that any are brought in guilty, and condemned, by virtue of spectre Evidence... but whether it is not purely by virtue of these spectre evidences, that these persons are found guilty, (considering what before has been said,) I leave you, and any man of sense, to judge and determine.</arg><arg name="[[Thomas Brattle]], October 8, 1692.<ref name">"georgelburr">{{cite book|last</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The later rejection of spectral evidence by Governor Phips and its exclusion from trial beginning in January 1693 resulted in no convictions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="upham"></extension><space/>Bancroft notes that Mather considered witches &quot;among the poor, and vile, and ragged beggars upon Earth&quot;,<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Bancroft</arg><arg>1874–1878</arg><arg name="p">85</arg></template><space/>and Bancroft asserts that Mather considered the people against the witch trials to be witch advocates.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Bancroft</arg><arg>1874–1878</arg><arg name="p">85</arg></template><space/>Calef places Mather at the scene of the execution of George Burroughs (and four others who were executed after Mather spoke) and shows him playing a direct and influential role:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Mr. Buroughs (sic) was carried in a Cart with others, through the streets of Salem, to Execution. When he was upon the Ladder, he made a speech for the clearing of his Innocency, with such Solemn and Serious Expressions as were to the Admiration of all present; his Prayer (which he concluded by repeating the Lord's Prayer) [as witches were not supposed to be able to recite] was so well worded, and uttered with such composedness as such fervency of spirit, as was very Affecting, and drew Tears from many, so that if seemed to some that the spectators would hinder the execution. The accusers said the black Man [Devil] stood and dictated to him. As soon as he was turned off [hung], Mr. Cotton Mather, being mounted upon a Horse, addressed himself to the People, partly to declare that he [Mr. Burroughs] was no ordained Minister, partly to possess the People of his guilt, saying that the devil often had been transformed into the Angel of Light. And this did somewhat appease the People, and the Executions went on; when he [Mr. Burroughs] was cut down, he was dragged by a Halter to a Hole, or Grave, between the Rocks, about two feet deep; his Shirt and Breeches being pulled off, and an old pair of Trousers of one Executed put on his lower parts: he was so put in, together with [John] Willard and [Martha] Carrier, that one of his Hands, and his Chin, and a Foot of one of them, was left uncovered.</arg><arg>Robert Calef</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Post-trial</heading><paragraph>In the years after the trials, of the principal actors in the trial, whose lives are recorded after, neither he nor<space/><link><target>William Stoughton (Massachusetts)</target><part>William Stoughton</part></link><space/>admitted to any misgivings.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Bancroft</arg><arg>1874–1878</arg><arg name="p">98</arg></template><space/>In the years after the trials, he became an increasingly vehement defender of them. At the request of then Lt.-Gov. Stoughton, Mather wrote<space/><italics><link><target>Wonders of the Invisible World</target></link></italics><space/>during the trials, which were published in 1693.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Babette</arg><arg name="last">Levy</arg><arg name="title">Cotton Mather</arg><arg name="publisher">Twayne</arg><arg name="location">Boston</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8057-7261-8</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>67</arg></template><space/>The book contained a few of Mather's sermons, the conditions of the colony and a description of witch trials in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref' name="craker"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first">Wendel D.</arg><arg name="last">Craker</arg><arg name="title">Spectral Evidence, Non-Spectral acts of Witchcraft, and Confessions at Salem in 1692</arg><arg name="journal">The Historical Journal</arg><arg name="volume">40</arg><arg name="number">2</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>335</arg></template><space/>He somewhat clarified the contradictory advice he had given in<space/><italics>Return of the Several Ministers</italics>, by defending the use of spectral evidence.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template><space/><italics>Wonders of the Invisible World</italics><space/>appeared at the same time as Increase Mather's ''Cases of Conscience.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Breslaw</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">455</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather did not sign his name or support his father's book initially:<template><target>Quote</target><arg name="There are fourteen worthy ministers that have newly set their hands unto a book now in the press, containing Cases of Conscience about Witchcraft. I did, in my Conscience think, that as the humors of this people now run, such a discourse going alone would not only enable the witch-advocates, very learnedly to cavil and nibble at the late proceedings against the witches, considered in parcels, while things as they lay in bulk, with their whole dependencies, were not exposed; but also everlastingly stifle any further proceedings of justice & more than so produce a public & open contest with the judges who would (tho beyond the intention of the worthy author & subscribers) find themselves brought unto the before the rashest mobile [mob] — October 20, 1692 letter to his uncle John Cotton.<ref>{{Citation|last">Holmes|first</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The last event in Mather's involvement with witchcraft was his attempt to cure Mercy Short and Margaret Rule.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Lovelace</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">202</arg></template><space/>Boston merchant<space/><link><target>Robert Calef</target></link><space/>began his eight-year campaign against the influential Mathers.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Breslaw</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="rp">455</arg></template><space/>Calef's book was inspired by the fear that Mather would succeed in once again stirring up new witchcraft trials, and the need to bear witness to the horrible experiences of 1692. He quotes the public apologies of the men on the jury and one of the judges. Upon reading Calef's<space/><italics>More Wonders of the Invisible World</italics>,<space/><link><target>Increase Mather</target></link>, Cotton's father, publicly burned the book in Harvard Yard.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Lovelace</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">22</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>19th Century Revision of Cotton Mather, Poole vs. Upham</heading><paragraph>In 1869,<space/><link><target>William Frederick Poole</target></link><space/>quoted from various school textbooks of the time demonstrating they were in agreement on Cotton Mather's role in the Witch Trials:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="If anyone imagines that we are stating the case too strongly, let him try an experiment with the first bright boy he meets by asking,...

'Who got up Salem Witchcraft?'... he will reply, 'Cotton Mather'. Let him try another boy...

'Who was Cotton Mather?' and the answer will come, 'The man who was on horseback, and hung witches.'<ref>{{cite book|last">Poole|first</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Poole was a librarian, and a lover of literature, including Mather's<space/><italics>Magnalia</italics><space/>&quot;and other books and tracts, numbering nearly 400 [which] were never so prized by collectors as today.&quot; Poole announced his intention to redeem Mather's name, using as a springboard a harsh critique of a recently published tome by<space/><link><target>Charles Wentworth Upham</target></link>,<space/><italics>Salem Witchcraft Volumes I and II With an Account of Salem Village and a History of Opinions on Witchcraft and Kindred Subjects</italics>, which runs to almost 1,000 pages, and a quick search of the name Mather (referring to either father, son, or ancestors) shows that it occurs 96 times. Poole's critique, in book form, runs less than 70 pages but the name &quot;Mather&quot; occurs many more times than the other book, which is more than ten times as long. Upham shows a balanced and complicated view of Cotton Mather, such as this first mention: &quot;One of Cotton Mather's most characteristic productions is the tribute to his venerated master. It flows from a heart warm with gratitude.&quot; Upham's book refers to<space/><link><target>Robert Calef</target></link><space/>no fewer than 25 times with the majority of these regarding documents compiled by Calef in the mid-1690s and stating: &quot;Although zealously devoted to the work of exposing the enormities connected with the witchcraft prosecutions, there is no ground to dispute the veracity of Calef as to matters of fact.&quot; He goes on to say that Calef's collection of writings &quot;gave a shock to Mather's influence, from which it never recovered.&quot;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Calef produced only the one book; he is self-effacing and apologetic for his limitations, and on the title page he is listed not as author but &quot;collector&quot;. Poole, champion of literature, cannot accept Calef whose &quot;faculties, as indicated by his writings appear to us to have been of an inferior order;...&quot; and his book &quot;in our opinon, has a reputation much beyond its merits.&quot; Poole refers to Calef as Mather's &quot;personal enemy&quot; and opens a line, &quot;Without discussing the character and motives of Calef...&quot; but does not follow up on this suggestive comment to discuss any actual or purported motive or reason to impune Calef. Upham responded to Poole in a book running five times as long and sharing the same title (referring to Poole as &quot;the Reviewer.&quot;) Many of Poole's arguments were addressed, but both authors emphasize the importance of Cotton Mather's difficult and contradictory view on spectral evidence, as copied in the final pages, called &quot;The Return of Several Ministers&quot;, of Increase Mather's &quot;Cases of Conscience&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://etext.virginia.edu/salem/witchcraft/speccol/mather/mather.html</arg><arg name="title">Witchcraft</arg><arg name="last">Mather</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Virginia</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1914, historian<space/><link><target>George Lincoln Burr</target></link><space/>sided with Upham in a note on<space/><link><target>Thomas Brattle</target></link>'s letter, &quot;The strange suggestion of W. F. Poole that Brattle here means Cotton Mather himself, is adequately answered by Upham...&quot; Burr reprinted Calef in full and dug deep into the historical record for information on the man and concludes &quot;...that he had else any grievance against the Mathers or their colleagues there is no reason to think.&quot; Burr finds that a comparison between Calef's work and original documents in the historical record collections &quot;testify to the care and exactness...&quot;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>20th century and ongoing revision</heading><paragraph>Poole's views have found followers and the revision of Cotton Mather continues, while<space/><link><target>Robert Calef</target></link>'s book is arguably less well-known. Chadwick Hansen's<space/><italics>Witchcraft at Salem</italics>, published in 1969, defined Mather as a positive influence on the Salem Trials. Hansen considered Mather's handling of the Goodwin children to be sane and temperate.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">168</arg></template><space/>Hansen posited that Mather was more concerned with helping the affected children than witch-hunting.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">60</arg></template><space/>Mather treated the affected children through prayer and fasting.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">24</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mather tried to convert<space/><link><target>Ann Glover</target><part>Goodwife Glover</part></link>, a Catholic, before she was executed, accused of practicing witchcraft on the Goodwin children.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">24</arg></template><space/>Hansen claimed Mather acted as a moderating influence in the trials by opposing the death penalty for those who confessed or feigned confession such as Tituba and Dorcas Good.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">23</arg></template><space/>Calef's observation of Mather's dealings with Margaret Rule suggested Mather's motivation for keeping quiet was blackmail, with Mather perceived as drawing information from her through leading questions, and possibly having a prurient interest in his intimate dealings with &quot;afflicted&quot; young women. Hansen claims that most negative impressions of Mather stem from his defense of the ongoing trials in<space/><italics>Wonders of the Invisible World</italics>. After some others had lamented the roles they played in the executions and imprisonments, Mather and Stoughton remained the chief defenders of the trials, which diminishes the view of him as a moderate influence.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Hansen</arg><arg>1969</arg><arg name="p">189</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Historian Larry Gragg highlights Mather's cloudy thinking and confusion between sympathy for the possessed, and the boundlessness of spectral evidence when Mather stated, &quot;the devil have sometimes represented the shapes of persons not only innocent, but also the very virtuous.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Larry</arg><arg name="last">Gregg</arg><arg name="title">The Salem Witch Crisis</arg><arg name="publisher">Praeger</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>88</arg></template><space/>Writing in the early 1980s, historian John Demos imputed to Mather a purportedly moderating influence on the trials.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="last">Demos</arg><arg name="title">Entertaining Satan: Witchcraft and the Culture of Early New England</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-503131-8</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>305</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Major</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Boston Ephermeris&quot; (1686)</listitem><listitem><italics>Ornaments for the Daughters of Zion</italics><space/>(1692)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/19'>''Wonders of the Invisible World''</link><space/>(1693)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Biblia Americana</italics><space/>(16931728)</listitem><listitem><italics>Decennium Luctuosom: a History of the Long War</italics><space/>(1699)</listitem><listitem><italics>Pillars of Salt</italics><space/>(1699)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://archive.org/details/magnaliachristi03robbgoog'>''Magnalia Christi Americana''</link><space/>(1702)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/28'>''The Negro Christianized''</link><space/>(1706)</listitem><listitem>''<link type='external' href='http://archive.org/details/corderiusameric00mathgoog'>Corderius Americanus: A Discourse on the Good Education of Children''</link><space/>(1708)</listitem><listitem><italics>Bonifacius</italics><space/>(1710)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/29'>''Theopolis Americana: An Essay on the Golden Street of the Holy City''</link><space/>(1710)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Christian Philosopher</italics><space/>(1721)</listitem><listitem><italics>Manductio ad Ministerium</italics><space/>(1726)</listitem></list><heading level='3'><italics>Boston Ephemeris</italics></heading><paragraph>The Boston Ephemeris was an<space/><link><target>almanac</target></link><space/>written by Mather in 1686. The content was similar to what is known today as the<space/><italics><link><target>Farmer's Almanac</target></link></italics>. This was particularly important because it shows that Cotton Mather had influence in mathematics during the time of Puritan New England. This almanac contained a significant amount of astronomy, celestial within the text of the almanac the positions and motions of these celestial bodies, which he must have calculated by hand.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Burdick<space/></arg><arg><space/>2009</arg></template><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>The Biblia Americana</italics></heading><paragraph>When Mather died, he left behind an abundance of unfinished writings, including one entitled<space/><italics>The Biblia Americana</italics>. Mather believed that<space/><italics>Biblia Americana</italics><space/>was the best thing he had ever written; his masterwork.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Hovey<space/></arg><arg><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>533</arg></template><space/><italics>Biblia Americana</italics><space/>contained Cotton Mather's thoughts and opinions on the Bible and how he interpreted it.<space/><italics>Biblia Americana</italics><space/>is incredibly large, and Mather worked on it from 1693 until 1728, when he died. Mather tried to convince others that philosophy and science could work together with religion instead of against it. People did not have to choose one or the other, and in<space/><italics>Biblia Americana</italics><space/>Mather looked at the Bible through a scientific perspective, completely opposite to his perspective in<space/><italics>The Christian Philosopher</italics>, in which he approached science in a religious manner.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Smolinski<space/></arg><arg><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="pp"><space/>280–81</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Pillars of Salt</italics></heading><paragraph>The Puritan execution sermon, preached on the occasion of a public hanging, then quickly printed up in pamphlet form and sold for a few pence, was an early form of true-crime literature. Mather's first published sermon, which appeared in 1686, concerned the crime and punishment of James Morgan, a reprobate who in a drunken rage impaled a man with an iron spit. Thirteen years later, following the execution of a Boston woman named Sarah Threeneedles for killing her baby, Mather issued<space/><italics>Pillars of Salt</italics>. This compilation of a dozen accounts (half of which, including the case of Morgan, had been previously published) stands as a landmark work, a Puritan precursor of the true-crime miscellanies that, stripped of all religious intent, would become a staple of the genre in subsequent centuries. In 2008,<space/><link><target>The Library of America</target></link><space/>reprinted the entirety of<space/><italics>Pillars of Salt</italics><space/>in its two-century retrospective of American True Crime.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mather<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cotton<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>etal<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Library of America<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>True Crime: An American Anthology<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59853-031-5</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.loa.org/volume.jsp?RequestID</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Magnalia Christi Americana</italics></heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>Magnalia Christi Americana</target></link></italics>, considered Mather's greatest work, was published in 1702, when he was 39. The book includes several biographies of saints<template><target>Vague</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><space/>and describes the process of the New England settlement.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Meyers<space/></arg><arg><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="pp"><space/>23–24</arg></template><space/>In this context &quot;saints&quot; does not refer to the canonized saints of the Catholic church, but to those Puritan divines about whom Mather is writing. It comprises seven total books, including<space/><italics>Pietas in Patriam: The life of His Excellency Sir William Phips</italics>, originally published anonymously in London in 1697. Despite being one of Mather's best-known works, many have openly criticized it<template><target>By whom</target><arg name="date"><space/>March 2010</arg></template>, labeling it as hard to follow and understand, and poorly paced and organized. However, other critics have praised Mather's work, citing it as one of the best efforts at properly documenting the establishment of America and growth of the people.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Halttunen<space/></arg><arg><space/>1978<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>311</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>The Christian Philosopher</italics></heading><paragraph>In 1721, Mather published<space/><italics>The Christian Philosopher</italics>, the first systematic book on science published in America. Mather attempted to show how Newtonian science and religion were in harmony. It was in part based on Robert Boyle's<space/><italics>The Christian Virtuoso</italics><space/>(1690). Mather reportedly took inspiration from<space/><italics><link><target>Hayy ibn Yaqdhan</target></link></italics>, by the 12th-century Islamic philosopher Abu Bakr<space/><link><target>Ibn Tufail</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite condemning the &quot;Mahometans&quot; as infidels, Mather viewed the novel's protagonist, Hayy, as a model for his ideal Christian philosopher and monotheistic scientist. Mather viewed Hayy as a<space/><link><target>noble savage</target></link><space/>and applied this in the context of attempting to understand the Native American Indians, in order to convert them to Puritan Christianity. Mather's short treatise on the<space/><link><target>Lord's Supper</target></link><space/>was later translated by his nephew<space/><link><target>Josiah Cotton</target></link><space/>in the Massachusett.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="publisher">To every tribe</arg><arg name="work">Josiah Cotton</arg><arg name="title">Thanksgiving's Wampanoag call: Come Over and Help Us!</arg><arg name="url">http://www.toeverytribe.org/tag/josiah-cotton</arg><arg name="accessdate">September 13, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Minor works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mather<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cotton<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Cotton Mather<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1689<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Family, Well-Ordered</arg></template>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph>Cotton Mather is played by<space/><link><target>Seth Gabel</target></link><space/>(as &quot;Reverend Cotton Mather&quot;) in the 2014 TV series<space/><italics><link><target>Salem (TV series)</target><part>Salem</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Calvinism</arg><arg>Biography</arg></template><template><target>Portal</target><arg>United States</arg><arg>Massachusetts</arg><arg>North America</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>John Ratcliff</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Aronson<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Stanley M<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Lucile<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Newman<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.brown.edu/Administration/News_Bureau/2002-03/02-017t.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>God Have Mercy on This House: Being a Brief Chronicle of Smallpox in Colonial New England<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Brown University]] News Service</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first">George<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Bancroft<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>History of the United States of America, from the discovery of the American continent<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Little, Brown, & co<space/></arg><arg name="location">Boston</arg><arg name="date">1874–1878<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-665-61404-7</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bercovitch<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Sacvan<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Cotton Mather<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Major Writers of Early American Literature<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Everett<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Emerson<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Wisconsin<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Wisconsin Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1972</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Blake<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John B<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>December 1952<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Inoculation Controversy in Boston: 1721–1722<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The New England Quarterly<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>25<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>489–506</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Boylston, Zabdiel.<space/><italics>An Historical Account of the Small-pox Inoculated in New England</italics>. London: S. Chandler, 1726.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Breslaw<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Elaine G<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Witches of the Atlantic World: A Historical Reader & Primary Sourcebook</arg><arg name="publisher">New York University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8147-9850-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Burdick</arg><arg name="first">Bruce</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Mathematical Works Printed in the Americas 1554–1700<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Johns Hopkins Press</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Baltimore, MD</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8018-8823-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Calef<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert<space/></arg><arg name="year">1700</arg><arg name="title"><space/>More Wonders of the Invisible World<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Nath Hillar on London Bridge<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London, [[England|ENG]], [[United Kingdom|UK]]</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Douglass<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>William<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1722<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Abuses and Scandals of Some Late Pamphlets in Favor of Inoculation of the Small Pox<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>J. Franklin</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Felker, Christopher D.<space/><italics>Reinventing Cotton Mather in the American Renaissance:<space/></italics>Magnalia Christi Americana<italics><space/>in Hawthorne, Stowe, and Stoddard</italics><space/>(Boston: Northeastern University Press, 1993); ISBN 1-55553-187-3</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gronim<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Sara Stidstone<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Imagining Inoculation: Smallpox, the Body, and Social Relations of Healing in the Eighteenth Century<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Bulletin of the History of Medicine<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>80<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>247–68</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Halttunen<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Karen<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1978<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/27553427<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cotton Mather and the Meaning of Suffering in the ''Magnalia Christi Americana<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Journal of American Studies]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>12<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>311–29</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hansen</arg><arg name="first">Chadwick<space/></arg><arg name="year">1969</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Witchcraft at Salem</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>George Braziller<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-451-61947-1</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hovey<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kenneth Alan<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Cotton Mather: 1663–1728<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heath Anthology of American Literature<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>A<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Lauter<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Houghton Mifflin Harcourt<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>531–33</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kennedy<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rick<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2015<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The First American Evangelical: A Short Life of Cotton Mather<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans</arg></template>, xiv, 162 pp.<space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lovelace<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard F<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The American Pietism of Cotton Mather: Origins of American Evangelicalism<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Grand Rapids, [[Michigan|MC]]; Washington, DC<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>American University Press; Christian College Consortium<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1979<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-8028-1750-5</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mather<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cotton<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1911–1912<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Cotton Mather<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Diary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Massachusetts Historical Society<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Collections<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>vii<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>vii–viii</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mather<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cotton<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Smolinski<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Reiner<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Threefold Paradise of Cotton Mather: An Edition of 'Triparadisus'<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Athens and London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Georgia Press<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-8203-1519-2<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/48/<space/></arg><arg name="author-mask"><space/>3</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mather<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cotton<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="author-mask"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Smolinski<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Reiner<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Biblia Americana<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1: Genesis<space/></arg><arg name="type"><space/>edited, with an introduction and annotations<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Grand Rapids and Tuebingen<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Baker Academic and Mohr Siebeck<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0-8010-3900-3</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Increase Mather</target><part>Mather, Increase</part></link><space/>(1692)<space/><link type='external' href='http://salem.lib.virginia.edu/speccol/mather/mather.html'>Cases of Conscience</link><space/>from<space/><link><target>University of Virginia</target></link><space/>Special Collections Library.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Meyers<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Karen<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Colonialism and the Revolutionary Period (Beginning–1800): American Literature in its Historical, Cultural, and Social Contexts<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>DWJ<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>New York</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Middlekauff</target><part>Middlekauff, Robert</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Mathers: Three Generations of Puritan Intellectuals, 15961728</italics>, ISBN 0-520-21930-9</listitem><listitem><link><target>E. Jennifer Monaghan</target><part>Monaghan, E. Jennifer</part></link><space/>(2005,7)<space/><italics>Learning to Read and Write in Colonial America</italics>; ISBN 978-1-55849-581-4</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Montagu<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mary Wortley<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Letters of the Right Honourable Lady M—y W—y M—e<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>3 vols<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>T. Becket and P.A. de Hondt<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1763</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Silverman, Kenneth.<space/><italics>The Life and Times of Cotton Mather</italics>; ISBN 1-56649-206-8</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smolinski<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Reiner<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Authority and Interpretation: Cotton Mather's Response to the European Spinozists<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Shaping the Stuart World, 1603–1714: The Atlantic Connection<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Arthur<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Williamson<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Allan<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>MacInnes<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Leyden<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Brill<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>175–203</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smolinski<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Reiner<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>November 3, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="author-mask"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How to Go to Heaven, or How to Heaven Goes? Natural Science and Interpretation in Cotton Mather's ''Biblia Americana'' (1693–1728)<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The New England Quarterly<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>81<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>278–329<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>MIT Press Journals, Longwood University Library<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Farmville, VA</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Upham<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles Wentworth<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1859<space/></arg><arg name="title">Salem Witchcraft</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Frederick Ungar<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-548-15034-6</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Upham<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles Wentworth<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1869<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26978/26978-h/26978-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Salem Witchcraft and Cotton Mather, A Reply<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>[[Morrisania, Bronx]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Project Gutenberg]]<space/></arg><arg name="author-mask"><space/>3</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Van De Wetering<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Maxine<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Reconsideration of the Inoculation Controversy<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The New England Quarterly<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>58<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>March 1985<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>46–67</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Wendell<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Barrett<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1891<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Barrett Wendell</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cotton Mather, the Puritan priest<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Dodd, Mead & co</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>White<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Andrew<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.todayinsci.com/B/Boylston_Zabdiel/Boylston_Zabdiel.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Zabdiel Boylston and Innoculation<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Today In Science History</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1721<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Several Arguments Proving that Inoculating the Smallpox is not Contained in the Law of Physick<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>J. Franklin</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Winslow<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ola Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Destroying Angel: The Conquest of Smallpox in Colonial Boston<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Houghton Mifflin<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1974</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Zirkle<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Conway<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015011424788<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The beginnings of plant hybridization<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Philadelphia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Pennsylvania Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1935</arg></template>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource author</target><arg>Cotton Mather</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Cotton Mather</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target><arg>Cotton Mather</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Mather,+Cotton</arg><arg name="name">Cotton Mather</arg></template><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/26978'>Salem Witchcraft and Cotton Mather by Charles Wentworth Upham at Project Gutenberg</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Cotton Mather</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gty.org/~phil/mather.htm'>Cotton Mather's writings</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://collegiateway.org/mather/'>Mather's influential commentary</link>, collegiateway.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/19'>''The Wonders of the Invisible World'' (1693 edition) in [[PDF</link>] format]</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/48'>''The Threefold Paradise of Cotton Mather: An Edition of &quot;Triparadisus&quot;''</link><space/>(PDF format)</listitem><listitem>Cotton Mather's &quot;~Resolved~&quot;,<space/><link type='external' href='http://neprimer.com/FathersLessonPlans.html'>''A Puritan Father's Lesson Plan''</link>, neprimer.com</listitem><listitem>Cotton Mather's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/400/prose/206.html'>&quot;The Story of Margaret Rule&quot;</link>, bartleby.com</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>salem</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Mather, Cotton</target></template><link><target>Category:1663 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1728 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century American writers</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century American writers</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Christian clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century Christian clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Calvinist and Reformed theologians</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century Calvinist and Reformed theologians</target></link><link><target>Category:Alumni of the University of Glasgow</target></link><link><target>Category:American colonial clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of English descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American religious writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American sermon writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American Calvinist and Reformed theologians</target></link><link><target>Category:Apocalypticists</target></link><link><target>Category:Demonologists</target></link><link><target>Category:Fellows of the Royal Society</target></link><link><target>Category:Harvard University alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:History of religion in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Massachusetts colonial-era clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century New England Puritan ministers</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century New England Puritan ministers</target></link><link><target>Category:People from colonial Boston, Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:People from North End, Boston</target></link><link><target>Category:People of the Salem witch trials</target></link><link><target>Category:Critics of the Catholic Church</target></link><link><target>Category:Boston Latin School alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Yale University</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials in Boston, Massachusetts</target></link></paragraph></article>