<article title='Assault'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the criminal act</arg><arg>tortious aspects of assault</arg><arg>Assault (tort)</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Assault (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Assailants</arg><arg>the EP by Lydia</arg><arg>Assailants (EP)</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Criminal law</target></template>In<space/><link><target>common law</target></link>,<space/><bold>assault</bold><space/>is harmful or offensive contact with a person.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Definition of Assault</arg><arg name="url">http://www.duhaime.org/LegalDictionary/A/Assault.aspx</arg><arg name="work">Duhaime Legal Dictionary</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 December 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An assault is carried out by a threat of bodily harm coupled with an apparent, present ability to cause the harm. It is both a crime and a tort and, therefore, may result in either criminal and/or civil liability. Generally, the common law definition is the same in criminal and tort law. There is, however, an additional criminal law category of assault consisting of an attempted but unsuccessful battery. The term is often confused with<space/><link><target>Battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>, which involves physical contact. The specific meaning of assault varies between countries, but can refer to an act that causes another to apprehend immediate and personal violence, or in the more limited sense of a threat of violence caused by an immediate show of force.<extension extension_name='ref'>Arkansas Code, Title 5, Chapter 13, Subchapter 2, 205207</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>California Penal Code, Part 1, Chapter 9, 240</extension><space/>Assault in many US jurisdictions<template><target>Which</target><arg name="date">July 2011</arg></template><space/>and<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link><space/>is defined more broadly still as any intentional physical contact with another person without their consent; but in<space/><link><target>England and Wales</target></link><space/>and in most<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><space/>other<space/><link><target>common law</target></link><space/>jurisdictions in the world, this is defined instead as<space/><link><target>battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>. Some jurisdictions have incorporated the definition of civil assault into the definition of the crime making it a criminal assault intentionally to cause another person to apprehend a harmful or offensive contact.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Related definitions</heading><heading level='3'>Battery</heading><paragraph>In common law, criminal assault often accompanies<space/><link><target>Battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>. See<space/><link><target>common assault</target></link>. The elements of battery are (1) a volitional act<extension extension_name='ref'>An act is volitional if it is purposeful and deliberate as opposed to reflexive or involuntary (see Dennis J. Baker, Glanville Williams,<space/><italics>Textbook of Criminal Law</italics><space/>(London, Sweet &amp; Maxwell 2012) at p 901. For example. a person who has restless leg syndrome kicks his wife while asleep. The contact, although, harmful, would not constitute battery because the act was not wilful.</extension><space/>(2) done for the purpose of causing a harmful or offensive contact with another person or under circumstances that make such contact substantially certain to occur and (3) which causes such contact.<extension extension_name='ref'>A criminal battery may also be committed if the harmful or offensive contact is due to the criminal negligence of the defendant.</extension><space/>Thus throwing a rock at someone for the purpose of hitting him is a battery if the rock in fact strikes the person, and is an assault if the rock misses.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aggravated assault</heading><paragraph><link><target>Aggravation (legal concept)</target><part>Aggravated</part></link><space/>assault is, in some jurisdictions, a stronger form of assault, usually using a<space/><link><target>deadly weapon</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Crime in the United States 2010: Aggravated Assault<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Federal Bureau of Investigation]]<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/crime-in-the-u.s/2010/crime-in-the-u.s.-2010/violent-crime/aggravatedassaultmain</arg></template></extension><space/>A person has committed an aggravated assault when that person attempts to:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>cause serious bodily injury to another person with a deadly weapon<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Baker</arg><arg name="first">Dennis</arg><arg name="last2">William</arg><arg name="first2">Glanville</arg><arg name="title">Textbook of Criminal Law</arg><arg name="publisher">London, Sweet & Maxwell</arg><arg name="chapter">9</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>cause<space/><link><target>grievous bodily harm</target></link><space/>to another person, such as rape or kidnapping</listitem><listitem>have sexual relations with a person who is under the age of consent</listitem><listitem>cause bodily harm by recklessly operating a<space/><link><target>motor vehicle</target></link>; often referred to as either<space/><bold>vehicular assault</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>aggravated assault with a motor vehicle.</bold></listitem></list><paragraph>Aggravated assault can also be charged in cases of attempted harm against police officers or other public servants.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Defenses</heading><paragraph>Although the range and precise application of defenses varies between jurisdictions, the following represents a list of the defenses that may apply to all levels of assault:</paragraph><heading level='3'>Consent</heading><paragraph>Exceptions exist to cover unsolicited physical contact which amount to normal social behavior known as<space/><link><target>de minimis</target></link><space/>harm. Assault can also be considered in cases involving the spitting on, or unwanted exposure of bodily fluids to others.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>consent (criminal law)</target><part>Consent</part></link><space/>may be a complete or partial defense to assault. In some jurisdictions, most notably England, it is not a defense where the degree of injury is severe, as long as there is no legally recognized good reason for the assault.<extension extension_name='ref'>(RvG ref 6. 1980): see<space/><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20071016125514<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://lawteacher.net/Criminal/Non+Fatal+Assaults/Consent+R+v+Brown.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">R v Brown (1993) 2 All ER 75</arg></template></extension><space/>This can have important consequences when dealing with issues such as consensual<space/><link><target>sadomasochism</target><part>sadomasochistic sexual activity</part></link>, the most notable case being the<space/><link><target>Operation Spanner</target></link><space/>case. Legally recognized good reasons for consent include surgery, activities within the rules of a game (<link><target>Mixed martial arts</target></link>,<space/><link><target>wrestling</target></link>,<space/><link><target>boxing</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>contact sports</target></link>), bodily adornment (R v Wilson), or horseplay (Jones and others). However, any activity outside the rules of the game is not legally recognized as a defense of consent. In Scottish Law, consent is not a defense for assault.<link type='external' href='http://www.bailii.org/scot/cases/ScotHC/1975/1975_JC_30.html'></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Arrest and other official acts</heading><paragraph><link><target>Police officers</target></link><space/>and court officials have a general power to use force for the purpose of performing an<space/><link><target>arrest</target></link><space/>or generally carrying out their official duties. Thus, a court officer taking possession of goods under a court order may use force if reasonably necessary.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Punishment</heading><paragraph>In some jurisdictions such as<space/><link><target>Caning in Singapore</target><part>Singapore</part></link>,<space/><link><target>judicial corporal punishment</target></link><space/>is part of the<space/><link><target>legal system</target></link>. The officers who administer the punishment have<space/><link><target>Sovereign immunity</target><part>immunity</part></link><space/>from prosecution for assault.</paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, the United Kingdom, Australia and Canada,<space/><link><target>Corporal punishment in the home#Where corporal punishment in the home is lawful</target><part>corporal punishment administered to children by their parent or legal guardian</part></link><space/>is not legally considered to be assault unless it is deemed to be excessive or unreasonable. What constitutes &quot;reasonable&quot; varies in both statutory law and<space/><link><target>case law</target></link>. Unreasonable physical punishment may be charged as assault or under a separate statute for<space/><link><target>child abuse</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Many countries, including some US states, also permit the use of less severe corporal punishment for<space/><link><target>School corporal punishment</target><part>children in school</part></link>. In<space/><link><target>English law</target></link>, s58<space/><link><target>Children Act 2004</target></link>, limits the availability of the lawful correction defense to common assault under s39<space/><link><target>Criminal Justice Act 1988</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Prevention of crime</heading><paragraph>This may or may not involve self-defense in that, using a reasonable degree of force to prevent another from committing a crime could involve preventing an assault, but it could be preventing a crime not involving the use of personal violence.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Defense of property</heading><paragraph>Some jurisdictions allow force to be used in<space/><link><target>defense of property</target></link>, to prevent damage either in its own right, or under one or both of the preceding classes of defense in that a threat or attempt to damage property might be considered a crime (in English law, under s5<space/><link><target>Criminal Damage Act 1971</target></link><space/>it may be argued that the defendant has a<space/><italics>lawful excuse</italics><space/>to damaging property during the defense and a defense under s3<space/><link><target>Criminal Law Act 1967</target></link>) subject to the need to deter<space/><link><target>vigilante</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and excessive self-help. Furthermore, some jurisdictions, such as Ohio, allow residents in their homes to use force when ejecting an intruder. The resident merely needs to assert to the court that he felt threatened by the intruder's presence.</paragraph><paragraph>This defense is not universal: in New Zealand (for example) homeowners have been convicted of assault for attacking burglars.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Regional details</heading><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph>Assault is an offence under s. 265 of the Canadian<space/><link><target>Criminal Code (Canada)</target><part>Criminal Code</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.canlii.org/en/ca/laws/stat/rsc-1985-c-c-46/latest/rsc-1985-c-c-46.html</arg><arg name="title">CanLII - Criminal Code, RSC 1985, c C-46</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>There is a wide range of the types of assault that can occur. Generally, an assault occurs when a person directly or indirectly applies force intentionally to another person without their consent. It can also occur when a person attempts to apply such force, or threatens to do so, without the consent of the other person. An injury need not occur for an assault to be committed, but the force used in the assault must be offensive in nature with an intention to apply force. It can be an assault to &quot;tap&quot;, &quot;pinch&quot;, &quot;push&quot;, or direct another such minor action toward another, but an accidental application of force is not an assault.</paragraph><paragraph>The potential punishment for an assault in Canada varies depending on the manner in which the charge proceeds through the court system and the type of assault that is committed. The Criminal Code defines assault as a dual offence (indictable or summary offence). Police officers can arrest someone without a warrant for an assault if it is in the public's interest to do so notwithstanding S.495(2)(d) of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension><space/>This public interest is usually satisfied by preventing a continuation or repetition of the offence on the same victim.</paragraph><paragraph>Some variations on the ordinary crime of assault include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Assault: The offence is defined by section 265 of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Assault with a weapon: Section 267(a) of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Assault causing bodily harm: See<space/><link><target>assault causing bodily harm</target></link><space/>Section 267(b) of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Aggravated assault: Section 268 of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Assaulting a peace officer, etc.: Section 270 of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Sexual assault: Section 271 of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Sexual assault with a weapon or threats or causing bodily harm: Section 272 of the Code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1985-46"></extension></listitem><listitem>Aggravated sexual assault: See<space/><link><target>aggravated sexual assault</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>An individual cannot consent to an assault with a weapon, assault causing bodily harm, aggravated assault, or any sexual assault. Consent will also be vitiated if two people consent to fight but serious bodily harm is intended and caused (R v Paice; R v Jobidon). A person cannot consent to serious bodily harm.</paragraph><heading level='3'>India</heading><paragraph>The Indian Penal Code covers the punishments and types of assault in Chapter 16,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">http://devgan.in/ipc/chapter_16.php#s351</arg><arg name="title">Indian Penal Code Chapter XVI</arg></template></extension><space/>sections 351 through 358.<template><target>Quotation</target><arg>Whoever makes any gesture, or any preparation intending or knowing it to be likely that such gesture or preparation will cause any person present to apprehend that he who makes that gesture or preparation is about to use criminal force to that person, is said to commit an assault.</arg><arg name="s.351 of the Indian Penal Code<ref>{{Cite web|url">http://www.vakilno1.com/bareacts/indianpenalcode/S351.htm|title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Code further explains that &quot;<italics>mere words do not amount to an assault. But the words which a person uses may give to his gestures or preparation such a meaning as may make those gestures or preparations amount to an assault.</italics>&quot; Assault is in Indian criminal law an attempt to use criminal force (with criminal force being described in s.350). The attempt itself has been made an offence in India, as in other states.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nigeria</heading><paragraph>The Criminal Code Act (chapter 29 of Part V; sections 351 to 365) creates a number of offences of assault.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nigeria-law.org/Criminal%20Code%20Act-PartV.htm#Chapter%2029</arg><arg name="title">Criminal Code Act-PartV</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Assault is defined by section 252 of that Act. Assault is a misdemeanor punishable by one year imprisonment; assault with &quot;intent to have carnal knowledge of him or her&quot; or who indecently assaults another, or who commits other more-serious variants of assault (as defined in the Act) are guilty of a felony, and longer prison terms are provided for.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nigeria-law.org/Criminal%20Code%20Act-PartV.htm#Chapter%2025</arg><arg name="title">Criminal Code Act-PartV</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pacific Islands</heading><paragraph><bold>Marshall Islands</bold></paragraph><paragraph>The offence of assault is created by section 113 of the Criminal Code.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www3.paclii.org/mh/legis/consol_act/cc94/'>Criminal Code [31 MIRC Ch 1&amp;#93;</link></extension><space/>A person is guilty of this offence if he unlawfully offers or attempts, with force or violence, to strike, beat, wound, or do bodily harm to, another.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Republic of Ireland</heading><paragraph>Section 2 of the<space/><link><target>Non-Fatal Offences against the Person Act 1997</target></link><space/>creates the offence of assault, and section 3 of that Act creates the offence of<space/><link><target>assault causing harm</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph><link><target>South African law</target></link><space/>does not draw the distinction between assault and battery.<space/><italics>Assault</italics><space/>is a<space/><link><target>common law crime</target></link><space/>defined as &quot;unlawfully and intentionally applying force to the person of another, or inspiring a belief in that other that force is immediately to be applied to him.&quot; The law also recognises the crime of<space/><italics>assault with intent to cause<space/><link><target>grievous bodily harm</target></link></italics>, where grievous bodily harm is defined as &quot;harm which in itself is such as seriously to interfere with health.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">John<space/></arg><arg name="last">Milton<space/></arg><arg name="title">South African Criminal Law and Procedure: Common-law crimes<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cape Town<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Juta & Co<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7021-3773-0<space/></arg><arg name="pages">405–437</arg></template></extension><space/>The common law crime of<space/><italics><link><target>indecent assault</target></link></italics><space/>was repealed by the<space/><link><target>Criminal Law (Sexual Offences and Related Matters) Amendment Act, 2007</target></link>, and replaced by a statutory crime of<space/><italics><link><target>sexual assault</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Piracy with violence</defkey><defval><space/>Section 2 of the<space/><link><target>Piracy Act 1837</target></link><space/>provides that it is an offence, amongst other things, for a person, with intent to commit or at the time of or immediately before or immediately after committing the crime of piracy in respect of any ship or vessel, to assault, with intent to<space/><link><target>Murder in English law</target><part>murder</part></link>, any person being on board of or belonging to such ship or vessel.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on an officer of Revenue and Customs</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 32(1) of the<space/><link><target>Commissioners for Revenue and Customs Act 2005</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting an immigration officer</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2007/30/section/22'>section 22(1)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>UK Borders Act 2007</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting a person designated under section 43 of the Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2005/15/section/51'>section 51(1)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting an accredited financial investigator</defkey><defval><space/>This section is created by section 453A of the<space/><link><target>Proceeds of Crime Act 2002</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Section 453A was inserted by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2007/27/section/81'>section 81(2)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Serious Crime Act 2007</target></link><space/>and amended by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2009/26/schedule/7/paragraph/94'>paragraph 94</link><space/>of Schedule 7 to the<space/><link><target>Policing and Crime Act 2009</target></link>.</extension></defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting a member of an international joint investigation team</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2005/15/section/57'>section 57(2)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Serious Organised Crime and Police Act 2005</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Attacks on internationally protected persons</defkey><defval><space/>Section 1(1)(a) of the<space/><link><target>Internationally Protected Persons Act 1978</target></link><space/>(c.17) makes provision for assault occasioning actual bodily harm or causing injury on &quot;protected persons&quot; (including Heads of State).</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Attacks on UN Staff workers</defkey><defval><space/>Section 1(2)(a) of the<space/><link><target>United Nations Personnel Act 1997</target></link><space/>(c.13) makes provision for assault causing injury, and section 1(2)(b) makes provision for assault occasioning actual bodily harm, on UN staff.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault by person committing an offence under the Night Poaching Act 1828</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 2 of the<space/><link><target>Night Poaching Act 1828</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><paragraph>Abolished offence:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on customs and excise officers, etc.</defkey><defval><space/>Section 16(1)(a) of the<space/><link><target>Customs and Excise Management Act 1979</target></link><space/>(c.2) provided that it was an offence to, amongst other things, assault any person duly engaged in the performance of any duty or the exercise of any power imposed or conferred on him by or under any enactment relating to an assigned matter, or any person acting in his aid. For the meaning of &quot;assault&quot; in this provision, see Logdon v. DPP [1976] Crim LR 121,<space/><link><target>Divisional Court (England and Wales)</target><part>DC</part></link>. This offence was abolished and replaced by the<space/><link><target>Commissioners for Revenue and Customs Act 2005</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><heading level='4'>England and Wales</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Battery (crime)#England and Wales</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>English law provides for two offences of assault:<space/><link><target>common assault</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>. Assault (or common assault) is committed if one intentionally or recklessly causes another person to apprehend immediate and unlawful personal violence.<space/><italics>Violence</italics><space/>in this context means any unlawful touching, though there is some debate over whether the touching must also be hostile. Confusingly, the terms &quot;assault&quot; and &quot;common assault&quot; often encompass the separate offence of<space/><link><target>battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>, even in statutory settings such as s 40(3)(a) of the<space/><link><target>Criminal Justice Act 1988</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>common assault</target></link><space/>is an assault that lacks any of the aggravating features which Parliament has deemed serious enough to deserve a higher penalty. Section 39 of the Criminal Justice Act 1988 provides that common assault, like battery, is triable only in the<space/><link><target>Magistrates' Court (England and Wales)</target><part>magistrates' court</part></link><space/>in England and Wales (unless it is linked to a more serious offence, which is triable in the<space/><link><target>Crown Court</target></link>). Additionally, if a Defendant has been charged on an indictment with assault occasioning actual bodily harm (ABH), or racially/religiously aggravated assault, then a jury in the Crown Court may acquit the Defendant of the more serious offence, but still convict of common assault if it finds common assault has been committed.</paragraph><heading level='5'>Aggravated assaults</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault occasioning actual bodily harm</defkey><defval><space/>The offence of<space/><link><target>assault occasioning actual bodily harm</target></link><space/>is created by section 47 of the<space/><link><target>Offences against the Person Act 1861</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault with intent to rob</defkey><defval><space/>The penalty for<space/><link><target>assault with intent to rob</target></link><space/>is provided by section 8(2) of the<space/><link><target>Theft Act 1968</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Racially or religiously aggravated common assault</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 29(1)(c) of the<space/><link><target>Crime and Disorder Act 1998</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Racially or religiously aggravated assault occasioning actual bodily harm</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 29(1)(b) of the<space/><link><target>Crime and Disorder Act 1998</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault with intent to resist arrest</defkey><defval><space/>The offence of<space/><link><target>assault with intent to resist arrest</target></link><space/>is created by section 38 of the<space/><link><target>Offences against the Person Act 1861</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on a constable in the execution of his duty</defkey><defval><space/><template><target>Main</target><arg>Assaulting a constable in the execution of his duty</arg></template><space/>Section 89(1) of the<space/><link><target>Police Act 1996</target></link><space/>provides that it is an offence for a person to assault either:</defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>a<space/><link><target>constable</target></link><space/>acting in the execution of his duty; or</listitem><listitem>a person assisting a constable in the execution of his duty.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting a traffic officer</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2004/18/section/10'>section 10(1)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Traffic Management Act 2004</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting a person designated or accredited under sections 38 or 39 or 41 or 41A of the Police Reform Act 2002</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2002/30/section/46'>section 46(1)</link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Police Reform Act 2002</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on a prison custody officer</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 90(1) of the<space/><link><target>Criminal Justice Act 1991</target></link><space/>(c.53).</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on a secure training centre custody officer</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 13(1) of the<space/><link><target>Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994</target></link><space/>(c.33).</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assault on officer saving wreck</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 37 of the<space/><link><target>Offences against the Person Act 1861</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Assaulting an officer of the court</defkey><defval><space/>This offence is created by section 14(1)(b) of the<space/><link><target>County Courts Act 1984</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Cruelty to persons under sixteen</defkey><defval><space/>Section 1(1) of the<space/><link><target>Children and Young Persons Act 1933</target></link><space/>provides that it is an offence for a person who has attained the age of sixteen years, and who has responsibility for a child or young person under that age, to, amongst other things, wilfully assault that child or young person, or to cause or procure that child or young person to be assaulted, in a manner likely to cause him unnecessary suffering or injury to health.</defval></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Sexual assault</defkey><defval><space/>The offence of<space/><link><target>Sexual assault#England and Wales</target><part>sexual assault</part></link><space/>created by section 3 of the<space/><link><target>Sexual Offences Act 2003</target></link>. It is not defined in terms of the offences of common assault or battery. It instead requires intentional touching and the absence of a reasonable belief in consent.</defval></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Scotland</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Scots Law</target></link>, assault is defined as an &quot;attack upon the person of another&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>MacDonald,<space/><italics>Criminal Law</italics><space/>(5th edn, 1948) p.155</extension><space/>There is no distinction made in Scotland between assault and battery (which is not a term used in Scots law), although, as in England and Wales, assault can be occasioned without a<space/><italics>physical</italics><space/>attack on another's person, as demonstrated in<space/><italics>Atkinson v.<space/><link><target>Lord Advocate</target><part>HM Advocate</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'>1987 SCCR 534</extension><space/>wherein the accused was found guilty of assaulting a shop assistant by simply jumping over a counter wearing a<space/><link><target>ski mask</target></link>. The court said:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>[A]n assault may be constituted by threatening gestures sufficient to produce alarm</arg><arg>Atkinson v. HM Advocate (1987)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Scottish law also provides for a more serious charge of aggravated assault on the basis of such factors as severity of injury, the use of a weapon, or<space/><italics>Hamesuken</italics><space/>(to assault a person in his own home). The<space/><italics><link><target>mens rea</target></link></italics><space/>for assault is simply &quot;evil intent&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>MacDonald, op. cit, p.155; Smart v. HM Advocate 1975 JC 30</extension><space/>although this has been held to mean no more than that assault<space/><italics>&quot;cannot be committed accidentally or recklessly or negligently&quot;</italics><space/>as upheld in<space/><italics><link><target>Lord Advocate's Reference</target></link><space/>No 2 of 1992</italics><space/>where it was found that a &quot;hold-up&quot; in a shop justified as a joke would still constitute an offence.</paragraph><paragraph>It is a separate offence to assault on a constable in the execution of his duty, under section 41 of the<space/><link><target>Police (Scotland) Act 1967</target></link><space/>which provides that it is an offence for a person to, amongst other things, assault a constable in the execution of his duty or a person assisting a constable in the execution of his duty.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Northern Ireland</heading><paragraph>Several offences of assault exist in Northern Ireland. The<space/><link><target>Offences against the Person Act 1861</target></link><space/>creates the offences of:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Common assault and battery: a summary offence, under section 42;</listitem><listitem>Aggravated assault and battery: a summary offence, under section 43</listitem><listitem>Common assault: under section 47</listitem><listitem>Assault occasioning actual bodily harm: under section 47</listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Criminal Justice (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act (Northern Ireland) 1968</target></link><space/>creates the offences of:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Assault with intent to resist arrest: under section 7(1)(b); this offence was formerly created by s.38 of the OAPA 1861.</listitem></list><paragraph>That Act formerly created the offence of 'Assault on a constable in the execution of his duty'. under secction 7(1)(a), but that section has been superseded by section 66(1) of the<space/><link><target>Police (Northern Ireland) Act 1998</target></link><space/>(c.32) which now provides that it is an offence for a person to, amongst other things, assault a constable in the execution of his duty, or a person assisting a constable in the execution of his duty.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Felony Sentences in State Courts.pdf</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Felony Sentences in State Courts'', study by the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Justice</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>American<space/><link><target>common law</target></link><space/>has defined assault as an attempt to commit a<space/><link><target>battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Assault is typically treated as a<space/><link><target>misdemeanor</target></link><space/>and not as a<space/><link><target>felony</target></link><space/>(unless it involves a<space/><link><target>Police</target><part>law enforcement</part></link><space/>officer). The more serious crime of aggravated assault is treated as a felony.</paragraph><paragraph>Four elements were required at common law:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The apparent, present ability to carry out;</listitem><listitem>An unlawful attempt;</listitem><listitem>To commit a violent injury;</listitem><listitem>Upon another.</listitem></list><paragraph>Simple assault can be distinguished without the intent of injury upon another person. The violation of one's personal space or touching in a way the victim deemed inappropriate can be simple assault. In common law states an assault is not committed by merely, for example, swearing at another; without threat of battery, there can be no assault.</paragraph><paragraph>As the criminal law evolved, element one was weakened in most jurisdictions so that a reasonable fear of bodily injury would suffice. These four elements were eventually codified in most states.</paragraph><paragraph>Laws on assault vary by state. Since each state has its own laws, there is no universal assault law. Acts classified as assault in one state may be classified as<space/><link><target>Battery (crime)</target><part>battery</part></link>,<space/><link><target>menacing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>intimidation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>reckless endangerment</target></link><space/>etc. in another state. Modern American statutes may define assault as including:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>an attempt to cause or purposely, knowingly, or recklessly causing bodily injury to another<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>negligently</target></link><space/>causing bodily injury to another with a dangerous weapon.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://legis.state.sd.us/statutes/DisplayStatute.aspx?Type</arg><arg name="title">South Dakota Legislature</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>causing bodily harm by reckless operation of a<space/><link><target>motor vehicle</target></link><space/>(vehicular assault).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://apps.leg.wa.gov/rcw/default.aspx?cite</arg><arg name="title">RCW 46.61.522: Vehicular assault — Penalty.</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>threatening another in a menacing manner.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://law.justia.com/codes/nebraska/2006/s28index/s2803010000.html</arg><arg name="title">§ 28-310 — Assault in the third degree; penalty. :: Chapter 28 — Crimes and Punishments :: 2006 Nebraska Revised Statutes :: Nebraska Revised Statutes :: US Codes and Statutes :: US Law :: Justia</arg><arg name="work">Justia Law</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>knowingly causing physical contact with another person knowing the other person will regard the contact as offensive or provocative<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.moga.mo.gov/statutes/C500-599/5650000070.HTM</arg><arg name="title">Section 565-070 Until December 31, 2016--Assault in the</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>causing stupor, unconsciousness or physical injury by intentionally administering a drug or controlled substance without consent<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://law.justia.com/codes/connecticut/2005/title53a/sec53a-60.html</arg><arg name="title">Sec. 53a-60. Assault in the second degree: Class D felony. :: Chapter 952 — Penal Code: Offenses (contains Secs. 53a-24 to 53a-323) :: Title 53a — Penal Code (contains Chapters 950 to 952) :: 2005 Connecticut Code :: Connecticut Code :: US Codes and Statutes :: US Law :: Justia</arg><arg name="work">Justia Law</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>purposely or knowingly causing reasonable apprehension of bodily injury in another<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://codes.lp.findlaw.com/mtcode/45/5/2/45-5-201</arg><arg name="title">MONT CODE ANN § 45-5-201 : Montana Code - Section 45-5-201: Assault</arg><arg name="work">Findlaw</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>any act which is intended to place another in fear of immediate physical contact which will be painful, injurious, insulting, or offensive, coupled with the apparent ability to execute the act.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://coolice.legis.iowa.gov/cool-ice/default.asp?category</arg><arg name="title">Iowa Code 708</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The laws on assault differ significantly from state to state as exemplified below.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Tennessee</target></link><space/>assault is defined as follows:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.lexisnexis.com/hottopics/tncode/</arg><arg name="title">LexisNexis® Custom Solution: Tennessee Code Research Tool</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>39-13-101. Assault.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>(a) A person commits assault who:</listitem><listitem>(1) Intentionally, knowingly or recklessly causes bodily injury to another;</listitem><listitem>(2) Intentionally or knowingly causes another to reasonably fear imminent bodily injury; or</listitem><listitem>(3) Intentionally or knowingly causes physical contact with another and a reasonable person would regard the contact as extremely offensive or provocative.</listitem></list><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Kansas</target></link><space/>the law on assault states:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://kansasstatutes.lesterama.org/Chapter_21/Article_34/#21-3408</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Assault.<space/></listitem><listitem>Assault is intentionally placing another person in reasonable apprehension of immediate bodily harm.</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>North Dakota</target></link><space/>law states:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.legis.nd.gov/cencode/t12-1c17.pdf?20130902151232</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Simple assault.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>1.A person is guilty of an offense if that person:</listitem><listitem>a. Willfully causes bodily injury to another human being; or</listitem><listitem>b. Negligently causes bodily injury to another human being by means of a firearm, destructive device, or other weapon, the use of which against a human being is likely to cause death or serious bodily injury.</listitem></list><paragraph>States vary on whether it is possible to commit an &quot;attempted assault&quot; since it can be considered a double<space/><link><target>inchoate offense</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In some states,<space/><link><target>consent (criminal law)</target><part>consent</part></link><space/>is a complete defense to assault. In other jurisdictions, mutual consent is an incomplete defense, with the result that the misdemeanor is treated as a<space/><italics>petty misdemeanor</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In New York State assault as defined in the New York State Penal Code Article 120,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ypdcrime.com/penal.law/article120.htm#p120.05</arg><arg name="title">Article 120 - NY Penal Law - Assault Menacing Stalking - Law</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 May 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>requires an actual injury. Other states define this as battery. There is no crime of battery in New York. The threat of imminent injury without physical contact in New York is called Menacing. New York also has specific laws against Hazing when such threats are made as requirement to join an organization.</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, the crime of assault generally requires that both the perpetrator and the victim of an assault be human. Thus, there is no assault if an ox gores a man. However, the<space/><link><target>Unborn Victims of Violence Act</target><part>Unborn Victims of Violence Act of 2004</part></link><space/>treats the<space/><link><target>fetus</target></link><space/>as a separate person for the purposes of assault and other violent crimes, under certain limited circumstances. See<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nrlc.org/uploads/unbornvictims/UVVAEnrolled.pdf'>H.R. 1997 / P.L. 108-212</link></paragraph><paragraph>Some possible examples of defenses, mitigating circumstances, or failures of proof are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A defendant could argue that since he was drunk, he could not form the<space/><link><target>specific intent</target></link><space/>to commit assault. This defense would most likely fail since only involuntary<space/><link><target>intoxication defense</target><part>intoxication</part></link><space/>is accepted as a defense in most American jurisdictions.</listitem><listitem>A defendant could also argue that he was engaged in mutually consensual behavior.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Ancient Greece</heading><paragraph>Assault in Ancient Greece was normally termed<space/><link><target>hubris</target></link>. Contrary to modern usage, the term did not have the extended connotation of overweening<space/><link><target>pride</target></link>, self-confidence or arrogance, often resulting in fatal retribution. In Ancient Greece, &quot;hubris&quot; referred to actions which, intentionally or not, shamed and humiliated the victim, and frequently the perpetrator as well. It was most evident in the public and private actions of the powerful and rich.</paragraph><paragraph>Violations of the law against hubris included what would today be termed assault and battery; sexual crimes ranging from forcible rape of women or children to consensual but improper activities; or the theft of public or sacred property.<extension extension_name='ref'>MacDowell (1976) p. 25.</extension><space/>Two well-known cases are found in the speeches of<space/><link><target>Demosthenes</target></link>, a prominent statesman and orator in ancient<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link>. These two examples occurred when first, Meidias punched Demosthenes in the face in the theater (Against Meidias), and second when (in Against Konon) a defendant allegedly assaulted a man and crowed over the victim.</paragraph><paragraph>Hubris, though not specifically defined, was a legal term and was considered a crime in classical Athens. It was also considered the greatest sin of the ancient Greek world. That was so because it not only was proof of excessive pride, but also resulted in violent acts by or to those involved. The category of acts constituting hubris for the ancient Greeks apparently broadened from the original specific reference to mutilation of a corpse, or a humiliation of a defeated foe, or irreverent, &quot;outrageous treatment&quot;, in general.</paragraph><paragraph>The meaning was eventually further generalized in its modern English usage to apply to any outrageous act or exhibition of pride or disregard for basic moral laws. Such an act may be referred to as an &quot;act of hubris&quot;, or the person committing the act may be said to be hubristic.<space/><link><target>At</target></link>, Greek for 'ruin, folly, delusion', is the action performed by the hero, usually because of his/her hubris, or great pride, that leads to his/her death or downfall.</paragraph><paragraph>Crucial to this definition are the ancient Greek concepts of honor (tim) and shame. The concept of tim included not only the exaltation of the one receiving honor, but also the shaming of the one overcome by the act of hubris. This concept of honor is akin to a<space/><link><target>zero-sum</target></link><space/>game.<space/><link><target>Rush Rehm</target></link><space/>simplifies this definition to the contemporary concept of &quot;insolence, contempt, and excessive violence&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Affray</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Battery (crime)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Assault (tort)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Street fighting</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Domestic violence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gay bashing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hate crime</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mayhem (crime)</target><part>Mayhem</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Misdemeanor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Offences against the Person Act 1861</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Terroristic threat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rape</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sexual assault</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Common assault</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Baker</arg><arg name="first">Dennis</arg><arg name="last2">William</arg><arg name="first2">Glanville</arg><arg name="title">Textbook of Criminal Law</arg><arg name="publisher">London, Sweet & Maxwell</arg></template><space/>chapter 9</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wiktionary</target><arg>beat up</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>assault</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.criminallawonline.com/artassaults.php'>A guide to the non fatal offences against the person</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/D?c108:5:./temp/~c1082ah2oE::'>H.R. 1997 / P.L. 108-212</link><space/>Unborn Victims of Violence Act of 2004</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://devgan.in/ipc/chapter_16.php'>IPC Chapter XVI</link><space/>(Mobile Friendly)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.anydifference.com/difference-assault-battery/'>The differences between Assault and Battery</link><space/>- Any difference</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>English criminal law navbox</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Assault</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Crimes</target></link><link><target>Category:Violence</target></link></paragraph></article>