<article title='Digital_Enhanced_Cordless_Telecommunications'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">March 2009</arg></template><link><target>File:cordless.phone.750pix.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The base unit and handset of a<space/><link><target>British Telecom</target></link><space/>DECT cordless telephone</part></link><link><target>File:Pulse_duration_measurement_of_a_DECT_phone.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>DECT pulduration measurement (100Hz / 10mS) on chanel 8</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications</bold><space/>(Digital European Cordless Telecommunications), usually known by the<space/><link><target>acronym</target></link><space/><bold>DECT</bold>, is a standard primarily used for creating<space/><link><target>cordless phone</target></link><space/>systems. It originated in Europe, where it is the universal standard, replacing earlier cordless phone standards, such as 900&amp;nbsp;MHz<space/><link><target>CT1</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>CT2</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="rohde"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www2.rohde-schwarz.com/en/technologies/Wireless_Connectivity/DECT/information/<space/></arg><arg name="title">DECT Information</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Beyond Europe, it has been adopted by<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>, and most countries in<space/><link><target>Asia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>. North American adoption was delayed by<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>radio frequency regulations. This forced development of a variation of DECT, called<space/><bold>DECT 6.0</bold>, using a slightly different frequency range. The technology is nearly identical, but the frequency difference makes the technology incompatible with systems in other areas, even from the same manufacturer. DECT has almost universally replaced other standards in most countries where it is used, with the exception of North America.</paragraph><paragraph>DECT is used primarily in home and small office systems, but is also available in many<space/><link><target>Private branch exchange</target><part>PBX</part></link><space/>systems for medium and large businesses. DECT can also be used for purposes other than cordless phones. Voice applications, such as<space/><link><target>baby monitor</target><trail>s</trail></link>, are becoming common. Data applications also exist, but have been eclipsed by<space/><link><target>Wi-Fi</target></link>.<space/><link><target>3G</target></link><space/>&amp;<space/><link><target>4G</target></link><space/>cellular also competes with both DECT and Wi-Fi for both voice and data. DECT is also used in special applications such as remote controls for industrial applications.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2011, development of a low power variant (DECT ULE - ultra low energy) was initiated to take advantage of the existing data channels for DECT to address markets such as home automation, security and climate control. The low power variant enables this standard to be used in battery powered devices and for many devices in the home to be connected through a single control unit.</paragraph><paragraph>The DECT standard includes a standardized interoperability profile for simple telephone capabilities, called<space/><link><target>Generic access profile</target><part>GAP</part></link>, which most manufacturers implement. GAP-conformance enables DECT handsets and bases from different manufacturers to interoperate at the most basic level of functionality, that of making and receiving calls. The standard also contains several other interoperability profiles, for data and for radio local-loop services.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Application</heading><paragraph>The DECT standard fully specifies a means for a portable unit, such as a cordless telephone, to access a fixed telecoms network via radio. But, unlike the<space/><link><target>GSM</target></link><space/>standards, does not specify any internal aspects of the fixed network itself. Connectivity to the fixed network (that may be of many different kinds) is done through a<space/><link><target>base station</target></link><space/>or &quot;Radio Fixed Part&quot; to terminate the radio link, and a<space/><link><target>Gateway (telecommunications)</target><part>gateway</part></link><space/>to connect calls to the fixed network. In most cases the gateway connection is to the<space/><link><target>public switched telephone network</target></link><space/>or telephone jack, although connectivity with newer technologies such as<space/><link><target>Voice over IP</target></link><space/>has become available. There are also other devices such as some<space/><link><target>baby monitor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>utilizing DECT, and in these devices there is no gateway functionality.</paragraph><paragraph>The DECT standard originally envisaged three major areas of application:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year"><space/>1997<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications (DECT); A high level guide to the DECT standardization<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://pda.etsi.org/pda/AQuery.asp?qSEARCH_STRING</arg><arg name="work"><space/>ETR 178<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>European Telecommunications Standards Institute<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2010-09-23</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Domestic cordless telephony, using a single base station to connect one or more handsets to the public telecoms network.</listitem><listitem>Enterprise premises cordless PABXs and wireless LANs, using many base stations for coverage. Calls continue as users move between different coverage cells, through a mechanism called handover. Calls can be both within the system and to the public telecoms network.</listitem><listitem>Public access, using large numbers of base stations to provide high capacity building or urban area coverage as part of a public telecoms network.</listitem></list><paragraph>Of these, the domestic application (cordless home telephones) has been extremely successful. The enterprise<space/><link><target>PABX</target></link><space/>market had some success, and all the major PABX vendors have offered DECT access options. The public access application did not succeed, since public cellular networks rapidly out-competed DECT by coupling their ubiquitous coverage with large increases in capacity and continuously falling costs. There has been only one major installation of DECT for public access: in early 1998<space/><link><target>Telecom Italia</target></link><space/>launched a DECT network known as &quot;Fido&quot; after much regulatory delay, covering major cities in Italy.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Dect for Cordless Terminal Mobility&quot; DECT Forum Newsletter 6 March 1998<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dectweb.com/DECTForum/news/NewsLettersPDF/nl199801.pdf'></link></extension><space/>The service was promoted for only a few months and, having peaked at 142,000 subscribers, was shut down in 2001.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.angelodenicola.it/articoli/messaggero/2000/2000_04_05.htm'>&quot;LA TELECOM SPEGNE &quot;FIDO&quot;&quot; Il Messaggero 5 April 2000</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>DECT has also been used for Fixed Wireless Access as a substitute for copper pairs in the &quot;last mile&quot; in countries such as India and South Africa.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2009</arg></template><space/>By using directional antennas and sacrificing some traffic capacity, cell coverage could extend to over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template>. In Europe the power limit laid down for use of the DECT spectrum (250&amp;nbsp;mW peak) was expressed in<space/><link><target>Effective radiated power</target><part>ERP</part></link>, rather than the more commonly used<space/><link><target>EIRP</target></link>, permitting the use of high-gain directional antennas to produce much higher EIRP and hence long ranges.</paragraph><paragraph>The standard is also used in electronic cash terminals, traffic lights, and remote door openers.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://dedected.org/trac/raw-attachment/wiki/25C3/talk-25c3.pdf<template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>DECT 6.0</heading><paragraph>The &quot;6.0&quot; in<space/><bold>DECT 6.0</bold><space/>does not equate to a spectrum band, but is a marketing term coined for DECT devices manufactured for use in the U.S. and Canada. Although DECT 6.0 operates at 1.9&amp;nbsp;GHz, it was decided the term<space/><bold>DECT 1.9</bold><space/>might have confused customers who equate larger numbers (such as the<space/><bold>2.4</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>5.8</bold><space/>in existing 2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz and 5.8&amp;nbsp;GHz cordless telephones) with later products. The DECT and DECT 6.0 technologies are essentially identical, except for operating frequency.</paragraph><paragraph>DECT 6.0 products do not support &quot;GAP&quot;, therefore phones of differing brands are not guaranteed to work together. E.g. A GE 28105EE1 DECT 6.0 headset will not receive calls if registered to a Uniden base unit.</paragraph><paragraph>The term<space/><bold>DECT 6.0</bold><space/>is also sometimes inappropriately used in Australia that uses the same allocated spectrum frequencies as Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://shop.bigpond.com/ProductSearch.asp?Action=HeaderSearch&amp;ProductName=dect+6.0 accessed on October 11, 2011</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>VoIP/IP-DECT</heading><paragraph>To facilitate migrations from traditional PBXs to VoIP, manufacturers such as<space/><link><target>Gigaset Communications</target><part>Gigaset</part></link><space/>(formerly<space/><link><target>Siemens</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Lantiq</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ascom Wireless Solutions</target><part>Ascom</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Aastra Technologies</target><part>Aastra</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Philips</target></link>,<space/><link><target>snom</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Grandstream</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Spectralink</target></link><space/>developed IP-DECT solutions where the backhaul from the base station is via VoIP (<link><target>H.323</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Session Initiation Protocol</target><part>SIP</part></link>) over ethernet, while communications between base and handsets is via DECT.</paragraph><paragraph>DECT was originally intended for use with<space/><link><target>plain old telephone service</target><part>traditional analog telephone</part></link><space/>networks, but DECT bases have higher bit-rates at their disposal than<space/><link><target>plain old telephone service</target><part>traditional analog telephone</part></link><space/>networks could provide. To take advantage of these higher-speed networks, ETSI released the<space/><link><target>CAT-iq</target></link><space/>standard in 2005, which, among other features, standardizes<space/><link><target>wideband audio</target></link><space/>over DECT. CAT-iq is backwards compatible with GAP.</paragraph><paragraph>For enterprises, DECT-plus-(cabled)VoIP has several significant advantages and disadvantages in comparison to VoIP-over-WiFi, where, typically, the handsets are directly WiFi+VoIP-enabled (instead of having the DECT-handset communicate via an intermediate VoIP-enabled base). On the one hand, VoIP-over-WiFi has a range advantage given sufficient access-points, while a DECT phone must remain in proximity to its own base (or repeaters thereof). On the other hand, for large networks VoIP-over-WiFi imposes significant design and maintenance complexity to ensure roaming facilities and high quality-of-service. In North-America, DECT suffers from major deficits, especially in comparison to DECT elsewhere, since the<space/><link><target>UPCS band</target></link><space/>(1920-1930&amp;nbsp;MHz) used for DECT in North-America is not free from heavy interference and only half as wide as that used in Europe (1880-1900&amp;nbsp;MHz), the 4&amp;nbsp;mW average transmission power limits the range to far less than the 10&amp;nbsp;mW permitted in Europe, and the commonplace lack of GAP-compatibility among US vendors binds companies to a single vendor. Other alternatives to DECT-plus-VoIP include local<space/><link><target>microcell</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(e.g. with<space/><link><target>OpenBTS</target></link>), which then enables use of standard cellular phones for local &quot;in-house&quot; telephony. In the Far-East, in particular in Japan and Taiwan, the<space/><link><target>Personal Handy-phone System</target></link><space/>renders the &quot;in-house&quot; (and PBX) concept superfluous by making the entire<space/><link><target>wireless local loop</target><part>&quot;last-mile&quot; wireless</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>DECT ULE</heading><paragraph>The latest DECT variant is DECT ULE, or DECT Ultra low energy. The standard was first discussed in January 2011 and the first commercial products were launched later that year by<space/><link><target>Dialog Semiconductor</target></link>. Like DECT, DECT ULE standard uses the 1.9&amp;nbsp;GHz band so suffers less interference than<space/><link><target>Zigbee</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bluetooth</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wi-Fi</target></link>, or microwave ovens, which all operate in the<space/><link><target>ISM band</target><part>ISM</part></link><space/>unlicensed 2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz band.</paragraph><paragraph>The standard has been created to enable home automation, security, healthcare and energy monitoring applications that are battery powered and can easily connect to the web using the large number of existing DECT enabled modems and be managed using a smartphone app.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Standards history</heading><paragraph>The DECT standard was developed by<space/><link><target>ETSI</target></link><space/>in several phases, the first of that took place between 1988 and 1992 when the first round of standards were published. These were the ETS 300-175 series in 9 parts defining the air interface, and ETS 300-176 defining how the units should be type approved. A technical report, ETR-178, was also published to explain the standard. Subsequent standards were developed and published by ETSI to cover interoperability profiles and standards for testing.</paragraph><paragraph>Initially named &quot;Digital European Cordless Telephone&quot; at its launch by CEPT in November 1987, following a suggestion by Enrico Tosato of Italy, its name was soon changed to &quot;Digital European Cordless Telecommunications&quot; to reflect its broader range of application, including data services. In 1995, due to its more global usage, the name was changed from &quot;European&quot; to &quot;Enhanced.&quot; It is an<space/><link><target>ETSI</target></link><space/>standard for digital<space/><link><target>portable phone</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(cordless home telephones), commonly used for domestic or corporate purposes. It is recognized by the<space/><link><target>ITU</target></link><space/>as fulfilling the<space/><link><target>IMT-2000</target></link><space/>requirements and thus qualifies as a<space/><link><target>3G</target></link><space/>system. Within the IMT-2000 group of technologies, DECT is referred to as 'IMT-2000 Frequency Time' (IMT-FT).</paragraph><paragraph>DECT was developed by ETSI but has since been adopted by many countries all over the World. The original DECT frequency band (1880&amp;nbsp;<link><target>MHz</target></link>1900&amp;nbsp;MHz) is used in all countries in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>. Outside Europe, it is used in most of<space/><link><target>Asia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>. In the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Federal Communications Commission</target></link><space/>in 2005 changed channelization and licensing costs in a nearby band (1920&amp;nbsp;MHz1930&amp;nbsp;MHz, or 1.9&amp;nbsp;<link><target>GHz</target></link>), known as<space/><link><target>Unlicensed Personal Communications Services</target></link><space/>(UPCS), allowing DECT devices to be sold in the U.S. with only minimal changes. These channels are reserved exclusively for voice communication applications and therefore are less likely to experience interference from other wireless devices such as<space/><link><target>baby monitor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>wireless network</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Technical features</heading><paragraph>Typical abilities of a domestic DECT<space/><link><target>Generic access profile</target><part>Generic Access Profile</part></link><space/>(GAP) system includes:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Multiple handsets to one base station and one phone line socket. This allows several cordless telephones to be placed around the house, all operating from the same telephone jack. Additional handsets have a battery charger station that does not plug into the telephone system. Handsets can in many cases be used as<space/><link><target>intercom</target><trail>s</trail></link>, communicating between each other, and sometimes as<space/><link><target>walkie-talkie</target><trail>s</trail></link>, intercommunicating without telephone line connection.</listitem><listitem>Interference-free wireless operation to around<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>yd</arg></template><space/>outdoors, much less indoors when separated by walls. Operates clearly in common congested domestic radio traffic situations, for instance, generally immune to interference from other DECT systems,<space/><link><target>Wi-Fi</target></link><space/>networks,<space/><link><target>video sender</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Bluetooth</target></link><space/>technology, baby monitors and other wireless devices.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Technical properties</heading><paragraph>ETSI standards documentation (ETSI EN 300 175-1/2/3/4/5/6/7/8, REN/DECT-000268-1/2/3/4/5/6/7/8) prescribes the following technical properties for DECT.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Audio codec:<space/><link><target>G.726</target></link><space/>(standard codec),<space/><link><target>G.711</target></link>,<space/><link><target>G.722</target></link><space/>(wideband),<space/><link><target>G.729.1</target></link><space/>(wideband) and<space/><link><target>MPEG-4</target></link><space/>ER LD AAC (wideband and super-wideband)</listitem><listitem>Net bit rate: 32 kbit/s</listitem><listitem>Frequency: Section 4.1.1 (&quot;Nominal position of RF carriers&quot;) of the ETSI standard states: &quot;DECT carriers are specified for the whole frequency range 1880 MHz to 1980 MHz and 2010 MHz to 2025 MHz. Carrier positions in the 902 MHz to 928 MHz ISM band and the 2400 MHz to 2483,5 MHz ISM band have been defined for the US market. [...] The most common spectrum allocation is 1880 MHz to 1900 MHz, but outside Europe spectrum is also available in 1900 MHz to 1920 MHz and in 1910 MHz to 1930 MHz (several countries).&quot;<space/><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1880 – 1900 MHz</arg></template><space/>in Europe,</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1880 – 1900 MHz</arg></template><space/>in South Africa,</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1880 – 1900 MHz</arg></template><space/>in Hong Kong<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beware of Buying Radiocommunications Equipment not Meeting Prescribed Specifications</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ofca.gov.hk/en/consumer_focus/education_corner/alerts/radiocomm/beware/index.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Office of the Communications Authority</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1900 – 1920 MHz</arg></template><space/>in China, till 2003, after 2003 2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1893 – 1906 MHz</arg></template><space/>in Japan,</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1910 – 1930 MHz</arg></template><space/>in Latin America,</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1910 – 1920 MHz</arg></template><space/>in Brazil, and</listitem><listitem><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>1920 – 1930 MHz</arg></template><space/>in the US and Canada<list type='bullet'><listitem>North-American DECT (&quot;<template><target>nowrap</target><arg>DECT 6.0</arg></template>&quot;) products may not be used in Europe/Africa as they cause and suffer from interference with the European/South African cellular networks. Use of such products is prohibited by European Telecommunications Authorities and Independent Communication Authority of South Africa. European DECT products may not be used in the US and Canada as they likewise cause and suffer from interference with US and Canada cellular networks, and use is prohibited by the<space/><link><target>Federal Communication Commission</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Industry Canada</target></link>. As DECT and<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>DECT 6.0</arg></template><space/>do not operate in the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>2.4 GHz</arg></template><space/><link><target>ISM band</target></link>, they are not subject to, nor cause interference with,<space/><link><target>IEEE 802.11b-1999</target><part>802.11b</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>IEEE 802.11g-2003</target><part>802.11g</part></link><space/>Wi-Fi, and<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>2.4 GHz</arg></template><space/>cordless phones. As such, they are sometimes marketed as 'WiFi friendly'.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://forums.whirlpool.net.au/archive/944523'>Wirlpool Forums - Wifi friendly home phones</link></extension></listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Carriers: 10 (1.728&amp;nbsp;MHz spacing) in Europe, 5 (1.728&amp;nbsp;MHz spacing) in the US</listitem><listitem>Time slots: 2 x 12 (up and down stream)</listitem><listitem>Channel allocation: dynamic</listitem><listitem>Average transmission power:<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>10 mW</arg></template><space/>(250&amp;nbsp;mW peak) in Europe, 4&amp;nbsp;mW (100&amp;nbsp;mW peak) in the US</listitem></list><paragraph>The DECT<space/><link><target>physical layer</target></link><space/>uses:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Frequency division multiple access</target></link><space/>(FDMA),</listitem><listitem><link><target>Time division multiple access</target></link><space/>(TDMA) and</listitem><listitem><link><target>Time division duplex</target></link><space/>(TDD)</listitem></list><paragraph>This means that the<space/><link><target>radio spectrum</target></link><space/>is divided into physical channels in two dimensions: frequency and time.</paragraph><paragraph>The maximum allowed power for portable equipment as well as base stations is 250&amp;nbsp;mW. A portable device radiates an average of about 10&amp;nbsp;mW during a call as it is only using one of 24 time slots to transmit.</paragraph><paragraph>The DECT<space/><link><target>media access control</target></link><space/>layer controls the physical layer and provides<space/><link><target>connection oriented</target></link>,<space/><link><target>connectionless</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Broadcasting</target><part>broadcast</part></link><space/>services to the higher layers.</paragraph><paragraph>The DECT<space/><link><target>data link layer</target></link><space/>uses LAPC (Link Access Protocol Control), a specially designed variant of the<space/><link><target>Integrated Services Digital Network</target><part>ISDN</part></link><space/>data link protocol called LAPD. They are based on<space/><link><target>HDLC</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The DECT<space/><link><target>network layer</target></link><space/>always contains the following protocol entities:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Call Control (CC)</listitem><listitem>Mobility Management (MM)</listitem></list><paragraph>Optionally it may also contain others:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Call Independent Supplementary Services (CISS)</listitem><listitem>Connection Oriented Message Service (COMS)</listitem><listitem>Connectionless Message Service (CLMS)</listitem></list><paragraph>All these communicate through a Link Control Entity (LCE).</paragraph><paragraph>The call control protocol is derived from<space/><link><target>ISDN</target></link><space/><link><target>DSS1</target></link>, which is a<space/><link><target>Q.931</target></link>-derived protocol. Many DECT-specific changes have been made.<template><target>Specify</target><arg name="date">June 2010</arg></template><space/>The mobility management protocol includes many elements similar to the GSM protocol, but also includes elements unique to DECT.</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike the GSM protocol, the DECT network specifications do not define cross-linkages between the operation of the entities (for example, Mobility Management and Call Control). The architecture presumes that such linkages will be designed into the interworking unit that connects the DECT access network to whatever mobility-enabled fixed network is involved. By keeping the entities separate, the handset is capable of responding to any combination of entity traffic, and this creates great flexibility in fixed network design without breaking full interoperability.</paragraph><paragraph>DECT<space/><link><target>Generic access profile</target><part>GAP</part></link><space/>is an interoperability profile for DECT. The intent is that two different products from different manufacturers that both conform not only to the DECT standard, but also to the GAP profile defined within the DECT standard, are able to interoperate for basic calling. The DECT standard includes full testing suites for GAP, and GAP products on the market from different manufacturers are in practice interoperable for the basic functions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Security</heading><paragraph>The DECT media access control layer also provides<space/><link><target>encryption</target></link><space/>services with the DECT Standard Cipher (DSC). The encryption is<space/><link><target>Key size</target><part>fairly weak</part></link>, using a 35-bit<space/><link><target>initialization vector</target></link><space/>and encrypting the voice stream with 64-bit encryption.</paragraph><paragraph>The security algorithm has been decoded.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.heise-online.co.uk/security/25C3-Serious-security-vulnerabilities-in-DECT-wireless-telephony--/news/112326
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Serious security vulnerabilities in DECT wireless telephony
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Heise
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2008-12-29
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="25c3"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://dedected.org/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/attachment/wiki/25C3/talk-25c3.pdf?format</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Andreas<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Schuler<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Tews, Erik<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Weinmann, Ralf-Philipp
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>deDECTed.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2008-12-29
</arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="dedected.org"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://dedected.org/trac/attachment/wiki/DSC-Analysis/FSE2010-166.pdf
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cryptanalysis of the DECT Standard Cipher
<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Karsten<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Nohl<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Erik<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Tews<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Ralf-Philipp<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Weinmann
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010-04-04
</arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Another attack involves impersonating a DECT base station, which allows calls to be listened to, recorded, and re-routed to a different destination.<extension extension_name='ref' name="25c3"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While most of the DECT standard is publicly available, the part describing the DECT Standard Cipher was only available under a<space/><link><target>non-disclosure agreement</target></link><space/>to the phones' manufacturers from<space/><link><target>European Telecommunications Standards Institute</target><part>ETSI</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>On June 8, 2002, a posting was made to the<space/><italics>alt.anonymous.messages</italics><space/><link><target>Usenet newsgroup</target><part>newsgroup</part></link><space/>containing what was claimed to be the<space/><link><target>Reverse engineering</target><part>reverse engineered</part></link><space/><link><target>source code</target></link><space/>of the implementation of the DECT Standard Cipher for the<space/><link><target>Samsung</target></link><space/>SP-R6150 telephone.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite newsgroup</target><arg name="message-id">adsq2u$p00$1@wanadoo.fr</arg><arg name="newsgroup">alt.anonymous.messages</arg><arg name="title">Do you like ice cream?</arg><arg name="url">http://groups.google.com/group/alt.anonymous.messages/browse_thread/thread/d311d0ebbe503835/0e28cfbc393d174c</arg></template></extension><space/>This claim has since been refuted.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://lists.gnumonks.org/pipermail/dedected/2009-January/000432.html
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>DSC - Reverse Engineering of the Samsung DECT SP-R6150<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2009-01-26
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ralf-Philipp<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Weinmann
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2008, members of the<space/><link type='external' href='http://dedected.org/'>deDECTed.org</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template><space/>project actually did reverse engineer the DECT Standard Cipher,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://dedected.org/trac/raw-attachment/wiki/25C3/talk-25c3.pdf'>talk-25c3.pdf</link><space/>Slides of the deDECTed.org presentation at the 25th Chaos Communication Congress<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">https://dedected.org/trac/raw-attachment/wiki/25C3/talk-25c3.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="date">20131012151415<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and as of 2010 there has been a viable attack on it that can recover the key.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dedected.org"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>DECT for data networks</heading><paragraph>Other interoperability profiles exist in the DECT suite of standards, and in particular the DPRS (DECT Packet Radio Services) bring together a number of prior interoperability profiles for the use of DECT as a wireless LAN and wireless internet access service. With good range (up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg></template><space/>indoors and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>using directional antennae outdoors), dedicated spectrum, high interference immunity, open interoperability and data speeds of around 500 kbit/s, DECT appeared at one time to be a superior alternative to<space/><link><target>Wi-Fi</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://scitation.aip.org/vsearch/servlet/VerityServlet?KEY</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Wireless LANs: developments in technology and standards
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IEE Journal of Computing and Control Engineering
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>October 1994
</arg></template></extension><space/>The protocol capabilities built into the DECT networking protocol standards were particularly good at supporting fast roaming in the public space, between hotspots operated by competing but connected providers. The first DECT product to reach the market, Olivetti's<space/><link><target>Net3</target><part>Net<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup></part></link>, was a wireless LAN, and German firms<space/><link><target>Dosch &amp; Amand</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hoeft &amp; Wessel</target></link><space/>built niche businesses on the supply of data transmission systems based on DECT.</paragraph><paragraph>However, the timing of the availability of DECT, in the mid-1990s, was too early to find wide application for wireless data outside niche industrial applications. Whilst contemporary providers of Wi-Fi struggled with the same issues, providers of DECT retreated to the more immediately lucrative market for cordless telephones. A key weakness was also the inaccessibility of the U.S. market, due to FCC spectrum restrictions at that time. By the time mass applications for wireless Internet had emerged, and the U.S. had opened up to DECT, well into the new century, the industry had moved far ahead in terms of performance and DECT's time as a technically competitive wireless data transport had passed.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Radio links</heading><paragraph>DECT operates in the 18801900&amp;nbsp;MHz band and defines ten channels from 1881.792&amp;nbsp;MHz to 1897.344&amp;nbsp;MHz with a band gap of 1728&amp;nbsp;kHz. Each base station frame provides 12 duplex speech channels, with each time slot occupying any channel. DECT operates in multicarrier/TDMA/TDD structure. DECT also provides<space/><link><target>Frequency-hopping spread spectrum</target></link><space/>over<space/><link><target>Time division multiple access</target><part>TDMA</part></link>/TDD structure. If frequency-hopping is avoided, each base station can provide up to 120 channels in the DECT spectrum before frequency reuse. Each timeslot can be assigned to a different channel in order to exploit advantages of frequency hopping and to avoid interference from other users in asynchronous fashion.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>XDECT R</heading><paragraph>XDECT R is a marketing term used by<space/><link><target>Uniden</target></link><space/>for its products for extending the range of DECT phones (apparently indefinitely) by using multiple repeater stations. The company has demonstrated the technology to a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2.2</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>range in Australia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Uniden News on XDECT R: http://www.uniden.com.au/AUSTRALIA/XDECTR_RangeTestPopUp.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Batteries</heading><paragraph>Typically DECT handsets use replaceable rechargeable batteries (e.g. a pair of AAA NiMH). Charge control sophistication varies but can cause limited battery endurance. Replacements should not be fully/over charged before fitting because some phones (e.g. Gigaset S79H) detect the voltage and will not work if mistaken for primary cells.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Health and safety</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Wireless electronic devices and health</arg></template>DECT is a UHF technology, with science similar to mobile phones, baby monitors, Wi-Fi, and other cordless telephone technologies, though the UK<space/><link><target>Health Protection Agency</target></link><space/>(HPA) claims that due to a mobile phone's adaptive power ability, a DECT cordless phone's radiation could actually exceed the radiation of a mobile phone (a DECT cordless phone's radiation has an average output power of 10&amp;nbsp;mW but is in the form of 100 bursts per second of 250&amp;nbsp;mW, a strength comparable to some mobile phones).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Health Effects from Radiofrequency Electromagnetic Fields</arg><arg name="url">http://www.hpa.org.uk/webc/HPAwebFile/HPAweb_C/1317133827077</arg><arg name="publisher">(UK) Health Protection Agency</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 September 2013</arg><arg name="author">Independent Advisory Group on Non-ionising Radiation</arg><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>As with all such wireless technologies, consensus is that there are negligible health effects from very low levels of radiation. Most studies have been unable to demonstrate any link to health effects, or have been inconclusive. Nevertheless, there has been persistent controversy over their health safety, and some national and international agencies have made specific recommendations about exposure.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.who.int/features/qa/30/en</arg><arg name="title"><space/>What are the health risks associated with mobile phones and their base stations?</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-01-19</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2005-12-05</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Online Q&A</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[World Health Organization]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.i-sis.org.uk/cordlessPhonesBrainTumours.php</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cat-iq</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>CorDECT</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cordless telephone</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>CT2</target></link><space/>(DECT's predecessor)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Generic access profile</target></link><space/>(GAP)</listitem><listitem><link><target>GSM Interworking Profile (DECT)</target><part>GSM Interworking Profile</part></link><space/>(GIP)</listitem><listitem><link><target>IP-DECT</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Microcell</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Net3</target><part>Net<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup></part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Unlicensed Personal Communications Services</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wideband Digital Enhanced Cordless Telecommunications</target><part>WDECT</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wireless local loop</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Cordless Telecommunications Worldwide<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Springer<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Wally H.W.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Tuttlebee<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-3-540-19970-0<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Personal Wireless Communication with DECT and PWT<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Artech<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John A.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Phillips<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Mac Namee, Gerard<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-89006-872-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://einstein.informatik.uni-oldenburg.de/rechnernetze/seite24.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rechnernetze – The DECT Standard<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2007-03-13<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2008-12-29<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Prof. Dr. W. Kowalk<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>DECT telephones</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dect.org/'>DECT Forum</link><space/>at dect.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.etsi.org/WebSite/Technologies/DECT.aspx'>DECT information</link><space/>at<space/><link><target>ETSI</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.etsi.org/website/newsandevents/2007_05_ng_dect.aspx'>DECT reaches a New Generation</link><space/>at dect.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dectweb.com/'>DECTWeb.com</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://dect.osmocom.org/'>Open source implementation of a DECT stack</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Internet access</target></template><template><target>Telecommunications</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Broadband</target></link><link><target>Category:Local loop</target></link><link><target>Category:Mobile telecommunications standards</target></link><link><target>Category:Software-defined radio</target></link></paragraph></article>