<article title='Brion_Gysin'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="name"><space/>Brion Gysin
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Brion Gysin.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>John Clifford Brian Gysin 
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>19 January 1916
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Taplow]], England
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1986|7|13|1916|1|19|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>Paris, France
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>painter, writer, poet
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>British/Canadian
</arg><arg name="movement"><space/>[[Beat Generation|Beat]], [[Postmodern]]
</arg></template><bold>Brion Gysin</bold><space/>(19 January 1916 13 July 1986) was a<space/><link><target>Painting</target><part>painter</part></link>, writer,<space/><link><target>sound poet</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>performance artist</target></link><space/>born in<space/><link><target>Taplow</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Buckinghamshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Geiger"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Geiger<space/></arg><arg name="first">John<space/></arg><arg name="title">Nothing Is True - Everything Is Permitted: The Life of Brion Gysin<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Disinformation Company<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages">130<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-932857-12-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He is best known for his discovery of the<space/><link><target>cut-up technique</target></link>, used by his friend, the novelist<space/><link><target>William S. Burroughs</target></link>. With the engineer<space/><link><target>Ian Sommerville (technician)</target><part>Ian Sommerville</part></link><space/>he invented the<space/><link><target>Dreamachine</target></link>, a flicker device designed as an art object to be viewed with the eyes closed. It was in painting and drawing, however, that Gysin devoted his greatest efforts, creating<space/><link><target>calligraphic</target></link><space/>works inspired by the cursive<space/><link><target>Japanese calligraphy</target><part>Japanese &quot;grass&quot; script</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arabic script</target></link>. Burroughs later stated that &quot;Brion Gysin was the only man I ever respected.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Burroughs, William. &quot;Introduction.&quot; in<space/><italics>Man from Nowhere: Storming the Citadels of Enlightenment with William Burroughs and Brion Gysin</italics>. Ambrose, Joe, Frank Rynne, Terry Wilson. Dublin: Sublimin, 1992, n.p.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Early years</heading><paragraph>John Clifford Brian Gysin was born at Taplow House, England, a Canadian military hospital. His mother, Stella Margaret Martin, was a Canadian from<space/><link><target>Deseronto, Ontario</target></link>. His father, Leonard Gysin, a captain with the<space/><link><target>Canadian Expeditionary Force</target></link>, was killed in action eight months after his son's birth. Stella returned to Canada and settled in<space/><link><target>Edmonton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Alberta</target></link><space/>where her son became &quot;the only Catholic day-boy at an Anglican boarding school&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. John Geiger's biographical essay on Gysin titled, 'Brion Gysin: His Life and Times' in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning into the Multimedia Age</italics>, ed. Jos Frez Kuri (London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 2003), p. 201.</extension><space/>Graduating at fifteen, Gysin was sent to<space/><link><target>Downside School</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Stratton-on-the-Fosse</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Bath, Somerset</target><part>Bath</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Somerset</target></link><space/>in England, a prestigious college run by the Benedictines and known as &quot;the Eton of Catholic public schools&quot;. Despite attending a Catholic school, Gysin became an atheist.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Nothing Is True-Everything is Permitted: The Life of Brion Gysin</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Red Wheel/Weiser</arg><arg name="isbn">9781609258719</arg><arg name="page">5</arg><arg name="author">John Geiger</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2013</arg><arg name="quote">Brion's view of Creating soon changed. By age fifteen he was an avowed atheist attending St. Joseph's Catholic High School.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Surrealism</heading><paragraph>In 1934, he moved to Paris to study<space/><italics>La Civilisation Franaise</italics>, an open course given at the<space/><link><target>University of Paris</target><part>Sorbonne</part></link><space/>where he made literary and artistic contacts through Marie Berthe Aurenche,<space/><link><target>Max Ernst</target></link>'s second wife.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fmmdmv">Cf. John Geiger, 'Brion Gysin: His Life and Times' in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning into the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 204.</extension><space/>He joined the Surrealist Group and began frequenting<space/><link><target>Valentine Hugo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Leonor Fini</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Salvador Dal</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Picasso</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dora Maar</target></link>. A year later, he had his first exhibition at the<space/><italics>Galerie Quatre Chemins</italics><space/>in Paris with Ernst, Picasso,<space/><link><target>Hans Arp</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hans Bellmer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Victor Brauner</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Giorgio de Chirico</target></link>, Dal,<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ren Magritte</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Man Ray</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Yves Tanguy</target></link>. On the day of the preview, however, he was expelled from the Surrealist Group by<space/><link><target>Andr Breton</target></link>, who ordered the poet<space/><link><target>Paul luard</target></link><space/>to take down his pictures. Gysin was 19 years old. His biographer, John Geiger, suggests the arbitrary expulsion &quot;had the effect of a curse. Years later, he blamed other failures on the Breton incident. It gave rise to conspiracy theories about the powerful interests who seek control of the art world. He gave various explanations for the expulsion, the more elaborate involving 'insubordination' or<space/><italics>lse majest</italics><space/>towards Breton&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fmmdmv"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>After World War II</heading><paragraph>After serving in the U.S. army during World War II, Gysin published a biography of<space/><link><target>Josiah Henson</target><part>Josiah &quot;Uncle Tom&quot; Henson</part></link><space/>titled,<space/><italics>To Master, a Long Goodnight: The History of Slavery in Canada</italics><space/>(1946). A gifted draughtsman, he took an 18-month course learning the Japanese language (including calligraphy) that would greatly influence his artwork. In 1949, he was among the first<space/><link><target>Fulbright Fellow</target><trail>s</trail></link>. His goal: to research the history of slavery at the University of Bordeaux and in the<space/><link><target>Archivo de Indias</target></link><space/>in Seville, Spain, a project that he later abandoned. He moved to<space/><link><target>Tangier</target></link>, Morocco after visiting the city with novelist and composer<space/><link><target>Paul Bowles</target></link><space/>in 1950.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Morocco and the Beat Hotel</heading><paragraph>In 1954 in Tangier, Gysin opened a restaurant called The 1001 Nights, with his friend<space/><link><target>Mohamed Hamri</target></link>, who was the cook. Gysin hired the<space/><link><target>Master Musicians of Jajouka</target></link><space/>from the village of Jajouka to perform alongside entertainment that included acrobats, a dancing boy and fire eaters.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene, Michelle,<space/><italics>The Dream at the End of the World</italics>, (New York, 1991), p. 123, p. 201</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Geiger, John,<space/><italics>Nothing is True, Everything is Permitted: the Life of Brion Gysin</italics>, (New York, 2005), p. 103</extension><space/>The musicians performed there for an international clientele that included William S. Burroughs. Gysin lost the business in 1958,<extension extension_name='ref'>In his essay &quot;Cut-Ups: A Project for Disastrous Success,&quot; Gysin explains that &quot;on January 5, 1958, I lost the business over a signature given to a friendly American couple who 'wanted to help me out.' I was out with the shirt on my back.&quot; in<space/><italics>A Williams Burroughs Reader</italics>, ed. John Calder (London: Picador, 1982), p. 276.</extension><space/>and the restaurant closed permanently. That same year, Gysin returned to Paris, taking lodgings in a flophouse located at 9 rue Gt-le-Coeur that would become famous as the<space/><link><target>Beat Hotel</target></link>. Working on a drawing, he discovered a<space/><link><target>Dada</target></link><space/>technique by accident:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>William Burroughs and I first went into techniques of writing, together, back in room No. 15 of the Beat Hotel during the cold Paris spring of 1958... Burroughs was more intent on Scotch-taping his photos together into one great continuum on the wall, where scenes faded and slipped into one another, than occupied with editing the monster manuscript...<space/><italics><link><target>Naked Lunch</target></link></italics><space/>appeared and Burroughs disappeared. He kicked his habit with<space/><link><target>Apomorphine</target></link><space/>and flew off to London to see Dr Dent, who had first turned him on to the cure. While cutting a mount for a drawing in room No. 15, I sliced through a pile of newspapers with my<space/><link><target>Stanley knife</target><part>Stanley blade</part></link><space/>and thought of what I had said to Burroughs some six months earlier about the necessity for turning painters' techniques directly into writing. I picked up the raw words and began to piece together texts that later appeared as &quot;First Cut-Ups&quot; in<space/><italics>Minutes to Go</italics><space/>(Two Cities, Paris 1960).<extension extension_name='ref'>Brion Gysin:<space/><italics>Cut-Ups: A Project for Disastrous Success</italics>, published in<space/><italics>Evergreen Review</italics><space/>and much later in<space/><italics>[Brion Gysin] Let the Mice In</italics>, Something Else Press, West Clover 1973; also in the<space/><italics>A Williams Burroughs Reader</italics>, John Calder (editor), Picador, London 1982, p. 272.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When Burroughs returned from London in September 1959, Gysin not only shared his discovery with his friend but the new techniques he had developed for it. Burroughs then put the techniques to use while completing<space/><italics><link><target>Naked Lunch</target></link></italics><space/>and the experiment dramatically changed the landscape of<space/><link><target>American literature</target></link>. Gysin helped Burroughs with the editing of several of his novels including<space/><italics><link><target>Interzone (book)</target><part>Interzone</part></link></italics>, and wrote a script for a film version of<space/><italics>Naked Lunch</italics>, which was never produced. The pair collaborated on a large manuscript for<space/><link><target>Grove Press</target></link><space/>titled<space/><italics><link><target>The Third Mind</target></link></italics><space/>but it was determined that it would be impractical to publish it as originally envisioned. The book later published under that title incorporates little of this material. Interviewed for<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics><space/>in 1997, Burroughs explained that Gysin was &quot;the only man that I've ever respected in my life. I've admired people, I've liked them, but he's the only man I've ever respected.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Guardian</italics>, January 18, 1997.</extension><space/>In 1969, Gysin completed his finest novel,<space/><italics><link><target>The Process (novel)</target><part>The Process</part></link></italics>, a work judged by critic Robert Palmer as &quot;a classic of 20th century modernism&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>From Palmer's forward to the novel published by The Overlook Press in 1987.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A consummate innovator, Gysin altered the cut-up technique to produce what he called permutation poems in which a single phrase was repeated several times with the words rearranged in a different order with each reiteration. An example of this is &quot;I don't dig work, man/Man, work I don't dig.&quot; Many of these permutations were derived using a random sequence generator in an early computer program written by<space/><link><target>Ian Sommerville (technician)</target><part>Ian Sommerville</part></link>. Commissioned by the<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>in 1960 to produce material for broadcast, Gysin's results included &quot;Pistol Poem&quot;, which was created by recording a gun firing at different distances and then splicing the sounds. That year, the piece was subsequently used as a theme for the Paris performance of<space/><link><target>Le Domaine Poetique</target></link>, a showcase for experimental works by people like Gysin,<space/><link><target>Franois Dufrne</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bernard Heidsieck</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Henri Chopin</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>With Sommerville, he built the<space/><link><target>Dreamachine</target></link><space/>in 1961. Described as &quot;the first art object to be seen with the eyes closed&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted on coverflap of<space/><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>.</extension><space/>the flicker device uses<space/><link><target>alpha waves</target></link><space/>in the 8-16<space/><link><target>Hertz</target><part>Hz</part></link><space/>range to produce a change of consciousness in receptive viewers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Later years</heading><paragraph>He also worked extensively with noted<space/><link><target>jazz</target></link><space/>soprano saxophonist<space/><link><target>Steve Lacy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>He recorded an album in 1986 with French musician Ramuntcho Matta, featuring himself singing/rapping his own texts, with performances by<space/><link><target>Don Cherry (jazz)</target><part>Don Cherry</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Elli Medeiros</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Steve Lacy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lizzy Mercier Descloux</target></link><space/>and more. The album was reissued on CD in 1993 by<space/><link><target>Crammed Discs</target></link>, under the title<space/><italics>Self-Portrait Jumping</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>As a joke, Gysin contributed a recipe for<space/><link><target>cannabis (drug)</target><part>marijuana</part></link><space/>fudge to a cookbook by<space/><link><target>Alice B. Toklas</target></link>; it was unintentionally included for publication, becoming famous under the name<space/><link><target>Alice B. Toklas brownie</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Biographer John Geiger writes that Gysin's restaurant,<space/><italics>The 1001 Nights</italics><space/>provided him &quot;with an entre into Tangiers society. His Moroccan culinary delights even merited an entry in Alice B. Toklas's famous cookbook, with a recipe for hashish fudge. Toklas, however, had no idea what the mysterious ingredient - cannabis - was, protesting later 'of course I didn't know the Latin name'.&quot; Cf. John Geiger, 'Brion Gysin: His Life and Times' in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning into the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 213.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A heavily edited version of his novel,<space/><italics>The Last Museum</italics>, was published posthumously in 1986 by<space/><link><target>Faber &amp; Faber</target></link><space/>(London) and by<space/><link><target>Grove Press</target></link><space/>(New York).</paragraph><paragraph>Made an American Commander of the French<space/><link><target>Ordre des Arts et des Lettres</target></link><space/>in 1985, Gysin died of<space/><link><target>lung cancer</target></link><space/>a year later, on July 13, 1986. An obituary by Robert Palmer published in<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>fittingly described him as a man who &quot;threw off the sort of ideas that ordinary artists would parlay into a lifetime career, great clumps of ideas, as casually as a locomotive throws off sparks&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. John Geiger, 'Brion Gysin: His Life and Times' in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning into the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 227.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Burroughs on the Gysin cut-up</heading><paragraph>In a 1966 interview by Conrad Knickerbocker for<space/><link><target>The Paris Review</target></link>, William S. Burroughs explained that Brion Gysin was, to his knowledge, &quot;the first to create cut-ups&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><paragraph>INTERVIEWER: How did you become interested in the cut-up technique?</paragraph><paragraph>BURROUGHS: A friend, Brion Gysin, an American poet and painter, who has lived in Europe for thirty years, was, as far as I know, the first to create cut-ups. His cut-up poem,<space/><italics>Minutes to Go</italics>, was broadcast by the BBC and later published in a pamphlet. I was in Paris in the summer of 1960; this was after the publication there of<space/><italics>Naked Lunch</italics>. I became interested in the possibilities of this technique, and I began experimenting myself. Of course, when you think of it,<space/><italics><link><target>The Waste Land</target></link></italics><space/>was the first great cut-up collage, and Tristan Tzara had done a bit along the same lines.<space/><link><target>Dos Passos</target></link><space/>used the same idea in 'The Camera Eye' sequences in<space/><italics><link><target>U.S.A. trilogy</target><part>USA</part></link></italics>. I felt I had been working toward the same goal; thus it was a major revelation to me when I actually saw it being done.<extension extension_name='ref'>Knickerbocker, Conrad, Burroughs, Williams S., 'The Paris Review Interview with William S. Burroughs' in<space/><italics>A Williams Burroughs Reader</italics>, ed. John Calder (London: Picador, 1982), p. 263.</extension></paragraph></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Influence</heading><paragraph>According to Jos Frez Kuri, author of<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics><space/>(2003) and co-curator of a major retrospective of the artist's work at The Edmonton Art Gallery in 1998, Gysin's wide range of &quot;radical ideas would become a source of inspiration for artists of the<space/><link><target>Beat Generation</target></link>, as well as for their successors (among them<space/><link><target>David Bowie</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mick Jagger</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Keith Haring</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Laurie Anderson</target></link>)&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kuri,<space/><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, coverflap.</extension><space/>Other artists include<space/><link><target>Genesis P-Orridge</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Zorn</target></link><space/>(as displayed on the 2013's<space/><link><target>Dreamachines</target></link><space/>album) and<space/><link><target>Brian Jones</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Quotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Copy section to Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Writing is fifty years behind painting.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Gysin quoted in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, ed. Jos Frez Kuri (Thames &amp; Hudson, London, 2003), p. 153.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;I enjoy inventing things out of fun. After all, life is a game, not a career.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 4.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;I view life as a fortuitous collaboration ascribable to the fact that one finds oneself at the right place at the same time.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 9.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;The Way Is Nor This Nor That.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 10.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Man is a bad animal....&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>https://www.goodreads.com/author/quotes/38278.Brion_Gysin</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Writers don't own their words. Since when do words belong to anybody? 'Your very own words,' indeed! And who are you?&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>- 'Cut-Ups Self-Explained' in<space/><italics>Brion Gysin Let the Mice In</italics><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 153.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;I may write only what I know in space: I am that I am.&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>-<space/><italics>Notes on Painting</italics><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 96.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;He covered tons of paper with his words and made them his very own words... he branded them like cattle he rustled out there on the free ranges of Literature... Used by another writer who was attempting cut-ups, one single word of Burroughs vocabulary could ruin a whole barrel of good everyday words, run the literary rot right through them. One sniff of that prose and you'd say, 'Why, that's a Burroughs.' &quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>- on the prose of William S. Burroughs in<space/><italics>Here to Go: Planet R-101</italics><space/>(Interviews with Terry Wilson)<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 159.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Of course the sands of Present Time are running out from under our feet. And why not? The Great Conundrum: 'What are we here for?' is all that ever held us here in the first place. Fear. The answer to the Riddle of the Ages has actually been out in the street since the First Step in Space. Who runs may read but few people run fast enough. What are we here for? Does the great metaphysical nut revolve around that? Well, I'll crack it for you, right now. What are we here for? We are here to go!&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>-<space/><italics>The Process</italics><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, p. 49.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Language is an abominable misunderstanding which makes up a part of matter. The painters and the physicists have treated matter pretty well. The poets have hardly touched it. In March 1958, when I was living at the Beat Hotel, I proposed to Burroughs to at least make available to literature the means that painters have been using for fifty years. Cut words into pieces and scramble them. You'll hear someone draw a bow-string. Who runs may read, To read better, practice your running. Speed is entirely up to us, since machines have delivered us from the horse. Henceforth the question is to deliver us from that other so-called superior animal, man. It's not worth it to chase out the merchants: their temple is dedicated to the unsuitable lie of the value of the Unique. The crime of separation gave birth to the idea of the Unique which would not be separate. In painting, matter has seen everything: from sand to stuffed goats. Disfigured more and more, the image has been geometrically multiplied to a dizzying degree. A snow of advertising could fall from the sky, and only collector babies and the chimpanzees who make abstract paintings would bother to pick one up.&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>-<space/><italics>Cut-Ups: A Project for Disastrous Success</italics></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;I Am the Artist when I am Open. When I am closed I am Brion Gysin.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>, back cover.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Selected bibliography</heading><paragraph>Gysin is the subject of John Geiger's biography,<space/><italics>Nothing Is True Everything Is Permitted: The Life of Brion Gysin</italics>, and features in<space/><italics>Chapel of Extreme Experience: A Short History of Stroboscopic Light and the Dream Machine</italics>, also by Geiger.<space/><italics>Man From Nowhere: Storming the Citadels of Enlightenment with William Burroughs and Brion Gysin</italics>, a biographical study of Burroughs and Gysin with a collection of homages to Gysin, was authored by Joe Ambrose,<space/><link><target>Frank Rynne</target></link>, and Terry Wilson with contributions by<space/><link><target>Marianne Faithfull</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Cale</target></link>, William S. Burroughs,<space/><link><target>John Giorno</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Stanley Booth</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bill Laswell</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mohamed Hamri</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Keith Haring</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Bowles</target></link>. A monograph on Gysin was published in 2003 by Thames and Hudson.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Works</heading><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-2</target></template><bold>Prose</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>To Master, A Long Goodnight: The History of Slavery in Canada</italics><space/>(1946)</listitem><listitem><italics>Minutes to Go</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Exterminator</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Process (novel)</target><part>The Process</part></link></italics><space/>(1969)</listitem><listitem><italics>Brion Gysin Let The Mice In</italics><space/>(1973)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Third Mind</italics><space/>(1978)</listitem><listitem><italics>Here To Go: Planet R-101</italics><space/>(first published 1982)</listitem><listitem><italics>Stories</italics><space/>(1984)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Last Museum</italics><space/>(1985)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Radio</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Pistol Poem</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem><italics>Permutations</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem><italics>I Am</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem><italics>No Poets</italics><space/>(1962)</listitem><listitem><italics>Junk is No Good Baby</italics><space/>(1962)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-2</target></template><bold>Cinema</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Scenario to<space/><link><target>Naked Lunch</target></link></italics><space/>(1973)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Music</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Songs</italics><space/>(with Steve Lacy) (rec. 1981)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Discogs release</target><arg name="id">1100307</arg><arg>Songs</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Junk</italics><space/>(1985)</listitem><listitem><italics>Self-Portrait Jumping</italics><space/>(with Ramuntcho Matta, Don Cherry, Steve Lacy) (1993)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Painting</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Les deux faux interlocuteurs</italics>,<space/><italics>Gradiva Rediviva Zoe Bertgang</italics>, and<space/><italics>Signe dans le paysage</italics><space/>(Surrealist ink drawings, 1935)</listitem><listitem><italics>Sahara Sand</italics><space/>(1958)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Songs of Marrakech</italics><space/>(1959)</listitem><listitem><italics>Unit II pink, Unit III yellow, Unit IV orange, Unit V blue</italics><space/>(1961)</listitem><listitem><italics>Francis in the Beat Hotel</italics><space/>(1962)</listitem><listitem><italics>For a Stained-Glass Window in Rheims</italics><space/>(1963)</listitem><listitem><italics>Roller Poem</italics><space/>(1971)</listitem><listitem><italics>Calligraffiti of Fire</italics><space/>(1986)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><heading level='3'>Print</heading><paragraph><xhtml:div style="font-size: 95%"><heading level='4'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Gysin, Brion.<space/><italics>To Master, A Long Goodnight: The History of Slavery in Canada</italics>. Creative Age Press, New York 1946.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Minutes to Go</italics><space/>(with<space/><link><target>Sinclair Beiles</target></link>, William S. Burroughs,<space/><link><target>Gregory Corso</target></link>). Two Cities Editions, Paris 1960.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>The Exterminator</italics><space/>(with William S. Burroughs). Auerhahn Press, San Francisco 1960.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics><link><target>The Process (novel)</target><part>The Process</part></link></italics>. Doubleday, New York 1969. Overlook Press, New York 1987.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Brion Gysin Let The Mice In</italics><space/>(with William S. Burroughs, Ian Sommerville). Ed. Jan Herman. Something Else Press, West Glover, VT, 1973.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>The Third Mind</italics><space/>(with William S. Burroughs). Viking, New York 1978.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Here To Go: Planet R-101.</italics><space/>Interviews with Terry Wilson. Quartet Books, London 1982. Creation Books, London 2003.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Stories</italics>. Inkblot Publications, Oakland 1984.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>The Last Museum</italics>.<space/><link><target>Grove Press</target></link>, New York 1986.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Who Runs May Read</italics>. Inkblot/Xochi, Oakland/Brisbane: Inkblot/Xochi, 2000.</listitem><listitem>.<space/><italics>Back in No Time: The Brion Gysin Reader</italics>. Ed. Jason Weiss. Wesleyan University Press, 2001.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Secondary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Kuri, Jos Frez, ed.<space/><italics>Brion Gysin: Tuning in to the Multimedia Age</italics>. London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 2003. ISBN 0-500-28438-5</listitem><listitem>Geiger, John.<space/><italics>Nothing Is True Everything Is Permitted: The Life of Brion Gysin</italics>. Disinformation Company, 2005. ISBN 1-932857-12-5</listitem><listitem>Geiger, John.<space/><italics>Chapel of Extreme Experience: A Short History of Stroboscopic Light and the Dream Machine</italics>. Soft Skull Press, 2003.</listitem><listitem>Ambrose, Joe, Frank Rynne, and Terry Wilson.<space/><italics>Man From Nowhere: Storming the Citadels of Enlightenment with William Burroughs and Brion Gysin</italics>. Williamsburg: Autonomedia, 1992</listitem><listitem>Vale, V.<space/><italics>William Burroughs, Brion Gysin, Throbbing Gristle</italics>. San Francisco: V/Search, 1982. ISBN 0-9650469-1-5</listitem></list></xhtml:div></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Asemic writing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brian Jones Presents The Pipes Of Pan At Jajouka</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>worldcat id</target><arg name="id">lccn-n79-26860</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ubu.com/sound/gysin.html'>UBU Sound</link><space/>Article on Brion Gysin</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.extrageographic.org/magazine/arts/2005/041001_brion_gysin_art.html'>Extrageographic Magazine article</link><space/>What Does Brion Gysin's Art Mean?</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.23degrees.net/cutup/'>Cutup</link><space/>The Burroughs &amp; Gysin Non-Linear Adding Machine</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jajouka.com/'>The Master Musicians of Jajouka led by Bachir Attar</link><space/>Official website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.joujouka.net/'>Master Musicians of Joujouka</link><space/>Official website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.villagevoice.com/books/0149,ashman,30459,10.html'>Village Voice</link><space/>Review of<space/><italics>Back in No Time: A Brion Gysin Reader</italics><space/>(2001)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.synergeticpress.com/fictiontitlesnew.html#perilous'>Perilous Passages</link><space/>Terry Wilson's account of his &quot;lifetime apprenticeship&quot; with Brion Gysin</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jajouka.com/williamsburroughs.html'>William Burroughs's letter</link><space/>on Gysin and Jajouka</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.inter-zone.org/dm.html'>Interzone documentation</link><space/>on the Dream Machine and free Dream Machine plans</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.flickerflicker.com'>Official website of FLicKeR</link><space/>a film on Brion Gysin and the Dream Machine based on Geiger's book</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eyewithwings.net/nechvatal/ThirdMind/wwwTHIRDMIND.htm'>''The Third Mind at Le Palais de Tokyo''</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Joseph Nechvatal</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.crammed.be/index.php?id=37&amp;amp;rel_id=52'>A page on the ''Self-Portrait Jumping'' album, including audio excerpts</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.briongysin.ca'>Brion Gysin Tribute</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Gysin, Brion
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Canadian artist
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>January 19, 1916
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Taplow]], England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>July 13, 1986
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Paris, France
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Gysin, Brion</target></template><link><target>Category:1916 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1986 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian people of English descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Beat Generation writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Contemporary painters</target></link><link><target>Category:William S. Burroughs</target></link><link><target>Category:People educated at Downside School</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Taplow</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian atheists</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century Canadian painters</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian male novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:Commandeurs of the Ordre des Arts et des Lettres</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century Canadian novelists</target></link></paragraph></article>