<article title='Arbor_Day'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target><arg>Arbor Day (disambiguation)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox holiday</target><arg name="holiday_name">Arbor Day<br/>Arbour Day
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>ArborDay2009treeplanters.JPG</arg><arg>right</arg><arg>250px</arg><arg>thumb
</arg><arg name="caption">Volunteers planting a tree for Arbor Day ([[Rochester, Minnesota]], 2009)
</arg><arg name="duration"><space/>1 day
</arg><arg name="frequency">annual
</arg><arg name="observedby">Multiple countries
</arg><arg name="celebrations">Planting and caring for trees, educating about the importance of trees.
</arg><arg name="originated">[[Nebraska City, Nebraska]]
</arg><arg name="type">Cultural
</arg><arg name="significance">A holiday celebrating trees.
</arg><arg name="relatedto">[[Greenery Day]] ([[Japan]])
</arg><arg name="nickname">
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Arbor Day</bold><space/>(or<space/><bold>Arbour</bold>; from the Latin<space/><italics>arbor</italics>, meaning tree) is a<space/><link><target>secular holiday</target><part>holiday</part></link><space/>in which individuals and groups are encouraged to plant and care for<space/><link><target>tree</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Today, many countries observe such a holiday. Though usually observed in the spring, the date varies, depending on<space/><link><target>climate</target></link><space/>and suitable planting season.<template><target>toc limit</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Fiesta del arbol.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The naturalist<space/><link><target>Miguel Herrero Uceda</target></link><space/>at the monument to the first Arbor Day in the world,<space/><link><target>Villanueva de la Sierra</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Spain</target></link>) 1805.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>First Arbor Day in the world</heading><paragraph>The Spanish village of Mondoedo held the first documented arbor plantation festival in the world organized by its mayor in 1594. The place remains as Alameda de los Remedios and it is still planted with lime and horsenut trees. A humble granite and a bronze plate recalls the event. Additionally the small Spanish village of Villanueva de la Sierra is the town where was held the first modern Arbor Day, an initiative launched in 1805, by the local priest with the enthusiastic support of the entire population.[1]</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg>While Napoleon was ravaging Europe with his ambition in this village in the Sierra de Gata lived a priest, don Ramón Vacas Roxo, which, according to the chronicles, "convinced of the importance of trees for health, hygiene, decoration, nature, environment and customs, decides to plant trees and give a festive air. The festival began on Carnival Tuesday with the ringing of two bells of the church, and the Middle and the Big. After the Mass, and even coated with church ornaments, don Ramón, accompanied by clergies, teachers and a large number of neighbours, planted the first tree, a poplar, in the place known as Valley of the Ejido. Tree plantations continued by Arroyada and Fuente de la Mora. Afterwards, there was a feast, and did not miss the dance. The party and plantations lasted three days. He drafted a manifesto in defence of the trees that was sent to surrounding towns to spread the love and respect for nature, and also he advised to make tree plantations in their localities.</arg><arg>Miguel Herrero Uceda</arg><arg>Arbor Day</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>First American Arbor Day</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Birdsey Northrop.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Birdsey Northrop</part></link>The first American Arbor Day was originated in<space/><link><target>Nebraska City, Nebraska</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Julius Sterling Morton</target><part>J. Sterling Morton</part></link>. On April 10, 1872, an estimated one million trees were planted in<space/><link><target>Nebraska</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="history"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Birdsey Northrop of<space/><link><target>Connecticut</target></link><space/>was responsible for globalizing it when he visited Japan in 1883 and delivered his Arbor Day and Village Improvement message. In that same year, the<space/><link><target>American Forestry Association</target></link><space/>made Northrop the Chairman of the committee to campaign for Arbor Day nationwide. He also brought his enthusiasm for Arbor Day to Australia, Canada, and Europe.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Arbor Day"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">Birdsey Grant Northrop</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ct.gov/dep/lib/dep/forestry/urban_forestry/arborday.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-04-25</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>McCreight and Roosevelt</heading><paragraph>Beginning in 1906,<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania</target></link><space/>conservationist<space/><link><target>Major Israel McCreight</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>DuBois, Pennsylvania</target></link>, argued that President<space/><link><target>Theodore Roosevelt</target></link>s conservation speeches were limited to businessmen in the lumber industry and recommended a campaign of youth education and a national policy on conservation education.<extension extension_name='ref'>M.I. McCreight, Theodore Roosevelt and Conservation Why: A Thirty-Four Year Moratorium on Unpublished Records (1940), Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, at p.12, Hereinafter cited &quot;Theodore Roosevelt and Conservation Why&quot;.</extension><space/>McCreight urged President Roosevelt to make a public statement to school children about trees and the destruction of American forests. Conservationist<space/><link><target>Gifford Pinchot</target></link>, Chief of the<space/><link><target>United States Forest Service</target></link>, embraced McCreights recommendations and asked the President to speak to the public school children of the United States about conservation. On April 15, 1907, Roosevelt issued an &quot;Arbor Day Proclamation to the School Children of the United States&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=oWgjAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;dq=theodore%20roosevelt%20proclamation%20to%20school%20children%201906%201907&amp;amp;pg=RA4-PA9#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>Arbor Day Proclamation to the School Children of the United States</link></extension><space/>about the importance of trees and that forestry deserves to be taught in U.S. schools. Pinchot wrote McCreight, &quot;we shall all be indebted to you for having made the suggestion.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Theodore Roosevelt and Conservation Why&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Around the world</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Arbor day in Algeria.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Arbor Day in<space/><link><target>Algeria</target></link></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph>National Schools Tree Day is held on the last Friday of July for schools and National Tree Day the last Sunday in July throughout Australia. Many states have Arbor Day although only Victoria has Arbor Week, which was suggested by Premier<space/><link><target>Dick Hamer</target></link><space/>in the 1980s. Arbor Day has been observed in Australia since 20 June 1889.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Belgium</heading><paragraph>International Day of Treeplanting is celebrated in<space/><link><target>Flanders</target></link><space/>on or around 21 March as a theme-day/educational-day/observance, not as public holidays. Tree planting is sometimes combined with awareness campaigns of the fight against cancer:<space/><italics>Kom Op Tegen Kanker</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Brazil</heading><paragraph>The Arbor Day (Dia da rvore) is celebrated on September 21. It's not a national holiday. However, schools nationwide celebrate this day with environment-related activities, namely tree planting.</paragraph><heading level='3'>British Virgin Islands</heading><paragraph>Arbour Day is celebrated on November 22. It is sponsored by the National Parks Trust of the Virgin Islands. Activities include an annual national Arbour Day Poetry Competition and tree planting ceremonies throughout the territory.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cambodia</heading><paragraph>Cambodia celebrates arbor day on 9 July with a tree planting ceremony attended by the king.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.akp.gov.kh/?p</arg><arg name="title">Cambodian King Attends the Celebration of Annual Arbor Day (July 9)<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">9 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="website">Agenche Kampuchea Presse<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Agenche Kampuchea Presse<space/></arg><arg name="access-date">11 October 2015<space/></arg><arg name="quote"></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph>Founded by Don Clark of Schomberg, Ontario for his wife Margret Clark in 1906. In Canada, Maple Leaf Day falls on the last Wednesday in September during National Forest Week.<space/><link><target>Ontario</target></link><space/>celebrates Arbor Week from the last Friday in April to the first Sunday in May.<space/><link><target>Nova Scotia</target></link><space/>celebrates Arbor Day on the Thursday during National Forest Week, which is the first full week in May. Prince Edward Island celebrates Arbor Day on the 3rd Friday in May during Arbor Week.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.arborday.org/arborday/arborDayDatesInternational.cfm'>&quot;Arbor Day Around The World&quot;. The Arbor Day Foundation. 20 July 2010</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Central African Republic</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on July 20.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>China</heading><paragraph>In 1981, the fourth session of the Fifth<space/><link><target>National People's Congress</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>China</target><part>People's Republic of China</part></link><space/>adopted the Resolution on the Unfolding of a Nationwide Voluntary Tree-planting Campaign. This resolution established the Arbor Day (<template><target>zh</target><arg name="s">植树节</arg></template>) and stipulated that every able-bodied citizen between the ages of 11 and 60 should plant three to five trees per year or do the equivalent amount of work in seedling, cultivation, tree tending or other services. Supporting documentation instructs all units to report population statistics to the local afforestation committees as the basis for workload allocation. Moreover, those failing to do their duty are expected to make up planting requirements, provide funds equivalent to the value of labor required or pay heavy fines. Therefore, the tree-planting campaign is actually compulsory,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2010</arg></template><space/>or at least obligatory (that is, an obligation to the community). The &quot;voluntary&quot; in the title referred to the fact that the tree-planters would &quot;volunteer&quot; their labour. The People's Republic of China celebrates Arbor Day on March 12, a day founded by Lin Daoyang, continue to use following the date of Arbor Day of Republic of China.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Costa Rica</heading><paragraph>&quot;Da del rbol&quot; is on June 15.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Egypt</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day is on January 15.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Germany</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day (&quot;Tag des Baumes&quot;) is on April 25. First celebration was in 1952.</paragraph><heading level='3'>India</heading><paragraph><link><target>Van Mahotsav</target></link><space/>is an annual pan-Indian tree planting festival, occupying a week in the month of July. During this event millions of trees are planted. It was initiated in 1950 by K. M. Munshi, the then Union Minister for Agriculture and Food to create an enthusiasm in the mind of the populace for the conservation of forests and planting of trees.</paragraph><paragraph>The name Van Mahotsava (the festival of trees) originated in July 1947 after a successful tree-planting drive was undertaken in<space/><link><target>Delhi</target></link>, in which national leaders like<space/><link><target>Jawaharlal Nehru</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dr Rajendra Prasad</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Abul Kalam Azad</target></link><space/>participated. Paryawaran Sachetak Samiti, a leading<space/><link><target>environmental movement</target><part>environmental</part></link><space/><link><target>organization</target></link><space/>conducts mass events &amp; concrete activities on this special day celebration each year. The week was simultaneously celebrated in a number of states in the country.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Iran</heading><paragraph>In Iran it is known as National Tree Planting Day. By<space/><link><target>Solar Hijri calendar</target></link>, it is on the 15th day of month Esfand which usually corresponds with March 5.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>This day is the first day of the Natural Recyclable Resources week (March 5 to 12).<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>This is the time in which the saplings of the all kinds in terms of different climates of different parts of Iran would be shared among the people. They also are going to be taught the ways of planting trees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="iran-tr-plnt-tbn"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Tree Planting Day</arg><arg name="url">http://english.tebyan.net/newindex.aspx?pid</arg><arg name="work">tebyan.net</arg><arg name="publisher">Tebyan Cultural and Information Center</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Israel</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:PikiWiki Israel 7673 Environment of Israel.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Tu Bishvat, Israel</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Jewish holiday<space/><link><target>Tu Bishvat</target></link>, the new year for trees, is on the 15th day of the month of<space/><link><target>Shvat</target></link>, which usually falls in January or February. Originally based on the date used to calculate the age of fruit trees for<space/><link><target>Tithe</target><part>tithing</part></link><space/>as mandated in<space/><link><target>Leviticus</target></link><space/>19:2325, the holiday now is most often observed by planting trees, or raising money to plant trees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JEWFAQ"><link type='external' href='http://www.jewfaq.org/holiday8.htm'>''Judaism 101: Tu B'Shevat</link>. Accessed August 20, 2007.</extension><space/>Tu Bishvat is a semi<space/><link><target>Public holidays in Israel</target><part>official holiday in Israel</part></link>, schools are open but Hebrew speaking schools will often go on tree planting excursions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Japan</heading><paragraph>Japan celebrates a similarly themed<space/><link><target>Greenery Day</target></link>, held on May 4. Although it has a similar theme to Arbor Day, its roots lie in celebration of the birthday of<space/><link><target>Emperor of Japan</target><part>Emperor</part></link><space/><link><target>Hirohito</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Kenya</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on April 21. Often people plant palm trees and coconut trees along the Indian Ocean that borders the East coast of Kenya.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Lesotho</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on March 21.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Luxembourg</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is in November since 1991. It is organized by natur&amp;mwelt.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Republic of Congo</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on November 6.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Republic of Macedonia</heading><paragraph>Having in mind the bad condition of the forest fund, and in particular the catastrophic<space/><link><target>wildfires</target></link><space/>which occurred in the summer of 2007, a citizen's initiative for afforestation was started in the<space/><link><target>Republic of Macedonia</target></link>. The campaign by the name 'Tree Day-Plant Your Future' was first organized on 12 March 2008, when an official non-working day was declared and more than 150,000 Macedonians planted 2 million trees in one day (symbolically, one for each citizen). Six million more were planted in November the same year, and another 12,5 million trees in 2009. This has been established as a tradition and takes place every year.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Malawi</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on the 2nd Monday of December.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mexico</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:EPN. Da del rbol.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>President<space/><link><target>Enrique Pea Nieto</target></link><space/>plants a tree in<space/><link><target>Balleza</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chihuahua (state)</target><part>Chihuahua</part></link><space/>to commemorate the ''Da del rbol'' 2013.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Da del rbol</italics><space/>was established in Mexico in 1959 with President<space/><link><target>Adolfo Lpez Mateos</target></link><space/>issuing a decree that it should be observed on the 2nd Thursday of July.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Azteca"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Hoy, Día del Árbol en México</arg><arg name="url">http://www.aztecanoticias.com.mx/notas/sociedad-y-medio-ambiente/160842/hoy-dia-del-arbol-en-mexico</arg><arg name="publisher">Azteca Noticias</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 October 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Mongolia</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on the 2nd Saturday of May and October. It is first National Tree Planting Day was celebrated on 2010-05-08</paragraph><heading level='3'>Namibia</heading><paragraph>Its first Arbor Day was celebrated on October 8 2004.<extension extension_name='ref' name="adatw"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.arborday.org/arborday/arborDayDatesInternational.cfm
</arg><arg name="title">Arbor Day Around The World
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-09-06
</arg><arg name="publisher">Arbor day foundation</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080918063655/http://www.arborday.org/arborday/arbordaydatesinternational.cfm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>18 September 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Netherlands</heading><paragraph>Since conference and of the<space/><link><target>Food and Agriculture Organization</target></link>'s publication<space/><italics><link><target>World Festival of Trees</target></link></italics>, and a resolution of the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>in 1954: &quot;The Conference, recognising the need of arousing mass consciousness of the aesthetic, physical and economic value of trees, recommends a World Festival of Trees to be celebrated annually in each member country on a date suited to local conditions&quot;; it has been adopted by the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>. In 1957, the National Committee Day of Planting Trees/Foundation of National Festival of Trees (<italics>Nationale Boomplantdag</italics>/<italics>Nationale Boomfeestdag</italics>) was created.</paragraph><paragraph>On the third Wednesday in March each year (near the spring equinox), three quarters of Dutch schoolchildren aged 10/11 and Dutch celebrities plant trees. Stichting Nationale Boomfeestdag organizes all the activities in the Netherlands for this day. Some municipalities however plant the trees around 21 September because of the planting season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Boomfeestdag http://www.boomfeestdag.nl/ the organisations address is Spoorlaan 444 5038 CH TILBURG</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2007, the 50th anniversary was celebrated with special golden jubilee-activities.</paragraph><heading level='3'>New Zealand</heading><paragraph><link><target>New Zealand</target></link>'s first Arbor Day planting was in<space/><link><target>Greytown, New Zealand</target><part>Greytown</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Wairarapa</target></link><space/>on 3 July 1890. The first official celebration will take place in<space/><link><target>Wellington</target></link><space/>in August 2012, with the planting of<space/><link><target>pohutukawa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Norfolk pines</target></link><space/>along Thorndon Esplanade.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Born in 1855, Dr<space/><link><target>Leonard Cockayne</target></link><space/>(generally recognised as the greatest botanist who has lived, worked, and died in New Zealand) worked extensively on native plants throughout New Zealand and wrote many notable botanical texts. Even as early as the 1920s he held a vision for school students of New Zealand to be involved in planting native trees and plants in their school grounds. This vision bore fruit and schools in New Zealand have long planted native trees on<space/><bold>Arbor Day</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>Since 1977, New Zealand has celebrated Arbor Day on June 5, which is also<space/><link><target>World Environment Day</target></link>, prior to then Arbor Day, in New Zealand, was celebrated on August 4 which is rather late in the year for tree planting in New Zealand hence the date change.</paragraph><paragraph>What the<space/><link><target>Department of Conservation (New Zealand)</target><part>Department of Conservation</part></link><space/>(<link><target>Department of Conservation (New Zealand)</target><part>DOC</part></link>) does for Arbor Day:Many of DOC's Arbor Day activities focus on ecological restoration projects using native plants to restore habitats that have been damaged or destroyed by humans or invasive pests and weeds. There are great restoration projects underway around New Zealand and many organisations including community groups, landowners, conservation organisations,<space/><link><target>iwi</target></link>, volunteers, schools, local businesses, nurseries and councils are involved in them. These projects are part of a vision to protect and restore the indigenous biodiversity.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Niger</heading><paragraph>Since 1975,<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link><space/>has celebrated Arbor Day as part of its<space/><link><target>Independence Day (Niger)</target><part>Independence Day</part></link>: 3 August. On this day, aiding the fight against<space/><link><target>desertification</target></link>, each Nigerien plants a<space/><link><target>tree</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pakistan</heading><paragraph>National tree plantation day of Pakistan ( ) is celebrated on 18 August.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nation.com.pk/pakistan-news-newspaper-daily-english-online/Regional/Islamabad/11-Aug-2009/August-18-declared-National-Tree-Planting-Day'>18 August declared as NTPD</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Philippines</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day in the Philippines has been institutionalized to be observed every June 25 throughout the nation by planting trees and ornamental plants and other forms of relevant activities. The necessity to promote a healthier ecosystem for the people through the rehabilitation and regreening of the environment was stressed in Proclamation No. 643 that amended Proclamation No. 396 of June 2, 2003. Proclamation No. 396 enjoined the &quot;active participation of all government agencies, including government-owned and controlled corporations, private sector, schools, civil society groups and the citizenry in tree planting activity and declaring June 25, 2003 as<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.gov.ph/banner-artwork/arbor-day/'>Philippines Arbor Day</link>.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>Poland</heading><paragraph>In Poland, Arbor Day is celebrated since 2002. Each year, on October 10. lots of Polish people plant trees as well as participate in events organized by ecological foundations. Moreover, Polish Forest Inspectorates and schools give special lectures and lead ecological awareness campaigns.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Portugal</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day is celebrated on March 21. It's not a national holiday but instead schools nationwide celebrate this day with environment-related activities, namely tree planting.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day was celebrated from 1945 until 2000 in<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>, when the national government extended it to National Arbor Week, which lasts from 17 September.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.plantzafrica.com/miscell/arborweek.htm'>Two trees</link>, one common and one rare, are highlighted to increase public awareness of indigenous trees, while various &quot;greening&quot; activities are undertaken by schools, businesses and other organizations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Sikmogil</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Arbor Day (Sikmogil, ) was a<space/><link><target>Public holidays in South Korea</target><part>public holiday</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link><space/>on April 5 until 2005. The day is still celebrated, though. On non-<link><target>leap year</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the day coincides with<space/><link><target>Hansik</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spain</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Plantando encinas.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Planting holm oaks in<space/><link><target>Pescueza</target></link></part></link>In Spain is usually held on the<space/><link><target>International Forest Day</target></link><space/>on 21 March, but following the 1915 decree spirit that forced to celebrate the Arbor Day throughout Spain, each municipality or collective decides the date for its Arbor Day, usually between February and May. In<space/><link><target>Villanueva de la Sierra</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Extremadura</target></link>), where the first Arbor Day in the world was held in 1805, it is celebrated, as on that occasion, on Tuesday Carnaval. It is a great day in the local festive calendar.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sierradegatadigital.es/articulo/cultura/villanueva-celebra-fiesta-medioambientalista-mas-antigua-mundo/20140225131113012653.html'>The oldest environmentalist festival in the world was celebrated in Villanueva</link>. Sierra de Gata News. February 26, 2014</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As an example of commitment to nature, the small town of<space/><link><target>Pescueza</target></link>, with only 180 inhabitants, organizes every spring a large plantation of holm oaks, which is called the &quot;Festivalino&quot; promoted by city council, several foundations and citizen participation where several thousand people together repopulates naked lands and regaining life. All wrapped up in a fun party atmosphere, joy, music and renew.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herrero Uceda, Miguel y Elisa:<space/><italics>Mi Extremadura</italics>. 2011, pages 147-148</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sri Lanka</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on November 15.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Taiwan</heading><paragraph>Arbor Day () has been a traditional<space/><link><target>Holidays in Taiwan</target><part>holiday</part></link><space/>in the<space/><bold><link><target>Republic of China</target></link></bold><space/>since 1927. In 1914, the founder of the<space/><link><target>Nanjing Agricultural University</target><part>agricultural college at Nanking University</part></link><space/>suggested to the now-defunct Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry that China should imitate the practice in the United States of Arbor Day. The holiday would be held the same day as the<space/><link><target>Qingming Festival</target></link>. However, for unknown reasons, the suggestion was not made through the formal process, so nothing came from this original request. After the successful conclusion of the<space/><link><target>Northern Expedition</target></link>, the now-defunct Ministry of Agriculture and Minerals formally petitioned the<space/><link><target>Executive Yuan</target></link><space/>to establish Arbor Day to commemorate the passing of<space/><link><target>Sun Yat-sen</target><part>Dr. Sun Yat-sen</part></link>, the Father of Modern China. He had been a major advocate of afforestation in his life, because it would increase<space/><link><target>Three Principles of the People</target><part>people's livelihoods</part></link>. The Executive Yuan approved Arbor Day in the spirit of Dr. Sun that year and has since been celebrated on March 12 for this purpose.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tanzania</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on April 1</paragraph><heading level='3'>Uganda</heading><paragraph>National Tree Planting Day is on March 24.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph>First mounted in 1975, National Tree Week is a celebration of the start of the winter tree planting season. Around a million trees are planted each year by schools, community organizations and local authorities.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:2009ArborDayRochesterMinnesota.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>256px</part><part>Arbor Day community festival in<space/><link><target>Rochester, Minnesota</target></link></part></link>Arbor Day was founded in 1872 by<space/><link><target>Julius Sterling Morton</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Nebraska City</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nebraska</target></link>. By the 1920s, each state in the United States had passed public laws that stipulated a certain day to be Arbor Day or Arbor and Bird Day observance.</paragraph><paragraph>National Arbor Day is celebrated every year on the last Friday in April; in<space/><link><target>Nebraska</target></link>, it is a<space/><link><target>civic holiday</target></link>. Each state celebrates its own state holiday. The customary observance is to plant a tree. On the first Arbor Day, April 10, 1872, an estimated one million trees were planted.<extension extension_name='ref' name="history"><link type='external' href='http://www.arborday.org/arborday/history.cfm'>&quot;The History of Arbor Day,&quot;</link>Arborday.org. Accessed: April 26, 2013.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Venezuela</heading><paragraph>Venezuela recognizes &quot;Da del Arbol&quot; on the last Sunday of May.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Trees</arg><arg>Forestry</arg><arg>Environment</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>National Arbor Day Foundation</target><part>Arbor Day Foundation</part></link><space/>(USA)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Earth Day</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Greenery Day</target></link><space/>(Japan)</listitem><listitem><link><target>International Day of Forests</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>National Public Lands Day</target></link><space/>(USA)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of environmental events</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tu Bishvat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>World Water Day</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Arbor Day</arg></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>wikisource</target><arg>Portal:Arbor Day</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arborday.org/arborday/arborDayDatesinternational.cfm'>International Arbor Days</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://landscaping.about.com/od/treeplantingprograms/a/arbor_day_facts.htm'>History of Arbor Day</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lessonplanet.com/ArborDayLessonPlans'>Arbor Day Lesson Plans for the Classroom</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arborday.org'>National Arbor Day Foundation</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arborday.org/arborday/arbordaydates.cfm'>State Arbor Days and state trees</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>gutenberg</target><arg name="no">17645<space/></arg><arg name="name">Arbor Day Leaves – A Complete Programme For Arbor Day Observance, Including Readings, Recitations, Music, and General Information</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Forestry</target><arg name="state">expanded</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:January observances</target></link><link><target>Category:March observances</target></link><link><target>Category:April observances</target></link><link><target>Category:May observances</target></link><link><target>Category:June observances</target></link><link><target>Category:July observances</target></link><link><target>Category:August observances</target></link><link><target>Category:September observances</target></link><link><target>Category:October observances</target></link><link><target>Category:November observances</target></link><link><target>Category:December observances</target></link><link><target>Category:Environmental awareness days</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Nebraska</target></link><link><target>Category:Public holidays in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Otoe County, Nebraska</target></link><link><target>Category:Spring holidays</target></link><link><target>Category:Trees</target></link><link><target>Category:1872 establishments in Nebraska</target></link><link><target>Category:Recurring events established in 1872</target></link><link><target>Category:Urban forestry</target></link><link><target>Category:Forestry in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Reforestation</target></link><link><target>Category:Types of secular holidays</target></link><link><target>Category:Forestry events</target></link></paragraph></article>