<article title='Drag_racing'><paragraph><template><target>redirect2</target><arg>Drag racer</arg><arg>Drag race</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Drag racing (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">November 2007</arg></template><link><target>Image:Tree counting down.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Christmas tree counting down at<space/><link><target>Saskatchewan International Raceway</target><part>SIR</part></link>, outside<space/><link><target>Saskatoon, Saskatchewan</target></link>. Note the blinder, to prevent the driver from being distracted by the lights for the other lane.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Drag racing</bold><space/>is a type of<space/><link><target>motorsport#Racing</target><part>motor racing</part></link><space/>in which<space/><link><target>automobile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>motorcycle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(usually specially prepared for the purpose) compete, usually two at a time, to be first to cross a set finish line. The race follows a short, straight course from a<space/><link><target>standing start</target></link><space/>over a measured distance, most commonly<space/><link><target>mile</target></link><space/>(<template><target>convert</target><arg>1,320</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>), with a shorter 3/16 mile 10 feet (<template><target>convert</target><arg>1,000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>) used by nitromethane powered<space/><link><target>Top Fuel</target></link><space/><link><target>dragster (car)</target><part>dragster</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>funny car</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>along with some bracket races, while<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>660</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(1/8&amp;nbsp;mi) is also popular in some circles. Electronic timing and speed sensing systems have been used to record race results since the 1960s.</paragraph><paragraph>Drag racing has existed in both<space/><link><target>street racing</target></link><space/>and regulated<space/><link><target>motorsport</target></link><space/>forms since automobiles and motorcycles were developed. The street racing form, which is usually illegal, is covered elsewhere; this article covers the legal sport.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Basics of drag racing</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Pro Street Camaro at launch.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Camaro at launch, with ''Altered Vision'' in the right lane.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Before each race (commonly known as a pass), each driver is allowed to perform a<space/><link><target>burnout (vehicle)</target><part>burnout</part></link>, which heats the driving tires and lays rubber down at the beginning of the track, improving traction. Each driver then lines up (or stages) at the starting line.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern professional races are started electronically by a system known as a<space/><italics><link><target>Christmas tree (drag racing)</target><part>Christmas tree</part></link></italics>, which consists of a column of lights for each driver/lane, and two light beam sensors per lane on the track at the starting line. Current NHRA trees, for example, feature one blue light (split into halves), then three amber, one green, and one red.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nhra.com/story/2011/4/12/new-tree-implemented-for-visitmyrtlebeachcom-nhra-four-wide-nationals/'></link><space/>New Tree implemented for NHRA VisitMyrtleBeach.com Four-Wide Nationals</extension><space/>When the first light beam is broken by a vehicle's front tire(s), the vehicle is &quot;pre-staged&quot; (approximately<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg></template><space/>from the starting line), and the pre-stage indicator on the tree is lit. When the second light beam is broken, the vehicle is &quot;staged&quot;, and the stage indicator on the tree is lit.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nhra.com/nhra101/basics.aspx'>NHRA.com</link><space/>Basics of Drag Racing</extension><space/>Vehicles may then leave the pre-stage beam, but must remain in the stage beam until the race starts.</paragraph><paragraph>Once one competitor is staged, their opponent has a set amount of time to stage or they will be instantly disqualified, indicated by a red light on the tree. Otherwise, once both drivers are staged, the system chooses a short delay at random (to prevent a driver being able to anticipate the start), then starts the race. The light sequence at this point varies slightly. For example, in NHRA Professional classes, three amber lights on the tree flash simultaneously, followed 0.4 seconds later by a green light (this is also known as a &quot;pro tree&quot;). In NHRA Sportsman classes, the amber lights illuminate in sequence from top to bottom, 0.5 seconds apart, followed 0.5 seconds later by the green light (this is also known as a &quot;sportsman tree&quot; or &quot;full tree&quot;). If a vehicle leaves the start line before the green light illuminates, the red light for that lane illuminates instead, and the driver is disqualified (also known as<space/><italics>redlighting</italics>). Even if both drivers leave early, the green light is automatically lit for the driver that left last, and they still may win the pass.</paragraph><paragraph>Several measurements are taken for each race: reaction time, elapsed time, and speed. Reaction time is the period from the green light illuminating to the vehicle leaving the starting line. Elapsed time is the period from the vehicle leaving the starting line to crossing the finish line. Speed is measured through a<space/><link><target>speed trap</target></link><space/>covering the final<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>66</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>to the finish line, indicating average speed of the vehicle during the run last 66 feet (20m).</paragraph><paragraph>Except where a breakout rule is in place, the winner is the first vehicle to cross the finish line, and therefore the driver with the lowest combined reaction time and elapsed time. Because these times are measured separately, a driver with a slower elapsed time can actually win if that driver's advantage in reaction time exceeds the elapsed time difference. In heads-up racing, this is known as a<space/><italics><link><target>holeshot</target></link><space/>win</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nhra.com/glossary.aspx</arg><arg name="title">NHRA Glossary</arg><arg name="publisher">NHRA</arg><arg name="accessdate">August 11, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>In categories where a breakout rule is in effect (for example, NHRA Junior Dragster, Super Comp, Super Gas, Super Stock, and Stock classes, as well as some dial-in classes), if a competitor is faster than their predetermined time (a &quot;breakout&quot;), that competitor loses. If both are faster than their predetermined time, the competitor that breaks out by less time wins. Regardless, a red light foul is worse than a breakout, except in Junior Dragster where exceeding the absolute limit is a cause for disqualification.</paragraph><paragraph>Most race events use a traditional<space/><link><target>Bracket (tournament)</target><part>bracket</part></link><space/>system, where the losing car and driver are eliminated from the event while the winner advances to the next round, until a champion is crowned. Events typically use 4, 8, or 16 car brackets. Drivers are typically<space/><link><target>Seed (sports)</target><part>seeded</part></link><space/>by elapsed times in qualifying. In bracket racing without a breakout (such as NHRA Competition Eliminator), pairings are based on times compared to their index (faster than index for class is better). In bracket racing with a breakout (Stock, Super Stock, but also the NHRA's Super classes), the closest to the index is favourable.</paragraph><paragraph>A popular alternative to the standard eliminations format is the Chicago Style format (also called the Three Round format in Australia), named for the US 30 Dragstrip in suburban<space/><link><target>Gary, Indiana</target></link><space/>where a midweek meet featured this format.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.competitionplus.com/drag-racing/news/14381-chicago-once-a-funny-car-heaven</arg><arg name="title">Encore Feature: Chicago Once a Funny Car Heaven</arg><arg name="publisher">Competition Plus</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 21, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>All entered cars participate in one qualifying round, and then are paired for the elimination round. The two fastest times among winners from this round participate in the championship round. Depending on the organisation, the next two fastest times may play for third, then fifth, and so forth, in consolation rounds.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://andra.com.au/latest-news/group-1/1730-revolutionary-new-event-format-promises-easter-thrills-at-willowbank-racewa.html</arg><arg name="title">Revolutionary new event format promises Easter thrills at Willowbank Raceway</arg><arg name="publisher">Australian National Drag Racing Association</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 21, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Funny Car.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Funny Car with body up.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Racing organization</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Delivering timeslips.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Chief Timer delivering timeslips to competitors after their passes.</part></link><link><target>File:Blown Altered.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blown<space/><link><target>Altered (drag racing)</target><part>altered</part></link><space/>doing a burnout at<space/><link><target>Interlake Dragways</target></link>, Gimli, Manitoba.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>North America</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>NHRA</target><part>National Hot Rod Association</part></link><space/>(NHRA) oversees the majority of drag racing events in North America. The next largest organization is the<space/><link><target>International Hot Rod Association</target></link><space/>(IHRA). Nearly all drag strips are associated with one sanctioning body or the other.</paragraph><paragraph>Besides NHRA and IHRA, there are niche organizations for muscle cars and nostalgia vehicles. The Nostalgia Drag Racing League (NDRL) based in Brownsburg, IN, runs a series of 1/4 mile (400m) drag races in the Midwest for 1979 and older nostalgic appearing cars, with four classes of competition running in an index system. Pro 7.0 and Pro 7.50 run heads up 200 mile per hour (320 kilometre per hour) passes, while Pro Comp and Pro Gas run 8.0 to 10.0 indices. NDRL competition vehicles typically include Front Engine Dragsters, Altereds, Funny Cars, early Pro Stock clones, Super Stocks and Gassers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NDRL Website"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Mullin</arg><arg name="title">NDRL - Nostalgia Drag Racing League</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nostalgiadragleague.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-01-03</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>National Electric Drag Racing Association</target></link><space/>(NEDRA) races<space/><link><target>electric vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>against high performance gasoline-powered vehicles such as<space/><link><target>Dodge Vipers</target></link><space/>or classic<space/><link><target>muscle car</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in 1/4 and 1/8&amp;nbsp;mile (400m &amp;nbsp; 200m) races. The current<space/><link><target>electric drag racing</target></link><space/>record is<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nedra.com/200mph_club.html'></link><space/>6.940 seconds at 201.37&amp;nbsp;mph (324.0736 kph) for a quarter mile (400m). Another niche organization is the<space/><link><target>VWDRC</target></link><space/>which run a VW-only championship with vehicles running under 7 seconds.</paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the founding of the NHRA and IHRA, smaller organizations sanctioned drag racing in the early years.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">August 2012</arg></template>The first Australian Nationals event was run in 1965 at Riverside raceway, near Melbourne. The Australian National Drag Racing Association (<link><target>ANDRA</target></link>) was established in 1973, and today they claim they are the &quot;best in the world outside the United States&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="andra"><link type='external' href='http://www.andra.com.au/subpage.asp?Menu=6&amp;amp;Page=History'>Australian National Drag Racing Association</link><space/>ANDRA History</extension><space/>ANDRA sanctions races throughout Australia and throughout the year at all levels, from Junior Dragster to<space/><link><target>Top Fuel</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The ANDRA Pro Series is for professional drivers and riders and includes<space/><link><target>Top Fuel</target></link>, Top Alcohol,<space/><link><target>Top Doorslammer</target></link><space/>(similar to the USA Pro Modified class), Pro Stock (using 400 cubic inch engines (6.5 litres)), Top Bike and Pro Stock Motorcycle. ANDRA is the only organisation that officially sanctions mile drag racing for Top Fuel.</paragraph><paragraph>The Rocket Allstars Racing Series is for sportsman drivers and riders and includes Competition, Super Stock, Super Compact, Competition Bike, Supercharged Outlaws, Modified, Super Sedan, Modified Bike, Super Street and Junior Dragster.</paragraph><paragraph>Broadcasting is provided on SBS Speedweek.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Europe</heading><paragraph><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template>Drag racing was imported to Europe by American NATO troops during the Cold War.<extension extension_name='ref' name="francedrag"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://translate.google.com/translate?langpair</arg><arg name="title">History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">francedrag.com</arg></template></extension><space/>Races were held in West Germany beginning in the 1960s at the airbases at Ramstein and Sembach<extension extension_name='ref' name="germany"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://translate.google.com/translate?langpair</arg><arg name="title">Drag racing history in Germany<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">dragracinghistory.de<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and in the UK at various airstrips and racing circuits<extension extension_name='ref' name="uk"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.trakbytes.co.uk/6064.html</arg><arg name="title">UK drag racing history 1960-1964</arg><arg name="publisher">www.trakbytes.co.uk</arg></template></extension><space/>before the opening of Europe's first permanent drag strip at<space/><link><target>Santa Pod Raceway</target></link><space/>in 1966.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>FIA</target></link><space/>organises a Europe-wide four wheeled championship for the Top Fuel, Top Methanol Dragster, Top Methanol Funny Car, Pro Modified and Pro Stock classes.<space/><link><target>Fdration Internationale de Motocyclisme</target><part>FIM Europe</part></link><space/>organises a similar championship for bike classes. In addition, championships are run for sportsman classes in many countries throughout Europe by the various national motorsport governing bodies.</paragraph><heading level='3'>New Zealand</heading><paragraph>Drag racing in New Zealand started in the 1960s. The New Zealand Hot Rod Association (NZHRA) sanctioned what is believed to have been the first drag meeting at an open cut coal mine at Kopuku, south of Auckland, sometime in 1966. In 1973, the first and only purpose built drag strip opened in Meremere by the Pukekohe Hot Rod Club. In April 1993 the governance of drag racing was separated from the NZHRA and the New Zealand Drag Racing Association (NZDRA) was formed. In 2014, New Zealand's second purpose built drag strip - Masterton Motorplex - opened.</paragraph><paragraph>The first New Zealand Drag Racing Nationals was held in the 1966/67 season at Kopuku, near Auckland.</paragraph><paragraph>There are now two governing bodies operating drag racing in New Zealand with the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ihra.com/'>IHRA</link><space/>sanctioning both of New Zealands major tracks at Ruapuna (<link type='external' href='http://www.pbdrc.co.nz/'>Pegasus Bay Drag Racing Association</link>) on the South Island and<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dragway.co.nz/'>Meremere Dragway Inc</link><space/>in the North Island.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South America</heading><paragraph>A lot of countries in South America race use 200 meters unlike United states and places like Australia who use the 400 meters 1/4 mile.<template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template>Organized drag racing in Colombia is Club G3's responsibility, which is a private organization. The events take part at<space/><link><target>Autdromo de Tocancip</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Caribbean</heading><paragraph><bold>Curaao</bold></paragraph><paragraph>On the island of<space/><link><target>Curaao</target></link>, organization of drag racing events is handled by the Curaao Autosport Foundation (FAC)<extension extension_name='ref' name="curacao drag"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.curacaodrag.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Drag racing on Curacao<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">curacaodrag.com</arg></template></extension><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>All racing events, including street legal competitions, happen at the Curaao International Raceway.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Asia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template>Organized drag racing is rapidly growing in India.<space/><italics>Autocar India</italics><space/>organised the country's first drag race meet in Mumbai in 2002.<extension extension_name='ref' name="india"><link type='external' href='http://www.telegraphindia.com/1060409/asp/look/story_6060932.asp'>''The Telegraph'', [[Calcutta</link>]], &quot;Men in Drag&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Drag racing is also gaining popularity in Pakistan, with private organizations organizing such events. The<space/><link><target>Bahria Town</target></link><space/><link><target>Public housing</target><part>housing project</part></link><space/>recently organized a drag racing event in<space/><link><target>Rawalpindi</target></link>, with the help of some of the country's best drivers.<extension extension_name='ref' name='Pakistan'><link type='external' href='http://thenews.com.pk/news.asp?cat_id=6&amp;amp;page=1'>''The News'', [[Islamabad</link>], &quot;Car Drag race&quot;]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sri Lanka has seen an immense growth in Drag racing through legal meets held by the Ceylon Motor Sports Club, an FiA sanctioned body. In recent years, exotic cars and Japanese power houses have been taking part in these popular events.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.ft.lk/2014/08/13/cmsc-slaf-drag-race-on-24-august/</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Middle East</heading><paragraph><link type='external' href='http://www.qrc.qa'>Qatar Racing Club</link><space/>is the home of Motorsports in the Middle East. QRC provides access to the best drag strip and drift skid pad in the world, which allows participants to unleash the power of their cars and bikes in a safe and controlled environment. QRC with the help of the fine Racing Organizations wish to establish common rules and seeks parity amongst classes within the Gulf Region. The goal of the QRC is to help, along with the other organizations to promote World Wide Awareness of the sport of Drag Racing &amp; Drifting.Driver can compete in a number of competitions including ADRL, QATAR MILE, NATIONAL STREET DRAG CHAMPIONSHIP, QATAR DRIFT CHAMPIONSHIP, FREESTYLE DRIFT and SEALINE SAND DRAGS.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph>Drag racing is an established sport in South Africa, with a number of strips around the country including<space/><link><target>Tarlton International Raceway</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ODI Raceway</target></link>. Drag racing is controlled by<space/><link><target>Motorsport South Africa</target></link><space/>and all drivers are required to hold a valid Motorsport South Africa license.<extension extension_name='ref' name="msa2010"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">2010 MSA Drag Racing Handbook</arg><arg name="url">http://www.tarltonrace.com/2010/2010%20MSA%20Drag%20Racing%20Rulebook.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">31 October 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Drivers can compete in a number of categories including Top Eliminator, Senior Eliminator, Super Competition Eliminator, Competition Eliminator, Pro Street Bikes, Superbike Eliminator, Supersport Shootout (motorcycle), Street Modified, and Factory Stock.<extension extension_name='ref' name="msa2010"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Classes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Caterpiller-sponsored dragster.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Caterpillar-sponsored dragster. Note wide slicks and high-mounted wing, to assist traction.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There are hundreds of classes in drag racing, each with different requirements and restrictions on things such as weight, engine size, body style, modifications, and many others.<space/><link><target>NHRA</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>International Hot Rod Association</target><part>IHRA</part></link><space/>share some of these classes, but many are solely used by one sanctioning body or the other. The NHRA boasts over 200 classes, while the IHRA has fewer. Some IHRA classes have multiple sub-classes in them to differentiate by engine components and other features. There is even a class for aspiring youngsters,<space/><link><target>Junior Dragster</target></link>, which typically uses an eighth-mile track, also favored by VW racers.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1997, the<space/><link><target>Fdration Internationale de l'Automobile</target><part>FIA</part></link><space/>(cars) and<space/><link><target>Union Europenne de Motocyclisme</target><part>UEM</part></link><space/>(bikes) began sanctioning drag racing in Europe with a fully established European Drag Racing Championship, in cooperation (and rules compliance) with NHRA. The major European drag strips include Santa Pod Raceway in Podington, England; Alastaro Circuit, Finland; Mantorp Park, Sweden; Gardermoen Raceway, Norway and the<space/><link><target>Hockenheimring</target></link><space/>in Germany. The major difference is the nitro-class distance, which is 300 meters at some tracks, although the NHRA and FIA are likely to discuss the distance change in the future.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:'Pain Killer' jr. dragster.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Pain Killer'' J/D. Note the driver, helmet off, is still in the car, which is under tow on the return road, headed for the pits.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There is a somewhat arbitrary definition of what constitutes a &quot;professional&quot; class. The NHRA includes 5 pro classes; Top Fuel, Funny Car, Pro Stock, Pro Modified and Pro Stock Motorcycle. The FIA features a different set of 5 pro classes; Top Fuel, Top Methanol Dragster, Top Methanol Funny Car, Pro Modified and Pro Stock. Other sanctioning bodies have similarly different definitions. A partial list of classes includes:</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Top Fuel.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Fuel dragsters</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Top Fuel</target></link><space/>Dragster (TF/D). The rail dragsters, or &quot;diggers&quot;, are the fastest class. Among the fastest-accelerating machines in the world, these cars can cover the dragstrip in less than 3.8 seconds and record trap speeds over 325&amp;nbsp;mph. Top Fuel cars are 25 feet long and weigh 2,320 pounds in race-ready trim. Methanol fuel mixed with up to 90%<space/><link><target>nitromethane</target></link><space/>is used.</listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Funny Car AAA.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Typical Funny Cars</part></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem>Top Fuel<space/><link><target>Funny Car</target></link><space/>(TF/FC) Similar to their Top Fuel counterparts but with a shorter wheelbase and a carbon-fiber body that loosely resembles a production-based automobile, Funny Cars, or floppers, routinely run in the 4.0s and can exceed 315&amp;nbsp;mph.</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:Pro Stock.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A typical Pro Stock car.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Pro Stock</target></link><space/>(NHRA, IHRA/MMPSA) Often called factory hot rods because of their resemblance to production-based cars (and because they must maintain a relatively stock appearance), commonly called &quot;doorslammers&quot;, Pro Stockers can record quarter-mile times in the 6.4 second range, and speeds over 210&amp;nbsp;mph. They can rev to more than 10,500 rpm and make in excess of 1,300 horsepower. NHRA engines can be no more than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500</arg><arg>cuin</arg><arg>L</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/><link><target>Engine displacement</target><part>displacement</part></link><space/>while IHRA/MMPSA cars can run a maximum of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>820</arg><arg>cuin</arg><arg>L</arg></template><space/>(called &quot;Mountain Motors&quot;). Both classes require the motors to be naturally aspirated.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Pro Stock Motorcycle</target></link><space/>(NHRA and ANDRA) These highly modified vehicles, which can run under 6.8 seconds at more than 195&amp;nbsp;mph, feature a purpose-built tube chassis and a lightweight, aerodynamically enhanced replica of original bodywork.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Pro Modified</target></link><space/>(Pro Mod) or<space/><link><target>Top Doorslammer</target></link><space/>(T/D) Some engine restrictions, very high power. Cars can run superchargers, turbochargers, or nitrous oxide. Cars running blowers are limited to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>527</arg><arg>cuin</arg><arg>L</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>while cars with nitrous can run up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>740</arg><arg>cuin</arg><arg>L</arg></template>. This class is globally recognised, although the name differs between North America and Australia.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Top Alcohol Dragster</target></link><space/>(TA/D). Known as Top Methanol Dragster in FIA competition. Top Alcohol Dragsters resemble Top Fuelers, but have significant differences. They may use a supercharged methanol-burning engine or an injected nitromethane combination. They can run in the 5.1s at more than 280&amp;nbsp;mph.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Top Alcohol Funny Car</target></link><space/>(TA/FC). Known as Top Methanol Funny Car in FIA competition. Similar in physical appearance to their nitro-burning Funny Car counterparts, Top Alcohol Funny Cars are restricted to the use of methanol fuel and have three-speed transmissions. They can run in the 5.4s at more than 265&amp;nbsp;mph. In the IHRA, Alcohol Funny Car is the fifth pro category, replacing NHRA's Pro Stock Bike.</listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Comp Eliminator.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A typical Comp car.</part></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Competition Eliminator</target></link><space/>This is the NHRA class with the most variety. Each of its 88 sections is assigned an index based on what a well-built car should run, and races are handicapped according to those indexes.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Outlaw Series</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Pro FWD</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Super Comp/Quick Rod</target></link><space/>The quickest of the heads-up Super classes (8.90 index) is composed primarily of dragsters. Most cars are capable of running well under the index but use electronic aids to run close to it without breaking out.</listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Super Gas Probe.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Super Gas Probe.</part></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Super Gas/Super Rod</target></link><space/>Super Gas entries, which run on a 9.90 index, are primarily full-bodied cars and street roadsters. No dragsters or altereds are permitted. As in Super Comp, competitors use electronic aids to run as close to the class standard without going under.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Super Street/Hot Rod</target></link><space/>Racers compete on a fixed 10.90 index. All vehicles must be full-bodied cars and weigh no less than 2,800 pounds except for six-cylinder cars (2,000) and four-cylinder and rotary-powered cars (1,200). Engine and chassis modifications are virtually unlimited.<space/><link><target>File:Super Street Mustang.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Super Street Mustang</part></link></listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Super Stock.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A typical Super Stock car</part></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Super Stock</target></link><space/>Super Stock vehicles resemble ordinary passenger cars, but are actually heavily modified. Entries are classified using factory shipping weight and horsepower and compete on indexes. The breakout rule is enforced.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Stock (drag racing class)</target><part>Stock</part></link><space/>Stock cars are similar to Super Stockers, but rules regarding everything from engine modifications to body alterations are much stricter. Virtually any car is eligible to compete, and entries are classified using factory shipping weight and horsepower.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Sport Compact</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Top Sportsman (NHRA and IHRA) Competitors in these full-bodied entries may choose their own dial for eliminations, generally from 6.00 to 7.99 seconds. Full Tree starts are used, and the breakout rule is enforced. Cars can run in the sixes at more than 200&amp;nbsp;mph.</listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Top Dragster.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blown Top Dragster</part></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem>Top Dragster (NHRA and IHRA) Competitors in these open-wheel entries may choose their own dial for eliminations, generally from 6.00 to 7.70 seconds. Full Tree starts are used, and the breakout rule is enforced. Cars can run in the sixes at more than 200&amp;nbsp;mph. Cars can run any combination of motor: blown, turbo, nitrous or just all motor,</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Top Fuel Funny Bike (high performance 5 second bikes)</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nostalgia Super Stock</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>NHRA and ANDRA<space/><link><target>Summit Racing</target></link><space/>series Super Pro, Pro, and bike.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Junior Dragster (racers between the ages of 8 and 18 may race a half scale version of the sport's fastest car, Top Fuel Dragster. Juniors run as following: 12.90-slower for 8-9&amp;nbsp;year olds, 10-12&amp;nbsp;year olds at 8.90, and 13-18&amp;nbsp;year olds 7.90 and slower at a top speed of 85&amp;nbsp;mph). These cars race at 1/8 mile or 1/16 mile.<space/></listitem><listitem>NHRA new class for Juniors is JR COMP running 6.90s at a top speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>110</arg><arg>mi/h</arg><arg>km/h</arg></template><space/>(1/8 mile or 1/16 mile).</listitem></list><paragraph>A complete listing of all classes can be found on the respective NHRA and IHRA official websites.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dragster engine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Note dual-plug heads, dual ignition magnetos, and intake snorkel</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The UEM also has a different structure of professional categories with Top Fuel Bike, Super Twin Top Fuel Bike, and Pro Stock Bike contested, leaving the entire European series with a total of 8 professional categories.</paragraph><paragraph>To allow different cars to compete against each other, some competitions are raced on a handicap basis, with faster cars delayed on the start line enough to theoretically even things up with the slower car. This may be based on rule differences between the cars in stock, super stock, and modified classes, or on a competitor's chosen &quot;dial-in&quot; in<space/><link><target>bracket racing</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dial-in</heading><paragraph>A &quot;dial-in&quot; is a time the driver estimates it will take his or her car to cross the finish line, and is generally displayed on one or more windows so the starter can adjust the starting lights on the tree accordingly. The slower car will then get a<space/><link><target>Head start (positioning)</target><part>head start</part></link><space/>equal to the difference in the two dial-ins, so if both cars perform perfectly, they would cross the finish line dead even. If either car goes faster than its dial-in (called breaking out), it is disqualified regardless of who has the lower elapsed time; if both cars break out, the one who breaks out by the smallest amount wins. However, if a driver had jump-started (red light) or crossed a boundary line, both violations override any break out (except in some classes with an absolute break out rule such as Junior classes). This eliminates any advantage from putting a slower time on the windshield to get a head start. The effect of the bracket racing rules is to place a premium on consistency of performance of the driver and car rather than on raw speed, in that victory goes to the driver able to precisely predict elapsed time, whether it is fast or slow. This in turn makes victory much less dependent on large infusions of money, and more dependent on skill. Therefore, bracket racing is popular with casual weekend racers. Many of these recreational racers will drive their vehicles to the track, race them, and then simply drive them home. As most tracks host only one NHRA national event, and two or three regional events (smaller tours, car shows,<space/><italics>etc.</italics>) annually, on most weekends these tracks host local casual and weekend racers. Organizationally, however, the tracks are run according to the rules of either the NHRA or the IHRA with regional points and a championship on the line. Even street vehicles must pass a safety inspection prior to being allowed to race.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Blazing Angel Jet Dragster.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Blazing Angel Jet Dragster</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historic cars</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1954 first<space/><link><target>Front engine dragster</target><part>slingshot</part></link>, built by<space/><link><target>Mickey Thompson</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hot Rod, 12/86, p.29 sidebar"><italics>Hot Rod</italics>, 12/86, p.&amp;nbsp;29 sidebar.</extension></listitem><listitem>1962 the Greer-<link><target>Keith Black (engineer)</target><part>Black</part></link>&amp;ndash;<link><target>Don Prudhomme</target><part>Prudhomme</part></link><space/>digger, with the best win record in NHRA history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hot Rod, 12/86, p.29 sidebar"></extension></listitem><listitem>1966<space/><italics>Eliminator I</italics>, the first true<space/><link><target>Funny Car</target></link>, built by the Logghe brothers<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hot Rod, 12/86, p.29 sidebar"></extension></listitem><listitem>1971<space/><italics>Swamp Rat XIV</italics><space/>(or<space/><italics>Swamp Rat 1-R</italics>), first successful rear-engined dragster, built by<space/><link><target>Don Garlits</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Hot Rod</italics>, 12/86, p.28.</extension><space/><link><target>Ed Donovan (engine builder)</target><part>Ed Donovan</part></link><space/>introduces the 417<space/><link><target>Donovan hemi</target></link>, an aluminum copy of the Chrysler<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Street Rodder</italics>, 7/94, p.144.</extension></listitem><listitem>1974 first tube chassis<space/><link><target>Pro Stock</target></link><space/>car,<space/><link><target>Bill Jenkins (racer)</target><part>Bill Jenkins</part></link>' '72<space/><link><target>Chevrolet Vega</target><part>Vega</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Super Chevy</italics>, 5/94, p.16.</extension></listitem><listitem>1986<space/><italics>Swamp Rat XXX</italics>, first streamlined dragster, built by Don Garlits.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Hot Rod</italics>, 12/86, p.24;<space/><link type='external' href='http://americanhistory.si.edu/ONTHEMOVE/collection/object_754.html'>Smithsonian Institution</link></extension><space/></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Glossary</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of motorsport terminology</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Back halfdistance from the 1/8 mile mark to the 1,000 foot and 1/4 mile mark of the track.</listitem><listitem>Beamstarting line electric eye controlling prestaged and staged lights.</listitem><listitem>Bottlenitrous system; also known as<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template><space/>the jug.</listitem><listitem>Blanketa ballistic cover, typically over the supercharged intake manifold assembly to contain shrapnel, in the case of an explosion.</listitem><listitem>Blowsupercharge; wreck. Said of an engine.</listitem><listitem>Blower<link><target>supercharger</target></link><space/>(occasionally<space/><link><target>turbocharger</target></link>); in '90s, generally grouped as &quot;power adder&quot; with turbocharger and<space/><link><target>nitrous oxide</target><part>nitrous</part></link></listitem><listitem>Blownsupercharged; wrecked. Said of an engine.</listitem><listitem>Blowoverflipping of a car, due to air under car lifting front wheels. Commonly suffered by dragsters</listitem><listitem>Breakoutrunning quicker than dial-in; also &quot;breaking out.&quot; In many classes (Competition Eliminator is the major exception), it is grounds for disqualification if opponent does not commit a foul start, cross boundary lines, or breaks out by a larger margin.</listitem><listitem>Bulb(ed)<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template>jump(ed) the start, left before tree turned green. This is a loss unless the opponent suffers a more serious foul.</listitem><listitem>Burnoutperformed to heat the tires up for better traction</listitem><listitem>Christmas tree (or tree)lights used to start a race in addition to showing starting violations</listitem><listitem>DAdensity altitude; a reference to qualities in the air.</listitem><listitem>Dial-in (bracket racing)estimated of expected e.t. for a pass, set before starting, used for handicapping the start</listitem><listitem>Diaperan absorbent containment blanket under the engine to prevent/reduce oil contact with the track, in the event of parts breakage</listitem><listitem>Dope(Southern U.S.) car using nitrous or propane injection on diesels<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Diggerdragster (as distinct from a bodied car or flopper)<extension extension_name='ref'>Emmons, Don, &quot;R&amp;C Modelrama&quot; in<space/><italics>Rod &amp; Custom</italics>, 9/00, p.147.</extension></listitem><listitem>First or worst<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template>-if both drivers commit a foul, the driver who commits the foul first loses, unless it is two separate fouls, where the loser is the driver who committed the worse foul (lane violation is worse than foul start, and failure to participate in a post-run inspection is worst).</listitem><listitem>FlopperFunny Car, short for &quot;fender flopper.&quot;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template><space/>Coined by dragster crews in the late 1960s to separate Funny Cars, which had fiberglass bodies with fenders, from dragsters. Erroneously attributed to flip-top bodies of Funny Cars.</listitem><listitem>Fuelmix of<space/><link><target>methanol</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>nitromethane</target></link><space/>(&quot;pop,&quot; nitro); race class using it</listitem><listitem>Fuelerany car running fuel or in Fuel class (most often, TFD or TF/FC)</listitem><listitem>Grenadewreck an engine (the engine &quot;grenaded&quot;) due to internal failure. Distinct from &quot;popping a blower&quot;.</listitem><listitem>Heads-up racingwhere both drivers leave at the same time. Used in all professional (&quot;pro&quot;) classes.</listitem><listitem>Holeshotgetting a significant advantage off the starting line. The other driver gets &quot;holeshotted&quot; or &quot;left at the tree&quot;. A &quot;holeshot win&quot; is any win in a heads-up class where a slower car beats a faster car because of better<space/><link><target>reaction time</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Hook upgood traction between tires and track resulting in increased acceleration and reduced slipping or smoking of tires.</listitem><listitem>James Bonddriver's reaction time (when he leaves the start line) is seven thousands of a second after the green light (.007). A &quot;James Bond Red&quot; is a reaction time of -.007 seconds (red light), which is disqualification unless the opponent commits a more serious violation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dragracecentral.com/drcstoryprint.asp?ID=282395'>|2014 Amalie Oil Gatornationals</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nhra.net/2009/events/race06/results/monday_ss.html'>2009 NHRA Summit Racing Equipment Nationals</link></extension></listitem><listitem>Kitturbo or nitrous kit<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Lit the tireslost traction, causing burning rubber</listitem><listitem>Methmethanol injection<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template><space/>used in conjunction with gasoline (non-leaded pump)</listitem><listitem>Millany<space/><link><target>internal combustion engine</target></link><space/>used in a drag car, or<space/><link><target>Hot rod#Common terms</target><part>hot rod</part></link></listitem><listitem>Nitro<link><target>nitromethane</target></link><space/>(sometimes incorrectly used to refer to nitrous oxide<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem>Nitrousnitrous oxide system; the gas used in such a system</listitem><listitem>Overdriveratio between the revolutions of the supercharger to the revolutions of the engine, controlling amount of boost; see underdrive</listitem><listitem>Oildownwhen a car's engine or lubrication breaks during a run, leaving a streak of oil and other fluids on the track. This is punishable by fines, point penalties, and/or suspension.</listitem><listitem>Pedalfestrace won by pedalling; or poor track conditions that necessitate pedalling</listitem><listitem>Pedallingworking the throttle to avoid lighting the tires, or as a way to sandbag; &quot;pedalled&quot; it, had to &quot;pedal&quot; it</listitem><listitem>Pro treetiming lights which flash all three yellow lights simultaneously, and after four tenths of a second, turn green.</listitem><listitem>Put on the trailerlost (got &quot;put on the trailer&quot;) or won (put the other driver on the trailer). From the obvious, losing drivers trailer their cars home.</listitem><listitem>Quick 8 (Q8)quickest eight cars in a defined race. Rules appear to differ per location/race.</listitem><listitem>Raildragster (as distinct from bodied car or flopper). From the exposed frame rails of early cars.</listitem><listitem>Redlight(ed)jump(ed) the start, left before tree turned green. This is a loss unless the opponent commits a more serious foul.</listitem><listitem>Red Cherry-jump(ed) the start, left before the tree turned green.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dragracingonline.com/raceresults/2012/xiv_11-andra-5.html'></link></extension></listitem><listitem>Sandbaggingreleasing the throttle or using the brakes at the end of the track during a bracket race after dialing a purposely slow time. Considered a dirty trick or tantamount to cheating in amateur classes.</listitem><listitem>Scattershieldmetal sheet protecting driver in case of transmission failure<extension extension_name='ref'>Its invention is credited to Vic King and Pete Wolley for their X/Gas digger in 1959. Dain Gingerelli, &quot;Midnight Oil!&quot; in<space/><italics>American Rodder</italics>, 6/94, p.81.</extension></listitem><listitem>Slapper bartraction bar</listitem><listitem>Slicksrear tires with no tread pattern and softer rubber compound, for increased traction</listitem><listitem>Slingshotearly front-engined dragster, named for the driving position behind the rear wheels (erroneously attributed to launch speed).<space/></listitem><listitem>Standard treetiming lights which flash in sequence five tenths of a second between each yellow light before turning green. Traditional form, before introduction of pro tree.</listitem><listitem>Struck the tiresloss of traction, causing them to smoke<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Throw a beltlosing the drive belt connecting the engine's crankshaft to the supercharger</listitem><listitem>Top endfinish line of strip; high part of engine's rev band.</listitem><listitem>Traction barsrear struts fixed to rear axle to keep rear axle from twisting, causing wheel hop and loss of traction; slapper bars.</listitem><listitem>Trap(s)the 20&amp;nbsp;meter (66&amp;nbsp;ft) timing lights at top end of race track to measure speed &amp; E.T.</listitem><listitem>Trap speed is the speed measured by the 60 foot speed trap near the finish line, indicating maximum speed reached in a run.</listitem><listitem>Wheel hopviolent shaking of the car as the tires lose and regain traction in quick succession.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wheelie#Wheelie bars</target><part>Wheelie bars</part></link>rear struts fixed to rear axle, which protrude out to rear of car to help prevent car's front from raising too high or flipping over on launch.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>ANDRA</target><part>Australian National Drag Racing Association (ANDRA)</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electric dragbike</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electric dragster</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fremont Dragstrip</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jet dragster</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>NHRA</target><part>National Hot Rod Association (NHRA)</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nostalgia drag racing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rocket dragster</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Santa Ana Drags</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drag boat racing</target></link></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Robert C. Post.<space/><italics>High Performance: The Culture and Technology of Drag Racing, 1950 - 2000</italics>.<space/><link><target>Johns Hopkins University Press</target></link>, revised edition 2001.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>dragster</arg></template><template><target>commons category-inline</target><arg>Drag racing</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nzdra.co.nz/'>New Zealand Drag Racing Association (NZDRA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.andra.com.au/'>Australian National Drag Racing Association (ANDRA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.powerracing.eu/'>European Championship Drag Racing (FIA/UEM)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nhra.com/'>National Hot Rod Association (NHRA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ihra.com/'>International Hot Rod Association (IHRA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.racepra.com/'>Pro Racing Association - Championship Volkswagen Drag Racing</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.speedhunters.com'>Drag Racing News, Cars &amp; Events from around the world</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://competitionplus.com/'>Drag Racing's Internet Magazine</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rearwheelhorsepower.com/forum'>Drag Racing Forum, Race Cars &amp; Racing Events from around the world</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eurodragster.com/'>EuroDragster - European Drag Racing News and Events</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dragtimes.com/'>DragTimes - Database of Drag Racing Timeslips</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Class of Auto racing</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Drag Racing</target></template><link><target>Category:Drag racing</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Auto racing by type</target></link></paragraph></article>