<article title='Emily_Bront%C3%AB'><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="name"><space/>Emily Jane Brontë
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Emily Brontë cropped.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="alt">
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>A portrait of Brontë made by her brother, [[Branwell Brontë]]
</arg><arg name="pseudonym"><space/>Ellis Bell
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Emily Jane Brontë
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1818|7|30|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Thornton, West Yorkshire|Thornton]], [[West Riding of Yorkshire]], England
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1848|12|19|1818|7|30|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Haworth]], [[West Riding of Yorkshire]], England
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Poet, novelist, governess
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="citizenship">
</arg><arg name="education">
</arg><arg name="alma_mater">
</arg><arg name="period">
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>Fiction, poetry
</arg><arg name="subject">
</arg><arg name="movement"><space/>[[Romantic Period]]
</arg><arg name="notableworks"><space/>''[[Wuthering Heights]]''
</arg><arg name="spouse">
</arg><arg name="partner">
</arg><arg name="children">
</arg><arg name="relatives"><space/>[[Brontë family]]
</arg><arg name="awards">
</arg><arg name="signature">
</arg><arg name="website">
</arg><arg name="portaldisp">
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Emily Jane Bront</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>r</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>i</arg></template>,<space/><italics>commonly</italics><space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>r</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>eɪ</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'>As given by<space/><italics>Merriam-Webster Encyclopedia of Literature</italics><space/>(Merriam-Webster, incorporated, Publishers: Springfield, Massachusetts, 1995), p. viii: &quot;When our research shows that an author's pronunciation of his or her name differs from common usage, the author's pronunciation is listed first, and the descriptor<space/><italics>commonly</italics><space/>precedes the more familiar pronunciation.&quot; See also entries on Anne, Charlotte and Emily Bront, pp. 175176.</extension><space/>30 July 1818 19 December 1848)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The New Encyclopædia Britannica, Volume 2</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="page">546</arg></template></extension><space/>was an English novelist and poet who is best known for her only novel,<space/><italics><link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link></italics>, now considered a classic of English literature. Emily was the third eldest of the four surviving<space/><link><target>Bront family</target><part>Bront siblings</part></link>, between the youngest<space/><link><target>Anne Bront</target><part>Anne</part></link><space/>and her brother<space/><link><target>Branwell Bront</target><part>Branwell</part></link>. She wrote under the pen name<space/><bold>Ellis Bell</bold>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life and education</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Painting of Bront sisters.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>The three Bront sisters, in an 1834 painting by their brother<space/><link><target>Branwell Bront</target></link>. From left to right: Anne, Emily and Charlotte. (Branwell used to be between Emily and Charlotte, but subsequently painted himself out.)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Emily Bront was born on 30 July 1818 in the village of<space/><link><target>Thornton, West Yorkshire</target><part>Thornton</part></link>,<space/><link><target>West Riding of Yorkshire</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>Northern England</target></link>, to<space/><link><target>Maria Branwell</target></link><space/>and an Irish father,<space/><link><target>Patrick Bront</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Houghton Mifflin Dictionary of Biography</italics><space/>(2003), p. 224</extension><space/>She was the younger sister of<space/><link><target>Charlotte Bront</target></link><space/>and the fifth of six children, though the two oldest girls,<space/><link><target>Maria Bront</target><part>Maria</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Bront</target><part>Elizabeth</part></link>, died in childhood.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hilda D. Spear,<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights by Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1985), p. 1</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Catherine Brighton,<space/><italics>The Bronts: Scenes from the Childhood of Charlotte, Branwell, Emily, and Anne</italics><space/>(2004)</extension><space/>In 1820, shortly after the birth of Emily's younger sister<space/><link><target>Anne Bront</target><part>Anne</part></link>, the family moved eight miles away to<space/><link><target>Haworth</target></link>, where Patrick was employed as<space/><link><target>perpetual curate</target></link>; here the children developed their literary talents.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rod Mengham,<space/><italics>Emily Bront, Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>(1988), p. 1</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;In 1824, the family moved to Haworth, where Emily's father was perpetual curate, and it was in these surroundings that their literary oddities flourished.&quot;<space/><italics>The Bront Collection</italics><space/>(2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the death of their mother in September 1821 from cancer, when Emily was three years old,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wuthering-heights.co.uk/brontegenealogy.htm'>''A DETAILED GENEALOGY OF THE BRONT FAMILY''</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Pykett">Lyn Pykett,<space/><italics>Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1989)</extension><space/>the older sisters<space/><link><target>Maria Bront</target><part>Maria</part></link>, Elizabeth and Charlotte were sent to the<space/><link><target>Cowan Bridge School</target><part>Clergy Daughters' School</part></link><space/>at Cowan Bridge, where they encountered abuse and privations later described by Charlotte in<space/><italics><link><target>Jane Eyre</target></link></italics>. At the age of six on 25 November 1824, Emily joined her sisters at school for a brief period.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">New Bronteana</arg><arg name="journal">The Journal of Education: A Monthly Record and Review</arg><arg name="date">January 1900</arg><arg name="volume">366</arg><arg name="page">36</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bl.uk/collection-items/school-report-on-the-bront-sisters#</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 July 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>When a<space/><link><target>typhoid</target></link><space/>epidemic swept the school, Maria and Elizabeth caught it. Maria, who may actually have had<space/><link><target>tuberculosis</target></link>, was sent home, where she died. Emily was subsequently removed from the school, in June 1825, along with Charlotte and Elizabeth. Elizabeth died soon after their return home.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pykett"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The three remaining sisters and their brother<space/><link><target>Branwell Bront</target><part>Patrick Branwell</part></link><space/>were thereafter educated at home by their father and aunt<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Branwell</target></link>, their mother's sister. Their father, an Irish<space/><link><target>Anglican</target></link><space/><link><target>clergyman</target></link>, was very strict and during the day he would work in his office while the children were to remain silent in a room together. Despite the lack of formal education, Emily and her siblings had access to a wide range of published material; favourites included<space/><link><target>Walter Scott</target><part>Sir Walter Scott</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lord Byron</target><part>Byron</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Percy Bysshe Shelley</target><part>Shelley</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Blackwood's Magazine</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pykett"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily Bront, although she led an almost secluded life, was not completely cut-off from literature. She read fairly widely. She and the other members of her family knew the older authors, especially Shakespeare, and also the contemporary romanticists like Scott, Wordsworth and Byron. Emily Bront was fond of reading the articles, reviews and stories, especially with a Gothic flavour, which were published in Blackwood's Magazine.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jibesh Bhattacharyya</arg><arg name="title">Emily Brontë's Wuthering Heights (the Atlantic Critical Studies)</arg><arg name="publisher">Atlantic Publishers & Dist</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="pages">7–8</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Gondal Poems.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>179 px</part><part>Emily's<space/><link><target>Gondal (fictional country)</target><part>Gondal</part></link><space/>poems</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In their leisure time the children began to write fiction at home, inspired by a box of toy soldiers Branwell had received as a gift<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard E. Mezo,<space/><italics>A Student's Guide to Wuthering Heights by Emily Bront</italics><space/>(2002), p. 1</extension><space/>and created a number of<space/><link><target>paracosm</target><part>fantasy worlds</part></link><space/>(including 'Angria') which featured in stories they wrote all &quot;very strange ones&quot; according to Charlotte<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;All our plays are very strange ones.&quot;<space/><italics>The life of Charlotte Bront</italics>, by Elizabeth Cleghorn Gaskell (1870), p. 62</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>storytelling game</target><part>enacted</part></link><space/>about the imaginary adventures of their toy soldiers along with the<space/><link><target>Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington</target><part>Duke of Wellington</part></link><space/>and his sons,<space/><link><target>Lord Charles Wellesley</target><part>Charles</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arthur Wellesley, 5th Duke of Wellington</target><part>Arthur Wellesley</part></link>. Little of Emily's work from this period survives, except for poems spoken by characters.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Bronts' Web of Childhood</italics>, by Fannie Ratchford, 1941</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>An analysis of Emily's use of paracosm play as a response to the deaths of her sisters is found in Delmont C. Morrison's<space/><italics>Memories of Loss and Dreams of Perfection</italics><space/>(Baywood, 2005), ISBN 0-89503-309-7.</extension>When Emily was 13, she and Anne withdrew from participation in the Angria story and began a new one about<space/><link><target>Gondal (fictional country)</target><part>Gondal</part></link>, a fictional island whose myths and legends were to preoccupy the two sisters throughout their lives.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pykett"></extension><space/>With the exception of Emily's Gondal poems and Anne's lists of Gondal's characters and place-names, their writings on Gondal were not preserved. Some &quot;diary papers&quot; of Emily's have survived in which she describes current events in Gondal, some of which were written, others enacted with Anne. One dates from 1841, when Emily was twenty-three: another from 1845, when she was twenty-seven.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://academic.brooklyn.cuny.edu/english/melani/novel_19c/wuthering/diary_papers#diary'>&quot;Emily Bront's Letters and Diary Papers&quot;</link>, City University of New York</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At seventeen, Emily attended the Roe Head Girls' School,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pykett"></extension><space/>where Charlotte was a teacher but managed to stay only a few months before being overcome by extreme<space/><link><target>homesickness</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Liberty was the breath of Emily's nostrils; without it she perished. The change from her own home to a school and from her own very noiseless, very secluded but unrestricted and unartificial mode of life, to one of disciplined routine (though under the kindest auspices), was what she failed in enduring... I felt in my heart she would die, if she did not go home, and with this conviction obtained her recall.&quot; Charlotte Bront, as quoted in<space/><italics>The life of Charlotte Bront</italics>, by Elizabeth Cleghorn Gaskell (1870), p. 101</extension><space/>She returned home and Anne took her place.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mick-armitage.staff.shef.ac.uk/anne/cast-2.html'>At Roe Head and Blake Hall</link><space/>with pictures of the school then and now, and descriptions of Anne's time there.</extension><space/>At this time, the girls' objective was to obtain sufficient education to open a small school of their own.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Adulthood</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Constantinheger1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Constantin Hger</target></link>, teacher of Charlotte and Emily during their stay in Brussels, on a<space/><link><target>daguerreotype</target></link><space/>dated c. 1865</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Emily became a teacher at Law Hill School in<space/><link><target>Halifax, West Yorkshire</target><part>Halifax</part></link><space/>beginning in September 1838, when she was twenty.<extension extension_name='ref'>Steven Vine,<space/><italics>Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1998), p. 11</extension><space/>Her health broke under the stress of the 17-hour work day and she returned home in April 1839.<extension extension_name='ref'>Christine L. Krueger,<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of British writers, 19th century</italics><space/>(2009), p. 41</extension><space/>Thereafter she became the stay-at-home daughter, doing most of the cooking, ironing, and cleaning and teaching Sunday school.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jean Pierre Petit,<space/><italics>Emily Bront: a critical anthology</italics><space/>(1973), p. 130</extension><space/>She taught herself German out of books and also practised piano.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;A deep and earnest student of German, a pianist of wonderful fire and brilliancy, a writer of marvelous promise, she did willingly and untiringly the heaviest household drudgery.&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>w:The Sacramento Union</target><part>The Record-Union</part></link></italics>, &quot;Sacramento&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82015104/1899-12-31/ed-1/seq-10/'></link>, 31 December 1899.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily was the serious pianist in the house, even before her study in Brussels.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Robert K. Wallace</arg><arg name="title">Emily Brontë and Beethoven: Romantic Equilibrium in Fiction and Music</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Georgia Press</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="page">223</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1842, Emily accompanied Charlotte to the Hger Pensionnat in<space/><link><target>Brussels</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Belgium</target></link>, where they attended the girls' academy run by<space/><link><target>Constantin Hger</target></link>. They planned to perfect their French and German in anticipation of opening their school. Nine of Emily's French essays survive from this period. Hger seems to have been impressed with the strength of Emily's character, and made the following assertion:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><xhtml:div>She should have been a man a great navigator. Her powerful reason would have deduced new spheres of discovery from the knowledge of the old; and her strong imperious will would never have been daunted by opposition or difficulty, never have given way but with life. She had a head for logic, and a capability of argument unusual in a man and rarer indeed in a woman... impairing this gift was her stubborn tenacity of will which rendered her obtuse to all reasoning where her own wishes, or her own sense of right, was concerned.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Constantin Hger</target></link>, 1842, referring to Emily Bront, as quoted in<space/><italics>The Oxford History of the Novel in English</italics><space/>(2011), Volume 3, p. 208</extension></xhtml:div></extension>The two sisters were committed to their studies and by the end of the term had attained such competence in French that Madame Hger made a proposal for both to stay another half-year, even offering to dismiss the English master, according to Charlotte, so that she could take his place, while Emily was to teach music.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Madame Heger has made a proposal for both me and Emily to stay another half year, offering to dismiss her English master, and take me as English teacher; also to employ Emily some part of each day in teaching music to a certain number of the pupils.&quot;<space/><link><target>Charlotte Bront</target></link>, Brussels, 1842, as quoted in Gaskell's<space/><italics>The life of Charlotte Bront</italics><space/>(1870), p. 176</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Jibesh Bhattacharyya,<space/><italics>Emily Bront's Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>(2006), p. 7</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily had become a competent piano teacher.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Norma Crandall</arg><arg name="title">Emily Brontë, a Psychological Portrait</arg><arg name="publisher">R. R. Smith Publisher</arg><arg name="year">1957</arg><arg name="page">85</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the illness and death of their aunt meant that they returned to Haworth and though they did try to open a school at their home, they were unable to attract students to the remote area.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1844, Emily began going through all the poems she had written, recopying them neatly into two notebooks. One was labelled &quot;Gondal Poems&quot;; the other was unlabelled. Scholars such as Fannie Ratchford and Derek Roper have attempted to piece together a Gondal storyline and chronology from these poems.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fannie Ratchford, ed.,<space/><italics>Gondal's Queen</italics>. University of Texas Press, 1955. ISBN 0-292-72711-9.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Derek Roper, ed.,<space/><italics>The Poems of Emily Bront</italics>. Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 0-19-812641-7.</extension>In the autumn of 1845, Charlotte discovered the notebooks and insisted that the poems be published. Emily, furious at the invasion of her privacy, at first refused<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;What actually distinguishes 'No coward soul is mine' as marking a distinctive moment in Emily Bront's career is not that it was her last poem but that it actually appears to have been the first poem that she wrote after Charlotte Bront read a manuscript volume of Emily's poetry without Emily's knowledge or permission, an act that Charlotte herself later admitted had profoundly upset her sister. For Charlotte Bront, the act seemed at least partially justified in hindsight because through it she discovered that her sister was a much more accomplished poet than she had realized. As Charlotte tells the story,her discovery of the remarkably high quality of some of Emily's poetry gave Charlotte the afflatus she had to that point been lacking to enlist both her sisters in publishing a volume of their poems, and soon thereafter they began to establish themselves as professional novelists.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Meredith L. McGill</arg><arg name="title">The Traffic in Poems: Nineteenth-century Poetry and Transatlantic Exchange</arg><arg name="publisher">Rutgers University Press</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="page">240</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily's literary success might not have occurred at all if Charlotte had not discovered a notebook containing her poems in the autumn of 1845. Emily was furious at the violation of her privacy and initially resisted Charlotte's urge to publish them. The poems eventually appeared alongside verses by Anne and Charlotte, published under a pseudonym in 1846 as Poems by Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell. The sisters chose masculine names in the hope that their works would be taken more seriously.&quot; Grace Moore,<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>(2012), 'About the author'</extension><space/>but relented when Anne brought out her own manuscripts and revealed she had been writing poems in secret as well.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;In 1845 Charlotte 'accidentally lighted upon' the manuscripts of Emily's poems, and on reading them was impressed by their power. She confronted her younger sister with her discovery, and admitted that she had been writing poetry too. Emily was nevertheless vexed at having been found out, though she eventually was persuaded to submit her work for publication. In the meantime, Anne quietly brought her own poetry manuscripts out of hiding.&quot; Wuthering Heights (1989), p. vi (ISBN 978-0812505160)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1846, the sisters' poems were published in one volume as<space/><italics><link><target>Poems by Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell</target></link></italics>. The Bront sisters had adopted pseudonyms for publication, preserving their initials: Charlotte was &quot;Currer Bell&quot;, Emily was &quot;Ellis Bell&quot; and Anne was &quot;Acton Bell&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Encyclopedia of British writers, 19th century</italics><space/>(2009), p. 41</extension><space/>Charlotte wrote in the 'Biographical Notice of Ellis and Acton Bell' that their &quot;ambiguous choice&quot; was &quot;dictated by a sort of conscientious scruple at assuming Christian names positively masculine, while we did not like to declare ourselves women, because... we had a vague impression that authoresses are liable to be looked on with prejudice&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Elizabeth Cleghorn Gaskell,<space/><italics>The life of Charlotte Bront</italics><space/>(1870), p. 218</extension><space/>Charlotte contributed 20 poems, and Emily and Anne each contributed 21. Although the sisters were told several months after publication that only two copies had sold,<extension extension_name='ref'>Winifred Grin,<space/><italics>Charlotte Bront: the evolution of genius</italics><space/>(1969), p. 322</extension><space/>they were not discouraged (of their two readers, one was impressed enough to request their autographs).<extension extension_name='ref'>Margot Peters,<space/><italics>Unquiet Soul: A Biography of Charlotte Bront</italics><space/>(1976), p. 219</extension><space/><italics>The Athenaeum</italics><space/>reviewer praised Ellis Bell's work for its music and power, singling out his poems as the best: &quot;Ellis possesses a fine, quaint spirit and an evident power of wing that may reach heights not here attempted&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>In the footsteps of the Bronts</italics><space/>(1895), p. 306</extension><space/>and<space/><italics>The Critic</italics><space/>reviewer recognised &quot;the presence of more genius than it was supposed this utilitarian age had devoted to the loftier exercises of the intellect.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The poems of Emily Jane Bront and Anne Bront</italics><space/>(1932), p. 102</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Personality and character</heading><paragraph>Emily Bront remains a mysterious figure and a challenge to biographers because information about her is sparse,<extension extension_name='ref'>Lorna Sage<space/><italics>The Cambridge Guide to Women's Writing in English</italics><space/>(1999), p. 90</extension><space/>due to her solitary and reclusive nature.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The life of Emily Bront is shrouded in mystery, and she remains an elusive and mysterious figure&quot; Lyn Pykett,<space/><italics>Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1989)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily's reclusive nature had already made her less known than the siblings who had moved in wider social circles&quot; U. C. Knoepflmacher,<space/><italics>Emily Bront: Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>(1989), p. 112</extension><space/>She does not seem to have made any friends outside her family.<extension extension_name='ref'>Grace Moore,<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>(2012), 'About the author'</extension><space/>Her sister<space/><link><target>Charlotte Bront</target><part>Charlotte</part></link><space/>remains the primary source of information about her, although as Emily's elder sister, writing publicly about her shortly after her death, Charlotte is not a neutral witness.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Then there is what might be called Charlotte's smoke-screen. Her sister evidently shocked her, to the point where she may even have doubted Emily's sanity. After her death, Charlotte rewrote Emily's character, history and even poems on a (to her and the bourgeois reading public) more acceptable model.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Stevie Davies</arg><arg name="title">Emily Brontë: Heretic</arg><arg name="publisher">Women's Press</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="page">16</arg></template></extension><space/>According to Lucasta Miller, in her analysis of Bront biographies, &quot;Charlotte took on the role of Emily's first mythographer.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Lucasta Miller</arg><arg name="title">The Brontë Myth</arg><arg name="publisher">Vintage</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="pages">171–174</arg><arg name="ISBN">0 09 928714 5</arg></template></extension><space/>In the<space/><italics>Preface</italics><space/>to the Second Edition of<space/><italics><link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link></italics>, in 1850, Charlotte wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><xhtml:div>My sister's disposition was not naturally gregarious; circumstances favoured and fostered her tendency to seclusion; except to go to church or take a walk on the hills, she rarely crossed the threshold of home. Though her feeling for the people round was benevolent, intercourse with them she never sought; nor, with very few exceptions, ever experienced. And yet she knew them: knew their ways, their language, their family histories; she could hear of them with interest, and talk of them with detail, minute, graphic, and accurate; but WITH them, she rarely exchanged a word.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>s:Wuthering Heights/Editor's Preface</target><part>Editor's ''Preface''</part></link><space/>to the Second Edition of<space/><italics><link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link></italics>, by<space/><link><target>Charlotte Bront</target></link>, 1850.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. Charlotte Bront's &quot;Biographical Notice of Ellis and Acton Bell&quot;, in<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights and Agnes Grey: In Two Volumes</italics>, Vol. I (1951), p. xiii: &quot;In Emily's nature the extremes of vigour and simplicity seemed to meet. Under an unsophisticated culture, inartificial tastes, and an unpretending outside, lay a secret power and fire that might have informed the brain and kindled the veins of a hero; but she had no worldly wisdom; her powers were unadapted to the practical business of life; she would fail to defend her most manifest rights, to consult her most legitimate advantage. An interpreter ought always to have stood between her and the world. Her will was not very flexible, and it generally opposed her interest. Her temper was magnanimous, but warm and sudden; her spirit altogether unbending.&quot;</extension></xhtml:div></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Emily's unsociability and extremely shy nature has subsequently been reported many times.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily Bront is altogether an enigma. We perceive a power about her which could not find reasonable vent or utterance, so shut in was it by her repulsive and unsocial qualities. The intense love of life is as strange a feature as any.&quot; The Living Age (1857), Volume 55, p. 409</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;[Emily Bront]'s leanings and affinities were all of a weird character. Unsocial, stubborn in will, destitute of affection for any human being, seemingly unsusceptible of influence or impression from her sisters...&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>w:The Ladies' Repository</target><part>The Ladies' Repository</part></link></italics>, February, 1861.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Emily Bront was quite unlike her sisters. She was eccentric, antisocial, painfully shy, and probably meant what she said when she expressed a preference for dogs over people&quot; Alexander, Sellars,<space/><italics>The Art of the Bronts</italics><space/>(1995), p. 100</extension><space/>According to Norma Crandall, her &quot;warm, human aspect&quot; was &quot;usually revealed only in her love of nature and of animals&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norma Crandall,<space/><italics>Emily Bront: a psychological portrait</italics><space/>(1957), p. 81</extension><space/>In a similar description,<space/><italics>Literary news</italics><space/>(1883) states: &quot;[Emily] loved the solemn moors, she loved all wild, free creatures and things&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Pylodet, Leypoldt,<space/><italics>Literary news</italics><space/>(1883) Volume 4, p. 152</extension><space/>and critics attest that her love of the moors is manifest in<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bront Society,<space/><italics>The Bronts Then and Now</italics><space/>(1947), p. 31</extension><space/>Over the years, Emily's love of nature has been the subject of many anecdotes. A newspaper dated 31 December 1899, gives the folksy account that &quot;with bird and beast [Emily] had the most intimate relations, and from her walks she often came with fledgling or young rabbit in hand, talking softly to it, quite sure, too, that it understood&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sacramento"><italics><link><target>w:The Sacramento Union</target><part>The Record-Union</part></link></italics>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82015104/1899-12-31/ed-1/seq-10/'>&quot;Sacramento&quot;</link>, 31 December 1899.</extension><space/>The following anecdote is also related:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><xhtml:div>Once she was bitten by a dog that she saw running by in great distress, and to which she offered water. The dog was mad. She said no word to any one, but herself burned the lacerated flesh to the bone with the red hot poker, and no one knew of it until the red scar was accidentally discovered some weeks after, and sympathetic questioning brought out this story.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sacramento"></extension></xhtml:div></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Queens of Literature of the Victorian Era</italics><space/>(1886), Eva Hope summarises Emily's character as &quot;a peculiar mixture of timidity and Spartan-like courage&quot;, and goes on to say, &quot;She was painfully shy, but physically she was brave to a surprising degree. She loved few persons, but those few with a passion of self-sacrificing tenderness and devotion. To other people's failings she was understanding and forgiving, but over herself she kept a continual and most austere watch, never allowing herself to deviate for one instant from what she considered her duty.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Eva Hope,<space/><italics>Queens of Literature of the Victorian Era</italics><space/>(1886), p. 168</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Wuthering.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Title page of the original edition of ''<link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link>'' (1847)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics></heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Wuthering Heights</arg></template>Emily Bront's<space/><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics><space/>was first published in<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>in 1847, appearing as the first two volumes of a three-volume set that included<space/><link><target>Anne Bront</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Agnes Grey</target></link></italics>. The authors were printed as being Ellis and Acton Bell; Emily's real name did not appear until 1850, when it was printed on the title page of an edited commercial edition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard E. Mezo,<space/><italics>A Student's Guide to Wuthering Heights by Emily Bront</italics><space/>(2002), p. 2</extension><space/>The novel's innovative structure somewhat puzzled critics.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics>'s violence and passion led the Victorian public and many early reviewers to think that it had been written by a man.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carter, McRae,<space/><italics>The Routledge History of Literature in English: Britain and Ireland</italics><space/>(2001), p. 240</extension><space/>According to<space/><link><target>Juliet Gardiner</target></link>, &quot;the vivid sexual passion and power of its language and imagery impressed, bewildered and appalled reviewers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Juliet Gardiner,<space/><italics>The History today who's who in British history</italics><space/>(2000), p. 109</extension><space/>Even though it received mixed reviews when it first came out, and was often condemned for its portrayal of amoral passion, the book subsequently became an English literary classic.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Wuthering Heights</italics>, Mobi Classics (2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although a letter from her publisher indicates that Emily had begun to write a second novel, the manuscript has never been found. Perhaps Emily, or a member of her family, eventually destroyed the manuscript, if it existed, when she was prevented by illness from completing it. It has also been suggested that, though less likely, the letter could have been intended for<space/><link><target>Anne Bront</target></link>, who was already writing<space/><italics><link><target>The Tenant of Wildfell Hall</target></link></italics>, her second novel. In any case, no manuscript of a second novel by Emily has survived.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The letters of Charlotte Bront</italics><space/>(1995), edited by Margaret Smith, Volume Two<space/><italics>18481851</italics>, p. 27</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Death</heading><paragraph>Emily believed that her health, like her sisters', had been weakened by the harsh local climate and by unsanitary conditions at home,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Gaskell, Elizabeth</arg><arg name="origyear">1857</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="title">The Life of Charlotte Brontë</arg><arg name="place">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin</arg><arg name="page">264</arg></template></extension><space/>the source of water being contaminated by runoff from the church's graveyard.<extension extension_name='ref'>A letter from Charlotte Bront to Ellen Nussey is quoted in Elizabeth Gaskell.<space/><italics>The Biography of Charlotte Bront</italics>. Oxford Edition 1996. Charlotte refers to the winter of 1833/4 which was unusually wet and there were a large number of deaths in the village thought to be caused by water running down from the churchyard.</extension><space/>She caught a severe cold<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Branwell died suddenly, on September 24, 1848, a Sunday. At his funeral service, a week later, Bront caught a severe cold which developed with deadly speed into inflammation of the lungs and consumption.&quot; Richard Benvenuto,<space/><italics>Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1982), p. 24</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Branwell collapsed and died on September 24; Emily caught a chill at his funeral and died of galloping consumption on December 19&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Encyclopedia Americana, Volume 1</arg><arg name="publisher">Americana Corp</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="page">596</arg></template></extension><space/>during the funeral of her brother<space/><link><target>Branwell Bront</target><part>Branwell</part></link><space/>in September 1848 and was soon showing symptoms of tuberculosis. (It should be noted by the modern reader, though many of her contemporaries believed otherwise, &quot;consumption&quot;, or tuberculosis does not originate from &quot;catching a cold&quot;. Tuberculosis is a communicable disease through mucus and saliva and anyone living in a house with another member would be likely to contract it, or certainly risked exposure. It is also a disease that can remain asymptomatic, so it is even possible that all of the children could have contracted it at the same time.) Though her condition worsened steadily, she rejected medical help and all proffered remedies, saying that she would have &quot;no poisoning doctor&quot; near her.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fraser"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Fraser</arg><arg name="first">Rebecca</arg><arg name="title">Charlotte Brontë: A Writer's Life</arg><arg name="publisher">Pegasus Books LLC</arg><arg name="location">45 Wall Street, Suite 1021 New York, NY 10005</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="edition">2</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-933648-88-0</arg><arg name="page">261</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;[Emily's] extraordinary temper... showed itself in its utmost exaggeration as bodily disease gained upon her. She rejected all sympathy and medical assistance; the sisters dared not notice her failing limbs and panting breath; she would receive help from none.&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>w:The Ladies' Repository</target><part>The Ladies' Repository</part></link></italics>, February, 1861.</extension><space/>On the morning of 19 December 1848,<space/><link><target>Charlotte Bront</target><part>Charlotte</part></link>, fearing for her sister, wrote this:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><xhtml:div>She grows daily weaker. The physician's opinion was expressed too obscurely to be of use he sent some medicine which she would not take. Moments so dark as these I have never known I pray for God's support to us all.<extension extension_name='ref'>Elizabeth Gaskell,<space/><italics>The life of Charlotte Bront</italics><space/>(1870), p. 281</extension></xhtml:div></extension>At noon, Emily was worse; she could only whisper in gasps. With her last audible words she said to Charlotte, &quot;If you will send for a doctor, I will see him now&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>w:The Ladies' Repository</target><part>The Ladies' Repository</part></link></italics><space/>for July 1857</extension><space/>but it was too late. She died that same day at about two in the afternoon while sitting on the sofa at<space/><link><target>w:Bront Parsonage Museum</target><part>Haworth Parsonage</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Folio Society,<space/><italics>The complete poems of Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1951), p. 282</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Written Lives">Javier Maras, Margaret Jull Costa,<space/><italics>Written Lives</italics><space/>(2006), p. 171</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;She dragged herself down to the sitting-room, and died there, about two o'clock. She must have had some horror of dying in that room of death overhead; for, at noon, when the last pains seized her, she refused to be taken back to it. Unterrified, indomitable, driven by her immortal passion for life, she fought terribly. Death took her as she tried to rise from the sofa and break from her sisters' arms that would have laid her there. Profoundly, piteously alienated, she must have felt that Anne and Charlotte were in league with death; that they fought with her and bound her down; and that in her escape from them she conquered.&quot; May Sinclair,<space/><italics>The Three Bronts</italics><space/>(2004), p. 22</extension><space/>It was less than three months since Branwell's death, which led a housemaid to declare that &quot;Miss Emily died of a broken heart for love of her brother&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Written Lives"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;To Martha Brown and her sisters, loyal servants of the Bront family, there never appeared to be any doubt that Emily died of grief for her brother. She was taken ill after his funeral and was dead within three months. It was as simple as that.&quot; Winifred Grin,<space/><italics>Emily Bront: a biography</italics><space/>(1971), p. 242</extension><space/>Emily had grown so thin that her coffin measured only 16 inches wide. The carpenter said he had never made a narrower one for an adult.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catherine Reef,<space/><italics>The Bront Sisters: The Brief Lives of Charlotte, Emily, and Anne</italics><space/>(2012)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Bront inscribed her desire on her flesh as hungerand her body became, in the absence of speech, the very text of her deprivation. She died on 19 December 1848 and was buried three days later. Her coffin maker, William Wood, had to construct the narrowest coffin he had ever made for an adult; it measured just 16 inches across&quot; Steven Vine,<space/><italics>Emily Bront</italics><space/>(1998), p. 20</extension><space/>She was interred in the Church of<space/><link><target>Michael (archangel)</target><part>St Michael</part></link><space/>and All Angels family capsule,<space/><link><target>Haworth</target></link>,<space/><link><target>West Yorkshire</target></link>, England. Emily Bront never knew the extent of fame she achieved with her one and only novel,<space/><italics><link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link></italics>, as she died a year after its publication, aged 30.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Novels</arg><arg>Poetry</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Walterclough Hall</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>A Death-Scene</target></link><space/>Poem published in 1846</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">yes</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">yes</arg><arg name="viaf">97097302</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Emily Bront</italics>, Charles Simpson</listitem><listitem><italics>In the Footsteps of the Bronts</italics>, Ellis Chadwick</listitem><listitem><italics>Last Things: Emily Bront's Poems</italics>,<space/><link><target>Janet Gezari</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>The Oxford Reader's Companion to the Bronts</italics>, Christine Alexander &amp; Margaret Smith</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Literature and Evil</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Georges Bataille</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>The Bront Myth</italics>,<space/><link><target>Lucasta Miller</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>Emily</italics>, Daniel Wynne</listitem><listitem><italics>Dark Quartet</italics>,<space/><link><target>Lynne Reid Banks</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>Emily Bront</italics>,<space/><link><target>Winifred Gerin</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>A Chainless Soul: A Life of Emily Bront</italics>,<space/><link><target>Katherine Frank</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>Emily Bront. Her Life and Work</italics>,<space/><link><target>Muriel Spark</target></link><space/>and Derek Stanford</listitem><listitem><italics>Emily's Ghost: A Novel of the Bront Sisters</italics>,<space/><link><target>Denise Giardina</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>Charlotte and Emily: A Novel of the Bronts</italics>, Jude Morgan</listitem><listitem>L. P. Hartley, 'Emily Bront In Gondal And Galdine', in L. P. Hartley,<space/><italics>The Novelist's Responsibility</italics><space/>(1967), p.&amp;nbsp;3553</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource author</target></template><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Emily Brontë</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Brontë,+Emily<space/></arg><arg name="name">Emily Brontë</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Emily Brontë</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">2072</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bronte.org.uk/'>Website of the Bront Scoeity and Bront Parsonage Museum in Haworth</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/emilybront00robi'>''Emily Bront''</link>, by A. Mary F Robinson, 1883 A Biography Archive.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.poetseers.org/the_great_poets/british_poets/emily_bronte_poems/'>Short biography and selected Poems</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=111811052051951249860.00043456f50a0204ad5d4&amp;amp;z=10&amp;amp;om=1'>Map of Locations associated with ''Wuthering Heights'' and Emily Bront</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Bront sisters</target></template><template><target>Wuthering Heights</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Brontë, Emily Jane
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">Bell, Ellis
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>English novelist and poetess
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>30 July 1818
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Thornton, West Yorkshire|Thornton]], [[West Riding of Yorkshire]], England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>19 December 1848
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Haworth]], West Riding of Yorkshire, England
</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Bronte, Emily</target></template><link><target>Category:1818 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1848 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:English novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:English women poets</target></link><link><target>Category:English women novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:English people of Irish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Women of the Victorian era</target></link><link><target>Category:Victorian novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:Victorian women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:English Anglicans</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from tuberculosis</target></link><link><target>Category:Governesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Pseudonymous writers</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Thornton and Allerton</target></link><link><target>Category:Bront family</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Infectious disease deaths in England</target></link><link><target>Category:British people of Cornish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century British novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century English writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials in West Yorkshire</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century women writers</target></link></paragraph></article>