<article title='%C3%86lle_of_Sussex'><paragraph><template><target>featured article</target></template><template><target>Infobox monarch</target><arg name="name">Ælle
</arg><arg name="image">Aelle name in 477 annal.png
</arg><arg name="caption">Ælle's name is visible in this line from the Parker manuscript of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', written c. 890
</arg><arg name="title">King of Sussex
</arg><arg name="rank">7th
</arg><arg name="reign">c.477 – c.514?<ref name</arg><arg name="successor">[[Cissa of Sussex|Cissa]]?<ref name</arg><arg name="issue">Cissa, Cymen, Wlencing</arg></template><bold>lle</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>ə</arg></template>; also<space/><bold>Aelle</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Ella</bold>) is recorded in early sources as the first<space/><link><target>monarchy</target><part>king</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Sussex</target><part>South Saxons</part></link>, reigning in what is now called<space/><link><target>Sussex</target></link>, England, from 477 to perhaps as late as 514.<extension extension_name='ref' name="greenway97"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the<space/><italics><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</target></link></italics>, lle and three of his sons are said to have landed at a place called<space/><link><target>Cymenshore</target><part>Cymensora</part></link><space/>and fought against the local<space/><link><target>Brython</target><part>Britons</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heron-Allen. Selsey Bill. Historic and Prehistoric. Duckworth. Ch.VII pp 88-90 Heron-Allen discusses the confusion by historians about the location of Cymens'ora and argues the case for it being Keynor</extension><space/>The chronicle goes on to report a victory in 491, at present day<space/><link><target>Pevensey</target></link>, where the battle ended with the Saxons slaughtering their opponents to the last man.</paragraph><paragraph>lle was the first king recorded by the 8th century chronicler<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link><space/>to have held &quot;<link><target>imperium</target></link>&quot;, or overlordship, over other<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxons</target><part>Anglo-Saxon</part></link><space/>kingdoms.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_111">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, II 5.</extension><space/>In the late 9th-century<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>(around four hundred years after his time) lle is recorded as being the first<space/><link><target>bretwalda</target></link>, or &quot;Britain-ruler&quot;, though there is no evidence that this was a contemporary title. lle's death is not recorded and although he may have been the founder of a South Saxon dynasty, there is no firm evidence linking him with later South Saxon rulers. The 12th-century chronicler<space/><link><target>Henry of Huntingdon</target></link><space/>produced an enhanced version of the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>that included 514 as the date of lle's death, but this is not secure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="greenway97"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="greenwaylxxxvi">Henry of Huntingdon.<space/><italics>Historia Anglorum</italics>. ed. Greenway. Sources section p.lxxxvi. &quot;Henry was one of the 'weaver' compilers of whom Bernard Guenee has written. Taking a phrase from here and a phrase from there, connecting with one there, he wove together a continuous narrative which, deriviative though it mostly is, is still very much his own creation,...&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical context</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Ella - John Speed.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Imaginary depiction of lle from<space/><link><target>John Speed</target></link>'s 1611 &quot;Saxon Heptarchy&quot;.</part></link>Historians are divided on the detail of lle's life and existence as it was during the least-documented period in English history of the last two millennia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CampbellTAS20">For example, James Campbell writes: &quot;The natural vice of historians is to claim to know about the past. Nowhere is this claim more dangerous than when it is staked in<space/><link><target>Sub-Roman Britain</target><part>Britain</part></link><space/>between AD 400 and 600&quot; (<italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 20).</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="welch9">Welch.<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>. p. 9. &quot;The AS Chronicle was a product of the West Saxon court and is concerned with glorifying the royal ancestry of Alfred the Great. Manipulation of royal genealogies, in this and other sources, to enhance the claims of present rulers was common. Literary formulas associated with original myths are a common feature of earlier entries. When Aella and his three sons land from three ships on a beach named after one of the sons, we are reading legend rather than real history.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the early 5th century Britain had been<space/><link><target>Roman Britain</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>for over three hundred and fifty years. The most troublesome enemies of Roman Britain were the<space/><link><target>Pict</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of central and northern<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Gaels</target></link><space/>known as<space/><link><target>Scoti</target></link>, who were raiders from<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link>. Also vexatious were the<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link>, the name Roman writers gave to the peoples who lived in the northern part of what is now Germany and the southern part of the<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link><space/>peninsula. Saxon raids on the southern and eastern shores of England had been sufficiently alarming by the late 3rd century for the Romans to build the<space/><link><target>Saxon Shore Forts</target><part>Saxon Shore forts</part></link>, and subsequently to establish the role of the<space/><link><target>Count of the Saxon Shore</target></link><space/>to command the defence against these incursions. Roman control of Britain finally ended in the early part of the 5th century; the date usually given as marking the end of Roman Britain is 410, when the Emperor<space/><link><target>Honorius (emperor)</target><part>Honorius</part></link><space/>sent letters to the British, urging them to look to their own defence. Britain had been repeatedly stripped of troops to support usurpers' claims to the Roman empire, and after 410 the Roman armies never returned.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_1">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, pp. 114.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_13">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics><space/>pp. 1316.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sources for events after this date are extremely scarce, but a tradition, reported as early as the mid-6th century by a British priest named<space/><link><target>Gildas</target></link>, records that the British sent for help against the barbarians to<space/><link><target>Flavius Aetius</target><part>Aetius</part></link>, a Roman<space/><link><target>consul</target></link>, probably in the late 440s. No help came. Subsequently, a British leader named<space/><link><target>Vortigern</target></link><space/>is supposed to have invited continental mercenaries to help fight the Picts who were attacking from the north. The leaders, whose names are recorded as<space/><link><target>Hengest</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Horsa</target></link>, rebelled, and a long period of warfare ensued. The invaders&amp;mdash;<link><target>Angles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Frisii</target><part>Frisians</part></link>&amp;mdash;gained control of parts of England, but lost a major battle at<space/><link><target>Mons Badonicus</target></link><space/>(the location of which is not known). Some authors have speculated that lle may have led the Saxon forces at this battle,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bradbury</arg><arg name="first">James</arg><arg name="title">The Routledge Companion to Medieval Warfare</arg><arg name="pages">140</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-415-22126-9</arg></template></extension><space/>while others reject the idea out of hand.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Warner</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="title">British Battlefields: The Midlands</arg><arg name="pages">23</arg><arg name="year">1972</arg><arg name="location">Reading</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey</arg><arg name="oclc">60058359</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British thus gained a respite, and peace lasted at least until the time<space/><link><target>Gildas</target></link><space/>was writing: that is, for perhaps forty or fifty years, from around the end of the 5th century until midway through the sixth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_13">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, pp. 1316.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_23">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics><space/>p. 23.</extension><space/>Shortly after Gildas's time the Anglo-Saxon advance was resumed, and by the late 6th century nearly all of southern England was under the control of the continental invaders.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_RBaEE_204">Hunter Blair (<italics>Roman Britain</italics>, p. 204) gives the twenty-five years from 550 to 575 as the dates of the final conquest.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early sources</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Parker chronicle f. 5a 455-490.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>A page from the [A] manuscript of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle''. lle's name, spelled &quot;Elle&quot;, can be seen in two of the entries at the end of the page. The last entry on the page, for 488, refers to events in<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Kent</target><part>Kent</part></link><space/>and does not mention lle.</part><trail>There</trail></link><space/>are two early sources that mention lle by name. The earliest is<space/><italics><link><target>Ecclesiastical History of the English People</target><part>The Ecclesiastical History of the English People</part></link></italics>, a history of the English church written in 731 by<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Northumbria</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>monk. Bede mentions lle as one of the Anglo-Saxon kings who exercised what he calls &quot;imperium&quot; over &quot;all the provinces south of the river<space/><link><target>Humber</target></link>&quot;; &quot;imperium&quot; is usually translated as &quot;overlordship&quot;. Bede gives a list of seven kings who held &quot;imperium&quot;, and lle is the first of them. The other information Bede gives is that lle was not a Christian&amp;mdash;Bede mentions a later king as &quot;the first to enter the kingdom of heaven&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_111"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second source is the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, a collection of annals assembled in the Kingdom of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link><space/>in c. 890, during the reign of<space/><link><target>Alfred the Great</target></link>. The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>has three entries for lle, from 477 to 491, as follows:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14">Translations are<space/><link><target>Michael Swanton</target></link>'s (<italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, p. 14), from the A text of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>; except that Frank M. Stenton's translation (<italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 1718) of part has been substituted to keep &quot;Andredes leag&quot; and &quot;Andredes cester&quot; in the text, for subsequent explanation.</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>477: lle and his 3 sons, Cymen and Wlencing and Cissa, came to the land of Britain with 3 ships at the place which is named<space/><link><target>Cymen's shore</target></link>, and there killed many Welsh and drove some to flight into the wood called Andredes leag.</listitem><listitem>485: Here lle fought against the Welsh near the margin of Mearcred's Burn.</listitem><listitem>491: Here lle and Cissa besieged Andredes cester, and killed all who lived in there; there was not even one Briton left there.</listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>was put together about four hundred years after these events. It is known that the annalists used material from earlier chronicles, as well as from oral sources such as sagas, but there is no way to tell where these lines came from.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_xviii">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. xviii-xix</extension><space/>It should also be noted that the terms 'British' and 'Welsh' were used interchangeably, as 'Welsh' is the Saxon word meaning 'foreigner', and was applied to all the native Romano-British of the era.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14_2">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, p. 14.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Three of the places named may be identified :</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Cymen's shore</target></link>&quot; (&quot;Cymenes ora&quot; in the original) is believed to be located at what is now a series of rocks and ledges, in the English Channel off<space/><link><target>Selsey Bill</target></link>, on the south coast, known as the Owers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ngia4">NIMA.Pub194. Sailing Directions. English Channel.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=m0zjxFyTSiQC&amp;amp;lpg=PA135&amp;amp;dq=channel%20pilot%20southcoast&amp;amp;pg=PA43#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>The Owers</link><space/>p. 43</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="kelly110">&quot;Kelly. Anglo-Saxon Charters VI. Charters of the Selsey .p. 3, p. 12 and p. 118</extension><space/>It has been suggested that Ower is derived from the word<space/><bold>ora</bold><space/>that is found only in placenames where Jutish and West Saxon dialects were in operation (mainly in southern England).<extension extension_name='ref' name="gelling179">Gelling. Placenames in the Landscape. pp. 179-180</extension><space/>It is possible that the stretch of low ground along the coast from<space/><link><target>Southampton</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Bognor, Sussex</target><part>Bognor</part></link><space/>was called<space/><italics>Ora</italics><space/>&quot;the shore&quot;, and that district names were used by the various coastal settlements, Cymens ora being one of them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gelling179"></extension></listitem><listitem>The wood called &quot;Andredes leag&quot; is the<space/><link><target>Weald</target></link>, which at that time was a forest extending from north-west<space/><link><target>Hampshire</target></link><space/>all through northern Sussex.</listitem><listitem>&quot;Andredes cester&quot; is thought to be<space/><link><target>Anderitum</target></link>, the Saxon Shore fort, built by the Roman rebel Carausius in the late 3rd century, at<space/><link><target>Pevensey Castle</target></link>, just outside the town.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BlairRBaEE_176">Blair. Roman Britain. p. 176</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_17">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 1719.</extension><space/>Some believe Andredes cester may have been an imperial stronghold somewhere else as Henry of Huntingdon described the place as a fortified city and gave a very full account of the siege which is inconsistent with the geography of ancient Pevensey and little archaeological evidence of sustained settlement there.<extension extension_name='ref' name="huntingdon92">Huntingdon. ed. Greenway. Historia Anglorum: The History of the English People. pp. 92-93</extension><space/>Also, in his<space/><link><target>William Camden#Britannia</target><part>&quot;Britannia&quot;</part></link>,<space/><link><target>William Camden</target></link><space/>suggests that it could be<space/><link><target>Newenden</target><part>Newenden, Kent</part></link><space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="camden40">Camden.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.philological.bham.ac.uk/cambrit/kenteng.html#kent40'>Britannia. Vol 2. Ch. 20. Section 40</link>. Retrieved 4 October 2015</extension></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Image:Owers sandbanks map 1780.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>A detail from a 1780 map, showing the Isle of Wight, Selsey Bill, and the Owers shoals to the south.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ngia4"></extension><space/>Pevensey is about thirty miles to the east, along the coast.</part><trail>The</trail></link><space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>mentions lle once more under the year 827, where he is listed as the first of the eight &quot;<link><target>bretwaldas</target></link>&quot;, or &quot;Britain-rulers&quot;. The list consists of Bede's original seven, plus<space/><link><target>Egbert of Wessex</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_60">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 6061.</extension><space/>There has been much scholarly debate over just what it meant to be a &quot;bretwalda&quot;, and the extent of lle's actual power in southern England is an open question.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_201">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, pp. 201202.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_53">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, pp. 5354.</extension><space/>It is also noteworthy that there is a long gap between lle and the second king on Bede's list,<space/><link><target>Ceawlin of Wessex</target></link>, whose reign began in the late 6th century; this may indicate a period in which Anglo-Saxon dominance was interrupted in some way.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_17"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Earlier sources than Bede exist which mention the South Saxons, though they do not name lle. The earliest reference is still quite late, however, at about 692: a charter of King<space/><link><target>Nothelm of Sussex</target><part>Nothelm</part></link>'s, which styles him &quot;King of the South Saxons&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_20">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 2021.</extension><space/>Charters are documents which granted land to followers or to churchmen, and which would be witnessed by the kings who had power to grant the land. They are one of the key documentary sources for Anglo-Saxon history, but no original charters survive from earlier than the end of the 7th century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BlairRBaEE_14">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>Roman Britain</italics>, pp. 1415.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_95_2">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, pp.9598.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are other early writers whose works can shed light on lle's time, though they do not mention either him or his kingdom. Gildas's description of the state of Britain in his time is useful for understanding the ebb and flow of the Anglo-Saxon incursions.<space/><link><target>Procopius</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Byzantine</target></link><space/>historian, writing not long after Gildas, adds to the meagre sources on population movement by including a chapter on England in one of his works. He records that the peoples of Britain&amp;mdash;he names the English, the British, and the Frisians&amp;mdash;were so numerous that they were migrating to the kingdom of the Franks in great numbers every year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_RBaEE_164">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>Roman Britain</italics>, p. 164.</extension><space/>Although this is probably a reference to Britons emigrating to<space/><link><target>Armorica</target></link><space/>to escape the Anglo-Saxons. They subsequently gave their name to the area they settled as<space/><link><target>Brittany</target></link>, or<space/><italics>la petite Bretagne</italics><space/>(literally little Britain).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Evidence from place names in Sussex</heading><paragraph>The early dates given in the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>for the colonization of Sussex are supported by an analysis of the place names of the region. The strongest evidence comes from place names that end in &quot;-ing&quot;, such as<space/><link><target>Worthing</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Angmering</target></link>. These are known to derive from an earlier form ending in &quot;-ingas&quot;. &quot;<link><target>Hastings</target></link>&quot; for example, derives from &quot;Hstingas&quot; which may mean &quot;the followers or dependents of a person named Hsta&quot;, although others suggest the heavily Romanised region may have had names of Gallo-Roman origin derived from &quot;-ienses&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BlairRBaEE_176_2">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>Roman Britain</italics>, pp. 176178.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From west of Selsey Bill to east of Pevensey can be found the densest concentration of these names anywhere in Britain. There are a total of about forty-five place names in Sussex of this form, however, personal names either were not associated with these places or fell out of use. This does not necessarily mean that the Saxons killed or drove out almost all of the native population, despite the slaughter of the Britons reported in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>entry for 491; however, it does imply that the invasion was on a scale that left little space for the British.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_17"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>These lines of reasoning cannot prove the dates given in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, much less the existence of lle himself, but they do support the idea of an early conquest and the establishment of a settled kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BlairRBaEE_176_2"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_22">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, p. 22.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reign</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:SE England Aelle.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>A map of south-eastern England showing places visited by lle, according to the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', and the area of modern Sussex.</part><trail>If</trail></link><space/>the dates given by the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>are accurate to within half a century, then lle's reign lies in the middle of the Anglo-Saxon expansion, and prior to the final conquest of the Britons. It also seems consistent with the dates given to assume that lle's battles predate Mons Badonicus. This in turn would explain the long gap, of fifty or more years, in the succession of the &quot;bretwaldas&quot;: if the peace gained by the Britons did indeed hold till the second half of the 6th century, it is not to be expected that an Anglo-Saxon leader should have anything resembling overlordship of England during that time. The idea of a pause in the Anglo-Saxon advance is also supported by the account in Procopius of 6th century migration from Britain to the kingdom of the<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_17"></extension><space/>Procopius's account is consistent with what is known to be a contemporary colonization of<space/><link><target>Armorica</target></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>Brittany</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>France</target></link>); the settlers appear to have been at least partly from<space/><link><target>Dumnonia</target></link><space/>(modern<space/><link><target>Cornwall</target></link>), and the area acquired regions known as Dumnone and Cornouaille.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_22">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 22.</extension><space/>It seems likely that something at that time was interrupting the general flow of the Anglo-Saxons from the continent to Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_12">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The dates for lle's battles are also reasonably consistent with what is known of events in the kingdom of the Franks at that time.<space/><link><target>Clovis I</target></link><space/>united the Franks into a single kingdom during the 480s and afterwards, and the Franks' ability to exercise power along the southern coast of the English channel may have diverted Saxon adventurers to England rather than the continent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_12"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is possible, therefore, that a historical king named lle existed, who arrived from the continent in the late 5th century, and who conquered much of what is now Sussex. He may have been a prominent war chief with a leadership role in a federation of Anglo-Saxon groups fighting for territory in Britain at that time. This may be the origin of the reputation that led Bede to list him as holding overlordship over southern Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fletcher_17">Fletcher,<space/><italics>Who's Who</italics>, p. 17.</extension><space/>The battles listed in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>are compatible with a conquest of Sussex from west to east, against British resistance stiff enough to last fourteen years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_17"></extension><space/>His area of military control may have extended as far as<space/><link><target>Hampshire</target></link><space/>and north to the upper<space/><link><target>Thames</target></link><space/>valley, but it certainly did not extend across all of England south of the Humber, as Bede asserts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_55">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 55.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The historian<space/><link><target>Guy Halsall</target></link><space/>argues that as lle immediately preceded the late sixth-century King Ceawlin as Bretwalda, it is far more likely that lle dates to the mid sixth century, and that the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>has moved his dates back a century in order to provide a foundation myth for Sussex which puts it chronologically and geographically between the origins of the kingdoms of Kent and Wessex.<extension extension_name='ref'>Halsall,<space/><italics>Worlds of Arthur</italics>, p. 71</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Death and burial</heading><paragraph>lle's death is not recorded by the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, which gives no information about him, or his sons, or the South Saxons until 675, when the South Saxon king<space/><link><target>Aethelwalh of Sussex</target><part>thelwalh</part></link><space/>was baptized.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_12"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It has been conjectured that, as Saxon war leader, lle may have met his death in the disastrous battle of<space/><link><target>Mount Badon</target></link><space/>when the Britons halted Saxon expansion<extension extension_name='ref' name="InSaxonSx">Alec Hamilton-Barr. In Saxon Sussex. The Arundel Press, Bognor Regis. p 21</extension><space/>If lle died within the borders of his own kingdom then it may well have been that he was buried on<space/><link><target>Highdown Hill</target></link><space/>with his weapons and ornaments in the usual mode of burial among the South Saxons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="InSaxonSx"></extension><space/>Highdown Hill is the traditional burial-place of the kings of Sussex.<extension extension_name='ref' name="InSaxonSx"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Timeline of the Anglo-Saxon invasion and takeover of Britain</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Primary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum|Ecclesiastical History of the English People]]</arg><arg name="others"><space/>Translated by Leo Sherley-Price, revised R.E. Latham, ed. D.H. Farmer</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-14-044565-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Swanton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-92129-5</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Secondary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Camden</arg><arg name="first"><space/>William<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brittannia Vol 2 Updated English version<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Joseph Wild</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1701</arg><arg name="authorlink">William Camden<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Campbell</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>John</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Eric</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Wormald</arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Patrick</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxons</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin Books</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-014395-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fletcher</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Who's Who in Roman Britain and Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Shepheard-Walwyn</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85683-089-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gelling</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Margaret</arg><arg name="title">''Place-Names in the Landscape''<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000</arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-84212-264-9</arg><arg name="publisher">Phoenix</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Guy</arg><arg name="last">Halsall</arg><arg name="authorlink">Guy Halsall</arg><arg name="title">Worlds of Arthur: Facts & Fictions of the Dark Ages</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-870084-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Heron-Allen</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Edward</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Selsey Historic and Prehistoric</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1911</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Duckworth</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="authorlink">Peter Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="title"><space/>An Introduction to Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="pages">13–16</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1960</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Roman Britain and Early England: 55 B.C. &ndash; A.D. 871</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1966</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>W.W. Norton & Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-393-00361-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">Henry of Huntingdon</arg><arg name="title">Historia Anglorum: the history of the English</arg><arg name="editor">Greenway, Diana E.</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-19-822224-6</arg><arg name="publisher">OUP</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="editor-last">Kelly</arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>S. E.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-Saxon Charters VI, Charters of Selsey</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998</arg><arg name="publisher">OUP for the British Academy</arg><arg name="ISBN">0-19-726175-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kirby</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.P.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Earliest English Kings</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-09086-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">NIMA</arg><arg name="title">Pub. 194 Sailing Directions(Enroute) English Channel. 11th edition</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">ProStar Publications, Inc.</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">1-57785-564-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Stenton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Frank M.</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Frank Stenton</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Clarendon Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-821716-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Welch</arg><arg name="first"><space/>M. G.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="publisher">English Heritage</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7134-6566-2</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Kings of Sussex</target></template><template><target>Bretwalda</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Ælle
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Aelle; Ella
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>First king of the South Saxons
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Aelle Of Sussex</target></template><link><target>Category:510s deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:South Saxon monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Founding monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century monarchs in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century English people</target></link><link><target>Category:5th-century English people</target></link><link><target>Category:Year of birth unknown</target></link></paragraph></article>