<article title='Economy_of_the_Bahamas'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox economy</target><arg name="country"><space/>Bahamas
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>
</arg><arg name="width"><space/>270
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>[[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]] is the capital and financial center of the [[Bahamas]]
</arg><arg name="currency"><space/>[[Bahamian dollar]] (BSD) 
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1 July - 30 June
</arg><arg name="organs"><space/>[[World Trade Organization|WTO]], [[CARICOM]]
</arg><arg name="gdp rank"><space/>[[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|140th]] (nominal) / [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|153rd]] (PPP)
</arg><arg name="gdp"><space/>$11.04 billion (2012 est. PPP)
</arg><arg name="growth"><space/>2.5% (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="per capita"><space/>$31,300 (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="sectors"><space/>agriculture: 2.1%, industry: 7.1%, services: 90.8% (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="inflation"><space/>2.5% (2012)
</arg><arg name="poverty"><space/>9.3% (2004)
</arg><arg name="labor"><space/>184,000 (2009)
</arg><arg name="occupations"><space/>agriculture 5%, industry 5%, tourism 50%, other services 40% (2005 est.)
</arg><arg name="unemployment"><space/>14.2% (2009 est.)
</arg><arg name="edbr"><space/>85th<ref name</arg><arg name="industries"><space/>[[tourism]], [[banking]], [[cement]], [[petroleum|oil]] [[transshipment]], [[salt]], [[rum]], [[aragonite]], [[pharmaceuticals]], spiral-welded steel pipe
</arg><arg name="exports"><space/>$790 million (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="export-goods"><space/>mineral products and salt, animal products, rum, chemicals, fruit and vegetables
</arg><arg name="export-partners"><space/>{{flag|Singapore}} 23.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|United States}} 19.5%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Dominican Republic}} 13.4%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Ecuador}} 9.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Canada}} 5.4%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Guatemala}} 4.4% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="imports"><space/>$2.882 billion (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="import-goods"><space/>machinery and transport equipment, manufactures, chemicals, mineral fuels; food and live animals
</arg><arg name="import-partners"><space/>{{flag|United States}} 29.9%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|India}} 20.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Singapore}} 8.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|South Korea}} 6.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|China}} 5.0%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Colombia}} 4.3%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Canada}} 4.2% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="debt"><space/>$342.6 million (2004 est.)
</arg><arg name="revenue"><space/>$1.5 billion (2012)
</arg><arg name="expenses"><space/>$1.8 billion (2012)
</arg><arg name="credit"><space/>BBB+ (Domestic)<br>BBB+ (Foreign)<br>A- (T&C Assessment)<br>([[Standard & Poor's]])<ref>{{cite web |title</arg><arg name="aid"><space/>''recipient'': $5 million (2004)
</arg><arg name="cianame"><space/>bf
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Bahamas</target></link><space/>is a stable, developing nation with an economy heavily dependent on<space/><link><target>tourism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>offshore banking</target></link>. Steady growth in tourism receipts and a boom in construction of new hotels, resorts, and residences had led to solid GDP growth for many years, but the slowdown in the US economy and the attacks of September 11, 2001 held back growth in these sectors in 2001-03. Financial services constitute the second-most important sector of the Bahamian economy, accounting for about 15% of GDP. However, since December 2000, when the government enacted new regulations on the financial sector, many international businesses have left The Bahamas. Manufacturing and agriculture together contribute approximately a tenth of GDP and show little growth, despite government incentives aimed at those sectors. Overall growth prospects in the short run rest heavily on the fortunes of the tourism sector, which depends on growth in the US, the source of more than 80% of the visitors. In addition to tourism and banking, the government supports the development of a &quot;2nd-pillar&quot;, e-commerce.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Basic Ingredients of the Bahamian Economy</heading><paragraph>The Bahamian economy is almost entirely dependent on tourism and financial services to generate foreign exchange earnings. Tourism alone provides an estimated 60% of the<space/><link><target>gross domestic product</target></link><space/>(GDP) and employs about half the Bahamian workforce. In 2004, over half a million tourists visited The Bahamas, most of whom are from the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A major contribution to the recent growth in the overall Bahamian economy is Kerzner International's Atlantis Resort and Casino, which took over the former Paradise Island Resort and has provided a much needed boost to the economy. In addition, the opening of Breezes Super Club and Sandals Resort also aided this turnaround. The Bahamian Government also has adopted a proactive approach to courting foreign investors and has conducted major investment missions to the<space/><link><target>Far East</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Latin America</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>. The primary purpose of the trips was to restore the reputation of The Bahamas in these markets.</paragraph><paragraph>Financial services constitute the second-most important sector of the Bahamian economy, accounting for up to 17% of GDP, due to the country's status as an offshore financial center. As of December 1998, the government had licensed 418 banks and trust companies in The Bahamas. The Bahamas promulgated the International Business Companies (IBC) Act in January 1990 to enhance the country's status as a leading financial center. The act served to simplify and reduce the cost of incorporating offshore companies in The Bahamas. Within 9 years, more than 84,000<space/><link><target>International Business Company</target><part>IBC</part></link>-type companies had been established. In February 1991, the government also legalized the establishment of<space/><link><target>Asset-protection trust</target><part>Asset Protection Trusts</part></link><space/>in The Bahamas. In December 2000, partly as a response to appearing the plenary<space/><link><target>FATF Blacklist</target></link>, the government enacted a legislative package to better regulate the financial sector, including creation of a Financial Intelligence Unit and enforcement of &quot;<link><target>Know your customer</target><part>know-your-customer</part></link>&quot; rules. Other initiatives include the enactment of the Foundations Act in 2004 and the planned introduction of legislation to regulate<space/><link><target>Trust company</target><part>Private Trust Companies</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Agriculture in the Bahamas</arg></template><template><target>see also</target><arg>Bahamian cuisine</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Agriculture</target></link><space/>and fisheries industry together account for 5% of GDP. The Bahamas exports lobster and some fish but does not raise these items commercially. There is no largescale agriculture, and most agricultural products are consumed domestically. The Bahamas imports more than $250 million in foodstuffs per year, representing about 80% of its food consumption. The government aims to expand food production to reduce imports and generate foreign exchange. It actively seeks foreign investment aimed at increasing agricultural exports, particularly specialty food items. The government officially lists beef and pork production and processing, fruits and nuts, dairy production, winter vegetables, and mariculture (shrimp farming) as the areas in which it wishes to encourage foreign investment.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bahamian Government maintains the value of the<space/><link><target>Bahamian dollar</target></link><space/>on a par with the<space/><link><target>U.S. dollar</target></link>. The Bahamas is a beneficiary of the U.S.-<link><target>Caribbean Basin Trade Partnership Act</target></link><space/>(CBTPA), Canada's<space/><link><target>CARIBCAN</target></link><space/>program, and the European Union's Lome IV Agreement. Although the Bahamas participates in the political aspects of the<space/><link><target>Caribbean Community</target></link><space/>(CARICOM), it has not entered into joint economic initiatives with other Caribbean states.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bahamas has a few notable industrial firms: the Freeport pharmaceutical firm, PharmaChem Technologies (GrandBahama) Ltd. (formerly Syntex); the BORCO oil facility, also in Freeport, which transships oil in the region; the<space/><link><target>Commonwealth Brewery</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Nassau, Bahamas</target><part>Nassau</part></link>, which produces<space/><link><target>Heineken Pilsener</target><part>Heineken</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Guinness</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Kalik</target></link><space/>beers;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.burnshouse.com'>Commonwealth Breweries / Burnshouse website</link></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bacardi</target><part>Bacardi Corp.</part></link>, which distills rum in Nassau for shipment to the U.S. and European markets. Other industries include sun-dried sea salt in Great Inagua, a wet dock facility in Freeport for repair of cruise ships, and mining of aragonitea type of limestone with several industrial usesfrom the sea floor at Ocean Cay. Other smaller but more nimble players in the banking industry include Fidelity Bank (Bahamas) Ltd. (FBB) and Royal Fidelity Merchant Bank &amp; Trust Limited (RFMBT). FBB offers a wide range of innovative banking products including loan products with built-in savings plans. RFMBT is the only merchant bank in The Bahamas and is a joint venture with Royal Bank of Canada. It provides investment products and services and attracts the majority of the corporate business deals in The Bahamas, most recently acting as financial advisor and placement agent for the largest Initial Public Offering (IPO) ever in The Bahamas with the IPO of Commonwealth Brewery, a Heineken subsidiary.</paragraph><paragraph>The Hawksbill Creek Agreement established a duty-free zone in Freeport, The Bahamas' second-largest city, with a nearby industrial park to encourage foreign industrial investment. The<space/><link><target>Hong Kong</target></link>-based firm,<space/><link><target>Hutchison Whampoa</target></link>, has opened a container port in Freeport. The Bahamian Parliament approved legislation in 1993 that extended most Freeport tax and duty exemptions through 2054.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bahamas is largely an<space/><link><target>International trade</target><part>import</part></link>,<space/><link><target>service economy</target></link>. There are about 110 U.S.-affiliated businesses operating in The Bahamas, and most are associated with<space/><link><target>tourism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>banking</target></link>. With few domestic resources and little industry, The Bahamas imports nearly all its food and manufactured goods from the United States. American goods and services tend to be favored by Bahamians due to cultural similarities and heavy exposure to American advertising.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Business environment</heading><paragraph>The Bahamas offers attractive features to the potential investor: a stable democratic environment, relief from personal and corporate income taxes, timely repatriation of corporate profits, proximity to the U.S. with extensive air and<space/><link><target>telecommunication</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>links, and a good pool of skilled professional workers. The Government of The Bahamas welcomes foreign<space/><link><target>investment</target></link><space/>in tourism and banking and has declared an interest in agricultural and industrial investments to generate local employment, particularly in white-collar or skilled jobs. Despite its interest in foreign investment to diversify the economy, the Bahamian Government responds to local concerns about foreign competition and tends to protect Bahamian business and labor interests. As a result of domestic resistance to foreign investment and high labor costs, growth can stagnate in sectors which the government wishes to diversify.</paragraph><paragraph>The country's infrastructure is best developed in the principal cities of Nassau and Freeport, where there are relatively good paved roads and international airports. Electricity is generally reliable, although many businesses have their own backup generators. In Nassau, there are two daily newspapers, three weeklies, and several international newspapers available for sale. There also are eight radio stations. Both Nassau and Freeport have a television station. Cable TV also is available locally and provides most American programs with some Canadian and European channels.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Taxation</heading><paragraph>The Bahamas has no income tax, corporate tax, capital gains tax, or wealth tax. Payroll taxes fund social insurance benefits and amount to 3.9% paid by the employee and 5.9% paid by the employer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Contributions Table</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nib-bahamas.com/_m1722/Brochures/default.aspx</arg><arg name="publisher">The National Insurance Board of The Commonwealth of The Bahamas</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-22</arg><arg name="date">2010-05-11</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2010, overall tax revenue as a percentage of GDP was 17.2%.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Bahamas, The</arg><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/bf.html</arg><arg name="work">[[The World Factbook]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Central Intelligence Agency]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-22</arg></template></extension><space/>A value-added tax (VAT) was instituted effective 1 January 2015.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Areas of opportunity</heading><paragraph>The best U.S. export opportunities remain in the traditional areas of foodstuffs and manufactured goods: vehicles and<space/><link><target>automobile parts</target></link>;<space/><link><target>hotel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>restaurant</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>medical</target></link><space/>supplies; and<space/><link><target>computer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and electronics. Bahamian tastes in consumer products roughly parallel those in the U.S. With approximately 85% of the population of primarily<space/><link><target>Ethnic groups of Africa</target><part>African</part></link><space/>descent, there is a large and growing market in the Bahamas for &quot;ethnic&quot; personal care products. Merchants in southern<space/><link><target>Florida</target></link><space/>have found it profitable to advertise in Bahamian publications. Most imports in this sector are subject to high but nondiscriminatory tariffs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Household income or consumption by percentage share&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem>highest 10%: 27% (2000)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Agriculture - products&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem>citrus, vegetables; poultry</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Electricity - production&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem>2,505 GWh (2007 est.) - Rank 133</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Electricity - consumption&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem>1,793 GWh (2007) - Rank 133</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Oil - consumption&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>convert</target><arg>26830</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2006 est.) - Rank 115</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Oil - exports&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem>transhipments of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>29000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2003)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>&quot;Exchange rates&quot;<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bahamian dollar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per<space/><link><target>US dollar</target></link><space/>- The Bahamian dollar is pegged to the U.S. dollar on a one-to-one basis</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>The Bahamas has the 47th freest economy in the world according to<space/><link><target>The Heritage Foundation</target></link><space/>2010<space/><italics><link><target>Index of Economic Freedom</target></link></italics>. The Bahamas is ranked 7th out of 29 countries in the South and Central America/Caribbean region, and its overall score is higher than the regional and world averages. Total government spending, including consumption and transfer payments, is relatively low. In the most recent year, government spending equaled 23.4 percent of GDP.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Some of the material in this article comes from the<space/><link><target>CIA World Factbook</target></link><space/>2009.</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://statistics.bahamas.gov.bs/key.php?cmd=view&amp;amp;id=164'>|title= Bahama Government Statistics</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Bahamas topics</target><arg name="state">uncollapsed</arg></template><template><target>Caribbean in topic</target><arg>Economy of</arg></template><template><target>Caricom</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Economy Of The Bahamas</target></template><link><target>Category:Economy of the Bahamas</target><part>*</part></link></paragraph></article>