<article title='Crossbow'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the weapon</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:DaVinci Crossbow.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Sketch by<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link>, c. 1500</part></link>A<space/><bold>crossbow</bold><space/>is a type of weapon, based on the<space/><link><target>Bow (archery)</target><part>bow</part></link>, consisting of a horizontal bow-like assembly mounted on a stock, that shoots projectiles called bolts or<space/><link><target>Quarrel (projectile)</target><part>quarrel</part><trail>s</trail></link>. The medieval crossbow was called by many names, most of which derived from the word<space/><link><target>ballista</target></link>, a torsion<space/><link><target>siege engine</target></link><space/>resembling a crossbow.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Payne-Gallwey<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ralph<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Sir Ralph Frankland-Payne-Gallwey, 3rd Baronet<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/></arg><arg name="title">The Crossbow<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1903<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Skyhorse Publishing Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-60239-010-X<space/></arg><arg name="page">2<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historically, crossbows played a significant role in the warfare of East Asia, Europe and the Mediterranean.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Tom Ukinski</arg><arg name="title">Drones: Mankind’s Always Had Them</arg><arg name="url">http://guardianlv.com/2013/05/drones-mankinds-always-had-them/</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 March 2015</arg><arg name="work">Guardian Liberty Voice</arg><arg name="date">23 May 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>The invention of the crossbow in<space/><link><target>History of Science and Technology in China</target><part>ancient China</part></link><space/>caused a major shift in the role of<space/><link><target>ranged weaponry</target><part>projectile weaponry</part></link>. The traditional<space/><link><target>bow and arrow</target></link><space/>had long been a specialized<space/><link><target>weapons system</target></link><space/>which required a considerable degree of lifetime training, physical strength and expertise to operate with any degree of efficiency; in many cultures, despite being usually drawn from the<space/><link><target>commoner</target><part>common</part></link><space/>class,<space/><link><target>bowmen</target></link><space/>were considered a separate and superior caste, as their<space/><link><target>archery</target></link><space/>skill-set (similar to many<space/><link><target>cavalry</target><part>horseman</part></link><space/>cultures) was essentially developed from birth and impossible to reproduce outside a pre-established cultural tradition, which many nations lacked. In contrast, the crossbow was the first projectile weapon to be simple, cheap and physically undemanding enough to be operated by large numbers of<space/><link><target>conscript</target></link><space/>soldiers, thus enabling virtually any nation to field a potent force of ranged crossbowmen with little expense beyond the cost of the weapons themselves.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Facts and interesting information about Medieval Weapons, Armor and arms, specifically, the Crossbow</arg><arg name="url">http://www.medieval-life-and-times.info/medieval-weapons/crossbow.htm</arg><arg name="website">medieval-life-and-times.info</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In Europe, where crossbows became widely used in the early medieval period, this led to the ascendancy of large<space/><link><target>mercenary</target></link><space/>armies of crossbowmen (best exemplified by the<space/><link><target>Genoese crossbowmen</target></link>), and the eventual death of the<space/><link><target>plate armor</target><part>heavily armored</part></link><space/><link><target>aristocratic</target></link><space/><link><target>knight</target></link><space/>as armies became progressively dominated by conscripts equipped with increasingly powerful ranged projectile weapons.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In modern times, although largely supplanted by<space/><link><target>firearm</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in most roles, crossbows are still widely used for<space/><link><target>shooting sport</target><trail>s</trail></link>, hunting, and when shooting in relative silence is an important consideration.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Construction</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Noix corde carreau arbalette.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Crossbow nut:<space/><template><target>ordered list</target><arg><space/>Nut.</arg><arg><space/>String.</arg><arg><space/>Quarrel.</arg><arg><space/>Trigger.</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A crossbow is a<space/><link><target>bow (weapon)</target><part>bow</part></link><space/>mounted on a stick (called a tiller or stock) with a mechanism in it which holds the drawn<space/><link><target>bow string</target></link>. The earliest designs featured a slot in the stock, down into which the string was placed. To shoot this design, a vertical rod is thrust up through a hole in the bottom of the notch, forcing the string out. This rod is usually attached perpendicular to a rear-facing lever called a trigger or &quot;tickler&quot;. A later design implemented a rolling cylindrical pawl called a &quot;nut&quot; to retain the string. This nut has a perpendicular center slot for the bolt, and an intersecting axial slot for the string, along with a lower face or slot against which the internal trigger sits. They often also have some form of strengthening internal &quot;sear&quot; or trigger face, usually of metal. These &quot;roller nuts&quot; were either free-floating in their close-fitting hole across the stock, tied in with a binding of sinew or other strong cording, or mounted on a metal axle or pins. Removable or integral plates of wood, ivory or metal on the sides of the stock kept the nut in place laterally. Nuts were made of antler, bone, or metal. Bows could be kept and ready to shoot for some time with little effort, allowing crossbowmen to aim better.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hanafi et al. 2011: 23</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The bow (called the &quot;prod&quot; or &quot;lath&quot; on a crossbow) of early crossbows was made of a single piece of wood, usually<space/><link><target>Ash tree</target><part>ash</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Taxus</target><part>yew</part></link>. Composite bows are made from layers of different materialoften wood, horn and sinewglued together and bound with animal tendon. These composite bows, made of several layers, are much stronger and more efficient in releasing energy than simple wooden bows. As steel became more widely available in Europe around the 14th century, steel prods came into use.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The crossbow prod is very short compared to ordinary bows, resulting in a short draw length. This leads to a higher draw weight in order to store the same amount of energy. Furthermore, the thick prods are a bit less efficient at releasing energy, but more energy can be stored by a crossbow. Traditionally the prod was often lashed to the stock with rope,<space/><link><target>whipcord</target></link>, or other strong cording. This cording is called the<space/><italics><link><target>bridle</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The strings for a crossbow are typically made of strong fibers that would not tend to fray. Whipcord was very common; however linen,<space/><link><target>hemp</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Tendon</target><part>sinew</part></link><space/>were used as well. In wet conditions, twisted<space/><link><target>mulberry</target></link><space/>root was occasionally used.</paragraph><paragraph>Very light crossbows can be drawn by hand, but heavier types need the help of mechanical devices. The simplest version of mechanical cocking device is a hook attached to a belt, drawing the bow by straightening the legs. Other devices are hinged levers which either pulled or pushed the string into place, cranked rack-and-pinion devices called &quot;cranequins&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.thebeckoning.com/medieval/crossbow/xbow-diagram.gif'>Cranequin</link></extension><space/>and multiple cord-and-pulley cranked devices called<space/><link><target>windlass</target><trail>es</trail></link>.<table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:The Martyrdom of St Sebastian (detail).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Stirrup</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Armborst 1, Nordisk familjebok.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Pull lever</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Armborst 2, Nordisk familjebok.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Push lever</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Armborst 3, Nordisk familjebok.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Cranequin (Rack &amp; Pinion)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Altarpiece of St Sebastian (detail).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Cranequin (Rack &amp; Pinion)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Armborst 4, Nordisk familjebok.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Windlass</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:HJRK A 2269 - Crossbow windlass, late 15th century.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Iron cranequin, South German, late 15th century</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Smland vapen.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>A lion holding a crossbow on the coat of arms of<space/><link><target>Smland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sweden</target></link>. The province's original coat of arms (1560) was of a crossbow alone, the lion being added later.</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='3'>Variants</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Recurve crossbow with bolts.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Modern recurve crossbow</part></link><link><target>File:Horton Hunter Supreme by IvE.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Modern compound crossbow</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Crossbows exist in different variants. One way to classify them is the acceleration system, while another is the size and energy, degree of automation or projectiles.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>recurve bow</target><part>recurve</part></link><space/>crossbow is a bow that has tips curving away from the archer. The recurve bow's bent limbs have a longer draw length than an equivalent straight-limbed bow, giving more acceleration to the projectile and less hand shock. Recurved limbs also put greater strain on the materials used to make the bow, and they may make more noise with the shot.</paragraph><paragraph>Multiple bow systems have a special system of pulling the sinew via several bows (which can be recurve bows). The workings can be compared to a modern compound bow system. The weapon uses several different bows instead of one bow with a tackle system to achieve a higher acceleration of the sinew via the multiplication with each bow's pulling effect.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A compound crossbow is a modern crossbow and is similar to a<space/><link><target>compound bow</target></link>. The limbs are usually much stiffer than those of a recurve crossbow. This limb stiffness makes the compound bow more energy efficient than other bows, but the limbs are too stiff to be drawn comfortably with a string attached directly to them. The compound bow has the string attached to the pulleys, one or both of which has one or more cables attached to the opposite limb. When the string is drawn back, the string causes the pulleys to turn. This causes the pulleys to pull the cables, which in turn causes the limbs to bend and thus store energy. Other types of compound bows use either (one or both) cam shaped or eccentrically mounted pulleys in order to provide a &quot;let off&quot;, such that the archer is not holding against the maximum draw weight of the bow while trying to aim. But in a crossbow the string is held back mechanically, so there is no advantage in providing a let off. Therefore, compound crossbows generally use only pulleys that are both round and concentrically mounted, in order to capture the maximum available energy from the relatively short draw length.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:HJRK A 108 - Wallarmbrust c. 1460-70.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>15th-century ''Wallarmbrust'', a heavy crossbow used for siege defense.</part></link>The smallest crossbows are pistol crossbows. Others are simple long stocks with the crossbow mounted on them. These could be shot from under the arm. The next step in development was stocks of the shape that would later be used<space/><link><target>Stock (firearms)</target><part>for firearms</part></link>, which allowed better aiming. The<space/><link><target>arbalest</target></link><space/>was a heavy crossbow which required special systems for pulling the sinew via windlasses. For<space/><link><target>siege warfare</target></link><space/>the size of crossbows was further increased to hurl large projectiles such as rocks at fortifications. The required crossbows needed a massive base frame and powerful windlass devices. Such devices include the<space/><link><target>oxybeles</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>ballista</target></link><space/>has<space/><link><target>torsion spring</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>replacing the elastic prod of the oxybeles, but later also developed into smaller versions.<extension extension_name='ref'>O'Connell, Robert L. (1989).<space/><italics>Of Arms and Men: A History of War, Weapons, and Aggression</italics>.<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-19-505359-1, p. 65</extension><space/>&quot;Ballista&quot; is still the<space/><link><target>root (linguistics)</target><part>root word</part></link><space/>for crossbow in<space/><link><target>Romance languages</target></link><space/>such as Italian (<italics>balestra</italics>) and Spanish (<italics>ballesta</italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>repeating crossbow</target></link><space/>automated the separate actions of stringing the bow, placing the projectile and shooting. This way the task can be accomplished with a simple one-handed movement, while keeping the weapon stationary. As a result, it is possible to shoot at a faster rate compared to unmodified version. The Greek<space/><link><target>Polybolos</target></link><space/>was an ancient repeating ballista reputedly invented by Dionysius of Alexandria in the 3rd century BC. The Chinese repeating crossbow,<space/><link><target>Chu Ko Nu</target></link>, is a handheld crossbow that accomplishes the task with a magazine containing a number of bolts on top. The mechanism is worked by moving a rectangular lever forward and backward. The weapon was mainly used as a weapon against lightly armored soldiers, since it shot small bolts that were often dipped in poison.</paragraph><paragraph>A bullet crossbow is a type of handheld crossbow which rather than arrows or bolts shoots spherical projectiles made of stone, clay or lead. There are two variants; one has a double string with a pocket for the projectile, and the other has a barrel with a slot for the string.<table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Gastraphetes - catapult ancestor - antica catapulta.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Cocking of a Greek<space/><italics><link><target>gastraphetes</target></link></italics></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Ancient Mechanical Artillery. Pic 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Arsenal of ancient mechanical artillery in the<space/><link><target>Saalburg</target></link>, Germany; left: polybolos reconstruction by the German engineer Erwin Schramm (1856-1935)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Chuangzi Nu1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Chinese<space/><italics>Chuangzi Nu</italics><space/>stationary windlass device with triple-bow arcuballista<template><target>dubious</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Zhugenu-payne.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Chinese<space/><link><target>repeating crossbow</target></link><space/>with pull lever and automatic reload magazine</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Liannu.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Chinese<space/><link><target>Lian Nu</target></link><space/>(), multiple shot crossbow without a visible nut or cocking aid</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:FrenchCrossbowMan.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>15th-century French soldier carrying an<space/><link><target>arbalest</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>pavise</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Ballista-quadrirotis.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Early modern four-wheeled ballista drawn by armored horses (1552)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:FrenchMountedCrossbowman.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>16th-century French mounted crossbowman (&quot;cranequinier&quot;). His crossbow is drawn with a rack-and-pinion &quot;cranequin&quot;, so it can be used while riding.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Crossbow pistol IMG 3841.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Pistol crossbow for home recreational shooting. Made by Frdric Siber in Morges, early 19th century. On display at Morges military museum.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:French cross-bow grenade thrower Arbalte sauterelle type A d'Imphy circa 1915.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>French cross-bow grenade thrower Arbalte sauterelle type A d'Imphy circa 1915</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='3'>Projectiles</heading><paragraph><link><target>File: .jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Arcuballista<template><target>dubious</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><space/>on wheels with a steel bow and incendiary bolt (15th century)</part></link><link><target>File:CrossbowBolt.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Modern crossbow bolt compared to a 1<space/><link><target>eurocent</target></link><space/>coin</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The arrow-like projectiles of a crossbow are called<space/><link><target>bolt (crossbow)</target><part>bolt</part><trail>s</trail></link>. These are much shorter than arrows, but can be several times heavier. There is an optimum weight for bolts to achieve maximum kinetic energy, which varies depending on the strength and characteristics of the crossbow, but most could pass through common mail. In ancient times the bolts of a strong crossbow were usually several times heavier than arrows. Modern bolts are stamped with a proof mark to ensure their consistent weight and do not have<space/><link><target>fletching</target><part>fletch</part><trail>ing</trail></link>, i.e. feathered ends like those commonly seen on<space/><link><target>arrow</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="foremosthunting1"><link type='external' href='http://www.foremosthunting.com/Resources/Crossbows/BoltsandArrows/tabid/1087/Default.aspx'>Bolts and Arrows: The Lighter Side of Hunting Projectile Name Calling</link>. Foremosthunting.com. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>Crossbow bolts can be fitted with a variety of heads, some with sickle-shaped heads to cut rope or rigging; but the most common today is a four-sided point called a<space/><link><target>Quarrel (projectile)</target><part>quarrel</part></link>. A highly specialized type of bolt is employed to collect blubber biopsy samples used in biology research.</paragraph><paragraph>Most modern crossbows are designed to shoot arrows instead of bolts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="foremosthunting1"></extension><space/>Crossbow arrows are of similar construction to ordinary bow arrows, just shorter in length because of reduced power stroke.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Crossbows can also be adapted to shoot lead bullets or rocks, in which case they are called<space/><bold>stone-bows</bold>. Primarily used for hunting<space/><link><target>Anatidae</target><part>wildfowl</part></link>, these usually have a double string with a pouch between the strings to hold the projectile.</paragraph><paragraph>Even relatively small differences in arrow weight can have a considerable impact on its drop and, conversely, its flight trajectory.<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="CrossbowArrowDrop"><link type='external' href='http://www.bestcrossbowsource.com/crossbow-arrow-drop-charted-test-results/'>Crossbow Arrow Drop - Charted Test Results</link>. BestCrossbowSource.com</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Accessories</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Crossbow telescopic sight reticle.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>The reticle of a modern crossbow<space/><link><target>telescopic sight</target></link><space/>allows the shooter to adjust for different ranges</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>History of Science and Technology in China</target><part>ancient Chinese</part></link><space/>crossbow often included a metal (i.e. bronze or steel) grid serving as<space/><link><target>iron sights</target></link>. Modern crossbow sights often use similar technology to modern firearm sights, such as<space/><link><target>red dot sight</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>telescopic sight</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Many crossbow scopes feature multiple<space/><link><target>crosshairs</target></link><space/>to compensate for the significant effects of<space/><link><target>gravity</target></link><space/>over different ranges. In most cases, a newly bought crossbow will need to be &quot;sighted&quot; for accurate shooting.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bestcrossbowsource.com/how-to-sight-a-crossbow</arg><arg name="title">Sighting a Crossbow</arg><arg name="work">Best Crossbow Source</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 October 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Quiver</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can be mounted to hold ammunition. These are often made from plastic and usually hold the bolts in fixed positions along the structure. A popular detachable design consists of a main arm that is attached to the weapon, a plate on one end that secures four or more individual bolts at a point on their shafts and at the other end a cover that secures their heads. This kind of quiver is attached under the front of the crossbow, parallel to the string and is designed to be quickly detached and reattached. Other designs hold bolts underneath the crossbow parallel to the stock, sometimes on either side of the crossbow.</paragraph><paragraph>A major cause of the sound of shooting a crossbow is vibration of various components. Crossbow silencers are multiple components placed on high vibration parts, such as the string and limbs, to dampen vibration and suppress the sound of loosing the bolt.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Crossbow</arg><arg name="url">http://www.reference.com/browse/crossbow</arg><arg name="website">[[reference.com]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Columbia University Press]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 March 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of crossbows</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>East Asia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Warring States or Western Han crossbow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A bronze crossbow trigger mechanism and butt plate that were mass-produced in the<space/><link><target>Warring States period</target></link><space/>(475-221 BC)</part></link></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The earliest evidence of crossbows in<space/><link><target>Spring and Autumn period</target><part>ancient China</part></link><space/>and neighboring peoples dates back to at least the 6th century BC. According to<space/><link><target>Joseph Needham</target><part>Sir Joseph Needham</part></link><space/>in his<space/><link><target>Science and Civilisation in China</target></link>, it is not possible to state which of the East Asian peoples invented the crossbow. Linguistically, it derives from outside China by their then neighbours, who were often hired as marksmen mercenaries, while the first records and finds are from China. However, there is undoubted evidence that it was used for military purposes during the Warring States period from the second half of the 4th century BC onwards.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Needham<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joseph<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Joseph Needham<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Science and Civilisation in China, Vol 5 Part 6<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-08732-5<space/></arg><arg name="page">135</arg></template></extension></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>Bronze<space/><link><target>History of crossbows</target><part>crossbow</part></link><space/>bolts dating as early as the mid-5th century BC were found at a<space/><link><target>Chu (state)</target><part>Kingdom of Chu</part></link><space/>burial site in Yutaishan,<space/><link><target>Hubei</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wagner (1993), 153, 157158.</extension><space/>The earliest handheld crossbow stocks with bronze trigger, dating from the 6th century BC, comes from Tomb 3 and 12 found at<space/><link><target>Qufu</target></link>, Shandong, capital of the<space/><link><target>Lu (state)</target><part>State of Lu</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="you 1994 80">You (1994), 80.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.atarn.org/chinese/bjng_xbow/bjng_xbow.htm'>A Crossbow Mechanism with Some Unique Features from Shandong, China</link>. Asian Traditional Archery Research Network. Retrieved on 20 August 2008.</extension><space/>Other early finds of crossbows were discovered in Tomb 138 at Saobatang,<space/><link><target>Hunan</target></link><space/>dated to the mid-4th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mao (1998), 109110.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wright (2001), 159.</extension><space/><link><target>Repeating crossbow</target><trail>s</trail></link>, first mentioned in the<space/><italics><link><target>Records of the Three Kingdoms</target></link></italics>, were discovered in 1986 in Tomb 47 at Qinjiazui, Hubei dated to around the 4th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lin (1993), 36.</extension><space/>The earliest Chinese document mentioning a crossbow is in scripts from the 4th to 3rd centuries BC attributed to the followers of<space/><link><target>Mohist</target><part>Mozi</part></link>. This source refers to the use of a giant crossbow in the 6th to 5th BC, corresponding to the late<space/><link><target>Spring and Autumn Period</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2009</arg></template><space/><link><target>Sun Tzu</target></link>'s influential book<space/><italics><link><target>The Art of War</target></link></italics><space/>(first appearance dated in between 500 BC to 300 BC<extension extension_name='ref'>James Clavell,<space/><italics>The Art of War</italics>, prelude</extension>) refers in chapter V to the traits and in XII to the use of crossbows.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Art Of War<space/></arg><arg name="author">Sun Tzu<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/132</arg></template></extension><space/>One of the earliest reliable records of this weapon in warfare is from an ambush, the<space/><link><target>Battle of Maling</target><part>Battle of Ma-Ling</part></link><space/>in 341 BC. By the 200s BC, the crossbow (<template><target>zh-cp</target><arg name="c">弩</arg><arg name="p">nǔ</arg></template>) was well developed and quite widely used in China.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>File:Earthenware architecture models, Eastern Han Dynasty, 5.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A miniature guard wielding a handheld crossbow from the top balcony of a model watchtower, made of glazed earthenware during the<space/><link><target>Han Dynasty</target><part>Eastern Han era</part></link><space/>(25220 AD) of China, from the<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The earliest textual evidence of the<space/><italics>handheld</italics><space/>crossbow<space/><link><target>Battle of Maling</target><part>used in battle</part></link><space/>dates to the 4th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wright 2001 42">Wright (2001), 42.</extension><space/>Handheld crossbows with complex bronze trigger mechanisms have also been found with the<space/><link><target>Terracotta Army</target></link><space/>in the tomb of<space/><link><target>Qin Shihuang</target></link><space/>(r. 221210 BC) that are similar to specimens from the subsequent<space/><link><target>Han Dynasty</target></link><space/>(202 BC220 AD), while crossbowmen described in the Qin and Han Dynasty learned drill formations, some were even mounted as<space/><link><target>Cavalry#East Asia</target><part>cavalry units</part></link>, and Han Dynasty writers attributed the success of numerous<space/><link><target>HanXiongnu War</target><part>battles against the Xiongnu</part></link><space/>to massed crossbow volleys.<extension extension_name='ref'>Needham (1986), Volume 5, Part 6, 124128.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (2000a), 45.</extension><space/>The bronze triggers were designed in such a way that they were able to store a large amount of energy within the bow when drawn, but was easily shot with little recoil when the trigger were pulled (this allowed it for precision shooting). The metal portions of the crossbow were also mass-produced with precision, with the bronze mechanisms being interchangeable. Finally, the Qin and Han Dynasties also developed crossbow shooting lines, with alternating rows of crossbowmen shooting and reloading in a manner similar to a musket firing line.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target><trail>ese</trail></link><space/>historical legend, the ruler and general<space/><link><target>Thc Phn</target></link><space/>who ruled over the ancient kingdom of<space/><link><target>u Lc</target></link><space/>from 257 to 207 BC is said to have owed his power to a magic crossbow, capable of shooting thousands of bolts at once.</paragraph><paragraph>Crossbow technology for multi-proded crossbows was transferred from the Chinese to<space/><link><target>Champa</target></link>, which Champa used in its invasion of the<space/><link><target>Khmer Empire</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link><space/>in 1177.</paragraph><paragraph>Different varieties of crossbows were also developed, such as the<space/><link><target>repeating crossbow</target></link>, multi-shot crossbow, and repeating multi-shot crossbow.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ancient Greece</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gastraphetes Rekonstruktion Saalburg.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Greek ''<link><target>gastraphetes</target></link>''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest reasonably reliable date for the utilization of crossbows in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link><space/>is in<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target><part>ancient Greece</part></link><space/>from the 5th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gurstelle, William (2004).<italics>The Art of the Catapult</italics>. Chicago Review Press. ISBN 1-55652-526-5, p. 49</extension><template><target>Better source</target><arg name="reason"></arg><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><space/>The historian<space/><link><target>Diodorus Siculus</target></link><space/>(fl. 1st century BC), described the invention of a mechanical arrow shooting catapult (<italics>katapeltikon</italics>) by a Greek task force in 399 BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Diod. Sic. 14.42.1</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.3">Duncan Campbell:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BC-AD 363</italics>, Osprey Publishing, Oxford 2003, ISBN 1-84176-634-8, p.3</extension><space/>According to the inventor<space/><link><target>Hero of Alexandria</target></link><space/>(fl. 1st century AD), who referred to the now lost works of the 3rd-century BC engineer<space/><link><target>Ctesibius</target></link>, this weapon was inspired by an earlier hand crossbow, called the<space/><italics><link><target>gastraphetes</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>belly shooter</italics>), which could store more energy than the Greek bows. A detailed description of the<space/><italics>gastraphetes</italics>, along with a drawing, is found in Heron's technical treatise<space/><italics>Belopoeica</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.4">Duncan Campbell:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BC-AD 363</italics>, Osprey Publishing, Oxford 2003, ISBN 1-84176-634-8, p.4</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Stanley M. Burstein, Walter Donlan, Sarah B. Pomeroy, and Jennifer Tolbert Roberts (1999).<space/><italics>Ancient Greece: A Political, Social, and Cultural History</italics>. Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-509742-4, p. 366</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>gastraphetes</italics><space/>was powered by a composite bow. It was cocked by resting the stomach in a concavity at the rear of the stock and pressing down with all strength. In this way considerably more energy can be summoned up than by using only one arm of the archer as in the hand-bow. The heavy weight and bulk of the<space/><italics>gastraphetes</italics><space/>may have necessitated a prop to keep it standing, i.e. by mounting it on a defensive wall or using a portable prop.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell (2003), 4.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A third Greek author, Biton (fl. 2nd century BC), whose reliability has been positively reevaluated by recent scholarship,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.3"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>M.J.T. Lewis:<space/><italics>When was Biton?</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Mnemosyne</target></link></italics>, Vol. 52, No. 2 (1999), pp. 159168</extension><space/>described two advanced forms of the<space/><italics>gastraphetes</italics>, which he credits to<space/><link><target>Zopyrus of Tarentum</target><part>Zopyros</part></link>, an engineer from<space/><link><target>Taranto</target><part>southern Italy</part></link>. Zopyrus has been plausibly equated with a<space/><link><target>Pythagoreanism</target><part>Pythagorean</part></link><space/>of that name who seems to have flourished in the late 5th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/pythagoreanism/'>Peter Kingsley: Ancient Philosophy, Mystery and Magic, Clarendon Press, Oxford 1995, p.150ff</link>. Plato.stanford.edu. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis established a lower date of no later than the mid-4th century (M.J.T. Lewis:<space/><italics>When was Biton?</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Mnemosyne</target></link></italics>, Vol. 52, No. 2 (1999), pp. 159168 (160)). Same de Camp (L. Sprague de Camp:<space/><italics>Master Gunner Apollonios</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Technology and Culture</target></link></italics>, Vol. 2, No. 3 (1961), pp. 240244 (241)</extension><space/>He probably designed his bow-machines on the occasion of the sieges of<space/><link><target>Cumae</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Milet</target></link><space/>between 421 BC and 401 BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Biton Biton 65.167.4 &amp; 61.1265.1</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.5">Duncan Campbell:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BC-AD 363</italics>, Osprey Publishing, Oxford 2003, ISBN 1-84176-634-8, p.5</extension><space/>The bows of these machines already featured a winched pull back system and could apparently throw two missiles at once.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.8"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>From the mid-4th century BC onwards, evidence of the Greek use of crossbows becomes more dense and varied: Arrow-shooting machines (<italics>katapeltai</italics>) are briefly mentioned by<space/><link><target>Aeneas Tacticus</target></link><space/>in his treatise on siegecraft written around 350 BC.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.8"></extension><space/>An Athenian inventory from 330329 BC includes catapults bolts with heads and flights.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Eric William Marsden, p.57"></extension><space/>Arrow-shooting machines in action are reported from<space/><link><target>Philip II of Macedon</target><part>Philip II</part></link>'s siege of<space/><link><target>Marmara Erelisi</target><part>Perinthos</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link><space/>in 340 BC.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Eric William Marsden, p.60">Eric William Marsden:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery: Historical Development</italics>, The Clarendon Press, Oxford 1969, ISBN 978-0-19-814268-3, p.60</extension><space/>At the same time, Greek fortifications began to feature high towers with shuttered windows in the top, presumably to house anti-personnel arrow shooters, as in<space/><link><target>Aigosthena</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Josiah Ober:<space/><italics>Early Artillery Towers: Messenia, Boiotia, Attica, Megarid</italics>,<space/><italics>American Journal of Archaeology</italics>, Vol. 91, No. 4. (1987), S. 569604 (569)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The transition to<space/><link><target>torsion (mechanics)</target><part>torsion</part></link><space/><link><target>catapult</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are not considered crossbows and came to dominate Greek and<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>artillery design, is first evident in inventories of the<space/><link><target>Athens</target><part>Athenian</part></link><space/>arsenal from between 338 and 326 BC.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duncan Campbell, p.8">Duncan Campbell:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery 399 BC-AD 363</italics>, Osprey Publishing, Oxford 2003, ISBN 1-84176-634-8, p.8ff.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Eric William Marsden, p.57">Eric William Marsden:<space/><italics>Greek and Roman Artillery: Historical Development</italics>, The Clarendon Press, Oxford 1969, ISBN 978-0-19-814268-3, p.57</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman Empire</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Roman crossbow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=0.7</part><part>Roman crossbow</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The ancient world knew a variety of mechanical hand-held weapons similar to the later<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target><part>medieval</part></link><space/>crossbow. The exact terminology is a subject of continuing scholarly debate.Roman authors like<space/><link><target>Vegetius</target></link><space/>(fl. 4th century) note repeatedly the use of arrow shooting weapons such as<space/><italics>arcuballista</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>manuballista</italics><space/>respectively<space/><italics>cheiroballista</italics>. While most scholars agree that one or more of these terms refer to handheld mechanical weapons, there is disagreement whether these were flexion bows or torsion powered like the recent<space/><link><target>Xanten</target></link><space/>find.<extension extension_name='ref'>Romanhideout.com:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.romanhideout.com/news/2005/20050224.asp'>Manuballista found near Xanten</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>commander<space/><link><target>Arrian</target></link><space/>(c. 86 after 146) records in his<space/><italics>Tactica</italics><space/>Roman cavalry training for shooting some mechanical handheld weapon from horseback.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Arrian</target></link><space/>Tact. 43.1;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Baatz</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">11–15</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Campbell</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="pp">117–132</arg></template></extension>Sculptural reliefs from<space/><link><target>Roman Gaul</target></link><space/>depict the use of crossbows in hunting scenes. These are remarkably similar to the later medieval crossbow.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dictionnaire: Arcuballista, Manuballista">Dictionnaire des antiquites grecques et romaines:<space/><link type='external' href='http://dagr.univ-tlse2.fr/sdx/dagr/feuilleter.xsp?tome=1&amp;amp;partie=1&amp;amp;numPage=400&amp;amp;filtre=arbal%C3%A8te%20&amp;amp;nomEntree=ARCUBALLISTA'>Arcuballista, Manuballista</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Medieval Europe</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Balestriere1.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A Medieval<space/><link><target>Arbalist (crossbowman)</target><part>crossbowman</part></link><space/>drawing his bow behind his<space/><link><target>pavise</target></link>. A hook on the end of a strap on his belt engages the bowstring. Holding the crossbow down by putting his foot through the stirrup, he draws the bow by straightening his legs</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The crossbow is portrayed as a hunting weapon on four<space/><link><target>Pictish stones</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Scotland in the Early Middle Ages</target><part>early medieval Scotland</part></link><space/>(6th to 9th centuries):<space/><link><target>St Vigeans</target><part>St. Vigeans no. 1</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Glenferness</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Shandwick</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Meigle</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>John M. Gilbert,<space/><italics>Hunting and Hunting Reserves in Medieval Scotland</italics><space/>(Edinburgh: John Donald, 1979), p. 62.</extension><space/>The use of crossbows in European warfare is again evident from the<space/><link><target>Battle of Hastings</target></link><space/>until about the year 1500. They almost completely superseded hand bows in many European armies in the 12th century for a number of reasons.In modern tests, longbows showed a higher rate of shot than crossbows of the same energy, due to the difficulty of the shooter in handling the mechanical parts for loading in the same time as the bow was pulled. With lots of training, a longbowman can achieve a high degree of accuracy that is comparable to the much steeper learning curve in aimed shooting with the crossbow. Despite strength training, there are physical limits to the longbow, unlike the crossbow, which can store several times the energy, but will be less efficient in translating stored into kinetic energy due to the thicker spring material.There is no record from the Middle Ages comparing longbowmen and crossbowmen shooting in one army from a similar position, although such occasions are known with visiting Englishmen in the Baltic and Scottish in the French army.</paragraph><paragraph>In the armies of Europe,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Verbruggen<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>J.F<space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>Second revised and enlarged, edition, in English translation<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The art of warfare in Western Europe during the Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Boydell&Brewer<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-85115-570-7<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>mounted and unmounted crossbowmen, often mixed with slingers, javeliners and archers, occupied a central position in battle formations. Usually they engaged the enemy in offensive skirmishes before an assault of mounted<space/><link><target>knight</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Crossbowmen were also valuable in counterattacks to protect their infantry. The rank of commanding officer of the crossbowmen corps was one of the highest positions in any army of this time. Along with<space/><link><target>Pole weapon</target><part>polearm</part></link><space/>weapons made from farming equipment, the crossbow was also a<space/><link><target>signature weapon</target><part>weapon of choice</part></link><space/>for insurgent peasants such as the<space/><link><target>Taborite</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Mounted knights armed with lances proved ineffective against formations of<space/><link><target>pike (weapon)</target><part>pike</part><trail>men</trail></link><space/>combined with crossbowmen whose weapons could penetrate most knights' armor. The invention of pushlever and ratchet drawing mechanisms enabled the use of crossbows on horseback, leading to the development of new<space/><link><target>cavalry tactics</target></link>. Knights and mercenaries deployed in triangular formations, with the most heavily armored knights at the front. Some of these riders would carry small, powerful all-metal crossbows of their own. Crossbows were eventually replaced in warfare by more powerful<space/><link><target>gunpowder</target></link><space/>weapons, although early guns had slower rates of fire and much worse accuracy than contemporary crossbows. Later, similar competing tactics would feature<space/><link><target>arquebus</target><part>harquebusiers</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>musket</target><trail>eers</trail></link><space/>in formation with pikemen (<link><target>pike and shot</target></link>), pitted against cavalry firing<space/><link><target>pistol</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>carbine</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Elsewhere</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ref-chamballista.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Wheelmounted and elephantmounted double-bow-arcuballistae of the<space/><link><target>Champa</target></link><space/>kingdom.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Saracen</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>called the crossbow<space/><italics>qaws Ferengi</italics>, or &quot;Frankish bow,&quot; as the Crusaders used the crossbow against the Arab and Turkic horsemen with remarkable success. The adapted crossbow was used by the Islamic armies in defence of their castles. Later footstrapped version become very popular among the Muslim armies in<space/><link><target>Iberian Peninsula</target><part>Iberia</part></link>. During the<space/><link><target>Crusades</target></link>, Europeans were exposed to Saracen<space/><link><target>composite bow</target><trail>s</trail></link>, made from layers of different materialoften wood, horn and sinewglued together and bound with animal tendon. These composite bows could be much more powerful than wooden bows, and were adopted for crossbow prods across Europe.Crossbow prods could be more easily waterproofed than hand bows, which was essential in the humid European climate.</paragraph><paragraph>In Western Africa and Central Africa,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.photographersdirect.com/buyers/stockphoto.asp?imageid=348455'>Baaka pygmy with crossbow</link>. Photographersdirect.com. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>crossbows served as a scouting weapon and for hunting, with enslaved Africans bringing this technology to natives in America.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cvplxd"><link type='external' href='http://www.diaspora.uiuc.edu/A-AAnewsletter/newsletter16.html'>Notes On West African Crossbow Technology</link>. Diaspora.uiuc.edu. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>In the<space/><link><target>American South</target></link>, the crossbow was used for hunting and warfare when firearms or gunpowder were unavailable because of economic hardships or isolation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cvplxd"></extension><space/>In the North of Northern America, light hunting crossbows were traditionally used by the<space/><link><target>Inuit</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Hunting Network</arg><arg name="title">The Crossbow: Four thousand years of traditional archery</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bowhunting.com/publisher/crossbow-information/2009/10/2/future-of-crossbow-hunting</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 March 2015</arg><arg name="publisher">bowhunting.com</arg><arg name="date">10 February 2009</arg></template></extension><template><target>tertiary source inline</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><space/>These are technologically similar to the African derived crossbows, but have a different route of influence.</paragraph><paragraph>The native<space/><link><target>Montagnard (Vietnam)</target><part>Montagnard</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of Vietnam's Central Highlands were also known to have used crossbows, as both a tool for hunting, and later, an effective weapon against the Viet Cong during the Vietnam War. Montagnard fighters armed with crossbows proved a highly valuable asset to the US Special Forces operating in Vietnam, and it was not uncommon for the Green Berets to integrate Montagnard crossbowmen into their strike teams.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">John Friedman</arg><arg name="title">The Crossbow History</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cacciaebalestra.altervista.org/INGLESE/lastoria.html</arg><arg name="website">www.cacciaebalestra.altervista.org</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 March 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern use</heading><heading level='3'>Hunting, leisure and science</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Fish0293 - Flickr - NOAA Photo Library.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Fisheries scientist obtaining tissue samples from dolphins swimming in the bow wave of a<space/><link><target>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</target><part>NOAA</part></link><space/>ship (2010).</part></link><link><target>File:Blubber biopsy sample.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>A whale shot by a modified crossbow bolt for a<space/><link><target>blubber</target></link><space/><link><target>biopsy</target></link><space/>sample.</part></link><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Crossbows are used for<space/><link><target>shooting sport</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>bowhunting</target></link><space/>in modern<space/><link><target>archery</target></link><space/>and for<space/><link><target>blubber</target></link><space/><link><target>biopsy</target></link><space/>samples in scientific research. In<space/><link><target>Laws on crossbows</target><part>some countries</part></link><space/>such as Canada or the United Kingdom, they may be less heavily regulated than firearms, and thus more popular for hunting; some jurisdictions have bow and/or crossbow only seasons.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://dr6j45jk9xcmk.cloudfront.net/documents/3311/2014-ontario-hunting-regulations.pdf</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern military and paramilitary use</heading><paragraph>In modern times, crossbows are no longer used for assassinations, but there are still some applications. For example, in the Americas, the<space/><link><target>Peru</target><trail>vian</trail></link><space/>army (Ejrcito) equips some soldiers with crossbows and rope, to establish a<space/><link><target>zip-line</target></link><space/>in difficult terrain.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.saorbats.com.ar/GaleriaSaorbats/Peruffaa04/images/b2aBriFFEE2_EP_jpg.jpg'>Ejercito prepare for deployment.</link></extension><space/>In Brazil the CIGS (Jungle Warfare Training Center) also trains soldiers in the use of crossbows.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.militaryphotos.net/forums/showthread.php?t=23940'>CIGS information thread</link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.segurancaedefesa.com/Besta.jpg'>CIGS photograph</link>.</extension><space/>In the United States, SAA International Ltd manufacture a 150&amp;nbsp;ftlb crossbow-launched version of the U.S. Army type classified Launched<space/><link><target>Grappling hook</target><part>Grapnel Hook</part></link><space/>(LGH), among other mine countermeasure solutions designed for the middle-eastern theatre. It has been successfully evaluated in Cambodia and Bosnia.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.janes.com/articles/Janes-Mines-and-Mine-Clearance/Launched-Grapnel-Hook-LGH-United-States.html'>Jane's LGH Mine Clearance by US forces Jul 2009</link>. Janes.com (9 June 2011). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>It is used to probe for and detonate tripwire initiated mines and booby traps at up to 50 meters. The concept is similar to the LGH device originally only fired from a rifle, as a plastic retrieval line is attached.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.saa-intl.com/products/images/crossbow2.jpg'>LGH Plastic Retrieval Line</link>. None. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>Reusable up to 20 times, the line can be reeled back in without exposing oneself. The device is of particular use in tactical situations where noise discipline is important.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.saa-intl.com/products/crossbow.html'>SAA Crossbow Launched Grapnel Hook</link>. Saa-intl.com. Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><link><target>File:PistolCrossbow122.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>A pistol crossbow</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In Europe, British-based Barnett International supplied crossbows to<space/><link><target>Serbs</target><part>Serbian</part></link><space/>forces which according to<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics><space/>were later used &quot;in<space/><link><target>ambushes</target></link><space/>and as a counter-sniper weapon&quot;, against the<space/><link><target>Kosovo Liberation Army</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Kosovo War</target></link><space/>in the areas of Pec and Djakovica, south west of Kosovo.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/1999/aug/09/balkans'>The Guardian</link>.</extension><space/>Whitehall launched an investigation, though the department of trade and industry established that not being &quot;on the military list&quot; crossbows were not covered by such export regulations. Paul Beaver of Jane's defence publications commented that, &quot;They are not only a silent killer, they also have a psychological effect&quot;. On 15 February 2008 Serbian Minister of Defence<space/><link><target>Dragan Sutanovac</target></link><space/>was pictured testing a Barnett crossbow during a public exercise of the Serbian army's Special Forces in Nis, 200&amp;nbsp;km south of capital<space/><link><target>Belgrade</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.daylife.com/photo/04ZU4Zr0xS4IA'>Day Life Serbia report</link>. Daylife.com (15 February 2008). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>Special forces in both Greece and<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>also continue to employ the crossbow.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://i96.photobucket.com/albums/l189/KORNET-E/162.jpg'>Greek soldiers uses crossbow</link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://i96.photobucket.com/albums/l189/KORNET-E/crosbow.jpg'>Turkish special ops</link>.</extension><space/>Spain's Green Berets still use the crossbow as well.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.boinasverdes.org/album/bataller/caperez/foto03.JPG'>Spanish Green Beret 2005 photo</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Asia, some Chinese armed forces use crossbows, including the<space/><link><target>Special forces</target><part>special force</part></link><space/><link><target>Snow Leopard Commando Unit</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>People's Armed Police</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>People's Liberation Army</target></link>. One justification for this comes in the crossbow's ability to stop persons carrying explosives without risk of causing detonation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20140202110148/http://english.pladaily.com.cn/site2/militarydatabase/2006-02/05/content_403376.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>17 August 2014<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://english.pladaily.com.cn/site2/militarydatabase/2006-02/05/content_403376.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>New crossbow shoots with great accuracy</arg></template></extension><space/>During the<space/><link><target>July 2009 rmqi riots</target><part>Xinjiang riots of July 2009</part></link>, crossbows were used alongside modern military hardware to quell protests.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bingham, John. (9 July 2009)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/china/5780852/Xinjiang-riots-Modern-Chinese-army-displays-ancient-preference-for-crossbow.html'>&quot;Xinjiang riots: Modern Chinese army displays ancient preference for crossbow&quot;</link>. Daily Telegraph (UK). Retrieved on 24 June 2011.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Indian Navy</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Marine Commando Force</target></link><space/>were equipped until the late 1980s with crossbows supplied with<space/><link><target>cyanide</target></link>-tipped bolts, as an alternative to<space/><link><target>suppressor</target><part>suppressed handgun</part><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Marines.html'>Marine Commandos&amp;#91;dead link&amp;#93;</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Comparison to conventional bows</heading><paragraph>With a crossbow, archers could release a draw force far in excess of what they could have handled with a bow. Furthermore, the crossbow could hold the tension for a long time, whereas even the strongest longbowman could only hold a drawn bow for so long. The ease of use of a crossbow allows it to be used effectively with little training, while other types of bows take far more skill to fire accurately. The disadvantage is the greater weight and clumsiness compared to a bow, as well as the slower rate of shooting and the lower efficiency of the acceleration system, but there would be reduced<space/><link><target>Hysteresis#Elastic hysteresis</target><part>elastic hysteresis</part></link>, making the crossbow a more accurate weapon.</paragraph><paragraph>Crossbows have a much smaller draw length than bows. This means that for the same energy to be imparted to the arrow (or bolt), the crossbow has to have a much higher draw weight.</paragraph><paragraph>A direct comparison between a fast hand-drawn replica crossbow and a longbow show a 6:10 rate of shooting<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HagCuGXJgUs&amp;amp;feature=grec_index'>Video comparing longbow and crossbow</link><space/>Retrieved 16 September 2010</extension><space/>or a 4:9 rate within 30 seconds and comparable weapons.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7g-0-RK3cjk'>longbow vs crossbow behind a pavese</link><space/>Retrieved 16 September 2010</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legal issues</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Laws on crossbows</arg></template><link><target>File:Armbrustschiessen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Modern competition crossbow</part></link>Can. 29 of the<space/><link><target>Second Lateran Council</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent II</target></link><space/>in 1139 banned the use of crossbows, as well as slings and bows, against Christians.<extension extension_name='ref'>The sources are collected in Hefele, Histoire des conciles d'apres les documents originaux, trans. and continued by H. Leclerq 190752., 5/1, 721722; but see also, Bernhardi Jahrbuecher der deutschen Geschichte, I Leipzig 1883, 154160:<space/><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/lateran2.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tenth Ecumenical Council: Lateran II 1139<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 May 2007<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 November 1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Internet Medieval Source Book<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The authenticity, interpretation and translation of this source is, however, contested.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Turner<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Monte<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Not So Diabolical Crossbow: A Re-Examination of Innocent II’s Supposed Ban Of The Crossbow at the Second Lateran Council
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Self-published thesis<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Today, the crossbow often has a complicated legal status due to the possibility of lethal use and its similarities to both firearms and archery weapons. While some jurisdictions regard crossbows the same as firearms, many others do not require any sort of license to own a crossbow. The legality of using a crossbow for hunting varies widely around the world, and even within different jurisdictions of some federal countries.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Arbalist (crossbowman)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bow (weapon)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of crossbows</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Master of Crossbowmen</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Modern competitive archery</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>target archery</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>bow (weapon)</target><part>bow</part><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Shooting sport</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baatz
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dietwulf
<space/></arg><arg name="author-link">
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Stuttgart
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bauten und Katapulte des römischen Heeres
<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Die römische Jagdarmbrust
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Franz Steiner Verlag
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>284–293
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>3-515-06566-0
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Payne-Gallwey, Ralph, Sir,<space/><italics>The Crossbow: Mediaeval and Modern, Military and Sporting; its Construction, History &amp; Management with a Treatise on the Balista and Catapult of the Ancients and An Appendix on the Catapult, Balista &amp; the Turkish Bow</italics>, New York : Bramhall House, 1958.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.atarn.org/chinese/yn_xbow/yn_xbow.htm'>The Crossbows of South-West China</link>, by Stephen Selby, 1999</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.diaspora.uiuc.edu/A-AAnewsletter/newsletter16.html'>African crossbow</link>, Donald B. Ball, 1996</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.escapeartist.com/efam/61/Thailand_Adventure.html'>Crossbow of the Hill Tribes</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Crossbows</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.medievalcrossbow.info/'>How To Make A Crossbow - Online Video Course</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.iau-crossbow.org/'>International Crossbow Shooting Union (IAU)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcrossbow.com/'>World Crossbow Shooting Association (WCSA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=wXVPAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq'>The Crossbow by Sir Ralph Payne-Gallwey, BT</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://users.utu.fi/sjsepp/paja/designing_crossbows/designing_crossbows.html'>Designing crossbows</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Archery</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template><template><target>Ancient mechanical artillery and hand-held missile weapons</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template><template><target>Medieval mechanical artillery and hand-held missile weapons</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Crossbows</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Heraldic charges</target></link></paragraph></article>