<article title='Conservatism'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>conservatism as a political and social philosophy</arg><arg></arg><arg>Conservatism (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Use American English</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Conservatism sidebar</target></template><template><target>Party politics</target></template><bold>Conservatism</bold><space/>as a<space/><link><target>political philosophy</target><part>political</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>social philosophy</target></link><space/>promotes retaining traditional social institutions in the context of<space/><link><target>culture</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>civilization</target></link>. Some conservatives seek to preserve things as they are, emphasizing stability and continuity, while others, called<space/><link><target>reactionary</target><part>reactionaries</part></link>, oppose modernism and seek a return to &quot;the way things were&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Iain McLean and Alistair McMillan, &quot;Conservatism&quot;,<space/><italics>Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics</italics>, Third Edition, &quot;Sometimes it (conservatism) has been outright opposition, based on an existing model of society that is considered right for all time. It can take a 'reactionary' form, harking back to, and attempting to reconstruct, forms of society which existed in an earlier period.&quot;, Oxford University Press, 2009, ISBN 978-0-19-920516-5.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="brit"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/133435/conservatism</arg><arg name="title">Conservatism (political philosophy)</arg><arg name="publisher">Britannica.com</arg></template><space/>Retrieved on 1&amp;nbsp;November 2009.</extension><space/>The first established use of the term in a political context originated with<space/><link><target>Franois-Ren de Chateaubriand</target></link><space/>in 1818,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jerry Z. Muller
</arg><arg name="title">Conservatism: An Anthology of Social and Political Thought from David Hume to the Present
</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton U.P.</arg><arg name="page">26
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Terms related to 'conservative' first found their way into political discourse in the title of the French weekly journal, ''Le Conservateur'', founded in 1818 by François-René de Chateaubriand with the aid of Louis de Bonald.</arg><arg name="isbn">0691037116
</arg></template></extension>during the period of<space/><link><target>Bourbon restoration</target></link><space/>that sought to roll back the policies of the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>. The term, historically associated with<space/><link><target>right-wing politics</target></link>, has since been used to describe a wide range of views. There is no single set of policies that are universally regarded as conservative, because the meaning of conservatism depends on what is considered traditional in a given place and time. Thus conservatives from different parts of the worldeach upholding their respective traditionsmay disagree on a wide range of issues.<link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link>, an 18th-century politician who opposed the French Revolution but supported the American Revolution, is credited as one of the main theorists of<space/><link><target>conservatism in the United Kingdom</target><part>conservatism in Great Britain in the 1790s</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Frank O'Gorman</arg><arg name="title">Edmund Burke: His Political Philosophy</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="page">171</arg><arg name="isbn">9780415326841</arg></template></extension><space/>According to<space/><link><target>Quintin Hogg, Baron Hailsham of St Marylebone</target><part>Quintin Hogg</part></link>, the chairman of the British<space/><link><target>Conservative Party (UK)</target><part>Conservative Party in 1959</part></link>, &quot;Conservatism is not so much a philosophy as an attitude, a constant force, performing a timeless function in the development of a free society, and corresponding to a deep and permanent requirement of human nature itself.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Quintin Hogg Baron Hailsham of St. Marylebone</arg><arg name="title">The Conservative Case</arg><arg name="url">https://www.google.com/search?tbo</arg><arg name="year">1959</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Development of Western conservatism</heading><heading level='3'>Great Britain</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in the United Kingdom</arg></template><template><target>Toryism</target><arg>Related</arg></template>In Britain, conservative ideas (though not yet called that) emerged in the<space/><link><target>Toryism</target><part>Tory</part></link><space/>movement during the<space/><link><target>Restoration (England)</target><part>Restoration</part></link><space/>period (16601688). Toryism supported a hierarchical society with a monarch who ruled by<space/><link><target>Divine right of kings</target><part>divine right</part></link>. Tories opposed the idea that sovereignty derived from the people, and rejected the authority of parliament and freedom of religion.<space/><link><target>Robert Filmer</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Patriarcha: or the Natural Power of Kings</italics>, published posthumously in 1680 but written before the<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link><space/>of 1642-1651, became accepted as the statement of their doctrine. However, the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link><space/>of 1688 destroyed this principle to some degree by establishing a constitutional government in England, leading to the hegemony of the Tory-opposed<space/><link><target>Whig (British political party)</target><part>Whig</part></link><space/>ideology. Faced with defeat, the Tories reformed their movement, now holding that sovereignty was vested in the three estates of Crown, Lords, and Commons<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, pp. ix, 21</extension><space/>rather than solely in the Crown. Toryism became marginalized during the long period of Whig ascendancy in the 18th century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:EdmundBurke1771.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>160px</part><part><link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link><space/>(17291797)</part></link>Conservatives typically see<space/><link><target>Richard Hooker</target></link><space/>(1554-1600) as the founding father of conservatism, along with the<space/><link><target>George Savile, 1st Marquess of Halifax</target><part>Marquess of Halifax</part></link><space/>(1633-1695),<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>(1711-1776) and<space/><link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link><space/>(1729-1797). Halifax promoted pragmatism in government, whilst Hume argued against political rationalism and utopianism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jerry Z. Muller, ed.<space/><italics>Conservatism: an anthology of social and political thought from David Hume to the present</italics><space/>(Princeton University Press, 1997); Sheldon Wolin, 'Hume and Conservatism',<space/><italics>American Political Science Review</italics><space/>48 (1954), 999-1016.</extension><space/>Burke served as the private secretary to the<space/><link><target>Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham</target><part>Marquis of Rockingham</part></link><space/>and as official pamphleteer to the<space/><link><target>Rockingham Whigs</target><part>Rockingham branch of the Whig party</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanlis, Peter J.<space/><italics>Edmund Burke: selected writings and speeches</italics>. New York: Transaction Publishers (2009), p. 18</extension><space/>Together with the Tories, they were the conservatives in the late 18th century United Kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">M. Morton Auerbach</arg><arg name="title">The Conservative Illusion</arg><arg name="url">http://www.unz.org/Pub/AuerbachMMorton-1959?View</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia University Press (1959)</arg><arg name="page">33</arg></template></extension><space/>Burke's views were a mixture of liberal and conservative. He supported the<space/><link><target>American Revolution</target></link><space/>of 1765-1783 but abhorred the violence of the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>(1789-1799). He accepted the liberal ideals of private property and the economics of<space/><link><target>Adam Smith</target></link><space/>(1723-1790), but thought that economics should remain subordinate to the conservative social ethic, that capitalism should be subordinate to the medieval social tradition and that the<space/><link><target>business</target></link><space/>class should be subordinate to<space/><link><target>aristocracy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auerbach,<space/><italics>The Conservative Illusion.</italics><space/>(1959), p. 40</extension><space/>He insisted on standards of honor derived from the medieval aristocratic tradition, and saw the aristocracy as the nation's natural leaders.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auerbach,<space/><italics>The Conservative Illusion</italics>. (1959), p. 37</extension><space/>That meant limits on the powers of the Crown, since he found the institutions of Parliament to be better informed than commissions appointed by the executive. He favored an<space/><link><target>established church</target></link>, but allowed for a degree of<space/><link><target>religious toleration</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auerbach,<space/><italics>The Conservative Illusion</italics><space/>(1959), pp. 5254</extension><space/>Burke justified the social order on the basis of tradition: tradition represented the wisdom of the species and he valued community and social harmony over social reforms.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auerbach,<space/><italics>The Conservative Illusion,</italics><space/>(1959), p. 41</extension><space/>Burke was a leading theorist in his day, finding extreme idealism (either Tory or Whig) an endangerment to broader liberties, and (like Hume) rejecting abstract reason as an unsound guide for political theory. Despite their influence on future conservative thought, none of these early contributors were explicitly involved in Tory politics. Hooker lived in the 16th century, long before the advent of<space/><link><target>toryism</target></link>, whilst Hume was an apolitical philosopher and Halifax similarly politically independent. Burke described himself as a<space/><link><target>Whigs (British political party)</target><part>Whig</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Shortly after Burke's death in 1797, conservatism revived as a mainstream political force as the Whigs suffered a series of internal divisions. This new generation of conservatives derived their politics not from Burke but from his predecessor, the<space/><link><target>Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke</target><part>Viscount Bolingbroke</part></link><space/>(1678-1751), who was a Jacobite and traditional Tory, lacking Burke's sympathies for Whiggish policies such as<space/><link><target>Catholic Emancipation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>American Revolution</target><part>American independence</part></link><space/>(famously attacked by<space/><link><target>Samuel Johnson</target></link><space/>in &quot;Taxation No Tyranny&quot;). In the first half of the 19th century many newspapers, magazines, and journals promoted loyalist or right-wing attitudes in religion, politics, and international affairs. Burke was seldom mentioned but<space/><link><target>William Pitt the Younger</target></link><space/>(1759-1806) became a conspicuous hero. The most prominent journals included<space/><italics>The Quarterly Review,</italics><space/>founded in 1809 as a counterweight to the Whigs'<space/><italics>Edinburgh Review</italics>, and the even more conservative<space/><italics>Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine</italics>. Sack finds that the<space/><italics>Quarterly Review</italics><space/>promoted a balanced Canningite toryism; was neutral on Catholic emancipation and only mildly critical of Nonconformist Dissent; it opposed slavery and supported the current poor laws. It was &quot;aggressively imperialist&quot;. The<space/><link><target>high-church</target></link><space/>clergy of the Church of England read the<space/><italics>Orthodox Churchman's Magazine</italics><space/>which was equally hostile to Jewish, Catholic,<space/><link><target>Jacobin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Methodist</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarian</part></link><space/>spokesmen. Anchoring the ultra tories,<space/><italics>Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine</italics><space/>stood firmly against Catholic emancipation, and favoured slavery, cheap money, mercantilism, the<space/><link><target>Navigation acts</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Holy Alliance</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>J.J. Sack, &quot;The Memory of Burke and the Memory of Pitt: English Conservatism Confronts Its Past, 1806-1829,&quot;<space/><italics>Historical Journal</italics><space/>(1987) 30#3 pp. 623-640;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2639162'>in JSTOR</link>; quote on p 627</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 19th century, conflict between wealthy<space/><link><target>businessmen</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Aristocracy (class)</target><part>aristocracy</part></link><space/>split the British conservative movement, with the aristocracy calling for a return to medieval ideas while the business classes advocated<space/><link><target>laissez-faire capitalism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auerbach, M. Morton<space/><italics>The Conservative Illusion.</italics><space/>Columbia University Press (1959), pp. 3940</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although conservatives opposed attempts to allow greater representation of the middle class in parliament, in 1834 they conceded that<space/><link><target>electoral reform</target></link><space/>could not be reversed and promised to support further reforms so long as they did not erode the institutions of church and state. These new principles were presented in the<space/><link><target>Tamworth Manifesto</target></link><space/>of 1834, which historians regard as the basic statement of the beliefs of the new Conservative Party.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, pp. 7980</extension><link><target>File:Robert Peel Portrait.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>alt=photograph</part><part><link><target>Robert Peel</target></link><space/>(17881850)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Some conservatives lamented the passing of a pastoral world where the ethos of<space/><italics><link><target>noblesse oblige</target></link></italics><space/>had promoted respect from the lower classes. They saw the<space/><link><target>Anglican Church</target></link><space/>and the aristocracy as balances against commercial wealth.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, p. 83</extension><space/>They worked toward legislation for improved working conditions and urban housing.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, p. 90</extension><space/>This viewpoint would later be called<space/><link><target>Tory Democracy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, p. 121</extension><space/>However, since Burke there has always been tension between traditional aristocratic conservatism and the wealthy business class.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eccleshall, pp. 67</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1834 Tory<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of the United Kingdom</target><part>Prime Minister</part></link><space/><link><target>Robert Peel</target></link><space/>issued the<space/><link><target>Tamworth Manifesto</target></link><space/>in which he pledged to endorse moderate political reform. This marked the beginning of the transformation of British conservatism from<space/><link><target>High Tory</target></link><space/>reactionism towards a more modern form based on &quot;conservation&quot;. The party became known as the<space/><link><target>Conservative Party (UK)</target><part>Conservative Party</part></link><space/>as a result, a name it has retained to this day. Peel, however, would also be the root of a split in the party between the traditional Tories (led by the<space/><link><target>Edward Smith-Stanley, 14th Earl of Derby</target><part>Earl of Derby</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Benjamin Disraeli</target></link>) and the 'Peelites' (led first by Peel himself, then by the<space/><link><target>George Hamilton-Gordon, 4th Earl of Aberdeen</target><part>Earl of Aberdeen</part></link>). The split occurred in 1846 over the issue of<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link>, which Peel supported, versus<space/><link><target>protectionism</target></link>, supported by Derby. The majority of the party sided with Derby, whilst about a third split away, eventually merging with the<space/><link><target>Whigs (British political party)</target><part>Whigs</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>radicalism (politics)</target><part>radicals</part></link><space/>to form the<space/><link><target>Liberal Party (UK)</target><part>Liberal Party</part></link>. Despite the split, the mainstream Conservative Party accepted the doctrine of free trade in 1852.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Margaret Thatcher.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>160px</part><part><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target></link><space/>(19252013)</part></link>In the second half of the 19th century the Liberal Party faced political schisms, especially over<space/><link><target>History of Ireland</target><part>Irish</part></link><space/><link><target>Irish Parliamentary Party</target><part>Home Rule</part></link>. Leader<space/><link><target>William Gladstone</target></link><space/>(himself a former Peelite) sought to give Ireland a degree of autonomy, a move that elements in both the left and right wings of his party opposed. These split off to become the<space/><link><target>Liberal Unionist Party</target><part>Liberal Unionists</part></link><space/>(led by<space/><link><target>Joseph Chamberlain</target></link>), forming a coalition with the Conservatives before merging with them in 1912. The Liberal Unionist influence dragged the Conservative Party towards the left; Conservative governments passing a number of progressive reforms at the turn of the 20th century. By the late 19th century the traditional business supporters of the UK<space/><link><target>Liberal Party (UK)</target><part>Liberal Party</part></link><space/>had joined the Conservatives, making them the party of business and<space/><link><target>commerce</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Feuchtwanger, p. 273</extension></paragraph><paragraph>After a period of Liberal dominance before the<space/><link><target>First World War</target></link>, the Conservatives gradually became more influential in government, regaining full control of the cabinet in 1922. In the interwar period conservatism was the major ideology in Britain<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>, as the Liberal Party vied with the<space/><link><target>Labour Party (UK)</target><part>Labour Party</part></link><space/>for control of the left. After the<space/><link><target>Second World War</target></link>, the first Labour government (1945-1951) under<space/><link><target>Clement Attlee</target></link><space/>embarked on a program of nationalization of industry and the promotion of social welfare. The Conservatives generally accepted those policies until the 1980s. In the 1980s the Conservative government of<space/><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target></link>, guided by<space/><link><target>neoliberalism</target><part>neoliberal</part></link><space/>economics, reversed many of Labour's programmes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Iain McLean and Laistair McMillan,<space/><italics>Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics</italics>, &quot;In the developed world neoliberalism is often coupled with Thatcherism ... .&quot;,p. 364, Oxford University Press, ISBN 978-0-19-920516-5.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Small conservative political parties -such as the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom Independence Party</target></link><space/>(founded in 1993) and the<space/><link><target>Democratic Unionist Party</target></link><space/>(founded in 1971) - began to appear, although they have yet to make any significant impact at Westminster (<template><target>as of</target><arg><space/>2014<space/></arg><arg name="lc"><space/>on</arg></template><space/>the DUP comprises the largest political party in the ruling coalition in the<space/><link><target>Northern Ireland Assembly</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Germany</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in Germany</arg></template>Conservative thought developed alongside nationalism in Germany, culminating in Germany's victory over France in the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian War</target></link>, the creation of the unified<space/><link><target>German Empire</target></link><space/>in 1871, and the simultaneous rise of<space/><link><target>Otto von Bismarck</target></link><space/>on the European political stage. Bismarck's &quot;balance of power&quot; model maintained peace in Europe for decades at the end of the 19th century. His &quot;revolutionary conservatism&quot; was a conservative state-building strategy designed to make ordinary Germansnot just the Junker elitemore loyal to state and emperor, he created the modern welfare state in Germany in the 1880s. According to Kees van Kersbergen and Barbara Vis, his strategy was:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>granting social rights to enhance the integration of a hierarchical society, to forge a bond between workers and the state so as to strengthen the latter, to maintain traditional relations of authority between social and status groups, and to provide a countervailing power against the modernist forces of liberalism and socialism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Kersbergen</arg><arg name="first1">Kees van</arg><arg name="last2">Vis</arg><arg name="first2">Barbara</arg><arg name="title">Comparative Welfare State Politics: Development, Opportunities, and Reform</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge UP</arg><arg name="page">38</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Bismarck also enacted universal male suffrage in the new German Empire in 1871.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Moore</arg><arg name="first1">Robert Laurence</arg><arg name="last2">Vaudagna</arg><arg name="first2">Maurizio</arg><arg name="title">The American Century in Europe</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell University Press</arg><arg name="page">226</arg></template></extension><space/>He became a great hero to German conservatives, who erected many monuments to his memory after he left office in 1890.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard E. Frankel, &quot;From the Beer Halls to the Halls of Power: The Cult of Bismarck and the Legitimization of a New German Right, 18981945,&quot;<space/><italics>German Studies Review,</italics><space/>Vol. 26, No. 3 (Oct., 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;543560<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1432746'>in JSTOR</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>With the rise of<space/><link><target>Nazism</target></link><space/>in 1933,<space/><link><target>agrarianism</target><part>agrarian movements</part></link><space/>faded and was supplanted by a more command-based economy and forced social integration. Though Adolf Hitler succeeded in garnering the support of many German industrialists, prominent traditionalists openly and secretly opposed his policies of euthanasia, genocide, and attacks on organized religion, including<space/><link><target>Claus von Stauffenberg</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dietrich Bonhoeffer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Henning von Tresckow</target></link>, Bishop<space/><link><target>Clemens August Graf von Galen</target></link>, and the monarchist<space/><link><target>Carl Friedrich Goerdeler</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>More recently, the work of conservative<space/><link><target>Christian Democratic Union (Germany)</target><part>CDU</part></link><space/>leader<space/><link><target>Helmut Kohl</target></link><space/>helped bring about<space/><link><target>German Reunification</target></link>, along with the closer integration of Europe in the form of the<space/><link><target>Maastricht Treaty</target></link>. Today, German conservatism is often associated with Chancellor<space/><link><target>Angela Merkel</target></link>, whose tenure has been marked by attempts to save the common European currency (EURO) from demise.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Conservatism in the United States</arg></template>In the United States, conservatism is rooted in the<space/><link><target>American Revolution</target></link><space/>and its commitment to<space/><link><target>Republicanism in the United States</target><part>republicanism</part></link>, sovereignty of the people, and the rights and liberties of Englishmen while expelling the king and his supporters. Most European conservative writers do not accept American conservatism as genuine; they consider it to be a variety of liberalism. Modern American liberals in the<space/><link><target>New Deal coalition</target><part>New Deal</part></link><space/>do not disagree with that consensus view, but conservatives spend much more emphasis on the Revolutionary origins, with the<space/><link><target>Tea Party movement</target><part>Tea Party</part></link><space/>advocates using<space/><link><target>Boston Tea Party</target><part>an episode from the 1770s</part></link><space/>for their name and some even dress in costumes from that era at their rallies.</paragraph><paragraph>Historian Gregory Schneider identifies several constants in<space/><bold>American conservatism</bold>: respect for tradition, support of republicanism, &quot;the rule of law and the Christian religion,&quot; and a defense of &quot;Western civilization from the challenges of modernist culture and totalitarian governments.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="GregorySchneider">Gregory Schneider,<space/><italics>The Conservative Century: From Reaction to Revolution<space/></italics><space/>(Rowman &amp; Littlefield. 2009) p. xii</extension><link><target>File:Jmaistre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part><link><target>Joseph de Maistre</target></link><space/>(17531821)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>Another form of conservatism developed in France in parallel to conservatism in Britain. It was influenced by<space/><link><target>Counter-Enlightenment</target></link><space/>works by men such as<space/><link><target>Joseph de Maistre</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Louis de Bonald</target></link>. Latin conservatism was less pragmatic and more<space/><link><target>reactionary</target></link><space/>than the conservatism of Burke.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg></template><space/>Many Continental or Traditionalist conservatives do not support<space/><link><target>separation of Church and state</target></link>, with most supporting state recognition of and cooperation with the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link>, such as had existed in France before the Revolution.</paragraph><paragraph>Eventually conservatives added<space/><link><target>patriotism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>nationalism</target></link><space/>to the list of traditional values they support. German conservatives were the first to embrace nationalism, which was previously associated with<space/><link><target>liberalism</target></link><space/>and the Revolution in France.<extension extension_name='ref'>ams, Ian Political Ideology Today (2nd edition), Manchester University Press, 2002, p. 46</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Forms of conservatism</heading><heading level='3'>Liberal conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Liberal conservatism</arg></template><link><target>Liberal conservatism</target></link><space/>is a variant of conservatism that combines conservative values and policies with classical<space/><link><target>Liberalism</target><part>liberal</part></link><space/>stances.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=xGNRRwkZFysC&amp;amp;pg=PA109'>Analyzing Politics: An Introduction to Political Science</link><space/>Ellen Grigsby, Cengage Learning, 2008 ISBN 978-0-495-50112-1, ISBN 978-0-495-50112-1 pp. 108, 109, 112, 347</extension><space/>As these latter two terms have had different meanings over time and across countries, liberal conservatism also has a wide variety of meanings. Historically, the term often referred to the combination of<space/><link><target>Liberal theory of economics</target><part>economic liberalism</part></link>, which champions<space/><link><target>laissez-faire</target></link><space/>markets, with the classical conservatism concern for established<space/><link><target>tradition</target></link>, respect for authority and religious values. It contrasted itself with<space/><link><target>classical liberalism</target></link>, which supported<space/><link><target>Individual freedom</target><part>freedom for the individual</part></link><space/>in both the economic and social spheres.</paragraph><paragraph>Over time, the general conservative ideology in many countries adopted economic liberal arguments, and the term<space/><italics>liberal conservatism</italics><space/>was replaced with<space/><italics>conservatism</italics>. This is also the case in countries where liberal economic ideas have been the tradition, such as the United States, and are thus considered conservative. In other countries where liberal conservative movements have entered the political mainstream, such as<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link>, the terms<space/><italics>liberal</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>conservative</italics><space/>may be synonymous. The liberal conservative tradition in the United States combines the economic<space/><link><target>individualism</target></link><space/>of the classical liberals with a<space/><link><target>Edmund Burke</target><part>Burkean</part></link><space/>form of conservatism (which has also become part of the<space/><link><target>American conservatism</target><part>American conservative</part></link><space/>tradition, such as in the writings of<space/><link><target>Russell Kirk</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>A secondary meaning for the term<space/><italics>liberal conservatism</italics><space/>that has developed in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link><space/>is a combination of more modern conservative (less traditionalist) views with those of<space/><link><target>social liberalism</target></link>. This has developed as an opposition to the more<space/><link><target>collectivist</target></link><space/>views of<space/><link><target>socialism</target></link>. Often this involves stressing what are now conservative views of free-market economics and belief in individual responsibility, with social liberal views on defence of<space/><link><target>civil rights</target></link>,<space/><link><target>environmentalism</target></link><space/>and support for a limited<space/><link><target>welfare state</target></link>. In continental Europe, this is sometimes also translated into<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>English</part></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>social conservatism</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Conservative liberalism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservative liberalism</arg></template><link><target>Conservative liberalism</target></link><space/>is a variant of<space/><link><target>liberalism</target></link><space/>that combines liberal values and policies with conservative stances, or, more simply, the right wing of the liberal movement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ipolitique.fr/liberalisme-conservateur.htm'>Ipolitique.fr</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.parties-and-elections.de/contents.html'>Parties-and-elections.de</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Mair"><link><target>Michael Gallagher (academic)</target><part>M. Gallagher</part></link>, M. Laver and<space/><link><target>Peter Mair</target><part>P. Mair</part></link>,<space/><italics>Representative Government in Europe</italics>, p. 221.</extension><space/>The roots of conservative liberalism are found at the beginning of the<space/><link><target>History of liberal thought</target><part>history of liberalism</part></link>. Until the two<space/><link><target>World Wars</target></link>, in most European countries the political class was formed by conservative liberals, from<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link>. Events after<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>brought the more radical version of classical liberalism to a more conservative (i.e. more moderate) type of liberalism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Allen R.T.,<space/><italics>Beyond Liberalism</italics>, p. 13.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Libertarian conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Libertarian conservatism</arg></template><link><target>Libertarian conservatism</target></link><space/>describes certain political ideologies within the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link><space/>which combine<space/><link><target>Libertarianism</target><part>libertarian</part></link><space/>economic issues with aspects of conservatism. Its five main branches are<space/><link><target>Constitutionalism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>paleolibertarianism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>right-libertarianism</target><part>neolibertarianism</part></link>,<space/><link><target>American conservatism</target><part>small government conservatism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Christian libertarianism</target></link>. They generally differ from<space/><link><target>paleoconservatives</target></link>, in that they are in favor of more<space/><link><target>liberty</target><part>personal</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>economic freedom</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Agorist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Samuel Edward Konkin III</target></link><space/>labeled libertarian conservatism<space/><link><target>right-libertarianism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nlm"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">New Libertarian Manifesto</arg><arg name="url">http://agorism.info/NewLibertarianManifesto.pdf</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="int"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Interview With Samuel Edward Konkin III</arg><arg name="url">http://www.spaz.org/~dan/individualist-anarchist/software/konkin-interview.html</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast to<space/><link><target>paleoconservative</target><trail>s</trail></link>, libertarian conservatives support strict<space/><link><target>laissez-faire</target></link><space/>policies such as<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link>, opposition to any national bank and opposition to<space/><link><target>regulations</target><part>business regulations</part></link>. They are vehemently opposed to<space/><link><target>environmental regulation</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>corporate welfare</target></link>,<space/><link><target>subsidies</target></link>, and other areas of economic intervention.</paragraph><paragraph>Many conservatives, especially in the United States, believe that the government should not play a major role in regulating business and managing the economy. They typically oppose efforts to charge high tax rates and to redistribute income to assist the poor. Such efforts, they argue, do not properly reward people who have earned their money through hard work.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Fiscal conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Fiscal conservatism</arg></template><link><target>Image:TeaPartyByFreedomFan.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Taxpayer March on Washington</target></link>: Conservative protesters walking down<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania Avenue (Washington, D.C.)</target><part>Pennsylvania Avenue</part></link>, Washington, D.C.</part></link><link><target>Fiscal conservatism</target></link><space/>is the economic philosophy of prudence in government spending and debt.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Correctional Organization and Management: Public Policy Challenges, Behavior, and Structure<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert M.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Freeman<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Elsevier<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="page">109<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7506-9897-9</arg></template></extension><space/>Edmund Burke, in his<space/><italics><link><target>Reflections on the Revolution in France</target></link></italics>, argued that a government does not have the right to run up large debts and then throw the burden on the taxpayer:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>...[I]t is to the property of the citizen, and not to the demands of the creditor of the state, that the first and original faith of civil society is pledged. The claim of the citizen is prior in time, paramount in title, superior in equity. The fortunes of individuals, whether possessed by acquisition or by descent or in virtue of a participation in the goods of some community, were no part of the creditor's security, expressed or implied...[T]he public, whether represented by a monarch or by a senate, can pledge nothing but the public estate; and it can have no public estate except in what it derives from a just and proportioned imposition upon the citizens at large.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most conservatives believe that government action cannot solve society's problems, such as poverty and inequality. Many believe that government programs that seek to provide services and opportunities for the poor actually encourage dependence and reduce self-reliance. Most conservatives oppose<space/><italics>affirmative action</italics><space/>policies-that is, policies in employment, education, and other areas that aim to counteract past discrimination by giving special help to members of disadvantaged groups. Conservatives believe that the government should not give special treatment to individuals on the basis of group identity.</paragraph><paragraph>Many conservatives, especially in the United States, believe that the government should not play a major role in regulating business and managing the economy. They typically oppose efforts to charge high tax rates and to redistribute income to assist the poor. Such efforts, they argue, do not properly reward people who have earned their money through hard work.</paragraph><heading level='3'>National and traditional conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>National conservatism</arg><arg>Traditional conservatism</arg></template><link><target>File:Gianfranco Fini 2004.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part><link><target>Gianfranco Fini</target></link>, former President of the Italian<space/><link><target>Chamber of Deputies (Italy)</target><part>Chamber of Deputies</part></link>, in 2004.</part></link>National conservatism is a<space/><link><target>politics</target><part>political</part></link><space/>term used primarily in Europe to describe a variant of conservatism which concentrates more on national interests than standard conservatism as well as upholding cultural and ethnic identity,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Dictionary Of Public Administration<space/></arg><arg name="last">Mandal<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>V.C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sarup & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-81-7625-784-8<space/></arg><arg name="page">306<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg></template></extension><space/>while not being outspokenly<space/><link><target>nationalism</target><part>nationalist</part></link><space/>or supporting a<space/><link><target>far-right politics</target><part>far-right</part></link><space/>approach.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2012</arg></template><space/>In Europe, national conservatives are usually<space/><link><target>Euroscepticism</target><part>eurosceptics</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.parties-and-elections.de/content.html</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="gua">Traynor, Ian,<space/><link type='external' href='http://commentisfree.guardian.co.uk/ian_traynor/2006/04/post_15.html'>The EU's weary travellers</link><space/><italics>The Guardian</italics>, April 4, 2006</extension></paragraph><paragraph>National conservatism is heavily oriented towards the traditional<space/><link><target>family</target></link><space/>and social stability as well as in favour of limiting<space/><link><target>immigration</target></link>. As such, national conservatives can be distinguished from economic conservatives, for whom<space/><link><target>free market</target></link><space/>economic policies,<space/><link><target>deregulation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fiscal conservatism</target></link><space/>are the main priorities. Some commentators have identified a growing gap between national and economic conservatism: &quot;most parties of the Right [today] are run by economic conservatives who, in varying degrees, have marginalized social, cultural, and national conservatives.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_n12_v49/ai_19559422'>National questions - conservatives fragmenting as liberals unite</link>, National Review, June 30, 1997</extension><space/>National conservatism is also related to<space/><link><target>traditionalist conservatism</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Traditionalist conservatism is a political philosophy emphasizing the need for the principles of<space/><link><target>natural law</target></link><space/>and transcendent moral order,<space/><link><target>tradition</target></link>,<space/><link><target>hierarchy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>organic unity</target></link>,<space/><link><target>agrarianism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>classicism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>high culture</target></link>, and the intersecting spheres of loyalty.<extension extension_name='ref'>Frohnen, Bruce, Jeremy Beer, and Jeffrey O. Nelson, ed. (2006)<space/><italics>American Conservatism: An Encyclopedia</italics><space/>Wilmington, DE: ISI Books, pp. 87075.</extension><space/>Some traditionalists have embraced the labels &quot;<link><target>reactionary</target></link>&quot; and &quot;<link><target>counterrevolution</target><trail>ary</trail></link>&quot;, defying the stigma that has attached to these terms since the<space/><link><target>Age of Enlightenment</target><part>Enlightenment</part></link>. Having a hierarchical view of society, many traditionalist conservatives, including a few Americans, defend the<space/><link><target>monarchy</target><part>monarchical</part></link><space/>political structure as the most natural and beneficial social arrangement.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cultural and social conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Cultural conservatism</arg><arg>social conservatism</arg></template>Cultural conservatives support the preservation of the heritage of one nation, or of a shared culture that is not defined by national boundaries.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Cultural Conservatism, Political Liberalism: From Criticism to Cultural Studies<space/></arg><arg name="first">James<space/></arg><arg name="last">Seaton<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Michigan Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-472-10645-5</arg></template></extension><space/>The shared culture may be as divergent as<space/><link><target>Western culture</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Chinese culture</target></link>. In the United States, the term<space/><italics>cultural conservative</italics><space/>may imply a conservative position in the<space/><link><target>culture war</target></link>. Cultural conservatives hold fast to traditional ways of thinking even in the face of monumental change. They believe strongly in traditional values and traditional politics, and often have an urgent sense of nationalism.</paragraph><paragraph>Social conservatism is distinct from cultural conservatism, although there are some overlaps. Social conservatives may believe that the government has a role in encouraging or enforcing traditional values or behaviours. A social conservative wants to preserve traditional morality and social mores, often by opposing what they consider radical policies or<space/><link><target>social engineering (political science)</target><part>social engineering</part></link>. Social change is generally regarded as suspect.</paragraph><paragraph>A second meaning of the term<space/><italics>social conservatism</italics><space/>developed in the<space/><link><target>Nordic countries</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>continental Europe</target></link>. There it refers to<space/><link><target>liberal conservatism</target><part>liberal conservatives</part></link><space/>supporting modern<space/><link><target>European welfare state</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Social conservatives (in the first meaning of the word) in many countries generally favour the<space/><link><target>pro-life</target></link><space/>position in the<space/><link><target>abortion controversy</target></link><space/>and oppose human<space/><link><target>embryonic stem cell</target></link><space/>research (particularly if publicly funded); oppose both<space/><link><target>eugenics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>human enhancement</target></link><space/>(<link><target>transhumanism</target></link>) while supporting<space/><link><target>bioconservatism</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.utne.com/2005-01-01/TheNextDigitalDivide.aspx?page=2'>The Next Digital Divide</link><space/>(utne article)</extension><space/>support a traditional definition of marriage as being one man and one woman; view the<space/><link><target>nuclear family</target></link><space/>model as society's foundational unit; oppose expansion of<space/><link><target>civil marriage</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>child adoption</target></link><space/>rights to couples in<space/><link><target>same-sex relationship</target><trail>s</trail></link>; promote<space/><link><target>public morality</target></link><space/>and traditional<space/><link><target>family values</target></link>; oppose atheism,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;No, I don't know that atheists should be considered as citizens, nor should they be considered patriots. This is one nation under God.&quot; President George H. W. Bush, http://www.positiveatheism.org/writ/ghwbush.htm</extension><space/>especially militant atheism,<space/><link><target>secularism</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>separation of church and state</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="MA1"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">The World & I.: Volume 1, Issue 5</arg><arg name="quote">militant atheism was incompatible with conservatism</arg><arg name="author">The World & I.: Volume 1, Issue 5</arg><arg name="publisher">Washington Times Corp.</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 August 2011</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1986</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="MA2"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">The Routledge Companion to Fascism and the Far Right</arg><arg name="quote">In addition, conservative Chrsitians often endorsed far-right remines as the lesser of two evils, especially when confronted with militant atheism in the USSR.</arg><arg name="author">Peter Davies; Derek Lynch</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Psychology Press]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 August 2011</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-415-21494-0</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Secularism"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">Religious America, Secular Europe?: A Theme and Variations</arg><arg name="quote">If anything the reverse is true: moral conservatives continue to oppose secular liberals on a wide range of issues.</arg><arg name="author">Peter L. Berger; Grace Davie; Effie Fokas</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Ashgate Publishing]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 August 2011</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7546-6011-8</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008</arg></template></extension><space/>support the prohibition of<space/><link><target>Prohibition (drugs)</target><part>drugs</part></link>,<space/><link><target>prostitution</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>euthanasia</target></link>; and support the<space/><link><target>censorship</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>pornography</target></link><space/>and what they consider to be<space/><link><target>obscenity</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>indecency</target></link>. Most conservatives in the U.S. support the<space/><link><target>death penalty</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Religious conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Religious Right</arg></template><link><target>File:Marche pour la vie 2012 - 6.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>March for Life (Paris)</target><part>March for Life</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, 2012</part></link>Religious conservatives principally seek to apply the teachings of particular religions to politics, sometimes by merely proclaiming the value of those teachings, at other times by having those teachings influence laws.<extension extension_name='ref'>Andersen, Margaret L., Taylor, Howard Francis.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=LP9bIrZ9xacC&amp;amp;pg=PA469'>''Sociology: Understanding a Diverse Society''</link><space/>Cengage Learning, 4th Ed. (2005), pp. 46970. ISBN 978-0-534-61716-5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In most modern democracies, political conservatism seeks to uphold traditional family structures and social values. Religious conservatives typically oppose abortion, homosexual behavior, drug use, and sexual activity outside of marriage. In some cases, conservative values are grounded in religious beliefs, and some conservatives seek to increase the role of religion in public life.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Progressive conservatism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Progressive conservatism</arg></template>Progressive conservatism incorporates<space/><link><target>Progressivism</target><part>progressive</part></link><space/>policies alongside conservative policies. It stresses the importance of a<space/><link><target>social safety net</target></link><space/>to deal with<space/><link><target>poverty</target></link>, support of limited<space/><link><target>redistribution of wealth</target></link><space/>along with government regulation to regulate markets in the interests of both consumers and producers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Patrick Dunleavy 2000. pp. 10708">Patrick Dunleavy, Paul Joseph Kelly, Michael Moran.<space/><italics>British Political Science: Fifty Years of Political Studies</italics>. Oxford, England, UK; Malden, Massachusetts, USA: Wiley-Blackwell, 2000. pp. 10708.</extension><space/>Progressive conservatism first arose as a distinct ideology in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>under Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Benjamin Disraeli</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>One nation conservatism</target><part>One Nation</part></link>&quot;<space/><link><target>Toryism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Patrick Dunleavy 2000. pp. 10708"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Robert Blake. Disraeli. Second Edition. London, England, UK: Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode (Publishers) Ltd, 1967. p. 524.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There have been a variety of progressive conservative governments. In the UK, the Prime Ministers Disraeli,<space/><link><target>Stanley Baldwin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Neville Chamberlain</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Harold Macmillan</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Trevor Russel. The Tory Party: its policies, divisions and future. Penguin, 1978. p. 167.</extension><space/>and present Prime Minister<space/><link><target>David Cameron</target></link><space/>are progressive conservatives.<extension extension_name='ref'>David Marr. &quot;Power Trip: The Political Journey of Kevin Rudd&quot;,<space/><italics>Issue 38 of Quarterly Essay Series</italics>. Black Inc., 2010. p. 126. (British Conservative Party leader<space/><link><target>David Cameron</target></link><space/>launched the Progressive Conservatism Project at Demos.)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Ruth Lister.<space/><italics>Understanding Theories and Concepts in Social Policy</italics>. Bristol, England, UK; Portland, Oregon, USA: The Policy Press, 2010. p. 53.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, the administration of President<space/><link><target>William Howard Taft</target></link><space/>was progressive conservative and he described himself as &quot;a believer in progressive conservatism&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Jonathan Lurie. William Howard Taft: The Travails of a Progressive Conservative. New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 2012. p. ix.</extension><space/>and President<space/><link><target>Dwight D. Eisenhower</target></link><space/>declared himself an advocate of &quot;progressive conservatism&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Gnter Bischof</target></link>. &quot;Eisenhower, the Judiciary, and Desegregation&quot; by Stanley I. Kutler,<space/><italics>Eisenhower: a centenary assessment</italics>. p. 98.</extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>, Chancellor<space/><link><target>Leo von Caprivi</target></link><space/>promoted a progressive conservative agenda called the &quot;New Course&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Alden Nichols.<space/><italics>Germany after Bismarck, the Caprivi era, 18901894: Issue 5</italics>. Harvard University Press, 1958. p. 260.</extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>, a variety of conservative governments have been progressive conservative, with Canada's major conservative movement being officially named the<space/><link><target>Progressive Conservative Party of Canada</target></link><space/>from 1942 to 2003.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hugh Segal 2011. pp. 11348">Hugh Segal. The Right Balance. Victoria, British Columbia, Canada: Douglas &amp; McIntyre, 2011. pp. 11348.</extension><space/>In Canada, the Prime Ministers<space/><link><target>Arthur Meighen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>R.B. Bennett</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Diefenbaker</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Joe Clark</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Brian Mulroney</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Kim Campbell</target></link><space/>led progressive conservative federal governments.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hugh Segal 2011. pp. 11348"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historic conservatism in different countries</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Right-wing politics</arg><arg>Political spectrum</arg></template>Conservative political parties vary widely from country to country in the goals they wish to achieve. Both conservative and liberal parties tend to favor private ownership of property, in opposition to communist, socialist and green parties, which favor communal ownership or laws requiring social responsibility on the part of property owners. Where conservatives and liberals differ is primarily on social issues. Conservatives tend to reject behavior that does not<space/><link><target>conformity</target><part>conform</part></link><space/>to some<space/><link><target>social norm</target></link>. Modern conservative parties often define themselves by their opposition to liberal or labor parties. The United States usage of the term<space/><italics>conservative</italics><space/>is unique to that country.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ware, Alan.<space/><italics>Political Parties and Party Systems</italics>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-19-878076-2, pp. 3133</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Alan Ware, Belgium, Denmark, Iceland, Finland, France, Greece, Iceland, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the UK retained viable conservative parties into the 1980s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ware, Alan.<space/><italics>Political Parties and Party Systems</italics>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-19-878076-2</extension><space/>Ware said that Australia, Germany, Israel, Italy, Japan, Malta, New Zealand, Spain and the US had no conservative parties, although they had either Christian Democrats or liberals as major right-wing parties. Canada, Ireland, and Portugal had right-wing political parties that defied categorization: the<space/><link><target>Progressive Conservative Party of Canada</target></link>;<space/><link><target>Fianna Fil</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Fine Gael</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Progressive Democrats</target></link><space/>in Ireland; and the<space/><link><target>Social Democratic Party (Portugal)</target><part>Social Democratic Party of Portugal</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ware, Alan.<space/><italics>Political Parties and Party Systems</italics>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-19-878076-2, p. 44</extension><space/>Since then, the<space/><link><target>Swiss People's Party</target></link><space/>has moved to the extreme right and is no longer considered to be conservative.<extension extension_name='ref'>Flecker, Jrg.<space/><italics>Changing working life and the appeal of the extreme right</italics>. Hampshire, UK: Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2007 ISBN 978-0-7546-4915-1, p. 19</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Klaus von Beyme</target></link>, who developed the method of party categorization, found that no modern Eastern European parties could be considered conservative, although the communist and communist-successor parties had strong similarities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis, Paul G.<space/><italics>Political parties in post-communist Eastern Europe</italics>. Routledge, 2000. ISBN 978-0-415-20182-7 pp. 54-55</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Italy, which was united by liberals and radicals (<italics><link><target>risorgimento</target></link></italics>), liberals not conservatives emerged as the party of the Right.<extension extension_name='ref'>Smith, Denis Mack.<space/><italics>Modern Italy: a political history</italics>. University of Michigan Press, 1997. ISBN 978-0-472-10895-4 p. 31</extension><space/>In the Netherlands, conservatives merged into a new Christian democratic party in 1980.<extension extension_name='ref'>Daalder, Hans and Irwin, Galen A.<space/><italics>Politics in the Netherlands: how much change?</italics><space/>Routledge, 1989. ISBN 0-7146-3361-5 pp. 154-57</extension><space/>In Austria, Germany, Portugal and Spain, conservatism was transformed into and incorporated into fascism or the<space/><link><target>far right</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Blinkhorn, Martin.<space/><italics>Fascists and conservatives</italics>. Routledge, 1990. p. 7</extension><space/>In 1940, all Japanese parties were merged into a single fascist party. Following the war, Japanese conservatives briefly returned to politics but were largely purged from public office.<extension extension_name='ref'>Takemae, Eiji, and Ricketts, Robert.<space/><italics>The allied occupation of Japan</italics>. New York: Continuum International Publishing Group, 2003. ISBN 978-0-8264-1521-9 pp. 26263</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Louis Hartz</target></link><space/>explained the absence of conservatism in Australia or the United States as a result of their settlement as radical or liberal fragments of Great Britain. Although he said English Canada had a negligible conservative influence, subsequent writers claimed that<space/><link><target>United Empire Loyalist</target><part>loyalists</part></link><space/>opposed to the American Revolution brought a Tory ideology into Canada. Hartz explained conservatism in Quebec and Latin America as a result of their settlement as feudal societies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fierlbeck, Katherine.<space/><italics>Political thought in Canada: an intellectual history</italics>. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2006. ISBN 978-1-55111-711-9 pp. 8788</extension><space/>The American conservative writer<space/><link><target>Russell Kirk</target></link><space/>provided the opinion that conservatism had been brought to the US and interpreted the American revolution as a &quot;conservative revolution&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kirk, Russell.<space/><italics>The Conservative Mind</italics>. Washington, DC: Regnery Publishing, 2001. ISBN 978-0-89526-171-7, 2001. ISBN 978-0-89526-171-7 pp. 6, 63</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Conservative elites have long dominated Latin American nations. Mostly this has been achieved through control of and support for civil institutions, the church and the armed forces, rather than through party politics. Typically the church was exempt from taxes and its employees immune from civil prosecution. Where national conservative parties were weak or non-existent, conservatives were more likely to rely on military dictatorship as a preferred form of government. However, in some nations where the elites were able to mobilize popular support for conservative parties, longer periods of political stability were achieved. Chile, Colombia and Venezuela are examples of nations that developed strong conservative parties. Argentina, Brazil, El Salvador and Peru are examples of nations where this did not occur.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlebrook, Kevin J.<space/><italics>Conservative parties, the right, and democracy in Latin America</italics>. Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000 ISBN 978-0-8018-6386-8 pp. 1-52</extension><space/>The Conservative Party of Venezuela disappeared following the<space/><link><target>Federal War</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of 1858-1863.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peeler, John A.<space/><italics>Latin American Democracies: Colombia, Costa Rica, Venezuela</italics>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press, 1985. p. 79</extension><space/>Chile's conservative party, the<space/><link><target>National Party (Chile, 19661973)</target><part>National Party</part></link><space/>disbanded in 1973 following a military coup and did not re-emerge as a political force following the subsequent return to democracy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Oppenheim, Lois Hecht.<space/><italics>Politics in Chile: socialism, authoritarianism, and market democracy</italics>. Boulder, CO: Westview Press, 2007. ISBN 978-0-8133-4227-6 pp. 15152</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Belgium</heading><paragraph>Founded in 1945 as the Christian People's Party, the<space/><link><target>Christen-Democratisch en Vlaams</target><part>Flemish Christian Democrats</part></link><space/>(CD&amp;V) dominated politics in post-war Belgium. In 1999, the party's support collapsed and it became the country's fifth largest party.<extension extension_name='ref'>Annesley, Claire.<space/><italics>A political and economic dictionary of Western Europe</italics>. London: Routledge, 2005. ISBN 978-1-85743-214-5, p. 124</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Zig Layton-Henry, ed.<space/><italics>Conservative Politics in Western Europe</italics><space/>(St. Martin's Press, 1982)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Lucardie and Hans-Martien Ten Napel, &quot;Between confessionalism and liberal conservatism: the Christian Democratic parties of Belgium and the Netherlands.&quot; in David Hanley, ed.<space/><italics>Christian Democracy in Europe: A Comparative Perspective</italics><space/>(London: Pinter 1994) pp: 51-70.</extension><space/>Currently the<space/><link><target>New Flemish Alliance</target><part>N-VA (nieuw-vlaamse alliantie / new-Flemish alliance)</part></link><space/>is the largest party in Belgium.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Philippe Siuberski</arg><arg name="title">Belgium gets new government with Michel as PM<space/></arg><arg name="agency">AFP<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://news.yahoo.com/belgium-parties-agree-form-govt-michel-pm-190206709.html<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Yahoo News<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 October 2014<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 November 2014<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in Canada</arg></template>Canada's<space/><italics>Conservatives</italics><space/>had their roots in the Loyalists Tories who left America after the American Revolution. They developed in the socio-economic and political cleavages that existed during the first three decades of the 19th century, and had the support of the business, professional and established Church (Anglican) elites in Ontario and to a lesser extent in Quebec. Holding a monopoly over administrative and judicial offices, they were called the &quot;<link><target>Family Compact</target></link>&quot; in Ontario and the &quot;<link><target>Chateau Clique</target></link>&quot; in Quebec.<space/><link><target>John A. Macdonald</target></link>'s successful leadership of the movement to confederate the provinces and his subsequent tenure as prime minister for most of the late 19th century rested on his ability to bring together the English-speaking Protestant oligarchy and the<space/><link><target>ultramontane</target></link><space/>Catholic hierarchy of Quebec and to keep them united in a conservative coalition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kornberg, Allan and Mishler, William.<space/><italics>Influence in Parliament, Canada</italics>. Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1976. p. 38</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Conservatives combined<space/><link><target>economic liberalism</target><part>pro-market liberalism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Toryism</target></link>. They generally supported an activist government and state intervention in the marketplace, and their policies were marked by<space/><italics><link><target>noblesse oblige</target></link></italics>, a paternalistic responsibility of the elites for the less well-off.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schultze, Rainer-Olaf; Sturm, Roland and Eberle, Dagmar.<space/><italics>Conservative parties and right-wing politics in North America: reaping the benefits of an ideological victory?</italics>. Germany: VS Verlag, 2003. ISBN 978-3-8100-3812-8 p. 15</extension><space/>From 1942, the party was known as the Progressive Conservatives, until 2003, when the national party merged with the<space/><link><target>Canadian Alliance</target></link><space/>to form the<space/><link><target>Conservative Party of Canada</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Panizza, Francisco.<space/><italics>Populism and the mirror of democracy</italics>. London: Verso, 2005. ISBN 978-1-85984-489-2 p. 180</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The conservative<space/><link><target>Union Nationale (Quebec)</target><part>Union Nationale</part></link><space/>governed the province of Quebec in periods from 1936 to 1960, in a close alliance with English Canadian business elites and the Catholic Church. This period, known as the<space/><link><target>Grande Noirceur</target><part>Great Darkness</part></link><space/>ended with the<space/><link><target>Quiet Revolution</target></link><space/>and the party went into terminal decline.<extension extension_name='ref'>Conway, John Frederick.<space/><italics>Debts to pay: the future of federalism in Quebec</italics>. Toronto: James Lorimer &amp; Company, 2004. ISBN 978-1-55028-814-8 pp. 57, 77</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Colombia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in Colombia</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Colombian Conservative Party</target></link>, founded in 1849, traces its origins to opponents of General<space/><link><target>Francisco de Paula Santander</target></link>'s 183337 administration. While the term &quot;liberal&quot; had been used to describe all political forces in Colombia, the conservatives began describing themselves as &quot;conservative liberals&quot; and their opponents as &quot;red liberals&quot;. From the 1860s until the present, the party has supported strong central government, and supported the Catholic Church, especially its role as protector of the sanctity of the family, and opposed separation of church and state. Its policies include the legal equality of all men, the citizen's right to own property and opposition to dictatorship. It has usually been Colombia's second largest party, with the<space/><link><target>Colombian Liberal Party</target></link><space/>being the largest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Osterling, p. 180</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Denmark</heading><paragraph>Founded in 1915, the<space/><link><target>Conservative People's Party (Denmark)</target><part>Conservative People's Party of Denmark</part></link>. was the successor of<space/><italics>Hjre</italics><space/>(literally &quot;<link><target>Right-wing politics</target><part>right&quot;</part></link>). In the 2005 election it won 18 out of 179 seats in the<space/><italics>Folketing</italics><space/>and became a junior partner in coalition with the Liberals.<extension extension_name='ref'>Annesley, Claire.<space/><italics>A political and economic dictionary of Western Europe</italics>. London: Routledge, 2005. ISBN 978-1-85743-214-5, p. 68</extension><space/>The party is preceded by 11 years by the<space/><link><target>Young Conservatives (Denmark)</target><part>Young Conservatives (KU)</part></link>, today the youth movement of the party. The Party suffered a major defeat in the parliamentary elections of September 2011 in which the party lost more than half of its seat and also lost governmental power. A liberal cultural policy dominated during the postwar period. However, by the 1990s disagreements regarding immigrants from entirely different cultures ignited a conservative backlash.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kasper Stvring, &quot;The Turn from Cultural Radicalism to National Conservatism: Cultural Policy in Denmark.&quot;<space/><italics>Telos</italics><space/>2009.148 (2009) pp: 54-72.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Finland</heading><paragraph>The conservative party in Finland is the<space/><link><target>National Coalition Party</target></link><space/>(in Finnish<space/><italics>Kansallinen Kokoomus</italics>,<space/><italics>Kok</italics>). The party was founded in 1918 when several monarchist parties united. Although in the past the party was right-wing, today it is a moderate party. While the party advocates<space/><link><target>economic liberalism</target></link>, it is committed to the<space/><link><target>social market economy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Siaroff, Alan.<space/><italics>Comparative European party systems: an analysis of parliamentary elections since 1945</italics>. New York and London: Garland Publishing Inc., 2000. ISBN 978-0-8153-2930-5, p. 243</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>Conservatism in France focused on The rejection of the French Revolution, support for the Catholic Church, and the restoration of the monarchy. The monarchist cause was on the verge of victory in the 1870s but then collapsed because of disagreements on who would be king, and what the national flag should be.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Roger Price</arg><arg name="title">A Concise History of France</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge UP</arg><arg name="page">225</arg></template></extension><space/>Religious tensions heightened in the 1890-1910 era, but moderated after the spirit of unity in fighting the First World War.<extension extension_name='ref'>Maurice Larkin,<space/><italics>Religion, politics and preferment in France since 1890: La Belle Epoque and its legacy</italics><space/>(Cambridge University Press, 2002)</extension><space/>An extreme form of conservatism characterized the<space/><link><target>Vichy France</target><part>Vichy regime</part></link><space/>of 1940-1944 with heightened anti-Semitism, opposition to individualism, emphasis on family life, and national direction of the economy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanley Hoffmann, &quot;The Vichy Circle of French Conservatives&quot; in Hoffmann,<space/><italics>Decline or Renewal? France since 1930s</italics><space/>(1974) pp: 3-25.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Following the Second World War, conservatives in France supported Gaullist groups and have been nationalistic, and emphasized tradition, order, and the regeneration of France.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Vinen, &quot;The Parti rpublicain de la Libert and the Reconstruction of French Conservatism, 19441951,&quot;<space/><italics>French History</italics><space/>(1993) 7#2 pp: 183-204.</extension><space/>Gaullists held divergent views on social issues. The number of Conservative groups, their lack of stability, and their tendency to be identified with local issues defy simple categorization. Conservatism has been the major political force in France since the second world war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Viereck, Peter and Ryn, Claes G. New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 2005. ISBN 978-0-7658-0576-8 p. 205</extension><space/>Unusually, post-war French conservatism was formed around the personality of a leader,<space/><link><target>Charles de Gaulle</target></link>, and did not draw on traditional French conservatism, but on the<space/><link><target>Bonapartism</target></link><space/>tradition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ware, Alan.<space/><italics>Political Parties and Party Systems</italics>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-19-878076-2, p. 32</extension><space/>Gaullism in France continues under<space/><link><target>Les Republicains</target></link><space/>(formerly<space/><link><target>Union for a Popular Movement</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Hauss, Charles.<space/><italics>Comparative Politics: Domestic Responses to Global Challenges</italics>. Belmont, CA: Cengage Learning, 2008. ISBN 978-0-495-50109-1 p. 116</extension><space/>The word &quot;conservative&quot; itself is a term of abuse in France.<extension extension_name='ref'>Knapp, Andrew and Wright, Vincent.<space/><italics>The government and politics of France</italics>. New York: Routledge, 2006. ISBN 978-0-415-35733-3 p. 211</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Greece</heading><paragraph>The main interwar conservative party was called the<space/><link><target>People's Party (Greece)</target><part>People's Party</part></link><space/>(PP), which supported<space/><link><target>Greek monarchy</target><part>constitutional monarchy</part></link><space/>and opposed the<space/><link><target>Second Hellenic Republic</target><part>republican</part></link><space/><link><target>Liberal Party (Greece)</target><part>Liberal Party</part></link>. Both it and the Liberal party were suppressed by the authoritarian, arch-conservative and royalist<space/><link><target>4th of August Regime</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ioannis Metaxas</target></link><space/>in 193641. The PP was able to re-group after the Second World War as part of a<space/><italics>United Nationalist Front</italics><space/>which achieved power campaigning on a simple anticommunist, ultranationalist platform during the<space/><link><target>Greek Civil War</target></link><space/>(194649). However, the vote received by the PP declined during the so-called &quot;Centrist Interlude&quot; in 195052. In 1952, Marshal<space/><link><target>Alexandros Papagos</target></link><space/>created the<space/><link><target>Greek Rally</target></link><space/>as an umbrella for the right-wing forces. The Greek Rally came to power in 1952 and remained the leading party in Greece until 1963after Papagos' death in 1955 reformed as the<space/><link><target>National Radical Union</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Konstantinos Karamanlis</target></link>. Right-wing governments backed by the palace and the army overthrew the<space/><link><target>Centre Union</target></link><space/>government in 1965, and governed the country until the establishment of the far-right<space/><link><target>Regime of the Colonels</target></link><space/>(196774). After the<space/><link><target>metapolitefsi</target><part>regime's collapse</part></link><space/>in August 1974, Karamanlis returned from exile to lead the government, and founded the<space/><link><target>New Democracy (Greece)</target><part>New Democratic Party</part></link>. The new party had four objectives: to confront<space/><link><target>Turkish invasion of Cyprus</target><part>Turkish expansionism in Cyprus</part></link>, to reestablish and solidify democratic rule, to give the country a strong government, and to make a powerful moderate party a force in Greek politics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Penniman, Howard Rae.<space/><italics>Greece at the polls: the national elections of 1974 and 1977</italics>. Washington: American Enterprise Institute, 1981. ISBN 978-0-8447-3434-7 pp. 4959</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Independent Greeks</target></link>, a newly formed political party in<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link><space/>has also supported conservatism, particularly<space/><link><target>National conservatism</target><part>national</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>religious conservatism</target></link>. The Founding Declaration of the Independent Greeks strongly emphasises in the preservation of the Greek state and its<space/><link><target>sovereignty</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Greek people</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Greek Orthodox Church</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://anexartitoiellines.gr/files/idritiki%20diakirixi.pdf'>Founding Declaration of Independent Greeks</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Iceland</heading><paragraph>Founded in 1926 as the Conservative Party, Iceland's<space/><link><target>Independence Party (Iceland)</target><part>Independence Party</part></link><space/>adopted its current name in 1929. From the beginning they have been the largest vote-winning party, averaging around 40%. They combine liberalism and conservatism, supporting nationalization and opposed to class conflict. While mostly in opposition during the 1930s, they embraced<space/><link><target>economic liberalism</target></link>, but accepted the welfare state after the war and participated in governments supportive of state intervention and protectionism. Unlike other Scandanivian conservative (and liberal) parties, it has always had a large working-class following.<extension extension_name='ref'>Grofman, Bernard and Lijpart, Arend, editors.<space/><italics>The evolution of electoral and party systems in the Nordic countries</italics>. New York: Agathon Press, 2002. &quot;The Icelandic electoral system 18441999&quot; by Olafur Th. Hardarson ISBN 978-0-87586-138-8, pp. 10708</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Italy</heading><paragraph>After WW2 in<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>the conservative theories were mainly represented by the<space/><link><target>Christian Democracy (Italy)</target><part>Christian Democracy</part></link>, which government form the foundation of the Republic until party's dissolution in 1994. Officially DC refused the ideology of Conservatism, but in many aspects, for example<space/><link><target>family values</target></link>, it was a typical<space/><link><target>social conservative</target></link><space/>party.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1994 the media tycoon and entrepreneur<space/><link><target>Silvio Berlusconi</target></link><space/>founded the<space/><link><target>liberal conservative</target></link><space/><link><target>Forza Italia</target></link><space/>movement. Berlusconi won three elections in<space/><link><target>Italian general election, 1994</target><part>1994</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Italian general election, 2001</target><part>2001</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Italian general election, 2008</target><part>2008</part></link><space/>governing the country for almost ten years as<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of Italy</target><part>Prime Minister</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Besides FI, now the conservative ideas are mainly expressed by the<space/><link><target>New Centre-Right</target></link><space/>party led by<space/><link><target>Angelino Alfano</target></link>, former Berlusconi's protg who split from the reborn<space/><link><target>Forza Italia (2013)</target><part>Forza Italia</part></link><space/>founding a new conservative movement. Alfano is the current<space/><link><target>Italian Minister of the Interior</target><part>Minister of the Interior</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Renzi Cabinet</target><part>government</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Matteo Renzi</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Luxembourg</heading><paragraph>Luxembourg's major conservative party, the<space/><link><target>Christian Social People's Party</target></link><space/>(CSV or PCS) was formed as the Party of the Right in 1914, and adopted its present name in 1945. It was consistently the largest political party in Luxembourg and dominated politics throughout the 20th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Urwin, Derek W.<space/><italics>A Dictionary of European History and Politics, 1945-1995</italics>. London: Pearson UK, 1996. ISBN 978-0-582-25874-7 p. 76.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Norway</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Conservative Party (Norway)</target><part>Conservative Party of Norway</part></link><space/>(Norwegian: Hyre, literally &quot;<link><target>Right-wing politics</target><part>right&quot;</part></link>) was formed by the old upper class of state officials and wealthy merchants to fight the populist democracy of the<space/><link><target>Liberal Party (Norway)</target><part>Liberal Party</part></link>, but lost power in 1884 when parliamentarian government was first practised. It formed its first government under parliamentarism in 1889, and continued to alternate in power with the Liberals until the 1930s, when Labour became the dominant political party. It has elements both of paternalism, stressing the responsibilities of the state, and of economic liberalism. It first returned to power in the 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Knut Heidar</target><part>Heidar, Knut</part></link>.<space/><italics>Norway: elites on trial</italics>. Boulder Westview Press, 2001. ISBN 978-0-8133-3200-0, pp. 6667</extension><space/>During<space/><link><target>Kre Willoch#Premiership</target><part>Kre Willoch's premiership</part></link><space/>in the 1980s, much emphasis was laid on liberalizing the credit- and housing market and abolishing the<space/><link><target>NRK</target></link><space/>TV and radio monopoly, while supporting<space/><link><target>Law and order (politics)</target><part>law and order</part></link><space/>in criminal justice and traditional norms in education<extension extension_name='ref'>Francis Sejersted<space/><link type='external' href='http://snl.no/H%C3%B8yreb%C3%B8lgen'>Hyreblgen</link><space/>Store norske leksikon. Retrieved 18 December 2013<space/><template><target>no icon</target></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sweden</heading><paragraph>Sweden's conservative party, the<space/><link><target>Moderate Party</target></link>, was formed in 1904, two years after the founding of the liberal party.<extension extension_name='ref'>Grofman, Bernard and Lijpart, Arend, editors.<space/><italics>The evolution of electoral and party systems in the Nordic countries</italics>. New York: Agathon Press, 2002. &quot;The Icelandic electoral system 1844-1999&quot; by Olafur Th. Hardarson ISBN 978-0-87586-138-8, pp. 107235</extension><space/>The party emphasizes tax reductions, deregulation of private enterprise, and privatization of schools, hospitals and kindergartens.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas, Clive S. (editor).<space/><italics>Political Parties and Interest Groups: Shaping Democratic Governance</italics>. Boulder: Lynne Rienner, 2001. ISBN 978-1-55587-978-5 &quot;Sweden: Weakening Links Between Political Parties and Interest Organizations&quot; by Anders Widfeldt</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Switzerland</heading><paragraph>There are a number of conservative parties in Switzerland's parliament, the Federal Assembly. These include the largest, the<space/><link><target>Swiss People's Party</target></link><space/>(SVP),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hans-Georg"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ziebertz</arg><arg name="first">Hans-Georg</arg><arg name="title">How Teachers in Europe Teach Religion: An International Empirical Study: An International Empirical Study in 16 Countries</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Lit Verlag</arg><arg name="isbn">978-3-643-10043-6</arg><arg name="page">237</arg></template></extension><space/>the<space/><link><target>Christian Democratic People's Party of Switzerland</target><part>Christian Democratic People's Party</part></link><space/>(CVP),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Juravich"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Juravich</arg><arg name="first">Tom</arg><arg name="title">Ravenswood: The Steelworkers' Victory and the Revival of American Labor</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8014-8666-1</arg><arg name="page">133</arg></template></extension><space/>represented in the Federal Council or cabinet by<space/><link><target>Doris Leuthard</target></link><space/>(in 2011), and the<space/><link><target>Conservative Democratic Party of Switzerland</target></link><space/>(BDP),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schwok"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Schwok</arg><arg name="first">René</arg><arg name="title">SWITZERLAND – EUROPEAN UNION: AN IMPOSSIBLE MEMBERSHIP?</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Peter Lang</arg><arg name="isbn">978-90-5201-576-7</arg><arg name="page">143</arg></template></extension><space/>which is a splinter of the SVP created after a failed attempt to expel Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf from the SVP.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schwok"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Swiss People's Party (SVP or UDC) was formed from the 1971 merger of the<space/><link><target>Party of Farmers, Traders and Independents</target><part>Party of Farmers, Traders, and Citizens</part></link>, formed in 1917 and the smaller Swiss Democratic Party, formed in 1942. The SVP emphasized agricultural policy, and was strong among farmers in German-speaking Protestant areas. As Switzerland considered closer relations with the European Union in the 1990s, the SVP adopted a more militant protectionist and isolationist stance. This stance has allowed it to expand into German-speaking Catholic mountainous areas.<extension extension_name='ref'>Siaroff, Alan<space/><italics>Comparative European Party Systems</italics>. New York: Garland, 2000. ISBN 0-8153-2930-X p. 446</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Anti-Defamation League</target></link>, a non-Swiss lobby group based in the USA has accused them of manipulating issues such as immigration, Swiss neutrality and welfare benefits, awakening anti-Semitism and racism.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Stephen Roth Institute.<space/><italics>Anti-semitism worldwide</italics><space/>Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2002 ISBN 0-8032-5943-3 p. 120</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target></link><space/>has called the SVP &quot;extreme right&quot;, although some scholars dispute this classification. Hans-Georg Betz for example describes it as &quot;populist radical right&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hainsworth, pp. 44, 74</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Conservatism in the United Kingdom</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern conservatism in different countries</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Angela Merkel (9307204896).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>European People's Party</target></link><space/>Congress in Bucharest in 2012</part></link>While conservatism has been seen as an appeal to traditional, hierarchical society, some writers, such as<space/><link><target>Samuel P. Huntington</target></link>, see it as situational. Under this definition, conservatives are seen as defending the established institutions of their time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Winthrop and Lovell, pp. 16366</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in Australia</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Liberal Party of Australia</target></link><space/>adheres to the principles of<space/><link><target>social conservatism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>liberal conservatism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barns, Greg.<space/><italics>Wanted:genuine liberal party for political scene</italics>. Sydney: Australian Broadcasting Corporation 2011</extension><space/>It is Liberal in the sense of economics. The party is considered to be more<space/><link><target>right-wing</target></link><space/>than the<space/><link><target>Conservative Party (UK)</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/unleashed/3667104.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Wanted: genuine liberal party for political scene<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Australian Broadcasting Corporation<space/></arg><arg name="last">Barns<space/></arg><arg name="first">Greg<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Greg Barns<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 March 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Other conservative parties are the<space/><link><target>National Party of Australia</target></link>, a sister party of the Liberals,<space/><link><target>Family First Party</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Democratic Labour Party (Australia)</target><part>Democratic Labor Party</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Shooters Party</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Katter's Australian Party</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The second largest party in the country, the<space/><link><target>Australian Labor Party</target></link>'s dominant faction is Labor Right, a<space/><link><target>socially conservative</target></link><space/>element. Australia undertook significant economic reform under the<space/><link><target>Australian Labor Party</target></link><space/>in the mid-1980s. Consequently, issues like protectionism, welfare reform, privatization and deregulation are no longer debated in the political space as they are in Europe or North America. Moser and Catley explain, &quot;In America, 'liberal' means left-of-center, and it is a pejorative term when used by conservatives in adversarial political debate. In Australia, of course, the conservatives are in the Liberal Party.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">David Mosler</arg><arg name="author2">Robert Catley</arg><arg name="title">America and Americans in Australia</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="page">83</arg><arg name="isbn">9780275962524</arg></template></extension><space/>Jupp points out that, &quot;[the] decline in English influences on Australian reformism and radicalism, and appropriation of the symbols of Empire by conservatives continued under the Liberal Party leadership of Sir<space/><link><target>Robert Menzies</target></link>, which lasted until 1966.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">James Jupp</arg><arg name="title">The English in Australia</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="page">172</arg><arg name="isbn">9780521542951</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in South Korea</arg></template>South Korea's major conservative party, the<space/><link><target>Saenuri Party</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target></target></link>, changed its form throughout its history. First it was the Democratic-Republican Party(1963~1980); its head was<space/><link><target>Park Chung-hee</target></link><space/>who seized power in a 1961 military coup d'tat and ruled as an unelected military strongman until his formal election as president in 1963. He was president for 16 years, until his assassination on October 26, 1979. The<space/><link><target>Democratic Justice Party</target></link><space/>inherited the same ideology as the Democrati-Republican Party. Its head,<space/><link><target>Chun Doo-hwan</target></link>, also gained power through a coup. His followers called themselves the Hanahoe. The Democratic Justice Party changed its form and acted to suppress the opposition party and to follow the people's demand for direct elections. The party's<space/><link><target>Roh Tae-woo</target></link><space/>became the first president who was elected through direct election. The next form of the major conservative party was the Democratic-Liberal Party. Again, through election, its second leader,<space/><link><target>Kim Young-sam</target></link>, became the fourteenth president of Korea. When the conservative party was beaten by the opposition party in the general election, it changed its form again to follow the party members' demand for reforms. It became the New Korean Party. It changed again one year later since the President Kim Young-sam was blamed by the citizen for the IMF<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template>. It changed its name to Grand National Party (Hannara-dang) (1998~2011). Since the late Kim Dae-jung assumed the presidency in 1998, GNP had not been the ruling party until Lee Myung-bak won the presidential election of 2007. It renamed to Saenoori Party () in 2011.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Conservatism in the United States</arg></template><link><target>File:President Reagan speaking in Minneapolis 1982.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>President Ronald Reagan in 1982</part></link>The meaning of &quot;conservatism&quot; in America has little in common with the way the word is used elsewhere. As Ribuffo (2011) notes, &quot;what Americans now call conservatism much of the world calls liberalism or neoliberalism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Leo P. Ribuffo, &quot;20 Suggestions for Studying the Right now that Studying the Right is Trendy,&quot;<space/><italics>Historically Speaking</italics><space/>Jan 2011 v.12#1 pp. 26, quote on p. 6</extension><space/>Since the 1950s conservatism in the United States has been chiefly associated with the<space/><link><target>History of the Republican Party (United States)</target><part>Republican Party</part></link>. However, during the era of<space/><link><target>Racial segregation in the United States</target><part>segregation</part></link><space/>many<space/><link><target>Southern Democrats</target></link><space/>were conservatives, and they played a key role in the<space/><link><target>Conservative Coalition</target></link><space/>that largely controlled domestic policy in Congress from 1937 to 1963.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kari Frederickson,<space/><italics>The Dixicrat Revolt and the End of the Solid South, 19321968</italics>, p. 12, &quot;...conservative southern Democrats viewed warily the potential of New Deal programs to threaten the region's economic dependence on cheap labor while stirring the democratic ambitions of the disfranchised and undermining white supremacy.&quot;, The University of North Carolina Press, 2000, ISBN 978-0-8078-4910-1</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Major priorities within American conservatism include support for tradition, law-and-order, Christianity,<space/><link><target>anti-communism</target></link>, and a defense of &quot;Western civilization from the challenges of modernist culture and totalitarian governments.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="GregorySchneider"></extension><space/>Economic conservatives and libertarians favor<space/><link><target>small government</target></link>, low taxes, limited regulation, and free enterprise. Some social conservatives see traditional social values threatened by secularism, so they support<space/><link><target>school prayer</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Opposition to the legalization of abortion</target><part>oppose abortion</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Opponents of same-sex marriage in the United States</target><part>homosexuality</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Social"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Texas Politics: Governing the Lone Star State</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Taylor & Francis]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 January 2012</arg><arg name="author">Cal Jillson</arg><arg name="date">22 February 2011</arg><arg name="quote">Social conservatives focus on moral or values issues, such as abortion, marriage, school prayer, and judicial appointments.</arg><arg name="isbn">9780203829417</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Neoconservatives</target></link><space/>want to expand American ideals throughout the world and show a strong support for Israel.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bruce Frohnen, ed.<space/><italics>American Conservatism: An Encyclopedia</italics><space/>(2006) pp. ixxiv</extension><space/><link><target>Paleoconservatives</target></link>, in opposition to multiculturalism, press for restrictions on immigration.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Paleoconservative2"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">American credo: the place of ideas in US politics</arg><arg name="author">Michael Foley</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]</arg><arg name="date">25 October 2007</arg><arg name="quote">Against accusations of being pre-modern or even anti-modern in outlook, paleoconservatives press for restrictions on immigration, a rollback of multicultural programmes, the decentralization of the federal polity, the restoration of controls upon free trade, a greater emphasis upon economic nationalism and isolationism in the conduct of American foreign policy, and a generally ''revanchist'' outlook upon a social order in need of recovering old lines of distinction and in particular the assignment of roles in accordance with traditional categories of gender, ethnicity, and race.</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>18 January 2012</arg><arg name="isbn">9780191528330</arg></template></extension><space/>Most U.S. conservatives prefer Republicans over Democrats, and most factions favor a strong foreign policy and a strong military. The conservative movement of the 1950s attempted to bring together these divergent strands, stressing the need for unity to prevent the spread of &quot;Godless Communism&quot;, which Reagan later labeled an &quot;<link><target>evil empire</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Edward Gottfried,<space/><italics>Conservatism in America: Making Sense of the American Right</italics>, p. 9, &quot;Postwar conservatives set about creating their own synthesis of free-market capitalism, Christian morality, and the global struggle against Communism.&quot; (2009); Gottfried,<space/><italics>Theologies and moral concern</italics><space/>(1995) p. 12</extension><space/>During the Reagan administration, conservatives also supported the so-called &quot;<link><target>Reagan Doctrine</target></link>&quot; under which the U.S., as part of a Cold War strategy, provided military and other support to guerrilla insurgencies that were fighting governments identified as socialist or communist.</paragraph><paragraph>Other modern conservative positions include opposition to<space/><link><target>world government</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>opposition to environmentalism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter J. Jacques; Riley E. Dunlap; Mark Freeman,<space/><italics>The organisation of denial: Conservative think tanks and environmental scepticism</italics>, Environmental Politics. v12 m3 (2008), pp. 34985</extension><space/>On average, American conservatives desire tougher foreign policies than liberals do.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sup.org/books/title/?id=23736'>Peter Hays Gries, ''The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs'' (Stanford, 2014).</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most recently, the<space/><link><target>Tea Party movement</target></link>, founded in 2009, has proven a large outlet for populist American conservative ideas. Their stated goals include rigorous adherence to the U.S. Constitution, lower taxes, and opposition to a growing role for the federal government in health care. Electorally, it was considered a key force in Republicans reclaiming control of the U.S. House of Representatives in 2010.<extension extension_name='ref'>Theda Skocpol and Vanessa Williamson,<space/><italics>The Tea Party and the Remaking of Republican Conservatism</italics><space/>(2012) pp. 4582</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-12030-503544.html'>&quot;Katie Couric interviews Tea Party Leaders&quot;, CBS News, January 25, 2010.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>India</heading><paragraph>In India,<space/><link><target>Bharatiya Janata Party</target></link><space/>(BJP) represents conservative politics nationally.<space/><link><target>Hindutva</target></link><space/>and Cultural Nationalism are two major ideologies of BJP.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Characteristics of conservatism in France, Italy, Russia, UK and US</heading><paragraph>This is a broad Checklist of modern conservatism in five major countries.</paragraph><table><tablerow><tablehead></tablehead><tablehead><template><target>flagicon</target><arg>France</arg></template><space/>France</tablehead><tablehead><template><target>Flagicon</target><arg>Italy</arg></template>Italy</tablehead><tablehead><template><target>flagicon</target><arg>Russia</arg></template><space/>Russia</tablehead><tablecell><template><target>flagicon</target><arg>United Kingdom</arg></template><space/>United Kingdom</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>flagicon</target><arg>United States</arg></template><space/>United States</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Main parties</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Les Rpublicains</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arise the Republic</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Movement for France</target></link>,<space/><link><target>National Front (France)</target><part>Front National</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Forza Italia (2013)</target><part>Forza Italia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lega Nord</target><part>Northern League</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Brothers of Italy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Centre-Right</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Conservatives and Reformists (Italy)</target><part>Conservatives and Reformists</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>United Russia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>LDPR (political party)</target><part>Liberal Democratic Party</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Conservative Party (UK)</target><part>Conservative Party</part></link>,<space/><link><target>UK Independence Party</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Democratic Unionist Party</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ulster Unionist Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Republican Party (United States)</target><part>Republican Party</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Government</tablecell><tablecell>Strong defenders of<space/><link><target>republicanism</target></link>. Opposed to Federalism</tablecell><tablecell>Proponents of<space/><link><target>presidentialism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>federalism</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Strong defenders of historical Russian sphere of influence<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Celebratory of Russia's<space/><link><target>History of Russia</target><part>Tsarist and Communist strong-man rule</part></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Defends<space/><link><target>monarchism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>British unionism</target><part>unionism</part></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Rejects republicanism.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Supports unelected House of Lords chamber.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Defends<space/><link><target>first-past-the-post</target></link><space/>voting system.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Originally opposed to but now accepting of<space/><link><target>Scottish Parliament</target><part>Scottish Devolution</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Welsh Assembly</target><part>Welsh Devolution</part></link>.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>In Favor of<space/><link><target>West Lothian Question</target><part>English Votes for English Laws</part></link><space/>and sympathetic to ideas of English Devolution</tablecell><tablecell>Supports<space/><link><target>federalism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>republicanism</target></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>State control</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Bonapartism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gaullism</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Moderate sized but centralised state</tablecell><tablecell>FI, NL: Small decentralised state.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Brothers of Italy, NCR: Small centralised state</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Statism</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Strong, powerful, centralised state.</tablecell><tablecell>Small centralised state.</tablecell><tablecell>Small, minimal, decentralised state particularly at federal level.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Strongly influenced by libertarianism.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Social views</tablecell><tablecell>Rule of law, traditionalism, authority, liberty, defence of traditional family, public healthcare.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Strongly supportive of French culture,<space/><link><target>wikt:Francophone</target><part>Francophone</part></link>, and against<space/><link><target>Americanisation</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Traditionalism,<space/><link><target>opposition to immigration</target></link>,<space/><link><target>criticism of multiculturalism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>individualism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cult of personality</target></link>, law and order, against abortion, gay marriage, civil unions and euthanasia.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Critics of the Italian constitution and the Italian judiciary</tablecell><tablecell>Rule of law, authority, cult of personality, state unity, public unity, law and order, traditionalism.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Against<space/><link><target>modernism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Western culture</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Hierarchy, rule of law, liberty, freedom, traditionalism,<space/><link><target>Stiff upper lip</target><part>British stoicism</part></link>, against abortion in Northern Ireland.</tablecell><tablecell>Freedom, liberty,<space/><link><target>individualism</target></link>, traditionalism, law and order, gun ownership, defence of traditional family, against euthanasia, abortion, and gay marriage.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Strong supporters of the<space/><link><target>American Constitution</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Separation of powers under the United States Constitution</target><part>separation of powers</part></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Religious views</tablecell><tablecell>Defends<space/><link><target>secularism</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Influenced by<space/><link><target>Catholic social teaching</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Critics of laicism, influenced by the<space/><link><target>Roman catholic church</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Strong adherents to the<space/><link><target>Russian Orthodox Church</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>High Anglicanism</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Presbyterianism</target></link><space/>in Scotland and Northern Ireland.</tablecell><tablecell>The 2012 Republican platform states: &quot;We support the public display of the Ten Commandments as a reflection of our history and of our countrys Judeo-Christian heritage.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>see<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.gop.com/platform/we-the-people/'>2012 Republican NationalPlatform</link></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Economic views</tablecell><tablecell>UMP, DLR and MPF:<space/><link><target>Social market economy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>distributism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>nationalisation</target></link><space/>of major industries, loosely influenced by<space/><link><target>neoliberalism</target></link>, moderate<space/><link><target>welfare economics</target><part>welfare system</part></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>FN: Nationalisation of major industries, protectionism and moderate re-distribution of wealth.</tablecell><tablecell>Neoliberalism, protectionism, low taxation,<space/><link><target>Flat tax</target></link>, opposition to<space/><link><target>wealth taxes</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Mixture of state regulation and market freedoms, nationalisation only of strategic industries, moderate re-distribution of wealth, rejection of<space/><link><target>communism</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Neoliberalism, low taxation, flat tax,<space/><link><target>privatisation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link>, small welfare state but unopposed to<space/><link><target>National Health Service</target><part>nationalised healthcare</part></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Neoliberalism,<space/><link><target>economic liberalism</target></link>, free trade, low taxation<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Opposes government-run healthcare.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>International government</tablecell><tablecell>UMP: Supportive of the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>. Moderately supportive of the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link>.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>FN, DLR and MPF: Sceptical about the United Nations, NATO and the European Union.</tablecell><tablecell>FI, NCR: Supportive of NATO, various factions are moderately supportive or sceptical about the EU.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Nl, Brothers of Italy: Sceptical about the EU and NATO</tablecell><tablecell>Supportive of<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of Independent States</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Eurasian Economic Union</target></link>. Sceptical about the United Nations.</tablecell><tablecell>Supportive of the United Nations, NATO, and<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of Nations</target><part>the Commonwealth</part></link>. Sceptical about the European Union.</tablecell><tablecell>Supportive of NATO.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Critical of United Nations.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Military Issues</tablecell><tablecell>Opposed to Nuclear Disarmament.</tablecell><tablecell>Nuclear disarmament</tablecell><tablecell>Opposed to Nuclear Disarmament.</tablecell><tablecell>Opposed to Nuclear Disarmament.</tablecell><tablecell>Opposed to Nuclear Disarmanent.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>International affairs</tablecell><tablecell>UMP:<space/><link><target>Interventionist</target></link><template><target>dn</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template>.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>FN, MPF and DLR:<space/><link><target>Non-interventionist</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell>Factions are variously interventionist or non-interventionalist.</tablecell><tablecell>Interventionist.</tablecell><tablecell>Conservatives, UUP and DUP: Interventionist.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>UKIP: Non-interventionist.</tablecell><tablecell>Factions are variously interventionist or non-interventionalist.</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Psychology</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Biology and political orientation</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Following the Second World War, psychologists conducted research into the different motives and tendencies that account for ideological differences between left and right. The early studies focused on conservatives, beginning with<space/><link><target>Theodor W. Adorno</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Authoritarian Personality</target></link></italics><space/>(1950) based on the<space/><link><target>F-scale (personality test)</target><part>F-scale</part></link><space/>personality test. This book has been heavily criticized on theoretical and methodological grounds, but some of its findings have been confirmed by further empirical research.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jost, J.J 2003">Jost, J.J, Glaser, J., Kruglanski, A.A., &amp; Sulloway, F.J. (2003). Political conservatism as motivated social cognition.<space/><italics>Psychological Bulletin, 129</italics>(3), 33975.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1973, British psychologist<space/><link><target>Glenn Wilson (psychologist)</target><part>Glenn Wilson</part></link><space/>published an influential book providing evidence that a general factor underlying conservative beliefs is &quot;fear of uncertainty&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wilson, G.D. (Ed.)(1973) The Psychology of Conservatism, London: Academic Press.</extension><space/>A meta-analysis of research literature by Jost, Glaser, Kruglanski, and Sulloway in 2003 found that many factors, such as<space/><link><target>Ambiguity tolerance</target><part>intolerance of ambiguity</part></link><space/>and need for<space/><link><target>Cognitive closure (psychology)</target><part>cognitive closure</part></link>, contribute to the degree of one's political conservatism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jost, J.J 2003"></extension><space/>A study by Kathleen Maclay stated these traits &quot;might be associated with such generally valued characteristics as personal commitment and unwavering loyalty.&quot; The research also suggested that while most people are resistant to change, liberals are more tolerant of it.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://berkeley.edu/news/media/releases/2003/07/22_politics.shtml'>Berkeley.edu</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to psychologist<space/><link><target>Bob Altemeyer</target></link>, individuals who are politically conservative tend to rank high in<space/><link><target>right-wing authoritarianism</target></link><space/>on his RWA scale.<extension extension_name='ref'>Altemeyer, B. (1981). Right-wing authoritarianism. Winnipeg, Canada: University of Manitoba Press.</extension><space/>This finding was echoed by<space/><link><target>Theodor Adorno</target></link>. A study done on Israeli and Palestinian students in Israel found that RWA scores of right-wing party supporters were significantly higher than those of left-wing party supporters.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Rubinstein<space/></arg><arg name="first1">G.<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/0022022196272005<space/></arg><arg name="title">Two Peoples in One Land: A Validation Study of Altemeyer's Right-Wing Authoritarianism Scale in the Palestinian and Jewish Societies in Israel<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="volume">27<space/></arg><arg name="pages">216–30<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2</arg></template></extension><space/>However, a 2005 study by H. Michael Crowson and colleagues suggested a moderate gap between RWA and other conservative positions. &quot;The results indicated that conservatism is not synonymous with RWA.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Crowson, H. Michael, Stephen J. Thoma, and Nita Hestevold. &quot;Is political conservatism synonymous with authoritarianism?.&quot; The Journal of Social Psychology 145.5 (Oct 2005): 571(22). Expanded Academic ASAP. Gale. Remote Access. 20 May 2009<space/><link type='external' href='http://find.galegroup.com/itx/start.do?prodId=EAIM'>Galegroup.com</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Psychologist Felicia Pratto and her colleagues have found evidence to support the idea that a high<space/><link><target>social dominance orientation</target></link><space/>(SDO) is strongly correlated with conservative political views, and opposition to social engineering to promote equality, though Pratto's findings have been highly controversial.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pratto"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Pratto<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Felicia<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Sidanius<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Jim<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Stallworth<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Lisa M.<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Malle<space/></arg><arg name="first4">Bertram F.<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.67.4.741<space/></arg><arg name="title">Social dominance orientation: A personality variable predicting social and political attitudes<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology<space/></arg><arg name="year">1994<space/></arg><arg name="volume">67<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>741–63<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Pratto and her colleagues found that high SDO scores were highly correlated with measures of<space/><link><target>prejudice</target></link>. They were refuted in this claim by<space/><link><target>David J. Schneider</target></link>, who wrote that &quot;correlations between prejudice and political conservative are reduced virtually to zero when controls for SDO are instituted&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>The psychology of stereotyping, David J. Schneider, Guilford Press, 2005 ISBN 978-1-59385-193-4, ISBN 978-1-59385-193-4. p. 275</extension><space/><link><target>Kenneth Minogue</target></link><space/>criticized Pratto's work, saying &quot;It is characteristic of the conservative temperament to value established identities, to praise habit and to respect prejudice, not because it is irrational, but because such things anchor the darting impulses of human beings in solidities of custom which we do not often begin to value until we are already losing them. Radicalism often generates youth movements, while conservatism is a condition found among the mature, who have discovered what it is in life they most value.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>The Social science encyclopedia, Jessica Kuper, Taylor &amp; Francis, 1985 ISBN 978-0-7102-0008-2, ISBN 978-0-7102-0008-2. pp. 15556</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 1996 study on the relationship between racism and conservatism found that the correlation was stronger among more educated individuals, though &quot;anti-Black affect had essentially no relationship with political conservatism at any level of educational or intellectual sophistication&quot;. They also found that the correlation between racism and conservatism could be entirely accounted for by their mutual relationship with social dominance orientation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sidanius96"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.70.3.476<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Sidanius<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Pratto<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>F<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Bobo<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>L<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="title">Racism, conservatism, affirmative action, and intellectual sophistication: A matter of principled conservatism or group dominance?<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>70<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>476–90<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.scholar.harvard.edu/files/bobo/files/1996_racism_conservatism_affirmative_action_and_journal_of_personality_and_social_psychology.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 2008 research report found that conservatives are happier than liberals, and that as income inequality increases, this difference in relative happiness increases, because conservatives (more than liberals) possess an ideological buffer against the negative hedonic effects of<space/><link><target>economic inequality</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Napier<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J. L.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Jost<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>J. T.<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02124.x<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Why Are Conservatives Happier Than Liberals?<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Psychological Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>19<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>6<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>565–572<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>18578846</arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Eccleshall, Robert.<space/><italics>English Conservatism since the Restoration: An Introduction and Anthology</italics>. London: Unwin Hyman, 1990 ISBN 978-0-04-445346-8</listitem><listitem>Hainsworth, Paul.<space/><italics>The extreme right in Western Europe</italics>, Abingdon, OXON: Routledge, 2008 ISBN 0-415-39682-4</listitem><listitem>Osterling, Jorge P.<space/><italics>Democracy in Colombia: Clientelist Politics and Guerrilla Warfare</italics>. New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 1989 ISBN 0887382290, 9780887382291</listitem><listitem>Winthrop, Norman and Lovell, David W. &quot;Varieties of Conservative Theory&quot;. In Winthrop, Norman.<space/><italics>Liberal Democratic Theory and Its Critics</italics>. Beckenham, Kent: Croom Helm Ltd., 1983 ISBN 0-7099-2766-5, 9780709927662</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Blee, Kathleen M., and Sandra McGee Deutsch, eds.<space/><italics>Women of the Right: Comparisons and Interplay Across Borders</italics><space/>(Penn State University Press; 2012) 312 pages; scholarly essays giving a global perspective on women in right-wing politics.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Anthony Daniels (psychiatrist)</target><part>Theodore Dalrymple</part></link>.<space/><italics>Our Culture, What's Left of It: the Mandarins and the masses</italics><space/>/, 2005</listitem><listitem>Blinkhorn, Martin.<space/><italics>Fascists and conservatives : the radical right and the establishment in twentieth-century Europe</italics><space/>/ 1990</listitem><listitem>Crunden, Robert Crunden.<space/><italics>The Superfluous Men: Critics of American Culture, 19001945</italics><space/>1999</listitem><listitem>Fryer., Russell G.<space/><italics>Recent conservative political thought : American perspectives</italics><space/>1979</listitem><listitem><italics>The Conservative Movement</italics><space/>/ Paul E. Gottfried., 1993</listitem><listitem><italics>The British Right : Conservative and right wing politics in Britain</italics><space/>/ Neill Nugent., 1977</listitem><listitem><italics>America alone: the neo-conservatives and the global order</italics><space/>/ Stefan A. Halper., 2004</listitem><listitem><italics>Conservatism</italics><space/>/<space/><link><target>Ted Honderich</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Conservative Mind</italics><space/>/<space/><link><target>Russell Kirk</target></link>., 2001</listitem><listitem><italics>The Politics of Prudence</italics><space/>/ Russell Kirk., 1993</listitem><listitem><italics>The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs</italics><space/>/ Peter Hays Gries, 2014 (Stanford University Press)</listitem><listitem><italics>The conservative press in twentieth-century America</italics><space/>/ Ronald Lora., 1999</listitem><listitem><italics>From the New Deal to the New Right: race and the southern origins of modern conservatism</italics><space/>/ Joseph E. Lowndes., 2008</listitem><listitem><italics>Conservatism</italics><space/>/ Jerry Z. Muller.</listitem><listitem><italics>Right-wing women: from conservatives to extremists around the world</italics><space/>/ P. Bacchetta., 2002</listitem><listitem><italics>Unmaking law: the Conservative campaign to roll back the common law</italics><space/>/ Jay M. Feinman., 2004</listitem><listitem><italics>Radicals or conservatives?: the contemporary American right</italics><space/>/ James McEvoy., 1971</listitem><listitem><italics>Conservatism: Dream and Reality</italics><space/>/<space/><link><target>Robert Nisbet</target></link>., 2001</listitem><listitem><italics>Ought the Neo-Cons be Considered Conservatives?: a philosophical response</italics><space/>/ AQ: Journal of Contemporary Analysis.<space/><link type='external' href='http://eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00003599/'>75(6):3233/40</link>. 2003</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Conservatism</italics><space/>/ Noel O'Sullivan.</listitem><listitem><italics>The new racism : conservatives and the ideology of the tribe</italics><space/>/ Martin Barker., 1982</listitem><listitem><italics>A time for choosing: the rise of modern American conservatism</italics><space/>/ Jonathan M. Schoenwald., 2001</listitem><listitem><italics>The Meaning of Conservatism</italics><space/>/<space/><link><target>Roger Scruton</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Facing fascism: the conservative party and the European dictators, 19351940</italics><space/>/ N. J. Crowson., 1997</listitem><listitem><italics>The End of Politics: triangulation, realignment and the battle for the center ground</italics><space/>/<space/><link><target>Alexander Lee (author)</target><part>Alexander Lee</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Timothy Stanley</target></link>., 2006</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Schneider, ed.<space/><italics>Conservatism in America since 1930: a reader</italics><space/>(2003)</listitem><listitem>Witonski, Peter, ed.<space/><italics>The wisdom of conservatism</italics><space/>(4 vol. Arlington House, 1971) 2396 pages)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Online sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Graphic Guide to Conservatism: a visual primer on the conservative worldview</italics><space/>/ Olivier Ballou.<space/><link type='external' href='http://issuu.com/ggtc/docs/issuu_ggtc_1'></link>. 2011</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/Conservatism-Kieron-OHara.php'>''Conservatism''</link><space/>/ Kieron O'Hara / Reaktion Books, 2011 (Reviewed in<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/Conservatism-Kieron-OHara.php'>The Montreal Review</link></italics>)</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">Carey<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>George</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Ronald<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Hamowy<space/></arg><arg name="editor-link">Ronald Hamowy<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Conservatism<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[SAGE Publications|SAGE]]; [[Cato Institute]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Thousand Oaks, CA<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-4129-6580-4<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">750831024</arg><arg name="lccn"><space/>2008009151<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>93–5<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/></arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Sister project links</target><arg>Conservatism</arg></template><template><target>Conservatism footer</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><template><target>Asia topic</target><arg>Conservatism in</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Europe topic</target><arg>Conservatism in</arg></template><template><target>North America topic</target><arg>Conservatism in</arg></template><template><target>South America topic</target><arg>Conservatism in</arg></template><template><target>Political ideologies</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Conservatism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Political ideologies</target></link><link><target>Category:Social theories</target></link></paragraph></article>