<article title='Biathlon'><paragraph><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>duathlon</arg><arg>biathle</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">June 2009</arg></template><template><target>Infobox sport</target><arg name="name"><space/>Biathlon
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Biathlon Schalke.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>200
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Several biathletes in the shooting area of a competition
</arg><arg name="union"><space/>''International Biathlon Union''
</arg><arg name="nickname">
</arg><arg name="first">
</arg><arg name="registered">
</arg><arg name="clubs">
</arg><arg name="contact">
</arg><arg name="team"><space/>Single competitors or relay teams
</arg><arg name="mgender"><space/>Yes
</arg><arg name="category">
</arg><arg name="equipment"><space/>[[Ski]]s, [[Ski pole#Cross-country and alpine ski poles|Poles]], [[Rifle]]
</arg><arg name="venue">
</arg><arg name="obsolete">
</arg><arg name="olympic"><space/>[[Military patrol at the 1924 Winter Olympics|1924]] ([[Military patrol]])<br /><space/>[[Biathlon at the 1960 Winter Olympics|1960]] (Officially)
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Biathlon</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>winter sport</target></link><space/>that combines<space/><link><target>cross-country skiing (sport)</target><part>cross-country skiing</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>shooting sport</target><part>rifle shooting</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>This sport has its origins in an exercise for<space/><link><target>Norway</target><part>Norwegian</part></link><space/>people, as an alternative training for the<space/><link><target>army</target><part>military</part></link>. Norwegian skiing regiments organized military skiing contests in the 18th century, divided in four classes: shooting at mark while skiing at top speed, downhill race among trees, downhill race on big hills without falling, and a long race on flat ground while carrying rifle and military pack. In modern terminology these military contests included downhill, slalom, biathlon and cross-country skiing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bergsland">Bergsland, Einar (1946):<space/><italics>P ski.</italics><space/>Oslo: Aschehoug.</extension><space/>One of the world's first known ski clubs, the Trysil Rifle and Ski Club, was formed in Norway in 1861 to promote national defense at the local level. 20th century variants include<space/><template><target>lang-no</target><arg>Forsvarsrennet</arg></template><space/>(the military contest) - a 17 km cross-country race with shooting, and the military cross-country race at 30 km including marksmanship. Modern biathlon is a civilian variant of the old military combined exercise.<extension extension_name='ref'>B, Olav:<space/><italics>Skiing throughout history</italics>, translated by W. Edson Richmond. Oslo: Samlaget, 1993.</extension><space/>In Norway, biathlon was until 1984 a branch of<space/><italics>Det frivillige Skyttervesen</italics>, an organization set up by the government to promote civilian marksmanship in support of national defense. In Norwegian biathlon is called<space/><italics>skiskyting</italics><space/>(literally<space/><italics>ski shooting</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Idrettsleksikon"><italics>Kunnskapsforlagets idrettsleksikon</italics><space/>(Encyclopedia of Sports), Oslo: Kunnskapsforlaget, 1990</extension><space/>In Norway there are still separate contests in<space/><italics>skifeltskyting</italics>, a cross-country race at 12 km with large-caliber rifle shooting at various targets with unknown range.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://snl.no/skifeltskyting</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Called<space/><link><target>military patrol</target></link>, the combination of skiing and shooting was contested at the<space/><link><target>Winter Olympic Games</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Military patrol at the 1924 Winter Olympics</target><part>1924</part></link>, and then<space/><link><target>Demonstration sport</target><part>demonstrated</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Military patrol at the 1928 Winter Olympics</target><part>1928</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Military patrol at the 1936 Winter Olympics</target><part>1936</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Military patrol at the 1948 Winter Olympics</target><part>1948</part></link>, but did not regain Olympic recognition then, as the small number of competing countries disagreed on the rules. During the mid-1950s, however, biathlon was introduced into the Soviet and Swedish winter sport circuits and was widely enjoyed by the public. This newfound popularity aided the effort of having biathlon gain entry into the Winter Olympics.</paragraph><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>Biathlon World Championship</target></link><space/>was held in 1958 in<space/><link><target>Austria</target></link>, and in 1960 the sport was finally included in the<space/><link><target>1960 Winter Olympics</target><part>Olympic Games</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Idrettsleksikon"></extension><space/>At<space/><link><target>1992 Winter Olympics</target><part>Albertville</part></link><space/>in 1992, women were first allowed in Olympic biathlon.</paragraph><paragraph>The competitions from 1958 to 1965 used high-power<space/><link><target>centerfire</target></link><space/><link><target>cartridge (firearms)</target><part>cartridges</part></link>, such as the<space/><link><target>.30-06&amp;nbsp;Springfield</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>7.62x51mm&amp;nbsp;NATO</target></link>, before the<space/><link><target>.22&amp;nbsp;Long Rifle</target></link><space/><link><target>Rimfire ammunition</target><part>rimfire</part></link><space/>cartridge was standardized in 1978. The ammunition was carried in a belt worn around the competitor's waist. The sole event was the men's<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>individual, encompassing four separate ranges and firing distances of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>m</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>m</arg></template>, and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>250</arg><arg>m</arg></template>. The target distance was reduced to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>with the addition of the relay in 1966. The shooting range was further reduced to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>in 1978 with the mechanical targets making their debut at the<space/><link><target>1980&amp;nbsp;Winter Olympics</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Lake Placid, New York</target><part>Lake Placid</part></link>.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Governing body</heading><paragraph>In 1948, the<space/><italics>Union Internationale de Pentathlon Moderne et Biathlon</italics>&amp;nbsp;(UIPMB) was founded, to standardise the rules for biathlon and<space/><link><target>modern pentathlon</target></link>. In 1993, the biathlon branch of the UIPMB created the<space/><link><target>International Biathlon Union</target></link>&amp;nbsp;(IBU), which officially separated from the UIPMB in 1998.</paragraph><paragraph>Presidents of the UIPMB/IBU:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>19471949:<space/><link><target>Tom Wiborn</target></link><space/>(Sweden)</listitem><listitem>19491960:<space/><link><target>Gustaf Dyrssen</target></link><space/>(Sweden)</listitem><listitem>19601988:<space/><link><target>Sven Thofelt</target></link>, (Sweden)</listitem><listitem>19881992:<space/><link><target>Igor Novikov (pentathlete)</target><part>Igor Novikov</part></link><space/>(<link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>USSR</part></link>/Russia)</listitem><listitem>Since&amp;nbsp;1992:<space/><link><target>Anders Besseberg</target></link><space/>(Norway)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Championships</heading><paragraph>The following articles list mr international biathlon events and medalists. Contrary to the Olympics and World Championships (BWCH), the World Cup (BWC) is an entire winter season of (mostly) weekly races, where the medalists are those with the highest sums of World Cup points at the end of the season.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Biathlon at the Winter Olympics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biathlon World Championships</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biathlon World Cup</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biathlon Junior World Championships</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Rules and equipment</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="align"><space/>right
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>300
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>Sylvie_Becaert_-_22-01-2010_-_Shooting.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>Prone position: Sylvie Becaert, Antholz 2010.
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Biathlon-Weltcup 2006 Antholz 1.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>Standing position: Raphaël Poirée (left) and Ole Einar Bjørndalen, Antholz 2006.
<space/></arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>The complete rules of biathlon are given in the official IBU rule books.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www6.biathlonworld.com/en/downloads.html'>IBU rule books</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Basic concepts</heading><paragraph>A biathlon competition consists of a race in which contestants ski around a cross-country trail system, and where the total distance is broken up by either two or four shooting rounds, half in prone position, the other half standing. Depending on the shooting performance, extra distance or time is added to the contestant's total running distance/time. The contestant with the shortest total time wins.</paragraph><paragraph>For each shooting round, the biathlete must hit five targets; the skier receives a penalty for each missed target, which varies according to the competition rules, as follows:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>IBU Congress
<space/></arg><arg name="first">
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>IBU Event and Competition Rules
<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Rules adopted by the 2012 10th Regular IBU Congress
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>International Biathlon Union
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2012
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www3.biathlonworld.com/en/downloads.html
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2014-11-05<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Skiing around a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg name="adj"><space/>on</arg></template><space/>penalty looptypically taking 2030 seconds for elite biathletes to complete, depending on weather and snow conditions.</listitem><listitem>Adding one minute to the skier's total time.</listitem><listitem>Use of an extra cartridge (placed at the shooting range) to hit the target; only three such extras are available for each round, and a penalty loop must be made for each target left standing.</listitem></list><paragraph>In order to keep track of the contestants' progress and relative standing throughout a race,<space/><link><target>split time</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(intermediate times) are taken at several points along the skiing track and upon finishing each shooting round. The large display screens commonly set up at biathlon arenas, as well as the information graphics shown as part of the TV picture, will typically list the split time of the fastest contestant at each intermediate point and the times and time differences to the closest runners-up.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Skiing details</heading><paragraph>All cross-country skiing techniques are permitted in biathlon, which means that the<space/><link><target>Cross-country skiing#Skate skiing</target><part>free technique</part></link><space/>is usually the preferred one, being the fastest. No equipment other than skis and ski poles may be used to move along the track. Minimum ski length is the height of the skier less<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>4</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg></template>. The rifle has to be carried by the skier during the race at all times.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Shooting details</heading><paragraph>The biathlete carries a small bore rifle, which weighs at least<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3.5</arg><arg>kg</arg><arg>lb</arg></template>, excluding ammunition and magazines. The rifles use<space/><link><target>.22 Long Rifle</target><part>.22 LR</part></link><space/>ammunition and are<space/><link><target>bolt action</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Bolt action#Other designs</target><part>Fortner</part></link><space/>(straight-pull bolt) action.</paragraph><paragraph>The target range shooting distance is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg></template>. There are five circular targets to be hit in each shooting round. When shooting in the<space/><link><target>prone position</target></link><space/>the target diameter is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>45</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg></template>; when shooting in the standing position the target diameter is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>115</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg></template>. On all modern biathlon ranges, the targets are self-indicating, in that they flip from black to white when hit, giving the biathlete as well as the spectators instant visual feedback for each shot fired.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Competition format</heading><heading level='3'>Individual</heading><paragraph>The<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>individual race (<template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>for women) is the oldest biathlon event; the distance is skied over five laps. The biathlete shoots four times at any shooting lane,<extension extension_name='ref'>Even in English-speaking countries such as Canada and the United States each country may use different terms for the same thing in biathlon. For example: Stage (USA) vs. Bout (Canada), Shooting Point (USA) vs. Shooting Lane (Canada)</extension><space/>in the order of prone, standing, prone, standing, totaling 20 targets. For each missed target a fixed penalty time, usually one minute, is added to the skiing time of the biathlete. Competitors' starts are staggered, normally by 30 seconds.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sprint</heading><paragraph>The sprint is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for men and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7.5</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for women; the distance is skied over three laps. The biathlete shoots twice at any shooting lane, once prone and once standing, for a total of 10 shots. For each miss, a penalty loop of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>must be skied before the race can be continued. As in the individual competition, the biathletes start in intervals.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pursuit</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Biathlon Oberhof 2013-039.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Olympic gold medalists Olga Zaitseva and Andrea Henkel at the World Cup pursuit race in Oberhof, 2013.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Pursuit racing</arg></template>In a pursuit, biathletes' starts are separated by their time differences from a previous race,<extension extension_name='ref'>To be precise; the pursuit competition start intervals are determined by<space/><link><target>Rounding#Rounding to integer</target><part>common rounding</part></link><space/>to the nearest whole second of the biathletes' time differences from the previous race<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template><space/>the amount of time each biathlete lagged after the winner to the finish line.</extension><space/>most commonly a sprint. The contestant crossing the finish line first is the winner. The distance is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12.5</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for men and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for women, skied over five laps; there are four shooting bouts (two prone, two standing, in that order), and each miss means a penalty loop of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg></template>. To prevent awkward and/or dangerous crowding of the skiing loops, and overcapacity at the shooting range, World Cup Pursuits are held with only the 60 top ranking biathletes after the preceding race. The biathletes shoot on a first-come, first-served basis at the lane corresponding to the position they arrived for all shooting bouts.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mass start</heading><paragraph>In the mass start, all biathletes start at the same time and the first across the finish line wins. In this<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for men or<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12.5</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>for women competition, the distance is skied over five laps; there are four bouts of shooting (two prone, two standing, in that order) with the first shooting bout being at the lane corresponding to the competitor's bib number (Bib #10 shoots at lane #10 regardless of position in race), with the rest of the shooting bouts being on a first-come, first-served basis (If a competitor arrives at the lane in fifth place, they shoot at lane 5). As in sprint and pursuit, competitors must ski one<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>penalty loop for each miss. Here again, to avoid unwanted congestion, World Cup Mass starts are held with only the 30 top ranking athletes on the start line (half that of the Pursuit as here all contestants start simultaneously).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Relay</heading><paragraph>The relay teams consist of four biathletes, who each ski<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7.5</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>(men) or<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg></template><space/>(women), each leg skied over three laps, with two shooting rounds; one prone, one standing. For every round of five targets there are eight bullets available, though the last three can only be single-loaded manually one at a time from spare round holders or bullets deposited by the competitor into trays or onto the mat at the firing line. If after eight bullets there are still misses, one 150&amp;nbsp;m (490&amp;nbsp;ft) penalty loop must be taken for each missed target remaining. The first-leg participants start all at the same time, and as in cross-country skiing relays, every athlete of a team must touch the team's next-leg participant to perform a valid changeover. On the first shooting stage of the first leg, the participant must shoot in the lane corresponding to their bib number (Bib #10 shoots at lane #10 regardless of position in race), then for the remainder of the relay, the relay team shoots on a first-come, first-served basis (arrive at the range in fifth place, shoot at lane 5).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mixed relay</heading><paragraph>The most recent addition to the number of biathlon competition variants, the mixed relay is similar to the ordinary relay but the teams are composed of two women and two men. Legs 1 and 2 are done by the women, legs 3 and 4 by the men. The women's legs are<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>and men's legs are<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7.5</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>as in ordinary relay competitions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Team (obsolete)</heading><paragraph>A team consists of four biathletes, but unlike the relay competition, all team members start at the same time. Two athletes must shoot in the prone shooting round, the other two in the standing round. In case of a miss, the two non-shooting biathletes must ski a penalty loop of 150&amp;nbsp;m (490&amp;nbsp;ft). The skiers must enter the shooting area together, and must also finish within 15 seconds of each other; otherwise a time penalty of one minute is added to the total time. Since 2004, this race format has been obsolete at the World Cup level.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Broadcasting</heading><paragraph>Biathlon events are broadcast most regularly where the sport enjoys its greatest popularity, namely Germany (<link><target>Das Erste</target><part>ARD</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ZDF</target></link>), Austria (<link><target>ORF (broadcaster)</target><part>ORF</part></link>), Norway (<link><target>Norsk Rikskringkasting</target><part>NRK</part></link>), Finland (<link><target>Yleisradio</target><part>YLE</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Estonia</target></link><space/>(<link><target>ETV (Estonia)</target><part>ETV</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Latvia</target></link><space/>(<link><target>LTV 7</target><part>LTV</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Lithuania</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Lithuanian_National_Radio_and_Television</target><part>LRT</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Croatia</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Hrvatska radiotelevizija</target><part>HRT</part></link>), Poland (<link><target>Telewizja Polska</target><part>TVP</part></link>), Sweden (<link><target>Sveriges Television</target><part>SVT</part></link>), Russia (<link><target>Russia-2</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Channel One Russia</target><part>Channel One</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Belarus</target></link><space/>(<link><target>TVR (Belarus)</target><part>TVR</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Slovenia</target></link><space/>(<link><target>RTV Slovenia</target><part>RTV</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Bosnia and Herzegovina</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Radio-televizija Bosne i Hercegovine</target><part>BHRT</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Bulgaria</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Bulgarian National Television</target><part>BNT</part></link>), and<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Korean Broadcasting System</target><part>KBS</part></link>); it is broadcast on European-wide<space/><link><target>Eurosport</target></link>, which also broadcasts to the Asia-Pacific region. World Cup races are streamed (without commentary) via the IBU website.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlonworld.com'>Startseite - www.biathlonworld.com</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The broadcast distribution being one indicator, the constellation of a sport's main<space/><link><target>sponsor (commercial)</target><part>sponsors</part></link><space/>usually gives a similar, and correlated, indication of popularity: for biathlon, these are the Germany-based companies<space/><link><target>E.ON</target><part>E.ON Ruhrgas</part></link><space/>(energy),<space/><link><target>Krombacher</target></link><space/>(beer), and<space/><link><target>Viessmann</target></link><space/>(boilers and other heating systems).<link><target>Image:Jeremy Teela 2002 Olympics.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>United States biathlete<space/><link><target>Jeremy Teela</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>2002 Winter Olympics</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biathlon records and statistics</heading><paragraph>Biathlon records, rules, news, videos, and statistics for many years back are available at the IBU (International Biathlon Union) web site Biathlonworld.Com</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biathlon variants</heading><paragraph>Two common variations on traditional winter biathlon are<space/><link><target>summer biathlon</target></link>, where skiing is replaced by a cross-country running or roller-skiing, and<space/><link><target>archery</target></link><space/>biathlon (<link><target>ski archery</target></link>), where the rifle is replaced by a<space/><link><target>recurve bow</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>There have also been summer competitions in<space/><link><target>roller skiing</target><part>roller-ski</part></link><space/>biathlon,<space/><link><target>mountain biking</target><part>mountain bike</part></link><space/>biathlon,<space/><link><target>orienteering</target></link><space/>biathlon, and<space/><link><target>run archery</target></link>. Primitive Biathlon uses<space/><link><target>snowshoes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Muzzleloading</target><part>muzzleloaders</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Boy Scouts of America</target></link><space/>offers a Bikeathlon variant at their<space/><link><target>National Scout jamboree (Boy Scouts of America)</target><part>national Scout jamboree</part></link><space/>that mixes<space/><link><target>BMX</target></link><space/>biking with<space/><link><target>air rifle</target></link><space/>shooting at biathlon type targets.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.crosman.com/site/crosman_u_bikathalon'>:: Crosman: Summer House - Bikathalon::</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Cadets Canada</target></link><space/>also offers biathlon to cadets across Canada, with three stages: zones, provincial, and national. Zone competitions are occasionally, due to lack of snow in some southern areas, held as summer biathlon. A .22LR caliber rifle is used at all levels. Races are shorter than world class events.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cadets.net/biathlon/'>National Cadet Biathlon Championship - 2007 - Championnat national de biathlon des cadets</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>World Police and Fire Games</target></link><space/>offer a summer variant which combines cross-country running with service pistol shooting.</paragraph><paragraph>The Russian Military runs<space/><link><target>tank biathlon</target></link><space/>competitions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Biathlon World Cup</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biathlon World Championships</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Olympic medalists in biathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Paralympic biathlon</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Biathlon's two sports disciplines:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cross-country skiing (sport)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Shooting sports#Rifle</target><part>Rifle shooting sports</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Other multi-discipline sports (otherwise unrelated to biathlon):</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Duathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nordic Combined</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Triathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pentathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Modern pentathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Heptathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Decathlon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chess boxing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Omnium</target></link><space/>(track cycling)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Biathlon World Cup seasons</target></template><template><target>Main world cups</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Biathlon</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlonworld.com'>Biathlonworld.Com</link>&amp;nbsp; A cooperation between IBU and<space/><link><target>European Broadcasting Union</target><part>EBU</part></link>; with race results/statistics, TV schedules, live competition results, and so on.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlon.by'>Belarusian Biathlon Union</link><space/><template><target>be icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rbu-biathlon.ru/'>Russian Biathlon Union</link><space/><template><target>ru icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://biathlonrus.com/eng/'>Russian Biathlon Union</link><space/><template><target>en icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathloncanada.ca/'>Biathlon Canada</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.usbiathlon.com'>U.S. Biathlon Association</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.skiarchery.com/'>U.S. Archery Biathlon</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.usbiathlon.org/history.html'>History of Biathlon</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlon-aufschalke.de/'>Veltins Biathlon World Team Challenge</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ww2.olntv.com/tvlistings/test-DB.asp?so=06%20BIATHLON'>Biathlon on OLN TV</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.xczone.tv'>Biathlon on DVD</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlon-russia.ru/'>Biathlon Russia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlon.com.ua'>Biathlon Ukraine</link><space/><template><target>ru icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlon.com.ua/?lang=eng'>Biathlon Ukraine</link><space/><template><target>en icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biathlonfrance.com'>BiathlonFrance.com</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ws-news.ru/history_biathlon.html'>Biathlon history</link><space/><template><target>ru icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.skiskyting.com'>Popular Norwegian site</link><space/><template><target>no icon</target></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Winter Olympic sports</target></template><template><target>Skiing</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Biathlon</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Multisports</target></link><link><target>Category:Winter Olympic sports</target></link><link><target>Category:Winter sports</target></link><link><target>Category:Cross-country skiing</target></link><link><target>Category:Nordic skiing</target></link><link><target>Category:Racing</target></link><link><target>Category:Rifle shooting sports</target></link><link><target>Category:Military sports</target></link></paragraph></article>