<article title='David_Ricardo'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox economist</target><arg name="school_tradition"><space/>[[Classical economics]]
<space/></arg><arg name="color"><space/>blue
 
<space/></arg><arg name="image"><space/>Portrait of David Ricardo by Thomas Phillips.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>240px
<space/></arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Portrait of David Ricardo by [[Thomas Phillips]], circa 1821. This painting shows Ricardo, aged 49, just two years before his death.
 
<space/></arg><arg name="name"><space/>David Ricardo
<space/></arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{Birth date|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[London]], England
<space/></arg><arg name="lived"><space/>[[Malta]]
<space/></arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{Death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Gloucestershire]], England
<space/></arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>British
<space/></arg><arg name="ethnicity"><space/>Jewish
<space/></arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Christianity]]
<space/></arg><arg name="field">
<space/></arg><arg name="influences"><space/>[[Adam Smith|Smith]]{{·}} [[Jeremy Bentham|Bentham]]
<space/></arg><arg name="influenced"><space/>[[Ricardian socialism|Ricardian Socialists]]{{·}} [[Henry George|George]]{{·}} [[John Stuart Mill]]{{·}} [[Piero Sraffa|Sraffa]]{{·}}[[Knut Wicksell|Wicksell]]{{·}}[[Robert J. Barro|Barro]]{{·}} [[John Ramsay McCulloch]]{{·}}[[Karl Marx]]{{·}} [[Franz Oppenheimer]]
<space/></arg><arg name="contributions"><space/>[[Ricardian equivalence]], [[labour theory of value]], [[comparative advantage]], [[Diminishing returns|law of diminishing returns]], [[Economic rent]]<ref>Miller, Roger LeRoy. ''Economics Today''. Fifteenth Edition. Boston, MA: Pearson Education. page 559</ref>
</arg></template><bold>David Ricardo</bold><space/>(18 April 1772 11 September 1823) was an English<space/><link><target>political economy</target><part>political economist</part></link>. He was one of the most influential of the<space/><link><target>classical economics</target><part>classical economists</part></link>, along with<space/><link><target>Thomas Malthus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Adam Smith</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>James Mill</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sowell, Thomas (2006).<space/><italics>On classical economics</italics>. New Haven, CT:<space/><link><target>Yale University Press</target></link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.policonomics.com/david-ricardo/</extension><space/>Perhaps his most important legacy is his theory of<space/><link><target>comparative advantage</target></link>, which suggests that a nation should concentrate its resources solely in industries where it is<space/><italics>most</italics><space/>internationally competitive while trading with other countries to obtain products either never produced nationally or no longer produced nationally as a result of industry specialisation. In essence, Ricardo promoted the idea of extreme industry specialization by nations, to the point of dismantling internationally competitive and otherwise profitable industries. In this world view Ricardo took as a given the existence of an industry policy aimed at promoting and/or subsidising some national industries to the detriment of others. For Ricardo central planning was a given. Ricardo's theory of comparative advantage has been challenged by, among others,<space/><link><target>Joan Robinson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Piero Sraffa</target></link>, but remains the cornerstone of the argument in favour of international free trade. Comparative advantage paved the way for the promotion of globalization via increased international trade, which is the guiding theme in the policies promoted by the<space/><link><target>OECD</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>World Trade Organization</target></link>, where it is assumed that international trade automatically leads to increased economic prosperity. The results of the implementation of this type of policy agenda are<space/><link><target>Free trade debate</target><part>debated</part></link><space/>and increasingly<space/><link type='external' href='http://economyincrisis.org/content/ten-problems-free-trade'>controversial</link>. That said, the assumption that increased levels of international trade is economically beneficial is generally unchallenged in mainstream economics. Ricardo began his professional life as a financial market broker and financial market<space/><link><target>speculation</target><part>speculator</part></link>. As a result he amassed a considerable personal fortune, with his largest windfall coming as a direct result of the carefully planned manipulation of British financial markets which he undertook during the Battle of Waterloo in 1814. Immediately following this questionable financial coup he retired. He was 41 years old. In February 1819 he entered British<space/><link><target>Parliament of the United Kingdom</target><part>Parliament</part></link><space/>following his purchase of a seat in August 1818. He held the seat until his death on September 11, 1823. He was 51 years old.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal life</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template>Born in London, England, Ricardo was the third of 17 children of a<space/><link><target>Sephardi Jews</target><part>Sephardic Jewish</part></link><space/>family of<space/><link><target>Portuguese people</target><part>Portuguese</part></link><space/>origin who had recently relocated from the<space/><link><target>Dutch Republic</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heertje"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Dutch and Portuguese-Jewish background of David Ricardo</arg><arg name="first">Arnold</arg><arg name="last">Heertje</arg><arg name="journal">European Journal of the History of Economic Thought</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="volume">11</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">281–294</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/0967256042000209288</arg></template></extension><space/>His father, Abraham Ricardo, was a successful<space/><link><target>stockbroker</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heertje"></extension><space/>He began working with his father at the age of 14. At age 21, Ricardo eloped with a<space/><link><target>Religious Society of Friends</target><part>Quaker</part></link>, Priscilla Anne Wilkinson, and, against his father's wishes, converted to Christianity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Francisco Solano Constancio, Paul Henri Alcide Fonteyraud. 1847.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/%C5%92uvres_compl%C3%A8tes_de_David_Ricardo/Notice'>uvres compltes de David Ricardo</link></italics>, Guillaumin, (pp. v-xlviii):<space/><italics>A part sa conversion au Christianisme et son mariage avec une femme qu'il eut l'audace grande d'aimer malgr les ordres de son pre</italics></extension><space/>This religious difference resulted in estrangement from his family, and he was led to adopt a position of independence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ricardo, David. 1919.<space/><italics>Principles of Political Economy and Taxation</italics>. G. Bell, p. LIX: &quot;by reason of a religious difference with his father, to adopt a position of independence at a time when he should have been undergoing that academic training&quot;</extension><space/>His father disowned him and his mother apparently never spoke to him again.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sraffa"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="author">Sraffa, Piero, David Ricardo<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo: Volume 10, Biographical Miscellany<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, UK<space/></arg><arg name="year">1955<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>434<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-06075-3<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Following his estrangement from his father he started a successful business as a broker with the support of Lubbocks and Forster, an eminent banking house. Although already successful as a broker, he made the bulk of his fortune as a result of speculation on the outcome of the<space/><link><target>Battle of Waterloo</target></link>, using methods which today would result in prosecution for<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.securitiestechnologymonitor.com/blogs/eliminating-stock-market-manipulation-30324-1.html'>insider trading and market manipulation</link>. Prior to the battle, Ricardo<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.economist.com/blogs/schumpeter/2011/01/economists_and_conflicts_interest'>posted an observer</link><space/>to convey early results of the outcome, he then deliberately created the mistaken impression the French had won by initially openly selling British securities. A market panic ensued. Following this panic he moved to buy British securities at a steep discount. The Sunday Times reported in Ricardos obituary, published on 14 September 1823, that during the Battle of Waterloo Ricardo &quot;netted upwards of a million sterling&quot;, a huge sum at the time. Following this trading coup, he retired. He purchased<space/><link><target>Gatcombe Park</target></link>, an estate in<space/><link><target>Gloucestershire</target></link>, now owned by Princess Anne, the Princess Royal. He was appointed<space/><link><target>High Sheriff of Gloucestershire</target></link><space/>for 181819.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>LondonGazette</target><arg name="issue">17326</arg><arg name="startpage">188</arg><arg name="date">24 January 1818</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some years into retirement Ricardo became keen to enter Parliament and in August 1818 he secured Lord Portarlingtons borough for 4,000, as part of the terms of a loan of 25,000. As a result, Ricardo entered the<space/><link><target>Parliament of the United Kingdom</target><part>House of Commons</part></link>, representing<space/><link><target>Portarlington (UK Parliament constituency)</target><part>Portarlington</part></link>, an Irish<space/><link><target>rotten borough</target></link>. He was 47 years of age. He held the seat until his death four years later.</paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo was a close friend of<space/><link><target>James Mill</target></link>. Other notable friends included<space/><link><target>Jeremy Bentham</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thomas Malthus</target></link>, with whom Ricardo had a considerable debate (in correspondence) over such things as the role of landowners in a society. He also was a member of Malthus'<space/><link><target>Political Economy Club</target></link>, and a member of the King of Clubs. He was one of the original members of<space/><link><target>The Geological Society</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sraffa"></extension><space/>His sister was author<space/><link><target>Sarah Ricardo-Porter</target></link><space/>(e.g.,<space/><italics>Conversations in Arithmetic</italics>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Death and legacy</heading><paragraph>Ten years after retiring and four years after entering Parliament Ricardo died from an infection of the middle ear that spread into the brain and induced<space/><link><target>septicaemia</target></link>. He was 51.</paragraph><paragraph>He had eight children, including three sons, of whom<space/><link><target>Osman Ricardo</target></link><space/>(17951881; MP for<space/><link><target>Worcester (UK Parliament constituency)</target><part>Worcester</part></link><space/>18471865) and another<space/><link><target>David Ricardo (the younger)</target><part>David Ricardo</part></link><space/>(18031864, MP for<space/><link><target>Stroud (UK Parliament constituency)</target><part>Stroud</part></link><space/>18321833), became Members of Parliament, while the third, Mortimer Ricardo, served as an officer in the<space/><link><target>Life Guards (British Army)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link><space/>and was a<space/><link><target>deputy lieutenant</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Oxfordshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.histparl.ac.uk/volume/1820-1832/member/ricardo-david-1772-1823</arg><arg name="title"><space/>RICARDO, David (1772–1823), of Gatcombe Park, Minchinhampton, Glos. and 56 Upper Brook Street, Grosvenor Square, Mdx.</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>History of Parliament Online</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>18 September 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo is buried in an ornate grave in the churchyard of<space/><link><target>Nicholas of Myra</target><part>Saint Nicholas</part></link><space/>in Hardenhuish, now a suburb of<space/><link><target>Chippenham</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wiltshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page</arg><arg name="title">David Ricardo – Find A Grave</arg><arg name="publisher">''findagrave.com''</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 December 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>The inscription on his grave reads: &quot;A Jew, born in Holland, he was one of the first free traders and a famous Radical in his day.&quot; At the time of his death his fortune was estimated at about 600,000.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ideas</heading><paragraph>Ricardo became interested in economics after reading<space/><link><target>Adam Smith</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Wealth of Nations</target></link></italics><space/>in 1799. He wrote his first economics article at age 37. Ricardo's idea became accepted in England and have become orthodox economic ideas in the modern western world where the government is seen as having a determining role in economic development.</paragraph><paragraph>He was also an<space/><link><target>abolitionism</target><part>abolitionist</part></link>, speaking at a meeting of the Court of the<space/><link><target>East India Company</target></link><space/>in March 1823, where he said he regarded<space/><link><target>slavery</target></link><space/>as stain on the character of the nation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">King</arg><arg name="first1">John</arg><arg name="title">David Ricardo</arg><arg name="date">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Palgrave Macmillan</arg><arg name="page">48</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>His sister, Hanna, had married David Samuda who owned a substantial number of slaves in<space/><link><target>Jamaica</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Okker</arg><arg name="first1">Rudolph</arg><arg name="title">Re: Samuda</arg><arg name="url">http://genforum.genealogy.com/englandcountry/messages/155286.html</arg><arg name="website">Gen Forum</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 September 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Comparative advantage</heading><paragraph>Between 1500 and 1750 most economists advocated<space/><link><target>Mercantilism</target></link><space/>which promoted the idea of international trade for the purpose of gaining bullion by running a trade surplus with other countries. Ricardo challenged the idea that the purpose of trade was merely to accumulate gold or silver. With &quot;comparative advantage&quot; Ricardo argued in favour of industry specialisation and<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link>. He attempted to prove, using simple mathematics, that industry specialization combined with free international trade always produces positive results. This theory expanded on the concept of<space/><link><target>absolute advantage</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo argued that there is mutual national benefit from trade even if one country is more competitive in every area than its trading counterpart and that a nation should concentrate resources only on industries where it had a comparative advantage,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">The Trade Question<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Roberts<space/></arg><arg name="first">Paul Craig<space/></arg><arg name="periodical">Washington Times<space/></arg><arg name="publication-date">2003-08-28<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>that is in those industries in which it has the greatest competitive edge. Ricardo suggested that national industries which were, in fact, profitable and internationally competitive should be jettisoned in favour of the most competitive industries. Ricardo's theory of<space/><link><target>comparative advantage</target></link><space/>assumes the existence of an industry and trade policy at a national level. It does not presume that business decisions are or should be made independently by entrepreneurs on the basis of viability or profit.</paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo attempted to prove, using a simple numerical example, that international trade is always beneficial.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ricardo, David (1817) On the Principles of Political Economy and Taxation. Piero Sraffa (Ed.) Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Volume I, Cambridge University Press, 1951, p.135.</extension><space/><link><target>Paul Samuelson</target></link><space/>called the numbers used in Ricardo's numerical example dealing with trade between England and Portugal the &quot;four magic numbers&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Samuelson, Paul A. (1972), &quot;The Way of an Economist.&quot; Reprinted in<space/><italics>The Collected Papers of Paul A. Samuelson</italics>. Ed. R. C. Merton. Cambridge: Cambridge MIT Press. p. 378.</extension><space/>&quot;In spite of the fact that the Portuguese could produce both cloth and wine with less amount of labor, Ricardo suggested that<space/><italics>theoretically</italics><space/>both countries benefit from trade with each other.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>As<space/><link><target>Joan Robinson</target></link><space/>subsequently pointed out in reality following an opening of free trade with England, Portugal endured centuries of economic underdevelopment: &quot;the imposition of free trade on Portugal killed off a promising textile industry and left her with a slow-growing export market for wine, while for England, exports of cotton cloth led to accumulation, mechanisation and the whole spiralling growth of the industrial revolution&quot;. Robinson argued that Ricardo's example required that economies were in static equilibrium positions with full employment and that there could not be a trade deficit or a trade surplus. These conditions, she wrote, were not relevant to the real world. She also argued that Ricardo's theory did not take into account that some countries may be at different levels of development and that this raised the prospect of 'unequal exchange' which might hamper a country's development, as we saw in the case of Portugal.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joan Robinson 'Aspects of Development and Underdevelopment' 1978<template><target>full</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Protectionism</heading><paragraph>Like Adam Smith, Ricardo was an opponent of<space/><link><target>protectionism</target></link><space/>for national economies, especially for agriculture. He believed that the British &quot;<link><target>Corn Laws</target></link>&quot;tariffs on agricultural productsensured that less-productive domestic land would be harvested and rents would be driven up<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Case</arg><arg>Fair</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">812, 813</arg></template>. Thus, profits would be directed toward landlords and away from the emerging industrial capitalists. Since Ricardo believed landlords tended to squander their wealth on luxuries, rather than invest, he believed that the Corn Laws were leading to the stagnation of the British economy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Letter of Mill http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=213&amp;chapter=61555&amp;layout=html&amp;Itemid=27</extension><space/>In 1846, his nephew<space/><link><target>John Ricardo</target><part>John Lewis Ricardo</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Member of Parliament</target><part>MP</part></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Stoke-upon-Trent (UK Parliament constituency)</target><part>Stoke-on-Trent</part></link>, advocated<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link><space/>and the repeal of the<space/><link><target>Corn Laws</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern empirical analysis of the Corn Laws yield mixed results.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/0014-4983(90)90007-L</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The impact of the Corn Laws just prior to repeal</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Explorations in Economic History</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>27</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>123</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990</arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Williamson<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J. G.<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Parliament repealed the Corn Laws in 1846.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Value theory</heading><paragraph>Ricardo's most famous work is his<space/><italics><link><target>Principles of Political Economy and Taxation</target></link></italics><space/>(1817). Ricardo opens the first chapter with a statement of the<space/><link><target>labor theory of value</target></link>. His labour theory of value required several assumptions:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>both sectors have the same wage rate and the same profit rate;</listitem><listitem>the capital employed in production is made up of wages only;</listitem><listitem>the period of production has the same length for both goods.</listitem></list><paragraph>Ricardo himself realized that the second and third assumptions were quite unrealistic and hence admitted two exceptions to his labour theory of value:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>production periods may differ;</listitem><listitem>the two production processes may employ instruments and equipment as capital and not just wages, and in very different proportions.</listitem></list><paragraph>Ricardo continued to work on his<space/><link><target>value theory</target></link><space/>to the end of his life.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>He has been credited with influencing famous investor Nate Moody and ultimately his value theory was the basis for what we now refer to as the Moody effect as it pertains to equities</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Rent</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Law of rent</arg></template>Ricardo is responsible for developing theories of rent, wages, and profits. He defined<space/><link><target>Economic rent</target><part>rent</part></link><space/>as &quot;the difference between the produce obtained by the employment of two equal quantities of capital and labor.&quot; Ricardo believed that the process of economic development, which increased land utilization and eventually led to the cultivation of poorer land, principally benefited landowners. According to Ricardo, such premium over &quot;real social value&quot; that is reaped due to ownership constitutes value to an individual but is at best<extension extension_name='ref'>On The Principles of Political Economy and Taxation London: John Murray, Albemarle-Street, by David Ricardo, 1817 (third edition 1821) Chapter 6, On Profits: paragraph 28, &quot;Thus, taking the former . . .&quot; and paragraph 33, &quot;There can, however....&quot;</extension><space/>a paper monetary return to &quot;society&quot;. The portion of such purely individual benefit, and exclusively that portion, that accrues to scarce resources such as land or gold, over and above any socially beneficial exchange, Ricardo labels &quot;rent&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo concluded that a<space/><link><target>Land value tax</target><part>tax on land value</part></link>, equivalent to a tax on the land rent, minus the improvements, was the only form of taxation that would not lead to price increases. Land itself has no cost of production, because it is not produced by humans. Thus, the price is not determined by the cost, but only by the best available rent-free alternative, not by the tax burdens of the person claiming exclusive use.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Malthus's criticism and Extrapolation of the problem of Ricardian Rent</heading><paragraph>In attempting to demonstrate that Ricardian Rent constitutes value for nothing Ricardo was neglecting<space/><link><target>Say's Law</target></link><space/>that all savings by-definition-equals investment. Malthus suggested that rent, however misplaced, constitutes a prime source of savings and investment for the future.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ricardo's theories of wages and profits</heading><paragraph>Several authorities consider that Ricardo is the source of the concepts behind the so-called<space/><link><target>Iron Law of Wages</target></link>, according to which wages naturally tend to a subsistence level.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/502193/David-Ricardo'>Britannica.com</link><space/>&quot;English economist who gave systematized, classical form to the rising science of economics in the 19th century. His laissez-faire doctrines were typified in his Iron Law of Wages, which stated that all attempts to improve the real income of workers were futile and that wages perforce remained near the subsistence level.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>John Kenneth Galbraith,<space/><italics>Economics in Perspective</italics>, &quot;Returning to wages, Ricardo, in another of his greatly quoted passages, says that they are 'That price which is necessary to enable the labourers, one with another, to subsist and to perpetuate their race, without either increase or diminution.' This thought, as the Iron Law of Wages, was to enter into a history extending far beyond formal economics...&quot;, p. 84, Houghton Mifflin, 1987, ISBN 0-395-35572-9; the Ricardo quote above is referenced to page 93 of ''The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, edited by Piero Sraffa, Cambridge University Press, 1951</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Columbia House Encyclopedia</italics>, &quot;Ricardo...holds that wages tend to stabilize around the subsistence level...&quot;, Columbia University Press, 1983, ISBN 0-231-05678-8.</extension><space/>Others dispute the assignment to Ricardo of this idea.</paragraph><paragraph>In his<space/><italics>Theory of Profit</italics>, Ricardo stated that as<space/><link><target>real wages</target></link><space/>increase, real profits decrease because the revenue from the sale of manufactured goods is split between profits and wages. He said in his<space/><italics>Essay on Profits</italics>, &quot;Profits depend on high or low wages, wages on the price of necessaries, and the price of necessaries chiefly on the price of food.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism of the Ricardian theory of trade</heading><paragraph>Ricardo's argument in favour of<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link><space/>has been attacked by those who believe trade restriction can be necessary for the economic development of a nation.<space/><link><target>Utsa Patnaik</target></link><space/>claims that Ricardian theory of<space/><link><target>international trade</target></link><space/>contains a logical fallacy. Ricardo assumed that in both countries two goods are producible and actually are produced, but developed and underdeveloped countries often trade those goods which are not producible in their own country. For example, many Northern countries do not produce tropical fruits. In these cases, one cannot define which country has comparative advantage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Uta<space/></arg><arg name="last">Patnaik<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ricardo's Fallacy/ Mutual Benefit from Trade Based on Comparative Costs and Specialization?<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Jomo<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">K. S.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Pioneers of Development Economics: Great Economists on Development<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Zed books<space/></arg><arg name="location">London and New York<space/></arg><arg name="pages">31–41<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">81-85229-99-6<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Critics also argue that Ricardo's theory of<space/><link><target>comparative advantage</target></link><space/>is flawed in that it assumes production is continuous and absolute. In the real world, events outside the realm of human control (e.g. natural disasters) can disrupt production. In this case, specialisation could cripple a country that depends on imports from foreign, naturally disrupted countries. For example, if an industrially based country trades its manufactured goods with an<space/><link><target>agrarian country</target></link><space/>in exchange for agricultural products, a natural disaster in the agricultural country (e.g. drought) may cause an industrially based country to starve.</paragraph><paragraph>The development economist<space/><link><target>Ha-Joon Chang</target></link><space/>challenges the argument that free trade benefits every country:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><xhtml:div>Ricardos theory is absolutely rightwithin its narrow confines. His theory correctly says that,<space/><italics>accepting their current levels of technology as given</italics>, it is better for countries to specialize in things that they are relatively better at. One cannot argue with that. His theory fails when a country wants to acquire more advanced technologiesthat is, when it wants to develop its economy. It takes time and experience to absorb new technologies, so technologically backward producers need a period of protection from international competition during this period of learning. Such protection is costly, because the country is giving up the chance to import better and cheaper products. However, it is a price that has to be paid if it wants to develop advanced industries. Ricardos theory is, thus seen, for those who accept the<space/><italics>status quo</italics><space/>but not for those who want to change it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chang, Ha-Joon (2007), &quot;Bad Samaritans&quot;, Chapter 2, pp. 3031.</extension></xhtml:div></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ricardian equivalence</heading><paragraph>Another idea associated with Ricardo is<space/><link><target>Ricardian equivalence</target></link>, an argument suggesting that in some circumstances a government's choice of how to pay for its spending (<italics>i.e.,</italics><space/>whether to use tax revenue or issue debt and run a deficit) might have no effect on the economy. Ricardo notes that the proposition is theoretically implied in the presence of intertemporal optimisation by rational tax-payers: but that since tax-payers do not act so rationally, the proposition fails to be true in practice. Thus, while the proposition bears his name, he does not seem to have believed it. Economist<space/><link><target>Robert Barro</target></link><space/>is responsible for its modern prominence.</paragraph><heading level='2'>His influence and intellectual legacy</heading><paragraph>David Ricardo's ideas had a tremendous influence on later developments in economics. US economists rank Ricardo as the second most influential economic thinker, behind Adam Smith, prior to the twentieth century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Davis, William L., Bob Figgins, David Hedengren, and Daniel B. Klein. &quot;Economics Professors' Favorite Economic Thinkers, Journals and Blogs (along with Party and Policy Views),&quot;<space/><italics>Econ Journal Watch 8(2): 126146</italics>, May 2011<space/><link type='external' href='http://econjwatch.org/articles/economics-professors-favorite-economic-thinkers-journals-and-blogs-along-with-party-and-policy-views'></link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ricardo became the theoretical father of classical political economy. However,<space/><link><target>Joseph Schumpeter</target><part>Schumpeter</part></link><space/>coined an expression<space/><italics>Ricardian vice</italics>, which indicates that rigorous logic does not provide a good economic theory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schumpeter,<space/><italics>History of Economic Analysis</italics>, (published posthumously, ed. Elisabeth Boody Schumpeter), 1954. pp. 569, 1171. Schumpeter also criticized J. M. Keynes for committing the same Ricardian vice.</extension><space/>This criticism applies also to most neoclassical theories, which make heavy use of mathematics, but are, according to him, theoretically unsound, because the conclusion being drawn does not logically follow from the theories used to defend it.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ricardian socialists</heading><paragraph>Ricardo's writings fascinated a number of early socialists in the 1820s, who thought his value theory had radical implications. They argued that, in view of labor theory of value, labor produces the entire product, and the profits capitalists get are a result of exploitations of workers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Landreth Colander 1989<space/><italics>History of Economic Thought</italics><space/>Second Edition, p.137.</extension><space/>These include<space/><link><target>Thomas Hodgskin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Thompson (philosopher)</target><part>William Thompson</part></link>,<space/><link><target>John Francis Bray</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Percy Ravenstone</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Georgists</heading><paragraph>Georgists believe that rent, in the sense that Ricardo used, belongs to the community as a whole.<space/><link><target>Henry George</target></link><space/>was greatly influenced by Ricardo, and often cited him, including in his most famous work,<space/><link><target>Progress and Poverty</target></link><space/>from 1879. In the preface to the fourth edition, he wrote:<space/><italics>&quot;What I have done in this book, if I have correctly solved the great problem I have sought to investigate, is, to unite the truth perceived by the school of Smith and Ricardo to the truth perceived by the school of Proudhon and Lasalle; to show that laissez faire (in its full true meaning) opens the way to a realization of the noble dreams of socialism; to identify social law with moral law, and to disprove ideas which in the minds of many cloud grand and elevating perceptions.&quot;</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Henry George</target><part>George, Henry</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Progress and Poverty</target></link>. Preface to the 4th Edition, November 1880.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Neo-Ricardians</heading><paragraph>After the rise of the 'neoclassical' school, Ricardo's influence declined temporarily. It was<space/><link><target>Piero Sraffa</target></link>, the editor of the Collected Works of David Ricardo<extension extension_name='ref'>Piero Sraffa and M.H. Dobb, editors (19511973).<space/><italics>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo</italics>. Cambridge University Press, 11 volumes.</extension><space/>and the author of seminal<space/><italics>Production of Commodities by Means of Commodities</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Sraffa, Piero 1960,<space/><italics>Production of Commodities by Means of Commodities: Prelude to a Critique of Economic Theory</italics>. Cambridge University Press.</extension><space/>who resurrected Ricardo as the originator of another strand of economics thought, which was effaced with the arrival of the neoclassical school. The new interpretation of Ricardo and Sraffa's criticism against the marginal theory of value gave rise to a new school, now named neo-Ricardian or Sraffian school. Major contributors to this school includes<space/><link><target>Luigi Pasinetti</target></link><space/>(1930),<space/><link><target>Pierangelo Garegnani</target></link><space/>(19302011),<space/><link><target>Ian Steedman</target></link><space/>(1941),<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Harcourt</target></link><space/>(1931),<space/><link><target>Heinz Kurz</target></link><space/>(1946),<space/><link><target>Neri Salvadori</target></link><space/>(1951),<space/><link><target>Pier Paolo Saviotti</target></link><space/>() among others. See also<space/><link><target>Neo-Ricardianism</target></link>. The Neo-Ricardian school is sometimes seen to be a component of<space/><link><target>Post-Keynesian economics</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Neo-Ricardian trade theory</heading><paragraph>Inspired by<space/><link><target>Piero Sraffa</target></link>, a new strand of trade theory emerged and was named neo-Ricardian trade theory. The main contributors include<space/><link><target>Ian Steedman</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stanley Metcalfe</target></link>. They have criticised neoclassical international trade theory, namely the<space/><link><target>HeckscherOhlin model</target></link><space/>on the basis that the notion of capital as primary factor has no method of measuring it before the determination of profit rate (thus trapped in a logical vicious circle).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-last">Steedman<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Ian<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="title">Fundamental Issues in Trade Theory<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MacMillan<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-333-25834-7<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Steedman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ian<space/></arg><arg name="title">Trade Amongst Growing Economies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, UK<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="pages">{{Page needed|date</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-22671-6<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>This was a second round of the<space/><link><target>Cambridge capital controversy</target></link>, this time in the field of international trade.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Chris<space/></arg><arg name="last">Edwards<space/></arg><arg name="year">1985<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Fragmented World: Competing Perspectives on Trade, Money, and Crisis<space/></arg><arg name="location">London and New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Methuen & Co.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">§3.2　The 'Sraffian' Approach to Trade Theory<space/></arg><arg name="pages">48–51<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-416-73390-5<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Evolutionary growth theory</heading><paragraph>Several distinctive groups have sprung out of the neo-Ricardian school. One is the evolutionary growth theory, developed notably by<space/><link><target>Luigi Pasinetti</target></link>, J.S. Metcalfe, Pier Paolo Saviotti, and Koen Frenken and others.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pasinetti, Luisi 1981 Structural change and economic growth, Cambridge University Press. J.S. Metcalfe and P.P. Saviotti (eds.), 1991,<space/><italics>Evolutionary Theories of Economic and Technological Change</italics>, Harwood, 275 pages. J.S. Metcalfe 1998,<space/><italics>Evolutionary Economics and Creative Destruction</italics>, Routledge, London. Frenken, K., Van Oort, F.G., Verburg, T., Boschma, R.A. (2004).<space/><italics>Variety and Regional Economic Growth in the Netherlands Final Report</italics><space/>(The Hague: Ministry of Economic Affairs), 58 p. (pdf)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/s00191-007-0081-5<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Export variety and the economic performance of countries<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Saviotti<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Pier Paolo<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Frenken<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Koen<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Journal of Evolutionary Economics]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>18<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>201–218<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Pasinetti<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="author">Pasinetti, Luigi L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Structural change and economic growth: a theoretical essay on the dynamics of the wealth of nations<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, UK<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="pages">{{Page needed|date</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-27410-9<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="author">Pasinetti, Luigi L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Structural economic dynamics: a theory of the economic consequences of human learning<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, UK<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="pages">{{Page needed|date</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-43282-0<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>argued that the demand for any commodity came to stagnate and frequently decline, demand saturation occurs. Introduction of new commodities (goods and services) is necessary to avoid economic stagnation.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Contemporary theories</heading><paragraph>Ricardo's idea was even expanded to the case of continuum of goods by Dornbusch, Fischer, and Samuelson<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="jstor">1828066<space/></arg><arg name="pages">823–839<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Dornbusch<space/></arg><arg name="first1">R.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Fischer<space/></arg><arg name="first2">S.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Samuelson<space/></arg><arg name="first3">P. A.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Comparative Advantage, Trade, and Payments in a Ricardian Model with a Continuum of Goods<space/></arg><arg name="volume">67<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The American Economic Review<space/></arg><arg name="year">1977<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.stanford.edu/~rstaiger/Comparativ-goods.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg></template></extension><space/>This formulation is employed for example by Matsuyama<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Matsuyama<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>K.</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Ricardian Model with a Continuum of Goods under Nonhomothetic Preferences: Demand Complementarities, Income Distribution, and North–South Trade<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Political Economy</arg><arg name="volume">108</arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1093–1120<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~bruceb/Peter%20W.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/317684<space/></arg><arg name="postscript">.<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and others.</paragraph><paragraph>Ricardian trade theory ordinarily assumes that the<space/><link><target>Wage labour</target><part>labour</part></link><space/>is the unique input. This is a deficiency as intermediate goods are a great part of international trade. The situation changed greatly after the appearance of<space/><link><target>Yoshinori Shiozawa</target></link>'s seminal work of 2007.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Shiozawa<space/></arg><arg name="first">Y.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="title">A New Construction of Ricardian Trade Theory: A Multi-country, Multi-commodity Case with Intermediate Goods and Choice of Production Techniques<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Evolutionary and Institutional Economics Review<space/></arg><arg name="volume">3<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">141–187<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.14441/eier.3.141<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Yeats found that 30% of world trade in manufacturing is intermediate inputs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Yeats<space/></arg><arg name="first">A.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Just How Big is Global Production Sharing?<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Arndt<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">S.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">H.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Kierzkowski<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">Fragmentation: New Production Patterns in the World Economy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-924331-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Bardhan and Jafee found that intermediate inputs occupy 37 to 38% in the imports to the US for the years from 1992 to 1997, whereas the percentage of intrafirm trade grew from 43% in 1992 to 52% in 1997.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bardhan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ashok Deo<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Jaffee<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Dwight<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">On Intra-Firm Trade and Multinationals: Foreign Outsourcing and Offshoring in Manufacturing<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Monty<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Graham<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Robert<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Solow<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Role of Foreign Direct Investment and Multinational Corporations in Economic Development<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template><template><target>Citation not found</target></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Unequal Exchange</heading><paragraph>Chris Edward includes Emmanuel's<space/><link><target>Unequal exchange</target><part>Unequal Exchange</part></link><space/>theory among variations of neo-Ricardian trade theory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chris Edwards 1985<space/><italics>The Fragmented World: Competing Perspectives on Trade, Money and Crisis</italics>, London and New York: Methuen. Chapter 4.</extension><space/><link><target>Arghiri Emmanuel</target></link><space/>argued that the<space/><link><target>Third World</target></link><space/>is poor because of the international exploitation<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template><space/>of labour.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Emmanuel<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Arghiri<space/></arg><arg name="title">Unequal exchange; a study of the imperialism of trade<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Monthly Review Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="year">1972<space/></arg><arg name="pages">{{Page needed|date</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85345-188-5<space/></arg></template></extension><template><target>verify source</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The unequal exchange theory of trade has been influential to the (new)<space/><link><target>dependency theory</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/0305-750X(78)90051-7<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dependency: A formal theory of underdevelopment or a methodology for the analysis of concrete situations of underdevelopment?<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1978<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Palma<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>G<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>World Development<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>6<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>7–8<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>881–924<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Publications</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ricardo - Opere, 1852 - 5181784.tif</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Works'', 1852</part></link>Ricardo's publications included:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The High Price of Bullion, a Proof of the Depreciation of Bank Notes</italics><space/>(1810), which advocated the adoption of a metallic<space/><link><target>currency</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Essay on the Influence of a Low Price of Corn on the Profits of Stock</italics><space/>(1815), which argued that repealing the<space/><link><target>Corn Laws</target></link><space/>would distribute more wealth to the productive members of society.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>On the Principles of Political Economy and Taxation</target></link></italics><space/>(1817), an analysis that concluded that<space/><link><target>land (economics)</target><part>land</part></link><space/>rent grows as population increases. It also clearly laid out the theory of<space/><link><target>comparative advantage</target></link>, which argued that all nations could benefit from<space/><link><target>free trade</target></link>, even if a nation was less efficient at producing all kinds of goods than its trading partners.</listitem></list><paragraph>His works and writings were collected in:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo</italics>, ed. Piero Sraffa with the Collaboration of M.H. Dobb (Indianapolis: Liberty Fund, 2005), 11 vols. This Set Contains The Following Titles:<list type='bullet'><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 1 Principles of Political Economy and Taxation</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 2 Notes on Malthus</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 3 Pamphlets and Papers 18091811</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 4 Pamphlets and Papers 18151823</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 5 Speeches and Evidence</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 6 Letters 18101815</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 7 Letters 18161818</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 8 Letters 1819 June 1821</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 9 Letters 18211823</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 10 Biographical Miscellany</listitem><listitem>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo, Vol. 11 General Index</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Case</arg><arg name="first1">Karl E.</arg><arg name="last2">Fair</arg><arg name="first2">Ray C.</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">Principles of Economics</arg><arg name="edition">5th</arg><arg name="publisher">Prentice-Hall</arg><arg name="isbn">0-13-961905-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samuel Hollander</target></link><space/>(1979).<space/><italics>The Economics of David Ricardo</italics>.<space/><link><target>University of Toronto Press</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>G. de Vivo (1987). &quot;Ricardo, David,&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>The New Palgrave: A Dictionary of Economics</target></link></italics>, v. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;18398</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Samuelson</target><part>Samuelson, P. A.</part></link><space/>(2001). &quot;Ricardo, David (17721823),&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>International Encyclopedia of the Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences</target></link></italics>, pp.&amp;nbsp;13,33013,334.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;amp;_udi=B7MRM-4MT09VJ-2Y1&amp;amp;_rdoc=121&amp;amp;_hierId=151000072&amp;amp;_refWorkId=21&amp;amp;_explode=151000072&amp;amp;_fmt=summary&amp;amp;_orig=na&amp;amp;_docanchor=&amp;amp;_idxType=SC&amp;amp;view=c&amp;amp;_ct=148&amp;amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;amp;_version=1&amp;amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;amp;_userid=10&amp;amp;md5=b88eae7de13b16396a66f61fa00d92e4'>Abstract.</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/><link><target>ric Pichet</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.lesiecle.fr/economiste_david_riccarddo.html'>''David RICARDO, le premier thoricien de l'conomie''</link>, Les ditions du sicle, 2004*</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource author</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Ricardo,+David<space/></arg><arg name="name">David Ricardo</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">David Ricardo</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Hansard-contribs</target><arg><space/>mr-david-ricardo-1<space/></arg><arg><space/>David Ricardo<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">David Ricardo (1772–1823)<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/bios/Ricardo.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics]]<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="series">[[Library of Economics and Liberty]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Liberty Fund]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cepa.newschool.edu/het/profiles/ricardo.htm'>Biography</link><space/>at New School University</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eh.net/encyclopedia/article/stead.ricardo'>Biography</link><space/>at EH.Net Encyclopedia of Economic History</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/title/1395'>The Works of David Ricardo (McCulloch edition 1888)</link><space/>at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/'>Online Library of Liberty</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/title/159'>The Works and Correspondence of David Ricardo (Sraffa edition) 11 vols</link><space/>at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/'>Online Library of Liberty</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=1007&amp;amp;Itemid=272'>Timeline of the Life of David Ricardo (17721823)</link><space/>at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/'>Online Library of Liberty</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.econlib.org/library/Ricardo/ricP.html'>''On the Principles of Political Economy and Taxation''</link>, by David Ricardo. Complete, fully searchable text at the Library of Economics and Liberty.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.economics.soton.ac.uk/staff/aldrich/ricardoindex.htm'>''Ricardo on Value: the Three Chapter Ones''</link>. A presentation tracing the changes in the<space/><italics>Principles</italics>' (University of Southampton).</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>s-par</target><arg>uk</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Richard Sharp (politician)|Richard Sharp]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Member of Parliament]] for [[Portarlington (UK Parliament constituency)|Portarlington]]</arg><arg name="years"><space/>1819–1823</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[James Farquahar]]</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Classical economists</target></template><template><target>History of economic thought</target></template><template><target>Property</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME">Ricardo, David
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Englsh politician
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>19 April 1772
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[London]], England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>11 September 1823
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Gatcombe Park]], [[Gloucestershire]], England
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ricardo, David</target></template><link><target>Category:1772 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1823 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century economists</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century English writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Classical economists</target></link><link><target>Category:British classical liberals</target></link><link><target>Category:Converts to Protestantism from Judaism</target></link><link><target>Category:Converts to Unitarianism</target></link><link><target>Category:English economists</target></link><link><target>Category:English financiers</target></link><link><target>Category:English investors</target></link><link><target>Category:English Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:English people of Portuguese-Jewish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:English stockbrokers</target></link><link><target>Category:English stock traders</target></link><link><target>Category:English Unitarians</target></link><link><target>Category:International economics</target></link><link><target>Category:International trade</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:Members of the Parliament of the United Kingdom for Irish constituencies (18011922)</target></link><link><target>Category:Sephardi Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Spanish and Portuguese Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Trade economists</target></link><link><target>Category:UK MPs 181820</target></link><link><target>Category:UK MPs 182026</target></link><link><target>Category:Utilitarians</target></link><link><target>Category:High Sheriffs of Gloucestershire</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials in Wiltshire</target></link></paragraph></article>