<article title='Aeronautics'><paragraph><template><target>For</target><arg>the album</arg><arg>Aeronautics (album)</arg></template><link><target>File:Atlantis on Shuttle Carrier Aircraft.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Space Shuttle Atlantis</target><part>Space Shuttle ''Atlantis''</part></link><space/>on a<space/><link><target>Shuttle Carrier Aircraft</target></link>.</part></link><bold>Aeronautics</bold><space/>(from the<space/><link><target>ancient Greek</target></link><space/>words<space/><italics>r</italics>, which means &quot;air&quot;, and<space/><italics>nautik</italics><space/>which means &quot;navigation&quot;, i.e. &quot;navigation of the air&quot;) is the science or art involved with the study,<space/><link><target>aircraft design process</target><part>design</part></link>, and manufacturing of air<space/><link><target>flight</target></link><space/>capable machines, and the techniques of operating<space/><link><target>aircraft</target></link><space/>and rockets within the atmosphere. The British<space/><link><target>Royal Aeronautical Society</target></link><space/>identifies the aspects of &quot;aeronautical Art, Science and Engineering&quot; and &quot;the profession of Aeronautics (which expression includes Astronautics).&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://aerosociety.com/About-Us/learnedsociety'>A Learned and Professional Society</link><space/>(Retrieved 8 March 2014)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the termliterally meaning &quot;sailing the air&quot;originally referred solely to the science of<space/><italics>operating</italics><space/>the aircraft, it has since been expanded to include technology, business and other aspects related to aircraft.<extension extension_name='ref' name="americana"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="title"><space/>Aeronautics
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>226
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1986
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Grolier<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The term &quot;<link><target>aviation</target></link>&quot; is sometimes, used interchangeably with aeronautics, although &quot;aeronautics&quot; includes<space/><link><target>lighter-than-air</target></link><space/>craft such as<space/><link><target>airship</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and includes<space/><link><target>ballistic vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>while &quot;aviation&quot; technically does not.<extension extension_name='ref' name="americana"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A significant part of<space/><bold>aeronautical science</bold><space/>is a branch of<space/><link><target>dynamics (mechanics)</target><part>dynamics</part></link><space/>called<space/><link><target>aerodynamics</target></link>, which deals with the motion of air and the way that it interacts with objects in motion, such as an aircraft.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Early ideas</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Leonardo da Vinci helicopter and lifting wing.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Designs for flying machines by Leonardo da Vinci, circa 1490</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Attempts to fly without any real aeronautical understanding have been made from the earliest times, typically by constructing wings and jumping from a tower with crippling or lethal results.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Wragg</arg><arg>1974</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Wiser investigators sought to gain some rational understanding through the study of bird flight. An early example appears in ancient Egyptian texts.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><space/>Later medieval Islamic scientists also made such studies. The founders of modern aeronautics,<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link><space/>in the Renaissance and Cayley around 1800, both began their investigations with studies of bird flight.</paragraph><paragraph>Man-carrying kites are believed to have been used extensively in ancient China. In 1282 the European explorer<space/><link><target>Marco Polo</target></link><space/>described the Chinese techniques then current.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pelham">Pelham, D.;<space/><italics>The Penguin book of kites</italics>, Penguin (1976)</extension><space/>The Chinese also constructed small hot air balloons, or lanterns, and rotary-wing toys.</paragraph><paragraph>An early European to provide any scientific discussion of flight was<space/><link><target>Roger Bacon</target></link>, who described principles of operation for the lighter-than-air<space/><link><target>Balloon (aircraft)</target><part>balloon</part></link><space/>and the flapping-wing<space/><link><target>ornithopter</target></link>, which he envisaged would be constructed in the future. The lifting medium for his balloon would be an &quot;aether&quot; whose composition he did not know.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Wragg</arg><arg>1974</arg><arg name="pp">10–11</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the late fifteenth century, Leonardo da Vinci followed up his study of birds with designs for some of the earliest flying machines, including the flapping-wing<space/><link><target>ornithopter</target></link><space/>and the rotating-wing<space/><link><target>helicopter</target></link>. Although his designs were rational, they were not based on particularly good science.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Wragg</arg><arg>1974</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template><space/>Many of his designs, such as a four-person screw-type helicopter, have severe flaws. He did at least understand that &quot;An object offers as much resistance to the air as the air does to the object.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fairlie</arg><arg>Cayley</arg><arg>1965</arg><arg name="p">163</arg></template><space/>(<link><target>Isaac Newton</target><part>Newton</part></link><space/>would not publish the<space/><link><target>Newton's laws of motion#Newton.27s third law</target><part>Third law of motion</part></link><space/>until 1687.) His analysis led to the realisation that manpower alone was not sufficient for sustained flight, and his later designs included a mechanical power source such as a spring. Da Vinci's work was lost after his death and did not reappear until it had been overtaken by the work of<space/><link><target>George Cayley</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Balloon flight</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of ballooning</arg></template><link><target>File:Flying boat.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Francesco Lana de Terzi's flying boat concept c.1670</part></link>The modern era of lighter-than-air flight began early in the 17th century with<space/><link><target>Galileo</target></link>'s experiments in which he showed that air has weight. Around 1650<space/><link><target>Cyrano de Bergerac</target></link><space/>wrote some fantasy novels in which he described the principle of ascent using a substance (dew) he supposed to be lighter than air, and descending by releasing a controlled amount of the substance.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ege</arg><arg>1973</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template><space/><link><target>Francesco Lana de Terzi</target></link><space/>measured the pressure of air at sea level and in 1670 proposed the first scientifically credible lifting medium in the form of hollow metal spheres from which all the air had been pumped out. These would be lighter than the displaced air and able to lift an<space/><link><target>airship</target></link>. His proposed methods of controlling height are still in use today; by carrying ballast which may be dropped overboard to gain height, and by venting the lifting containers to lose height.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ege</arg><arg>1973</arg><arg name="p">7</arg></template><space/>In practice de Terzi's spheres would have collapsed under air pressure, and further developments had to wait for more practicable lifting gases.</paragraph><paragraph>From the mid-18th century the<space/><link><target>Montgolfier brothers</target></link><space/>in France began experimenting with balloons. Their balloons were made of paper, and early experiments using steam as the lifting gas were short-lived due to its effect on the paper as it condensed. Mistaking smoke for a kind of steam, they began filling their balloons with hot smoky air which they called &quot;electric smoke&quot; and, despite not fully understanding the principles at work, made some successful launches and in 1783 were invited to give a demonstration to the French Academie des Sciences.</paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, the discovery of<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>led<space/><link><target>Joseph Black</target></link><space/>in c. 1780 to propose its use as a lifting gas, though practical demonstration awaited a gastight balloon material. On hearing of the Montgolfier Brothers' invitation, the French Academy member<space/><link><target>Jacques Charles</target></link><space/>offered a similar demonstration of a hydrogen balloon. Charles and two craftsmen, the Robert brothers, developed a gastight material of rubberised silk for the envelope. The hydrogen gas was to be generated by chemical reaction during the filling process.</paragraph><paragraph>The Montgolfier designs had several shortcomings, not least the need for dry weather and a tendency for sparks from the fire to set light to the paper balloon. The manned design had a gallery around the base of the balloon rather than the hanging basket of the first, unmanned design, which brought the paper closer to the fire. On their free flight, De Rozier and d'Arlandes took buckets of water and sponges to douse these fires as they arose. On the other hand, the manned design of Charles was essentially modern.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ege</arg><arg>1973</arg><arg name="pp">97–100</arg></template><space/>As a result of these exploits, the hot-air ballon became known as the<space/><italics>Montgolfire</italics><space/>type and the hydrogen balloon the<space/><italics>Charlire</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Charles and the Robert brothers' next balloon,<space/><italics><link><target>Robert brothers#Further ballooning activities La Caroline</target><part>La Caroline</part></link></italics>, was a Charlire that followed<space/><link><target>Jean Baptiste Meusnier</target></link>'s proposals for an elongated dirigible balloon, and was notable for having an outer envelope with the gas contained in a second, inner ballonet. On 19 September 1784, it completed the first flight of over 100&amp;nbsp;km, between Paris and<space/><link><target>Beuvry</target></link>, despite the man-powered propulsive devices proving useless.</paragraph><paragraph>In an attempt the next year to provide both endurance and controllability, de Rozier developed a balloon having both hot air and hydrogen gas bags, a design which was soon named after him as the<space/><italics>Rozire.</italics><space/>The principle was to use the hydrogen section for constant lift and to navigate vertically by heating and allowing to cool the hot air section, in order to catch the most favourable wind at whatever altitude it was blowing. The balloon envelope was made of<space/><link><target>goldbeaters skin</target></link>. The first flight ended in disaster and the approach has seldom been used since.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ege</arg><arg>1965</arg><arg name="p">105</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cayley and the foundation of modern aeronautics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Sir George Cayley</target></link><space/>(1773-1857) is widely acknowledged as the founder of modern aeronautics. He was first called the &quot;father of the aeroplane&quot; in 1846<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fairlie</arg><arg>Cayley</arg><arg>1965</arg></template><space/>and Henson called him the &quot;father of aerial navigation.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Wragg</arg><arg>1974</arg></template><space/>He was the first true scientific aerial investigator to publish his work, which included for the first time the underlying principles and forces of flight.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Sir George Carley</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flyingmachines.org/cayl.html</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Flyingmachines.org</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-07-26</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Sir George Cayley is one of the most important people in the history of aeronautics. Many consider him the first true scientific aerial investigator and the first person to understand the underlying principles and forces of flight.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1809 he began the publication of a landmark three-part treatise titled &quot;On Aerial Navigation&quot; (18091810).<extension extension_name='ref' name="AerNav123"><italics>Cayley, George</italics>. &quot;On Aerial Navigation&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aeronautics.nasa.gov/fap/OnAerialNavigationPt1.pdf'>Part 1</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aeronautics.nasa.gov/fap/OnAerialNavigationPt2.pdf'>Part 2</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aeronautics.nasa.gov/fap/OnAerialNavigationPt3.pdf'>Part 3</link><space/><italics>Nicholson's Journal of Natural Philosophy</italics>, 18091810. (Via<space/><link><target>NASA</target></link>).<space/><link type='external' href='http://invention.psychology.msstate.edu/i/Cayley/Cayley.html'>Raw text</link>. Retrieved: 30 May 2010.</extension><space/>In it he wrote the first scientific statement of the problem, &quot;The whole problem is confined within these limits, viz. to make a surface support a given weight by the application of power to the resistance of air.&quot; He identified the four vector forces that influence an aircraft:<space/><italics><link><target>thrust</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Lift (force)</target><part>lift</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Aerodynamic drag</target><part>drag</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>weight</target></link></italics><space/>and distinguished stability and control in his designs.</paragraph><paragraph>He developed the modern conventional form of the fixed-wing aeroplane having a stabilising tail with both horizontal and vertical surfaces, flying gliders both unmanned and manned.</paragraph><paragraph>He introduced the use of the whirling arm test rig to investigate the aerodynamics of flight, using it to discover the benefits of the curved or<space/><link><target>camber (aerodynamics)</target><part>cambered</part></link><space/><link><target>aerofoil</target></link><space/>over the flat wing he had used for his first glider. He also identified and described the importance of<space/><link><target>Dihedral (aircraft)</target><part>dihedral</part></link>, diagonal bracing and drag reduction, and contributed to the understanding and design of<space/><link><target>ornithopter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>parachute</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Wragg</arg><arg>1974</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another significant invention was the tension-spoked wheel, which he devised in order to create a light, strong wheel for aircraft undercarriage.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The 19th century</heading><paragraph>During the 19th century Cayley's ideas were refined, proved and expanded on. Important investigators included<space/><link><target>Otto Lilienthal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Horatio Phillips</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Branches</heading><paragraph>Aeronautics may be divided into three main branches comprising<space/><link><target>Aviation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Aeronautical science</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aeronautical engineering</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aviation</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Aviation</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Aviation is the art or practice of aeronautics. Historically aviation meant only heavier-than-air flight, but nowadays it includes flying in balloons and airships.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aeronautical science</heading><paragraph>Aeronautical science covers the practical theory of aeronautics and aviation, including operations, navigation, air safety and human factors.</paragraph><paragraph>A candidate pilot is likely to study for a qualification in aeronautical science.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aeronautical engineering</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Aerospace engineering</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Aeronautical engineering covers the design and construction of aircraft, including how they are powered, how they are used and how they are controlled for safe operation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gla.ac.uk/undergraduate/degrees/aeronauticalengineering/'>Aeronautical engineering</link>, University of Glasgow.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A major part of aeronautical engineering is aerodynamics, the science of passage through the air.</paragraph><paragraph>With the increasing activity in spaceflight, nowadays aeronautics and astronautics are often combined as<space/><link><target>aerospace engineering</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Aerodynamics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Aerodynamics</arg></template>The science of aerodynamics deals with the motion of air and the way that it interacts with objects in motion, such as an aircraft.</paragraph><paragraph>The study of aerodynamics falls broadly into three areas:</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Incompressible flow</target></link></italics><space/>occurs where the air simply moves to avoid objects, typically at subsonic speeds below that of sound (Mach 1).</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Compressible flow</target></link></italics><space/>occurs where shock waves appear at points where the air becomes compressed, typically at speeds above Mach 1.</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Transonic flow</target></link></italics><space/>occurs in the intermediate speed range around Mach 1, where the airflow over an object may be locally subsonic at one point and locally supersonic at another.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Rocketry</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Rocket</arg></template><link><target>File:Apollo 15 launch.ogg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Launch of ''<link><target>Apollo 15</target></link>''<space/><link><target>Saturn V</target></link><space/>rocket: ''T'' - 30 s through ''T'' + 40 s.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>rocket</target></link><space/>or rocket vehicle is a<space/><link><target>missile</target></link>, spacecraft,<space/><link><target>aircraft</target></link><space/>or other<space/><link><target>vehicle</target></link><space/>which obtains<space/><link><target>thrust</target></link><space/>from a<space/><link><target>rocket engine</target></link>. In all rockets, the exhaust is formed entirely from<space/><link><target>propellant</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>carried within the rocket before use.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RPE7"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sutton<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>George<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rocket Propulsion Elements<space/></arg><arg name="edition">7th<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Wiley & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Chichester<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-471-32642-7</arg><arg name="chapter">1</arg></template></extension><space/>Rocket engines work by<space/><link><target>Reaction (physics)</target><part>action and reaction</part></link>. Rocket engines push rockets forwards simply by throwing their exhaust backwards extremely fast.</paragraph><paragraph>Rockets for military and recreational uses date back to at least 13th century<space/><link><target>China</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NASA EARLY"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>MSFC History Office</arg></template><space/>&quot;Rockets in Ancient Times (100 B.C. to 17th Century)&quot;</extension><space/>Significant scientific, interplanetary and industrial use did not occur until the 20th century, when rocketry was the enabling technology of the<space/><link><target>Space Age</target></link>, including<space/><link><target>Apollo 11</target><part>setting foot on the moon</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Rockets are used for<space/><link><target>fireworks</target></link>, weaponry,<space/><link><target>ejection seat</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>launch vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>artificial satellite</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>human spaceflight</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Space exploration</target><part>exploration</part></link><space/>of other planets. While comparatively inefficient for low speed use, they are very lightweight and powerful, capable of generating large accelerations and of attaining<space/><link><target>escape velocity</target><part>extremely high speeds</part></link><space/>with reasonable efficiency.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Chemical rocket</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are the most common type of rocket and they typically create their exhaust by the combustion of<space/><link><target>rocket propellant</target></link>. Chemical rockets store a large amount of energy in an easily released form, and can be very dangerous. However, careful design, testing, construction and use minimizes risks.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Typhoon f2 zj910 arp.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Eurofighter Typhoon</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:An-225 Mriya.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Antonov An-225 Mriya</target><part>Antonov An-225 ''Mriya''</part></link>, the largest aeroplane ever built.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>columns-list</target><arg>2</arg><arg>
* [[Aeronautical abbreviations]]
* [[Aeronautics Defense Systems]]
* [[Aerospace engineering]]
* [[Aerostatics]]
* [[Air safety]]
* [[Aircraft design process]]
* [[Aircraft flight control system]]
* [[Aircraft flight mechanics]]
* [[American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics]]
* [[Astronautics]]
* [[wikt:Appendix:Aviation, aerospace, and aeronautical terms|Aviation, aerospace, and aeronautical terms]]
* [[Avionics]]
* [[Flight dynamics]]
* [[Longitudinal static stability]]
* [[The Royal Aeronautical Society]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ege<space/></arg><arg name="first">L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Balloons and airships<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blandford<space/></arg><arg name="year">1973<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Fairlie<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Gerard<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Cayley<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="title">The life of a genius<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hodder and Stoughton<space/></arg><arg name="year">1965<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wragg<space/></arg><arg name="first">D.W.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Flight before flying<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey<space/></arg><arg name="year">1974<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0850451655<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://howthingsfly.si.edu'>Smithsonian National Air and Space Museum's How Things Fly website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.habitat.org.tr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=486:nud36&amp;amp;catid=89:basarihikayeleri&amp;amp;Itemid=98'>Aeronautics History in Turkey</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.literature.at/elib/index.php5?title=Aeronautics_History_-_Charles_Vivian_-_1920'>Aeronautics History - Charles Vivian - 1920 (eLibrary Project - eLib full text)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/aeronautics-and-astronautics/'>Aerospace courses</link><space/>at MIT OpenCourseWare</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.academy.aero'>American Academy of Aeronautics</link><space/>aeronautical science</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vtol.org'>American Helicopter Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aiaa.org'>American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aerodyndesign.com'>Examples of Aeronautic Designs</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://world-airship2008.ru/08/content/?id=17#1eng'>What is aeronautics?</link><space/>The history of world Aeronautics (Russian)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://adg.stanford.edu/aa241/AircraftDesign.html'>Aircraft Design: Synthesis and Analysis</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.easn.net/research-technology-areas/2/'>ACARE Taxonomy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://innopedia.wikidot.com/create'>CREating innovative Air transport Technologies for Europe</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/coll/gt.html'>The Gaston and Albert Tissandier Collection</link><space/>in the Rare Book and Special Collections Division in the<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link><space/>contains publications relating to the history of aeronautics, (1,800 titles).</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Aeronautics</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>