<article title='Boer'><paragraph><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>Boyar</arg></template><template><target>For</target><arg>the surname</arg><arg>Boer (surname)</arg></template><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox ethnic group</target><arg name="group"><space/>Boer<space/><br><space/><small><space/>Boere<space/></small>
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:Paul Kruger.jpg|70x82px|Paul Kruger]][[File:Andries Pretorius.jpg|70x82px|Andries Pretorius]]
[[File:Sarel-Cilliers.jpg|70x82px|Sarel Cilliers]][[File:Pjjoubert.jpg|70x82px|Petrus Jacobus Joubert]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>[[Paul Kruger]], [[Andries Pretorius]], [[Sarel Cilliers]], and [[Petrus Jacobus Joubert]]
</arg><arg name="pop"><space/>approx. 1.5 million.<ref>{{cite book | url<space/></arg><arg name="languages"><space/>[[Afrikaans]], [[Dutch language|Dutch]]
</arg><arg name="religions"><space/>[[Protestant]] , [[Afrikaner Calvinism]], [[Calvinism]], [[Reformed churches]]
</arg><arg name="related"><space/>[[Afrikaner people|Afrikaner]], [[Dutch people|Dutch]], [[Flemish people|Flemish]], [[Frisians]]; [[Germans]], [[French people|French]], [[Scottish people|Scots]], [[English people|English]]; [[Cape Coloureds]], [[Basters]], [[Griquas]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Boer</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>lang</arg><arg>pron</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>.</arg><arg>ər</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>b</arg><arg>ɔr</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>b</arg><arg>ʊər</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Jones<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Daniel<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink1">Daniel Jones (phonetician)<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Gimson<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Alfred C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink2">Alfred C. Gimson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Everyman's English Pronunciation Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="edition">14<space/></arg><arg name="series">Everyman's Reference Library<space/></arg><arg name="year">1977<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1917<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">J. M. Dent & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-460-03029-9</arg></template></extension><space/><template><target>IPA-af</target><arg>buːr</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>) is the<space/><link><target>Dutch language</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Afrikaans language</target><part>Afrikaans</part></link><space/>word for &quot;farmer.&quot; As used in South Africa, it was used to denote the descendants of the Dutch-speaking<space/><link><target>settler</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the eastern Cape frontier<extension extension_name='ref' name="Du Toit 1998 1"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a</arg><arg name="first">Brian M.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Du Toit<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Boers in East Africa: Ethnicity and Identity<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="page">1<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-02</arg></template></extension><space/>in Southern Africa during the 18th century. For a time the<space/><link><target>Dutch East India Company</target></link><space/>controlled this area, but it was taken over by the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In addition the term was applied to those who left the<space/><link><target>British Cape Colony</target><part>Cape Colony</part></link><space/>during the 19th century to settle in the<space/><link><target>Orange Free State</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target><part>Transvaal</part></link><space/>(which are together known as the<space/><link><target>Boer Republics</target></link>), and to a lesser extent<space/><link><target>Natalia Republic</target><part>Natal</part></link>. They left the Cape primarily to escape British rule and get away from the constant border wars between the British imperial government and the tribes on the eastern frontier.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Origin</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Charles Bell - Jan van Riebeeck se aankoms aan die Kaap.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Painting of an account of the arrival of<space/><link><target>Jan van Riebeeck</target></link>, by<space/><link><target>Charles Bell (surveyor)</target><part>Charles Bell</part></link>.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>Dutch East India Company</target></link><space/>had been formed in the<space/><link><target>Dutch Republic</target></link><space/>in 1602, and the Dutch had entered keenly into the competition for the colonial and imperial trade of commerce in Southeast Asia. In 1648 one of their ships was stranded in<space/><link><target>Table Bay</target></link>, and the shipwrecked crew had to forage for themselves on shore for several months. They were so impressed with the natural resources of the country that on their return to the Republic, they represented to the directors of the company the great advantages to the Dutch Eastern trade to be had from a properly provided and fortified station of call at the Cape. The result was that in 1652, a Dutch expedition led by surgeon<space/><link><target>Jan van Riebeek</target></link><space/>constructed a fort and laid out vegetable gardens at Table Bay.</paragraph><paragraph>Landing at Table Bay, Van Riebeek took control over<space/><link><target>Cape Town</target></link>, the settlement developed during the previous 10 years. In 1657 a few soldiers and sailors discharged by the Dutch East India Company were allotted farms; they constituted the first so-called free burghers. In 1671 the Dutch first purchased land from the native<space/><link><target>Khoikhoi</target></link><space/>beyond the limits of the fort built by Van Riebeek; this marked the development of<space/><link><target>Dutch Cape Colony</target><part>the Colony proper</part></link>. The earliest colonists were for the most part people of low station; but, as the result of the investigations of a 1685 commissioner, the government worked to recruit a greater variety of immigrants to develop a stable community.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>More settlers were landed from time to time, including a number of orphan girls from<space/><link><target>Amsterdam</target></link>, and during 16881689, the colony was greatly strengthened by the arrival of some three hundred French<space/><link><target>Huguenots</target></link><space/>(men, women and children). Political refugees from the religious wars in France, following the revocation of the Edict of Nantes, they were settled at<space/><link><target>Stellenbosch</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Drakenstein</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franschhoek</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paarl</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>H. C. Viljoen,<space/><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20091025222633/http://geocities.com/sa_stamouers/huguenots.htm'>The Contribution of the Huguenots in South Africa</link>, 25 OCtober 2009</extension><space/>The influence of this small body of immigrants on the character of the Dutch settlers was marked. The Company in 1701 directed that only<space/><link><target>Dutch language</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/>should be taught in the schools. This resulted in the Huguenots assimilating by the middle of the 18th century, with a loss to the community in the use and knowledge of the<space/><link><target>French language</target></link>. The little settlement gradually spread eastwards, and in 1754 the country as far as<space/><link><target>Algoa Bay</target></link><space/>was included in the colony.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>At this time the European (white) colonists numbered eight to ten thousand. They possessed numerous slaves, grew wheat in sufficient quantity to make it a commodity crop for export, and were famed for the good quality of their wines. But their chief wealth was in cattle. They enjoyed considerable prosperity.<space/><link><target>File:Flag of the Dutch East India Company.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Flag of the<space/><link><target>Dutch East India Company</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Through the latter half of the 17th and the whole of the 18th century, troubles arose between the colonists and the government. The administration of the Dutch East India Company was extremely<space/><link><target>despotism</target><part>despotic</part></link>. Its policies were not directed at development of the colony, but to using it to profit the Company. The Company closed the colony against free immigration, kept the whole of the trade in its own hands, combined the administrative, legislative and judicial powers in one body, prescribed to the farmers the nature of the crops they were to grow, demanded a large part of their produce as a kind of tax, and made other exactions.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>:s:1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</target><part>1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</part></link><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>The most complete account of the company's tenure and government of the Cape was written in 1857 by [[Egidius Benedictus Watermeyer|E. B. Watermeyer]], a Cape colonist of Dutch descent residing in Cape Town. He points out that it was only after failing to find a route by the northeast to China and Japan that the Dutch turned their eyes to the Cape route. The Cape of Good Hope subsequently "became not a colony of the Republic of the United Provinces, but a dependency of the ‘Netherlands Chartered General East India Company’ for mercantile purposes; and to this fact principally can be traced the slow progress, in all but extension of territory, of a country which was settled by Europeans within thirty years of the time when the Pilgrim Fathers, the founders of a mighty empire, landed at Plymouth to plant democratic institutions and European civilization in the West."</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>:s:1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</target><part>1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</part></link><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>On the settlement under van Riebeek, and the position in it which the so-called “free burghers” enjoyed, Watermeyer asserts, “The people who came here with Riebeek himself were not colonists intending permanently to settle at the Cape…. The proposition that any freemen or burghers not in the pay of the company should be encouraged to cultivate the ground was first made about three years after Riebeek's arrival. Accordingly, some discharged sailors and soldiers, who received on certain conditions plots of ground extending from the Fresh River to the Liesbeek, were the first free burghers of the colony…. Here it is sufficient to say that, generally, the term ‘free burgher’ was a complete misnomer. The first burghers were, in truth, a mere change from paid to unpaid servants of the company. They thought, in obtaining their discharge, that they had much improved their condition, but they soon discovered the reverse to be the fact. And henceforward, to the end of the last [18th] century we find the constantly repeated and well-founded complaint, that the company and its officers possessed every advantage, while the freemen were not allowed even the fruit of their own toil…. The natural effect of this narrow and tyrannous rule was discontent, amounting often to disaffection. After a time every endeavour was made to escape beyond the immediate control of the authorities. Thus the ‘trekking’ system, with its attendant evils, the bane of South Africa, was born. By their illiberal spirit, which sought but temporary commercial advantage in connexion with the Eastern trade, the Dutch authorities themselves, although generally humanely disposed towards the natives, created the system which caused their oppression and extermination.”</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>:s:1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</target><part>1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</part></link><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>When it is borne in mind that the Dutch at the Cape were for 143 years under the rule of the Dutch East India Company, the importance of a correct appreciation of the nature of that rule to any student of South African history is obvious. No modern writer approaches Watermeyer either in the completeness of his facts or the severity of his indictment.

Referring to the policy of the company, Watermeyer says: — 

The Dutch colonial system as exemplified at the Cape of Good Hope, or rather the system of the Dutch East India Company (for the nation should not wholly suffer under the condemnation justly incurred by a trading association that sought only pecuniary profit), was almost without one redeeming feature, and was a dishonour to the Netherlands' national name. In all things political it was purely despotic; in all things commercial, it was purely monopolist. The Dutch East India Company cared nought for the progress of the colony — provided only that they had a refreshment station for their richly laden fleets, and that the English, French, Danes and Portuguese had not. Whatever tended to infringe in the slightest degree on their darling monopoly was visited with the severest penalties, whether the culprit chanced to be high in rank or low. An instance of this, ludicrous while grossly tyrannical, is preserved in the records. Commander van Quaelbergen, the third of the Dutch governors of the colony, was dismissed from the government in 1667, and expelled the service of the company, because he had interchanged civilities with a French governor bound eastwards, the United Provinces being then at peace with France.

Of this nature was the foreign policy of the Dutch company at the Cape of Good Hope; modified, indeed, in some degree from time to time, but governed by principles of jealous, stringent monopoly until the surrender of the colony by Commissioner Sluysken in 1795. The internal government of the colonists for the entire duration of the East India Company's rule was always tyrannical, often oppressive in the extreme. With proclamations, placaats and statutes abundantly filling huge tomes, the caprice of the governor was in truth the law. A mockery of popular institutions, under the name of a burgher council, indeed existed; but this was a mere delusion, and must not be confounded with the system of local government by means of district burgher councils which that most able man, Commissioner de Mist, sought to establish during the brief government of the Batavian Republic from 1803 to 1806, when the Dutch nation, convinced and ashamed of the false policy by which they had permitted a mere money-making association to disgrace the Batavian name, and to entail degradation on what might have been a free and prosperous colony, sought to redeem their error by making this country a national colonial possession, instead of a slavish property, to be neglected, oppressed or ruined, as the caprice or avarice of its merchant owners might dictate.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Trekboer</heading><paragraph>From time to time, servants in the direct employment of the company were endowed with the right of freeburghers; but the company retained the power to compel them to return into its service whenever they deemed it necessary. This right to force into servitude those who might incur the displeasure of the governor or other high officers was not only exercised with reference to the individuals themselves who had received this conditional freedom; it was claimed by the government to be applicable likewise to the children of all such.</paragraph><paragraph>The effect of this<space/><link><target>tyranny</target></link><space/>was inevitable: it drove men to desperation. They fled from oppression, and even before 1700<space/><link><target>Trekboer</target><part>trekking</part></link><space/>began. In 1780,<space/><link><target>Joachim van Plettenberg</target></link>, the governor, proclaimed the<space/><link><target>Sneeuberge</target></link><space/>to be the northern boundary of the colony, expressing the anxious hope that no more extension should take place, and with heavy penalties forbidding the rambling peasants to wander beyond. In 1789, so strong had feeling amongst the burghers become that delegates were sent from the Cape to interview the authorities at<space/><link><target>Amsterdam</target></link>. After this deputation, some nominal reforms were granted.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>:s:1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</target><part>1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/South Africa</part></link><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>but in 1795 a number of burghers settled in the Swellendam and Graaf Reinet districts drove out the officials of the company and established independent governments. The rebellion was accompanied by an assertion of rights on the part of the burghers or freemen, which contained the following clause, the spirit of which animated many of the Trek Boers: — 

That every Bushman or Hottentot, male or female, whether made prisoner by commanders or caught by individuals, as well in time past as in future, shall for life be the lawful property of such burghers as may possess them, and serve in bondage from generation to generation. And if such Hottentots should escape, the owner shall be entitled to follow them up and to punish them, according to their merits in his discretion.

And as to the ordinary Hottentot, already in service, brought up at the places of Christians, the children of these shall be compelled to serve until their twenty-fifth year, and may not go into the service of any other save with their master's consent; that no Hottentot, in future deserting his service shall be entitled to refuge or protection in any part of the colony, but that the authorities throughout the country shall immediately, whatever be the alleged cause of desertion, send back the fugitive to his master.

After 143 years, the rule of the Dutch East India Company came to an end at the Cape. Watermeyer recapitulates its effects as follows: — 

The effects of this pseudo-colonization were that the Dutch, as a commercial nation, destroyed commerce. The most industrious race of Europe, they repressed industry. One of the freest states in the world, they encouraged a despotic misrule in which falsely-called free citizens were enslaved. These men, in their turn, became tyrants. Utter anarchy was the result. Some national feeling may have lingered, but, substantially, every man in the country, of every hue, was benehted when the incubus of the tyranny of the Dutch East India Company was removed.</arg></template></extension><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Ox-drawn wagons in South Africa</arg></template><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Burchell02.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Descending from the Sneeuberge, a scene near<space/><link><target>Graaff-Reinet</target></link>, by<space/><link><target>William John Burchell</target><part>Burchell</part></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Charles Michell03.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Passing Cradock Pass,<space/><link><target>Outeniqua Mountains</target></link>, by<space/><link><target>Charles Collier Michell</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Daniell Trekboer.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>An<space/><link><target>aquatint</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Samuel Daniell</target></link><space/>of Trekboers making camp.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:TrekBoers crossing the Karoo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Trekboers crossing the<space/><link><target>Karoo</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Charles Davidson Bell</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><paragraph>To this mischievous policy is ascribed that dislike to orderly government, and that desire to escape from its control, which characterized for many generations the boer or farmer class of<space/><link><target>Cape Dutch</target><part>Dutch settlers</part></link><space/>qualities utterly at variance with the character of the<space/><link><target>Dutch people</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/>in their native country. It was largely to escape oppression that the farmers trekked farther and farther from the seat of government. The company, to control the emigrants, established a magistracy at<space/><link><target>Swellendam</target></link><space/>in 1745 and another at<space/><link><target>Graaff Reinet</target></link><space/>in 1786. The<space/><link><target>Gamtoos River</target></link><space/>had been declared, c. 1740, the eastern frontier of the<space/><link><target>Dutch Cape Colony</target><part>colony</part></link>; but it was soon passed. In 1780, however, the Dutch, to avoid collision with the warlike<space/><link><target>Bantu peoples</target><part>Bantu</part></link><space/>tribes advancing south and west from east central Africa, agreed with them to make the<space/><link><target>Great Fish River</target></link><space/>the common boundary. In 1795 the heavily taxed burghers of the frontier districts, who were afforded no protection against the Bantus, expelled the officials of the<space/><link><target>Dutch East India Company</target></link>, and set up independent governments at<space/><link><target>Swellendam</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Graaff Reinet</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>trekboer</target><part>Trek Boers</part></link><space/>of the 19th century were the lineal descendants of the Trek Boers of the 18th century. What they had learnt of government from the Dutch East India Company they carried into the wilderness with them. The end of the 19th century saw a revival of this same tyrannical monopolist policy in the<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target><part>Transvaal</part></link>. If the formula, In all things political, purely despotic; in all things commercial, purely monopolist, was true of the government of the Dutch East India Company in the 18th century, it was equally true of<space/><link><target>Paul Kruger</target><part>Kruger</part></link>'s government in the latter part of the 19th.</paragraph><paragraph>The underlying fact which made the<space/><link><target>great Trek</target><part>trek</part></link><space/>possible is that the Dutch-descended colonists in the eastern and northeastern parts of the colony were not cultivators of the soil, but of purely pastoral and nomadic habits, ever ready to seek new pastures for their flocks and herds, and possessing no special affection for any particular locality. These people, thinly scattered over a wide territory, had lived for so long with little restraint from law that when, in 1815, by the institution of Commissions of Circuit, justice was brought nearer to their homes, various offences were brought to light, the remedying of which caused much resentment.</paragraph><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Trekboer migration map.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>A map of the expansion of the Trekboers (1700-1800)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Nederlandse Kaapkolonie.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Evolution of the<space/><link><target>Dutch Cape Colony</target></link><space/>(1700-1800)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Kapkolonie 1795.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Administrative divisions of the Dutch Cape Colony</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Cape Colony00.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Map of the<space/><link><target>Cape Colony</target></link><space/>in 1809, early<space/><link><target>History of the Cape Colony from 1806 to 1870</target><part>British rule</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><space/>&lt;/center&gt;<template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="quote"><space/>The Dutch colony prospered to the extent that the Cape Town market for agricultural produce became glutted. With market stagnation and with slaves providing most of the manual labour in the colony, there were few economic opportunities for the burgeoning white population. Eventually more than half of these people turned to the self-sufficient life of the trekboeren (literally “wandering farmers” but perhaps better translated as “dispersed ranchers”).<br>The Boers were hostile toward indigenous African peoples, with whom they fought frequent range wars, and toward the government of the Cape, which was attempting to control Boer movements and commerce. They overtly compared their way of life to that of the Israel patriarchs of the Bible, developing independent patriarchal communities based upon a mobile pastoralist economy. Staunch Calvinists, they saw themselves as the children of God in the wilderness, a Christian elect divinely ordained to rule the land and the backward natives therein. By the end of the 18th century the cultural links between the Boers and their urban counterparts were diminishing, although both groups continued to speak a type of Flemish.<ref>[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/71276/Boer Encyclopædia Britannica Online] Boer (people)</ref>
<space/></arg><arg name="source"><space/>[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]]
<space/></arg><arg name="align"><space/>right
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>30%
<space/></arg><arg name="border"><space/>black
<space/></arg><arg name="bgcolor"><space/>orange
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>British involvement</heading><paragraph>In 1795,<space/><link><target>Dutch Republic</target><part>Holland</part></link><space/>having fallen under<space/><link><target>French First Republic</target><part>the revolutionary government of France</part></link>, a British force under<space/><link><target>General (United Kingdom)</target><part>General</part></link><space/>Sir<space/><link><target>James Henry Craig</target></link><space/>was sent to<space/><link><target>Cape Town</target></link><space/>to secure the colony for the prince of Orange a refugee in England against the French.<space/><link><target>Dutch Cape Colony#Commanders and governors of the Cape Colony (16521806)</target><part>The governor of Cape Town</part></link><space/>at first refused to obey the instructions from the prince; but, when the British proceeded to take forcible possession, he capitulated. His action was hastened by the fact that the Khoikhoi, deserting their former masters, flocked to the British standard. The burghers of Graaff Reinet did not surrender until a force had been sent against them; in 1799 and again in 1801 they rose in revolt. In February 1803, as a result of the<space/><link><target>peace of Amiens</target></link><space/>(February 1803), the colony was handed over to the<space/><link><target>Batavian Republic</target></link>, which introduced many needed reforms, as had the British during their eight years' rule. One of the first acts of General Craig had been to abolish torture in the administration of justice. Still the country remained essentially Dutch, and few British settlers were attracted to it. Its cost to the British exchequer during this period was<space/><link><target></target></link>16.000.000. The Batavian Republic entertained very liberal views as to the administration of the country, but they had little opportunity for giving them effect.</paragraph><paragraph>War having broken out in 1803, a British force was once more sent to the Cape. After an engagement (January 1806) on the shores of Table Bay, the Dutch garrison of<space/><link><target>Cape Castle</target></link><space/>surrendered to the British under<space/><link><target>David Baird, 1st Baronet</target><part>Sir David Baird</part></link>, and in 1814 the colony was ceded outright by Holland to<space/><link><target>British Empire</target><part>the British crown</part></link>. At that time the colony extended to the line of mountains guarding the vast central plateau, then called<space/><link><target>San people</target><part>Bushmansland</part></link>, and had an area of about 120.000 sq. m. and a population of some 60.000, of whom 27.000 were whites, 17.000 free Khoikhoi and the rest slaves, mostly imported blacks and Malays.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Dislike of British Rule</heading><paragraph>Although the colony was fairly prosperous, many of the Dutch farmers were as dissatisfied with British rule as they had been with that of the Dutch East India Company, though their grounds for complaint were not the same. In 1792<space/><link><target>Margraviate of Moravia</target><part>Moravian</part></link><space/>missions had been established for the benefit of the<space/><link><target>Khoikhoi</target></link>, and in 1799 the<space/><link><target>London Missionary Society</target></link><space/>began work among both Khoikhoi and<space/><link><target>Bantus</target></link>. The missionaries' championing of Khoikhoi grievances caused much dissatisfaction among the majority of the colonists, whose views temporarily prevailed, for in 1812 an ordinance was issued which empowered magistrates to bind Khoikhoi children as apprentices under conditions differing little from that of<space/><link><target>slavery</target></link>. Meantime, however, the movement for the<space/><link><target>abolition of slavery</target></link><space/>was gaining strength in England, and the missionaries appealed from the colonists to the mother country. An incident which occurred in 18151816 did much to make permanent the hostility of the frontiersmen to the British.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Slachter's Nek</heading><paragraph>A farmer named Frederick Bezuidenhout refused to obey a summons issued on the complaint of a Khoikhoi, and, firing on the party sent to arrest him, was himself killed by the return fire. This caused a small<space/><link><target>rebellion</target></link>, known as<space/><link><target>Slachter's Nek Rebellion</target><part>Slachters Nek</part></link>, in 1815, called the most insane attempt ever made by a set of men to wage war against their sovereign (<link><target>Henry Cloete</target></link>). Upon its suppression five ringleaders were publicly hanged at the spot where they had sworn to expel the English tyrants. The feeling caused by the hanging of these men was deepened by the circumstances of the execution, for the scaffold on which the rebels were simultaneously hanged broke down from their united weight and the men were afterwards hanged one by one. An ordinance was passed in 1827, abolishing the old Dutch courts of landroost and heemraden (resident magistrates being substituted) and establishing that henceforth all legal proceedings should be conducted in English. The granting in 1828, as a result of the representations of the missionaries, of equal rights with whites to the<space/><link><target>Khoikhoi</target></link><space/>and other free<space/><link><target>coloured</target></link><space/>people, the imposition (1830) of heavy penalties for harsh treatment of slaves, and finally the emancipation of the slaves in 1834, were measures which combined to aggravate the farmers' dislike of government. Moreover, the inadequate compensation awarded to slave-owners, and the suspicions engendered by the method of payment, caused much resentment; and in 1835 the farmers again removed to unknown country to escape an unloved government.<space/><link><target>Emigration</target></link><space/>beyond the colonial border had in fact been continuous for 150 years, but it now took on larger proportions.</paragraph><paragraph>Probably the most powerful motive of the<space/><link><target>Great Trek</target></link><space/>was the equality between the black and white races, as proposed by the British. The Boers considered such an equality to be intolerable. This sentiment, which found formal recognition later on in the constitution of the<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target></link>, was held in fullest force by the voortrekkers. The exasperation caused by just grievances unremedied was no stronger a motive with the trekkers than the desire to be free from the restraints imposed on British subjects and the wish to be able to deal with the natives after their own fashion.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Sixth Frontier War</heading><paragraph>[[File:Eastern Frontier, Cape of Good Hope, ca 1835.png|thumb|Eastern frontier of the colony, c. 1835<template><target>legend</target><arg>PaleGreen</arg><arg>Settled colonial area, showing districts established in 1820 (in various shades)</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>white</arg><arg>Neutral zone since 1820, as agreed by [[Lord Charles Somerset|Lord Somerset]] and the [[Ngqika|Gaika]] (Xhosa)</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>yellow</arg><arg>Tribal areas under British administration</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>red</arg><arg>Military forts and district boundaries</arg></template>]]The year which witnessed the emancipation of the slaves and the creation of the first treaty state also saw the beginning of<space/><link><target>Xhosa Wars#Sixth war (18341836)</target><part>another disastrous Frontier war</part></link>. Fighting began in December 1834, and lasted nearly a year. The<space/><link><target>Xhosa people</target><part>Xhosa</part></link><space/>wrought great havoc; and Sir<space/><link><target>Benjamin D'Urban</target></link>, the governor, in order to secure peace, extended the boundary of the colony to the<space/><link><target>Kei River</target></link>. The Xhosa had suffered much<space/><link><target>injustice</target></link>, especially from the<space/><link><target>commando</target></link>-reprisal system, but they had also committed many injustices, and the vacillating policy of the Cape government was largely to blame for the disturbed state of the border. Sir Benjamin's policy, which had support of both Dutch and British colonists, was one of close settlement by whites in certain districts and military control of the Bantus in other regions, and it would have done much to ensure peace.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Lord Glenelg</target></link>, secretary for the colonies in<space/><link><target>Lord Melbourne</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Second Melbourne ministry</target><part>second administration</part></link>, held that the Xhosa were in the right in the quarrel, and he compelled D'Urban to abandon the conquered territory, an unwise decision adopted largely on the advice of<space/><link><target>John Philip (missionary)</target><part>John Philip</part></link><space/>and his supporters. By 1836 a critical state had arisen in South Africa. The colonists had lost their slaves, the eastern frontier was in a state of insecurity,<space/><link><target>History of the Cape Colony from 1806 to 1870#1820 settlers</target><part>the British immigrants of 1820</part></link><space/>were still struggling against heavy odds, and the Dutch colonists were in a state of great indignation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ransford, Oliver. The Great Trek. John Murray. Great Britain. 1972. Page 28.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Great trek</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Great Trek</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Great Trek</target></link><space/>occurred between 1835 and the early 1840s. During that period some 12,000 to 14,000 Boers (including women and children), impatient of British rule, emigrated from<space/><link><target>Cape Colony</target></link><space/>into the great plains beyond the<space/><link><target>Orange River</target></link>, and across them again into<space/><link><target>Natalia Republic</target><part>Natal</part></link><space/>and the vastness of the<space/><link><target>Zoutspansberg</target></link>, in the northern part of the<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target><part>Transvaal</part></link>. Those Trekboere who occupied the eastern Cape were semi-nomadic. A significant number in the eastern Cape frontier later became Grensboere (&quot;border farmers&quot;) who were the direct ancestors of the<space/><link><target>Voortrekkers</target></link>.<link><target>File:Map of the Route of the Dorsland Trekkers.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>210px</part><part>Map of the Route of the<space/><link><target>Dorsland Trek</target><trail>kers</trail></link><space/>(solid line)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Anglo-Boer wars</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>First Boer War</arg><arg>Second Boer War</arg></template>Though the Boers accepted British rule without resistance in 1877, they fought two<space/><link><target>Boer Wars</target></link><space/>in the late 19th century to defend their internationally-recognised independent countries, the republics of the Transvaal (the<space/><link><target>Zuid-Afrikaansche Republiek</target></link>, or ZAR) and the<space/><link><target>Orange Free State</target></link><space/>(OFS), against the threat of annexation by the British Crown.This led the key figure in organising the resistance,<space/><link><target>Paul Kruger</target></link>, into conflict with the British.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Martin<space/></arg><arg name="last">Meredith<space/></arg><arg name="title">Diamonds, Gold, and War: The British, the Boers, and the Making of South Africa<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Public Affairs<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="page">74<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-58648-473-6</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Boer War diaspora</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Afrikaner#Post Boer War diaspora</arg><arg name="l1">Boer War diaspora</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>After the second Anglo-Boer War, a Boer<space/><link><target>diaspora</target></link><space/>occurred. Starting in 1903, the largest group emigrated to the<space/><link><target>Patagonia</target></link><space/>region of<space/><link><target>Argentina</target></link>. Another group emigrated to<space/><link><target>Kenya Colony</target><part>British-ruled Kenya</part></link>, from where most returned to South Africa during the 1930s, while a third group under the leadership of General<space/><link><target>Ben Viljoen</target></link><space/>emigrated to<space/><link><target>Mexico</target></link><space/>and to<space/><link><target>New Mexico</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link><space/>in the southwestern United States.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:JOPIE FOURIE.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Jopie Fourie, executed by firing squad for treason.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Boer Revolt</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Maritz Rebellion</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Maritz Rebellion or the Boer Revolt or the Five Shilling Rebellion or the Third Boer War, occurred in 1914 at the start of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, in which men who supported the re-creation of the old<space/><link><target>Boer republics</target></link><space/>rose up against the government of the<space/><link><target>Union of South Africa</target></link><space/>because they did not want to side with the British against<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>so soon after a long bloody war with the British. Many Boers had<space/><link><target>Germans</target><part>German ancestry</part></link><space/>and many members of the government were themselves former Boer military leaders who had fought with the Maritz rebels against the British in the<space/><link><target>Second Boer War</target></link>. The rebellion was put down by<space/><link><target>Louis Botha</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jan Smuts</target></link>, and the ringleaders received heavy fines and terms of imprisonment. One,<space/><link><target>Jopie Fourie</target></link>, was convicted for treason when, as an officer in the<space/><link><target>South African Army</target><part>Union Defence Force</part></link>, he refused to take up arms with the British, and was executed in 1914.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Characteristics</heading><heading level='3'>Culture</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:TrekBoers crossing the Karoo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Trekboere crossing the<space/><link><target>Karoo</target></link>.</part></link>The desire to wander, known as<space/><italics>trekgees</italics>, was a notable characteristic of the Boers. It figured prominently in the late 17th century when the Trekboere began to inhabit the northern and eastern Cape frontiers, again during the Great Trek when the Voortrekkers left the eastern Cape<space/><italics>en masse</italics>, and after the major republics were established during the Thirstland (<italics>Dorsland</italics>) Trek.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ransford"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://www.ourcivilisation.com/smartboard/shop/ransford/chap13.htm<space/></arg><arg name="first">Oliver<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ransford<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Great Trek<space/></arg><arg name="year">1973<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">13: Epilogue<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-02</arg></template></extension><space/>When one such trekker was asked why he has emigrated he explained, &quot;a drifting spirit was in our hearts, and we ourselves could not understand it. We just sold our farms and set out northwestwards to find a new home.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ransford"></extension>A rustic characteristic and tradition was developed quite early on as Boer society was born on the frontiers of white settlement and on the outskirts of civilisation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Du Toit 1998 1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The separation and declaration of the republics were made out of necessity rather than a personal choice. The Dutch were unwilling to protect the people they abandoned at the<space/><link><target>Cape of Good Hope</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Boer quest for independence manifested in a tradition of declaring republics, which predates the arrival of the British; when the British arrived, Boer republics had already been declared and were in rebellion from the VOC (<link><target>Dutch East India Company</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mills"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://husky1.smu.ca/~wmills/course316/18White_Settlers.html<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wallace G.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Mills<space/></arg><arg name="title">White Settlers in South Africa to 1870<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-02</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Beliefs</heading><paragraph>The Boers of the frontier were known for their independent spirit, resourcefulness, hardiness, and self-sufficiency, whose political notions verged on anarchy but had begun to be influenced by republicanism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mills"></extension><space/>Most of the men were also skilled with the use of<space/><link><target>gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as they would hunt and also were able to protect their families with them.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Boerfamily1886.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Boer family, 1886</part></link>The Boers had cut their ties to Europe as they emerged from the Trekboer group.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ourcivilisation.com/smartboard/shop/ransford/chap1.htm</arg><arg name="first">Oliver<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ransford<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Great Trek<space/></arg><arg name="year">1973<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">1: Trekboers<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-02</arg></template></extension><space/>They developed strong sense of<space/><link><target>independence</target></link>, born out of hundreds of years of fighting against<space/><link><target>imperialism</target></link><space/>and from enduring the harsh African climate.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Calvinism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Afrikaner Calvinism</arg></template>The Boer nation is mainly descended from the Dutch, Germans, and French Huguenots, who migrated to South Africa during the 17th, 18th and early 19th centuries. The Boer nation has revealed a distinct<space/><link><target>Calvinist</target></link><space/>culture and the majority of Boers today are still members of a<space/><link><target>Reformed Church</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Nederduitsch Hervormde Kerk</target></link><space/>was the national Church of the<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target></link><space/>(18521902). The &quot;Orange&quot; in<space/><link><target>Orange Free State</target></link><space/>(18541902) was named after the<space/><link><target>Protestant</target></link><space/><link><target>House of Orange</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Calvinist influence, in such fundamental Calvinist doctrines such as unconditional<space/><link><target>predestination</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>divine providence</target></link>, remains present in much of Boer culture, who see their role in society as abiding by the national laws and accepting calamity and hardship as part of their Christian duty.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.calvinistcorner.com/predestination.htm'>Calvinist Corner.</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.calvinistcorner.com/predestination.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20150205172319<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A small number of Boers may also be members of<space/><link><target>Baptist</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pentecostal movement</target><part>Pentecostal</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target><part>Lutheran Churches</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern usage</heading><paragraph>During recent times, mainly during the<space/><link><target>apartheid</target></link><space/>reform and post-1994 eras, some white<space/><link><target>Afrikaans</target></link>-speaking people, mainly with &quot;conservative&quot; political views and of Trekboer and Voortrekker descent, have chosen to be called &quot;Boere&quot;, rather than &quot;Afrikaners,&quot; to distinguish their identity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="web. archive. org"><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20080422063509/http://www.chico.mweb.co.za/art/2007/2007mar/070309-bang.html'>Yolandi Groenewald. &quot;Bang bang youre dead&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Mail &amp; Guardian Online</italics>.]</extension><space/>They believe that many people of<space/><link><target>Voortrekker</target></link><space/>descent were not assimilated into what they see as the<space/><link><target>Cape Province</target><part>Cape</part></link>-based Afrikaner identity. They suggest that this developed after the<space/><link><target>Second Anglo-Boer War</target></link><space/>and the subsequent establishment of the<space/><link><target>Union of South Africa</target></link><space/>in 1910. Certain Boer nationalists have asserted that they do not identify as a<space/><link><target>Right-wing politics</target><part>right-wing</part></link><space/>element of the political spectrum.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20031001202018/rebellie.org/Raaktief/rk_openletter_ISS.htm'>Dr. Tobias Louw. &quot;Open Letter to the Institute for Security Studies&quot;</link>, 1 October 2003</extension></paragraph><paragraph>They contend that the Boers of the<space/><link><target>South African Republic</target></link><space/>(ZAR) and<space/><link><target>Orange Free State</target></link><space/>republics were recognised as a separate people or cultural group under international law by the<space/><link><target>Sand River Convention</target></link><space/>(which created the South African Republic in 1852),<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.everything2.com/index.pl?node_id=1741482'>The Sand River Convention.</link></extension><space/>the<space/><link><target>Bloemfontein Convention</target></link><space/>(which created the Orange Free State Republic in 1854), the<space/><link><target>Pretoria Convention</target></link><space/>(which re-established the independence of the South African Republic 1881), the<space/><link><target>London Convention (1884)</target><part>London Convention</part></link><space/>(which granted the full independence to the South African Republic in 1884), and the<space/><link><target>Peace of Vereeniging</target><part>Vereeniging Peace Treaty</part></link>, which formally ended the<space/><link><target>Second Anglo-Boer War</target></link><space/>on 31 May 1902. Others contend, however, that these treaties dealt only with agreements between governmental entities and do not imply the recognition of a Boer cultural identity<space/><italics>per se</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The supporters of these views feel that the Afrikaner designation (or label) was used from the 1930s onwards as a means of unifying (politically at least) the white Afrikaans speakers of the Western Cape with those of Trekboer and Voortrekker descent (whose ancestors began migrating eastward during the late 17th century and throughout the 18th century and later northward during the<space/><link><target>Great Trek</target></link><space/>of the 1830s) in the north of South Africa, where the Boer Republics were established.<extension extension_name='ref' name="web. archive. org"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since the Anglo-Boer war, the term &quot;Boerevolk&quot; was rarely used in the 20th century by the various regimes because of the effort to assimilate the Boerevolk with the Afrikaners. A portion of those who are the descendants of the Boerevolk have reasserted use of this designation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="web. archive. org"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The supporters of the &quot;Boer&quot; designation view the term &quot;Afrikaner&quot; as an artificial political label which usurped their history and culture, turning &quot;Boer&quot; achievements into &quot;Afrikaner&quot; achievements. They feel that the Western-Cape based Afrikaners whose ancestors did not trek eastwards or northwards took advantage of the republican Boers' destitution following the Anglo-Boer War. At that time, the Afrikaners attempted to assimilate the Boers into a new politically based cultural label as &quot;Afrikaners&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20080422063509/http://www.chico.mweb.co.za/art/2007/2007mar/070309-bang.html'>Yolandi Groenewald. Bang bang you're dead.&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Mail &amp; Guardian Online,</italics><space/>March 2007</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.oulitnet.co.za/seminarroom/marais_swart.asp'>Sandra Swart. ''Journal of Southern African Studies.'' 30.4, Dec 2004</link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Adriana Stuijt (former South African journalist). &quot;Boer, Afrikaner Or White Which Are You?&quot; 2004.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contemporary South Africa, Boer and Afrikaner have often been used interchangeably. The Boers are the smaller segment within the Afrikaner designation, as the Afrikaners of Cape Dutch origin are more numerous. Afrikaner directly translated means &quot;African,&quot; and thus refers to all Afrikaans-speaking people in Africa who have their origins in the Cape Colony founded by Jan Van Riebeeck. Boer is the specific group within the larger Afrikaans-speaking population.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Politics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Freedom Front Plus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Herstigte Nasionale Party</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Education</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>BCVO</target></link><space/>(Movement for Christian-National Education) is a federation of 47 Calvinist private schools, primarily in the Free State and the Transvaal, committed to educating Boer children from grade 0 through to 12.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bcvo.co.za/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Beweging vir Christelik Volkseie Onderwys<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-01</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Media</heading><paragraph>Some local Radio stations promote the ideals of those who identify with the Boer people, like<space/><link><target>Radio Rosestad</target></link><space/>(in Bloemfontein),<space/><link><target>Overvaal Stereo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Radio Pretoria</target></link>. An internet-based radio station,<space/><italics><link><target>Boerevolk Radio</target></link></italics>, serves as a mouthpiece for Boer separatists.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Territories</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Volkstaat</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Territorial areas are being developed as settlements exclusively for Boer/Afrikaners, notably<space/><link><target>Orania, Northern Cape</target><part>Orania</part></link><space/>in the Northern Cape and<space/><link><target>Kleinfontein</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Pretoria</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Boers</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Voortrekker leaders</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Sarel Cilliers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Andries Hendrik Potgieter</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Andries Pretorius</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Piet Retief</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Great trek</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Racheltjie de Beer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dirkie Uys</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Participants in the Second Anglo-Boer War</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Koos de la Rey</target></link>, general and regarded as being one of the great military leaders of the Second Anglo-Boer War.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Danie Theron</target></link>, soldier</listitem><listitem><link><target>Christiaan Rudolf de Wet</target></link>, general</listitem><listitem><link><target>Siener van Rensburg</target></link>, considered a prophet by some.</listitem><listitem>Sergeant Major Meyder Johannes Leibbrandt, father of<space/><link><target>Robey Leibbrandt</target></link>, German special agent of the<space/><link><target>Abwehr</target></link><space/>during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Politicians</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Louis Botha</target></link>, first prime minister of South Africa (19101919) and former Boer general</listitem><listitem><link><target>Petrus Jacobus Joubert</target></link>, general and cabinet member of the Transvaal Republic</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Kruger</target></link>, president of the<space/><link><target>Transvaal Republic</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Eugene Terre'Blanche</target></link>, founder of the<space/><link><target>Afrikaner Weerstandsbeweging</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Spies</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fritz Joubert Duquesne</target></link>, a Boer Captain known as the<space/><italics>Black Panther</italics>, served in the<space/><link><target>Second Boer War</target></link>. Captured in<space/><link><target>Mozambique</target></link>, he escaped prison in Portugal and returned to South Africa as a British officer. In 1901, he was caught planning to sabotage strategic British installations in<space/><link><target>Cape Town</target></link><space/>and sentenced to life in prison; however, he escaped and was re-captured several times again throughout his life. In<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, Duquesne spied for Germany, earning the<space/><link><target>Iron Cross</target></link><space/>for allegedly sinking the<space/><link><target>HMS Hampshire (1903)</target><part>HMS ''Hampshire''</part></link><space/>thereby killing<space/><link><target>Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener</target><part>Lord Kitchener</part></link><space/>in 1916. He also served as a<space/><link><target>Nazi</target></link><space/>spy in the United States and, in 1941, he was caught by the<space/><link><target>Federal Bureau of Investigation</target></link><space/>(FBI) in the largest espionage case in US history: The<space/><italics><link><target>Duquesne Spy Ring</target></link></italics>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>columns-list</target><arg>4</arg><arg>
* [[Boerboel]]
* ''[[Boerehaat]]''
* [[Boer goat]]
* [[Boer music]]
* [[Great Trek]]
* [[Natalia Republic]]
* [[Orange Free State]]
* [[South African farm attacks]]
* [[South African Republic]]
* [[Transvaal Colony]]
* [[Volkstaat]]
* [[Voortrekker]]
* [[Transvaal civil war]], 1854 conflict</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite NIE</target><arg name="wstitle">Boer</arg><arg name="year">1905<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Commons category-inline</target><arg>Boers</arg></template><template><target>Ethnic slurs</target></template><template><target>Ethnic groups in South Africa</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Afrikaner people</target></link><link><target>Category:South African society</target></link><link><target>Category:Great Trek</target></link><link><target>Category:Dutch words and phrases</target></link><link><target>Category:Afrikaans words and phrases</target></link><link><target>Category:White South African people</target></link></paragraph></article>