<article title='Discordianism'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Sacred Chao</arg><arg>the German thrash metal band by that name</arg><arg>Living Death</arg></template><link><target>File:Eris (Discordia).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Eris (mythology)</target><part>Eris</part></link>, the Greek<space/><link><target>goddess</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>wikt:discord</target><part>discord</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Discordianism</bold><space/>is a religion and subsequent philosophy based on the veneration or worship of the<space/><link><target>Eris (mythology)</target><part>Eris</part></link><space/>Discordia, the Goddess of chaos, or archetypes or ideals associated with her. It was founded after the 1963 publication of its holy book, the<space/><italics><link><target>Principia Discordia</target></link>,</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Wilson</arg><arg name="first1">Robert Anton</arg><arg name="title">Cosmic Trigger I: Final Secret of the Illuminati</arg><arg name="date">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">New Falcon Publications</arg><arg name="location">Scottsdale, AZ</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1561840038</arg><arg name="page">65</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>written by Greg Hill with Kerry Wendell Thornley, the two working under the pseudonyms<space/><link><target>Malaclypse the Younger</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kerry Wendell Thornley</target><part>Omar Khayyam Ravenhurst</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The religion has been likened to<space/><link><target>Zen</target></link><space/>based on similarities with<space/><link><target>absurdism</target><part>absurdist</part></link><space/>interpretations of the<space/><link><target>Rinzai school</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>Taoism</target><part>Taoist</part></link><space/>philosophy. Discordianism is centered on the idea that both<space/><link><target>Cosmos</target><part>order</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Chaos theory</target><part>disorder</part></link><space/>are illusions imposed on the universe by the human<space/><link><target>nervous system</target></link>, and that neither of these illusions of apparent order and disorder is any more accurate or<space/><link><target>Objectivity (philosophy)</target><part>objective</part><trail>ly</trail></link><space/>true than the other.</paragraph><paragraph>There is some division as to whether it should be regarded as a<space/><link><target>parody religion</target></link>, and if so to what degree.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;...It should on no account be taken seriously but is far more serious than most jokes&quot; and &quot;See ... [also]<space/><italics>ha ha only serious</italics>&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/D/Discordianism.html'>The Jargon File v4.4.7</link><space/>but present at least as far back as v4.0.0, (1996, July 24); The entry for discordianism begins, &quot;Somewhere between parody, social commentary, and religion...&quot; Rabinovitch, Shelly &amp;<space/><link><target>James R. Lewis (scholar)</target><part>Lewis, James R.</part></link><space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of Modern Witchcraft and Neo-Paganism</italics>, pp 7576. Citadel Press. 2002. ISBN 0-8065-2406-5; &quot;These organisations [Discordianism &amp; The Church of the Subgenius] are just two of a whole raft of mock religions...&quot; Phillips, M. (2004, Sept. 14). Wizards of ID cook up divine pile of spaghetti bolognese.<space/><italics>The West Australian</italics>, p. Metro 18; &quot;The explosion of the American counter-culture and the revival of surrealism met Discordianism (1960's and 70's) and the result was a Neo-<link><target>Pagan</target></link><space/>parody religion of mirth and laughter.&quot; (p. 3) E. K. Discorida. (2005).<space/><italics>The Book of Eris</italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://syngen.co.uk/'>Synaptyclypse Generator</link></extension><space/>Discordians use<space/><link><target>wikt:subversive</target><part>subversive</part></link><space/>humor to spread their<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>and to prevent their beliefs from becoming dogmatic<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2014</arg></template>. It is difficult to estimate the number of Discordians because they are not required to hold Discordianism as their only belief system,<extension extension_name='ref'>Rabinovitch, Shelly &amp; Lewis, James. ''The Encyclopedia of Modern Witchcraft and Neo-Paganism&quot;. Pp 7576. Citadel Press. 2002. ISBN 0-8065-2406-5.</extension><space/>and because there is an encouragement to form<space/><link><target>schism</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cabal</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a</arg><arg name="title">WitchVox Traditions Discordianism Article<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Witchvox.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-08-31<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20070930154947/http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a</arg><arg name="archivedate">30 September 2007<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://s23.org/wiki/Discordian_Cabals<space/></arg><arg name="title">Discordian Cabals – S23Wiki<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">S23.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-03-26</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Founding</heading><paragraph>The foundational document of Discordianism is the<space/><italics><link><target>Principia Discordia</target></link></italics>, fourth edition, written by<space/><link><target>Malaclypse the Younger</target></link>, an alias of Greg Hill. This book contains many references to an earlier source,<space/><italics><link><target>The Honest Book of Truth</target></link></italics><space/>(HBT). From the quotations, the HBT seems to be arranged like the<space/><link><target>Bible</target></link>, consisting of verses grouped into chapters grouped into books grouped into the HBT itself. The<space/><italics>Principia</italics><space/>includes a large portion (or possibly all) of a chapter of &quot;The Book of Explanations&quot; which recounts how the HBT was revealed to<space/><link><target>Kerry Wendell Thornley</target><part>Lord Omar Khayyam Ravenhurst</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Malaclypse the Younger,<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>, Page 00041</extension><space/>The tale of the discovery of the HBT contains many similarities to the tale of the discovery of the<space/><link><target>Book of Mormon</target></link>, and Ravenhurst had been a<space/><link><target>Mormon</target></link>. It also includes part of the next chapter, telling how the HBT was taken by a garbage collector, who refused to return it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Malaclypse the Younger,<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>, Page 00030</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics><space/>often hints that Discordianism was founded as a<space/><link><target>dialectic</target></link><space/><link><target>antithesis</target></link><space/>to more popular religions based on order, although the<space/><link><target>rhetoric</target></link><space/>throughout the book describes chaos as a much more underlying impulse of the universe. This may have been done with the intention of merely &quot;balancing out&quot; the creative forces of order and disorder, but the focus is on the more disorderly aspects of the world at times the forces of order are even vilified. There are other religions that revere the principles of<space/><link><target>harmonia (mythology)</target><part>harmony</part></link><space/>and order in the Universe, but few that show a respect for the disorder which we all face.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.worldreligions.psu.edu/world_religions15.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">World Religions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Worldreligions.psu.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-08-31</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/d/design.htm#SSH2c.i<space/></arg><arg name="title">Design Arguments for the Existence of God [Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy&#93;<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Iep.utm.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-04-12<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-08-31</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Organization</heading><paragraph>While Discordianism embraces the idea that The Discordian Society has no definition,<extension extension_name='ref'>Malaclypse the Younger,<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>, Page 00032</extension><space/>there is a loose schema present in the Principia Discordia. Discordianism is divided into a number of sects led by Episkopos (<italics>overseer</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>bishop</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Koine Greek</target></link>, the same word used in the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Bishop (Christianity)</target><part>Christian Bishops</part></link>), who have received a unique (and often contradictory) revelation from Eris via their pineal gland. Discordians who do not form their own sects, whether they belong to someone else's sect or not, make up the Legion of Dynamic Discord, and may be referred to as Legionnaires.</paragraph><paragraph>Much of the Principia Discordia is devoted to the<space/><italics>Paratheo-Anametamystikhood Of Eris Esoteric</italics><space/>(POEE), which is the sect of Discordianism founded by Malaclypse the Younger. There are five degrees in the hierarchy of the POEE. The highest order, Popes consist of every person on Earth. Below the Popes is the High Priest, Malaclypse the Younger, who ordains priests and runs the head temple of the POEE, the Joshua Norton Cabal. Below the High Priest are the priests and chaplins, who administer POEE cabals and appoint legionnaire deacons. Below legionnaire deacons are the legionnaire disciples, who may initiate others as legionnaires.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Philosophy</heading><heading level='3'>Cosmogony</heading><paragraph>In typical Discordian fashion, two contradictory creations myths are presented in the Principia Discordia. In one, Primal Chaos is born from an interaction of the Hodge and Podge, and the Force of Discord (said to be a manifestation of the Nonexistent Chao) fathers Eris with the Queen - the whole story paralleling the Five Ages or Five Seasons of Discordianism: Chaos, Discord, Confusion, Bureaucracy and the Aftermath. In the other, Void gives birth to the rival goddesses Eris, who is fertile and creative, and Aneris, who is infertile and destructive. They quarrel due to Aneris' jealousy of her sister, order is created and disorder emerges, and Void births a son, Spirituality. When the quarreling sisters confront Void over Spirituality, he declares that their brother will reside with Aneris, before proceeding to Eris and finally returning to the Void from whence he came. The whole story is an allegory for the journey of the spirit.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pentabarf</heading><paragraph>The Pentabarf is as follows:<extension extension_name='ref' name="pentabarf">Malaclypse the Younger,<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>, Page 00004</extension></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>There is no Goddess but Goddess and She is Your Goddess. There is no Erisian Movement but The Erisian Movement and it is The Erisian Movement. And every Golden Apple Corps is the beloved home of a Golden Worm.</listitem><listitem>A Discordian Shall Always use the Official Discordian Document Numbering System.</listitem><listitem>A Discordian is Required during his early Illumination to Go Off Alone &amp; Partake Joyously of a Hot Dog on a Friday; this Devotive Ceremony to Remonstrate against the popular<space/><link><target>Paganism</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the Day: of<space/><link><target>Catholic</target></link><space/>Christendom (no meat on Friday), of<space/><link><target>Judaism</target></link><space/>(no meat of Pork), of<space/><link><target>Hindi</target><trail>c</trail></link><space/>Peoples (no meat of Beef), of<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(no meat of animal), and of Discordians (No Hot Dog Buns).</listitem><listitem>A Discordian shall Partake of No Hot Dog Buns, for Such was the Solace of Our Goddess when She was Confronted with The Original Snub.</listitem><listitem>A Discordian is Prohibited of Believing What he Reads.</listitem></list><paragraph>The Pentabarf is a set of five rules, supposedly discovered by the Apostle Zarathud, that bears a resemblance to the<space/><link><target>10 Commandments</target></link>. The first point satirizes the Islamic<space/><link><target>shahada</target></link>, the third point mocks dietary restrictions, and the final point mandates skepticism in place of blind faith. The third and fourth laws are designed to contradict each other.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The Sacred Chao</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sacred-Chao.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Sacred Chao</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Sacred Chao is a variation on the Chinese<space/><link><target>Taijitu</target></link><space/>symbol, with a golden apple and pentagon replacing the smaller circles of each half. Rather than symbolizing yin and yang, the Sacred Chao symbolizes the hodge-podge and the eristic and aneristic principles, and has connections to key Discordian doctrines, like the Law of Fives and the story of the Original Snub.</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Hodge-Podge</heading><paragraph>Hodge and Podge occur as terms frequently throughout the Principia Discordia. There is little uniting the usages of these terms, but one instance of note is in one of the creation stories, in which the Primal Chaos emerges from the interactions of the Hodge and Podge.</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Eristic and Aneristic Principles</heading><paragraph>The golden apple symbolizes the eristic principle (disorder). The apple comes from the Original Snub, which is a Discordian retelling of the Greek myth of the wedding of<space/><link><target>Peleus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thetis</target></link><space/>into which the uninvited Eris throws an Apple of Discord with the words Kallisti (&quot;to the fairest&quot;), and the subsequent<space/><link><target>Judgment of Paris</target></link>. The pentagon symbolizes the aneristic principle (order). The pentagon is related to the Law of Fives, which is the Discordian doctrine that all things relate to five in some way (see<space/><link><target>23 Enigma</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>confirmation bias</target></link><space/>for similar concepts.)</paragraph><paragraph>Discordianism attempts to correct two possible errors in thinking: the Eristic and Aneristic Illusions. A distinction is drawn between truth and Truth (similar to the<space/><link><target>Two Truths</target></link><space/>doctrine of Buddhism), and these illusions are what happens when one thinks that a particular perspective of order or disorder is a Truth, and not merely a truth.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Curse of Greyface</heading><paragraph>According to the<space/><italics>Principia</italics>, Greyface existed and had followers whom he encouraged to &quot;Look at all the order around you&quot; (<italics>Principia Discordia</italics><space/>page 00042), and he somehow convinced mankind to agree with his ideas about Serious Order. The<space/><italics>Principia</italics><space/>notes that it is something of a mystery why Greyface gained so many followers when anyone could have looked at all of the<space/><italics>disorder</italics><space/>in the world.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Greyface and his followers took the game of playing at life more seriously than they took life itself and were known even to destroy other living beings whose ways of life differed from their own.</arg><arg>Malaclypse the Younger</arg><arg>''Principia Discordia'', Page 00042</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In addition to the generic advice of cultivating your natural love of chaos and playing with Her, the<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics><space/>provides &quot;The Turkey Curse Revealed by the Apostle Dr. Van Van Mojo&quot; to counteract The Curse of Greyface.<extension extension_name='ref'>Malaclypse the Younger,<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>, Page 64</extension><space/>The Turkey Curse is designed to counteract destructive order. It derives its name from the fact that the incantation resembles the sounds of a turkey.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pineal gland</heading><paragraph>&quot;Consult your<space/><link><target>pineal gland</target></link>&quot; is a common saying in Discordianism. This might be a reference to the ideas of past philosophers, such as<space/><link><target>Ren Descartes</target></link>, who dedicated much time to the study of the pineal gland, calling it the &quot;principal seat of the soul&quot;. He believed it to be the point of connection between the intellect and the body.</paragraph><paragraph>The pineal gland is theorized by some, such as<space/><link><target>Rick Strassman</target></link>, to produce trace amounts of DMT (<link><target>dimethyltryptamine</target></link>), a<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target><part>psychedelic</part></link><space/>chemical which is believed to play a role in dreaming and other mystical states.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://rickstrassman.com/dmt/chaptersummaries.html</arg><arg name="title">Chapter Summaries for DMT: The Spirit Molecule</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-09-12</arg><arg name="author">[[Rick Strassman]]<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20060826175610/http://www.rickstrassman.com/dmt/chaptersummaries.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2006-08-26</arg></template></extension><space/>Endogenous DMT has been detected throughout the human body and in mammalian pineal glands.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F00365510510013604<space/></arg><arg name="title">Potentially hallucinogenic 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor ligands bufotenine and dimethyltryptamine in blood and tissues</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-03-18</arg><arg name="author">Kärkkäinen J., Forsström T., Tornaeus J., Wähälä K., Kiuru P., Honkanen A., Stenman U.-H., Turpeinen U., Hesso A. Scandinavian Journal of Clinical and Laboratory Investigation 65 (3): 189–199.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/bmc.2981/abstract<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Barker SA, Borjigin J, Lomnicka I, Strassman R (Jul 2013). "LC/MS/MS analysis of the endogenous dimethyltryptamine hallucinogens, their precursors, and major metabolites in rat pineal gland microdialysate"<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-03-18</arg><arg name="author">Barker SA, Borjigin J, Lomnicka I, Strassman R</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Discordian-inspired works</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of Discordian works</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>The Illuminatus! Trilogy</target></link></italics>, speculative fiction novels by<space/><link><target>Robert Shea</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Robert Anton Wilson</target></link>, popularized Discordianism with various quotes and references.</listitem><listitem>Discordian texts and scriptures include<space/><italics>Aeturnus Ille Discordia,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#Apocrypha Discordia</target><part>Apocrypha Discordia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#The Black Iron Prison</target><part>The Black Iron Prison</part></link>, The Book of the Apocalypso, The Book of Chaos, The Book of Chaos and Its Virtue, The Book of Eris, The Book of Inconveniences, The Book of Life, Book 5 (The Zenarchist's Cookbook), Chao Te Ching,<space/><link><target>A Discordian Coloring Book</target></link>,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#Ek-sen-trik-kuh Discordia: The Tales of Shamlicht</target><part>Ek-sen-trik-kuh Discordia: The Tales of Shamlicht</part></link>,<space/><link><target>The Honest Book of Truth</target></link></italics><space/>(portions of which are used in<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics>), Jonesboria Discordia, Lorem Ipsum Discordiana,<space/><link><target>Principia Discordia</target></link>, Metaclysmia Discordia, Novus Ordo Discordia, Principia Entropius, Principia Harmonia,<space/><link><target>Schrdinger's Cat Trilogy</target></link>, The Shamlicht Kids Club Handbook, Summa Discordia,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#Voices of Chaos</target><part>Voices of Chaos</part></link>, Warehouse 23, The Wise Book of Baloney,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#Zen Without Zen Masters</target><part>Zen Without Zen Masters</part></link>,<space/><link><target>List of Discordian works#Zenarchy</target><part>Zenarchy</part></link><italics>, and<space/></italics>Zenarchy Unapologia''.</listitem><listitem><link><target>The KLF</target></link>'s entire body of work is Discordian both in subject matter and in approach.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Absurdism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Church of the SubGenius</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chaos magic</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Critical rationalism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Philosophical Taoist</target><part>Daojia</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Devival</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Epistemological anarchism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Emperor Norton</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Operation Mindfuck</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Schrdinger's Cat Trilogy</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Subjectivism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Surrealism</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Illuminatus! Trilogy</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Trivialism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rinzai school</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Anton Wilson</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Zenarchy</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://principiadiscordia.com'>PrincipiaDiscordia.com</link><space/>contains the<space/><italics>Principia Discordia</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>HTML</target></link>. Also has Discordian<space/><link><target>message boards</target></link><space/>and other resources.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://appendix.23ae.com/archives.html'>The Semi-Official Quasi-Clandestine Bavarian Illuminati/Discordian Archives</link><space/>An archive of early Discordian documents, photos and paraphernalia.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://calendar.discordipedia.org/'>Discordian Calendar Calculator</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://nmrk2359.wix.com/dolmmm'>Discordian Online Library of the M'.'M'.'M'.'</link><space/>A vast collection of various Discordian documents they have collected that are considered important (or not) by the various cabal's/groups/individuals among the Discordian community.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jubal.westnet.com/hyperdiscordia/'>HyperDiscordia</link><space/>hypertext Discordian encyclopedia.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.kbuxton.com/discordia/'>Kristin Buxton's Discordianism site</link><space/>long-standing Web repository of Discordiana</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/19990117002658/http://www.cs.monash.edu.au/~acb/discordianism/saints.html'>Discordian Saints</link><space/>1999 archive from Andrew C. Bulhak.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.groovygravytrain.i8.com/Discordia2.htm'>The Discordian Saints</link><space/>compiles 4 lists (Andrew Bulhak as anon.; Pope Icky Fundament, PZK; Tonisoa Postatis; Snorri Abrahamsem)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.elsewhere.org/ddeck/'>Discordian Tarot with 'Reading'</link><space/>the free deck consists of 73 cards, incl. 23 Trumps (also as<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.elsewhere.org/ddeck/v2/discocardsall.pdf'>PDF</link>, 0.7 MB)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Discordianism</target><arg name="state">expanded</arg></template><template><target>Robert Anton Wilson</target></template><template><target>Greek religion</target></template><template><target>New religious movements</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Discordianism</target><part>*</part></link></paragraph></article>