<article title='Das_Boot'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the Wolfgang Petersen film</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Das Boot (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Infobox film</target><arg name="name"><space/>Das Boot
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Das_boot_ver1.jpg
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Original 1981 theatrical poster
</arg><arg name="director"><space/>[[Wolfgang Petersen]]
</arg><arg name="producer"><space/>[[Günter Rohrbach]]
</arg><arg name="screenplay"><space/>Wolfgang Petersen
</arg><arg name="based on"><space/>{{Based on|''[[Das Boot (novel)|Das Boot]]''|[[Lothar-Günther Buchheim]]}}
</arg><arg name="narrator"><space/>[[Herbert Grönemeyer]] {{small|(Uncut version)}}
</arg><arg name="starring"><space/>[[Jürgen Prochnow]]<br />[[Herbert Grönemeyer]]<br />[[Klaus Wennemann]]
</arg><arg name="music"><space/>[[Klaus Doldinger]]
</arg><arg name="cinematography"><space/>[[Jost Vacano]]
</arg><arg name="editing"><space/>[[Hannes Nikel]]
</arg><arg name="studio"><space/>[[Bavaria Film]]<br />[[Producers Sales Organization|PSO International]]
</arg><arg name="distributor"><space/>[[Columbia Pictures]]
</arg><arg name="released"><space/>{{Film date|1981|9|17|df</arg><arg name="runtime"><space/>149 minutes<br />209 minutes {{small|([[Director's cut]])}}<br />293 minutes {{small|(Uncut)}}
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>West Germany
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>German<br />English<br />French
</arg><arg name="budget"><space/>32 million [[German mark|DM]] {{small|($12 million)}}<br />{{small|([[Euro|€]]24.3 million, ''2009'')}}
</arg><arg name="gross"><space/>$84.9 million<ref>[http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/1982/0DABO.php Box Office Information for ''Das Boot''.] The Numbers. Retrieved March 27, 2013.</ref>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold><italics>Das Boot</italics></bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-de</target><arg>das ˈboːt</arg></template>, German meaning &quot;<bold>The Boat</bold>&quot;) is a 1981<space/><link><target>Cinema of Germany</target><part>German</part></link><space/><link><target>Epic film</target><part>epic</part></link><space/><link><target>war film</target></link><space/>written and directed by<space/><link><target>Wolfgang Petersen</target></link>, produced by Gnter Rohrbach, and starring<space/><link><target>Jrgen Prochnow</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Herbert Grnemeyer</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Klaus Wennemann</target></link>. It has been exhibited both as a<space/><link><target>theatrical release</target></link><space/>and as a TV<space/><link><target>miniseries</target></link>, and in several different<space/><link><target>home video</target></link><space/>versions of various running times.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Das Boot</italics><space/>is an adaptation of the 1973 German novel of the same name by<space/><link><target>Lothar-Gnther Buchheim</target></link>. Set during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, the film tells the fictional story of U-96 and its crew. It depicts both the excitement of battle and the tedium of the fruitless hunt, and shows the men serving aboard<space/><link><target>U-boat#World War II</target><part>U-boats</part></link><space/>as ordinary individuals with a desire to do their best for their comrades and their country. The screenplay used an amalgamation of exploits from the real<space/><template><target>GS</target><arg>U-96</arg><arg>1940</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, a<space/><link><target>German Type VII submarine</target><part>Type VIIC-class U-boat</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Development for<space/><italics>Das Boot</italics><space/>began in 1979. Several American directors were considered three years earlier before the film was shelved. During the film's production,<space/><link><target>Heinrich Lehmann-Willenbrock</target></link>, the captain of the real<italics><space/>U-96</italics><space/>and one of Germany's top U-boat &quot;tonnage aces&quot; during the war, and Hans-Joachim Krug, former first officer on<space/><template><target>GS</target><arg>U-219</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, served as consultants. One of Petersen's goals was to guide the audience through &quot;a journey to the edge of the mind&quot; (the film's German tagline<space/><italics>Eine Reise ans Ende des Verstandes</italics>), showing &quot;what war is all about&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Produced with a budget of 32 million<space/><link><target>Deutsche Mark</target><part>DM</part></link><space/>(about $18.5 million), the film was released on September 17, 1981, and was later released in 1997 in a<space/><link><target>director's cut</target></link><space/>version supervised by Petersen. It grossed over $80 million ($<template><target>Inflation</target><arg>US</arg><arg>80</arg><arg>1981</arg><arg name="r">0</arg></template><space/>million in #expr: prices) worldwide between its theatrical releases and received critical acclaim. Its high production cost ranks it among the most expensive films in the history of<space/><link><target>Cinema of Germany</target><part>German cinema</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot</heading><paragraph>The story is told from the viewpoint of Lt. Werner (<link><target>Herbert Grnemeyer</target></link>), who has been assigned as a<space/><link><target>war correspondent</target></link><space/>on the German submarine<space/><italics><link><target>German submarine U-96 (1940)</target><part>U-96</part></link></italics><space/>in October 1941. He meets its captain (<link><target>Jrgen Prochnow</target></link>), chief engineer (<link><target>Klaus Wennemann</target></link>), and the crew in a French nightclub. Thomsen (<link><target>Otto Sander</target></link>), another captain, gives a crude drunken speech to celebrate his<space/><link><target>Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross</target><part>''Ritterkreuz'' award</part></link>, in which he openly mocks not only<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link><space/>but implicitly<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target></link><space/>as well.</paragraph><paragraph>The next morning, they sail out of the<space/><link><target>harbour</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>La Rochelle</target></link><space/>to a cheering crowd and playing band. Werner is given a tour of the boat. As time passes, he observes ideological differences between the new crew members and the hardened veterans, particularly the captain, who is embittered and cynical about the war. The new men, including Werner, are often mocked by the rest of the crew, who share a tight bond. After days of boredom, the crew is excited by another U-boat's spotting of an enemy convoy, but they soon locate a British<space/><link><target>destroyer</target></link>, and are bombarded with<space/><link><target>depth charge</target><trail>s</trail></link>. They narrowly escape with only light damage.</paragraph><paragraph>The next three weeks are spent enduring a relentless storm. Morale drops after a series of misfortunes, but the crew is cheered temporarily by a chance encounter with Thomsen's boat. Shortly after the storm ends, the boat encounters a British<space/><link><target>convoy</target></link><space/>and quickly launches four torpedoes, sinking two ships. They are spotted by a destroyer and have to dive below the<space/><link><target>Submarine depth ratings</target><part>submarine's rated limit</part></link>. During the ensuing depth-charge attack, the chief mechanic, Johann, panics and has to be restrained. The boat sustains heavy damage, but is eventually able to safely surface in darkness. An enemy tanker remains afloat and on fire, so they torpedo the ship, only to realize that there are still sailors aboard; they watch in horror as the sailors, some on fire, leap overboard and swim towards them. Following<space/><link><target>War Order No. 154</target><part>orders not to take prisoners</part></link>, the captain gives the command to back the ship away.</paragraph><paragraph>The worn-out U-boat crew looks forward to returning home to La Rochelle in time for<space/><link><target>Christmas</target></link>, but the ship is ordered to<space/><link><target>La Spezia</target></link>, Italy, which means passing through the<space/><link><target>Strait of Gibraltar</target></link>an area heavily defended by the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>. The U-boat makes a secret night rendezvous at the harbour of<space/><link><target>Vigo</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>Neutral country</target><part>neutral</part></link><space/>although Axis-friendly Spain, with the<space/><link><target>SS Weser</target><part>SS ''Weser''</part></link>, an<space/><link><target>interned</target></link><space/>German<space/><link><target>merchant ship</target></link><space/>that clandestinely provides U-boats with fuel, torpedoes, and other supplies. The filthy officers seem out of place on the opulent luxury liner, but are warmly greeted by enthusiastic officers eager to hear their exploits. The captain learns from an envoy of the German consulate that his request for Werner and the chief engineer to be sent back to Germany has been denied.</paragraph><paragraph>The crew finishes resupplying and departs for Italy. As they carefully approach Gibraltar and are just about to dive, they are suddenly attacked by a British<space/><link><target>fighter plane</target></link>, wounding the navigator. The captain orders the boat directly south towards the African coast at full speed. British ships begin closing in and they are forced to dive; it is later implied that the ships used<space/><link><target>radar</target></link><space/>to locate the sub. When attempting to level off, the boat does not respond and continues to sink until, just before being crushed by the pressure, it lands on a sea shelf, at the depth of 280 metres. The crew work desperately to make numerous repairs before running out of oxygen. After over 16 hours, they are able to surface by blowing out their<space/><link><target>ballast tank</target><part>ballast</part></link><space/>of water, and limp back to La Rochelle under cover of darkness.</paragraph><paragraph>The crew is pale and weary upon reaching La Rochelle on<space/><link><target>Christmas Eve</target></link>. Shortly after the wounded navigator is taken ashore to a waiting ambulance,<space/><link><target>Allies of World War II</target><part>Allied</part></link><space/>planes bomb and strafe the facilities, wounding or killing many of the crew. Ullmann, Johann and the 2nd Watch Officer are killed. Frenssen,<space/><italics>Bootsmann</italics><space/>Lamprecht and Hinrich are seriously wounded. After the raid, Werner leaves the<space/><link><target>submarine pen</target><part>U-boat bunker</part></link><space/>in which he had taken shelter and finds the captain, badly injured by shrapnel and bleeding from the mouth, watching the U-boat sink at the dock. Just after the boat disappears under the water, the captain collapses and dies. Werner runs to his body, recoils, and quickly glances around at the destruction, his face frozen with distress. He then looks down at the captain's body, with tears in his eyes.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cast</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:DasBootcast.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The U-96 officers. From<space/><template><target>abbr</target><arg>l.<space/></arg><arg>left</arg></template><space/>to<space/><template><target>abbr</target><arg>r.<space/></arg><arg>right</arg></template>: the II. WO (Semmelrogge), the Commander (Prochnow), Navigator Kriechbaum (Tauber), the I. WO (Bengsch), Lt. Werner (Grnemeyer), &quot;Little&quot; Benjamin (Hoffmann), Cadet Ullmann (May), and Pilgrim (Fedder).</part></link><link><target>File:DasbootLIJohann.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Johann (Leder) and the LI (Wennemann) inspecting the engine.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Jrgen Prochnow</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Captain lieutenant</target><part>Kapitnleutnant</part></link><space/>(abbr. &quot;Kaleun&quot;,<space/><template><target>IPA-de</target><arg>kaˈlɔɪ̯n</arg></template>) and also called &quot;Der Alte&quot; (&quot;The Old Man&quot;) by his crew: A 30-year-old battle-hardened sea veteran, who complains to Werner that most of his crew are boys.<extension extension_name='ref'>See comment by Wolfgang Petersen in 'Extra Features' --&gt; 'The Making Of/Behind The Scenes,<space/><italics>Das Boot: The Director's Cut</italics><space/>(1997). DVD.</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Herbert Grnemeyer</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Leutnant</italics><space/>(Ensign) Werner, War Correspondent: The naive but honest narrator sent out to sea with the crew to gather photographs of them in action and bring them back to use for Nazi Propaganda purposes. Werner is mocked for his lack of experience, and soon learns the true horrors of service on a U-boat. (Actually he is the narrator of the story; this is not made explicit in the movie, but still present in the background.)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Klaus Wennemann</target></link><space/>as Chief Engineer (<italics>Leitender Ingenieur</italics><space/>or LI, Rank:<space/><italics>Oberleutnant</italics>): A quiet and well-respected man. At age 27, the oldest crew member besides the Captain. Tormented by the uncertain fate of his wife, especially after hearing about an Allied<space/><link><target>Strategic bombing during World War II</target><part>air raid</part></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Cologne</target></link>. The second most important crewman, as he oversees diving operations and makes sure the systems are running correctly.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hubertus Bengsch</target></link><space/>as 1st Watch Officer (I. WO, Rank:<space/><italics>Oberleutnant</italics>): A young, by-the-book officer, an ardent Nazi and a staunch believer in victory. He has a condescending attitude and is the only crewman who makes the effort to maintain his proper uniform and trim appearance. Raised in some wealth in Mexico by his stepparents who owned a plantation. His German fiance died in a British air raid. He spends his days writing his thoughts on military training and leadership for the High Command.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Martin Semmelrogge</target></link><space/>as 2nd Watch Officer (II. WO, Rank:<space/><italics>Oberleutnant</italics>): A vulgar, comedic officer. He is short, red-haired and speaks with a mild<space/><link><target>Berlinerisch dialect</target><part>Berlin dialect</part></link>. One of his primary duties is to decode messages from base, using the<space/><link><target>Enigma machine</target><part>Enigma code machine</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bernd Tauber</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Obersteuermann</italics><space/>(&quot;Chief Helmsman&quot;) Kriechbaum: The navigator and 3rd Watch Officer (III. WO). Always slightly skeptical of the Captain and without enthusiasm during the voyage, he shows no anger when a convoy is too far away to be attacked. Kriechbaum has four sons, with another on the way.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Erwin Leder</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Obermaschinist</italics><space/>(&quot;Chief Mechanic&quot;) Johann, also called &quot;Das Gespenst&quot; (&quot;The Ghost&quot;): He is obsessed with a near-fetish love for the<space/><italics>U-96</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s engines. Johann suffers a temporary mental breakdown during an attack by two destroyers. He is able to redeem himself by valiantly working to stop water leaks when the boat is trapped underwater near Gibraltar. Speaks<space/><link><target>Austro-Bavarian language</target><part>Austro-Bavarian</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>Martin May as<space/><italics>Fhnrich</italics><space/>(Senior Cadet) Ullmann: A young officer candidate who has a pregnant<space/><link><target>French people</target><part>French</part></link><space/>fiance (which is considered treason by the French<space/><link><target>French Resistance</target><part>partisans</part></link>) and worries about her safety. He is one of the few crew members with whom Werner is able to connect; Werner offers to deliver Ullmann's stack of love letters when Werner is ordered to leave the submarine.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Heinz Hoenig</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Maat</italics><space/>(Petty Officer) Hinrich: The radioman, sonar controller and ship's<space/><link><target>combat medic</target></link>. He is in many ways the third most important crewman, since he gauges speed and direction of targets and enemy destroyers. Hinrich is one of the few officers that the Captain is able to relate to.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Uwe Ochsenknecht</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Bootsmann</italics><space/>(&quot;Boatswain&quot;) Lamprecht: The severe chief who shows Werner around the<space/><italics>U-96</italics>, and supervises the firing and reloading of the torpedo tubes. He gets upset after hearing on the radio that the football team most of the crew supports (<link><target>FC Schalke 04</target></link>) are losing a match, and they will &quot;never make the final now&quot;. He speaks a<space/><link><target>Mannheim</target></link><space/>dialect.</listitem><listitem>Claude-Oliver Rudolph as Ario: The burly mechanic who tells everyone that Dufte is getting married to an ugly woman, and throws pictures around of Dufte's fiance in order to laugh at them both.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jan Fedder</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Maat</italics><space/>(Petty Officer) Pilgrim: Another sailor (watch officer and diving planes operator), gets almost swept off the submarine during a storma genuine accident during filming in which Fedder broke several ribs and was hospitalised for a while.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><space/>Speaks<space/><link><target>Hamburgisch</target><part>Hamburg dialect</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ralf Richter (actor)</target><part>Ralf Richter</part></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Maat</italics><space/>(Petty Officer) Frenssen: Pilgrim's best friend. Pilgrim and Frenssen love to trade dirty jokes and stories. He speaks<space/><link><target>Ruhr</target><part>Ruhr dialect</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>Joachim Bernhard as<space/><italics>Bibelforscher</italics><space/>(&quot;Bible scholar&quot;, also the contemporary German term for a member of<space/><link><target>Jehovah's Witnesses</target></link>): A very young religious sailor who is constantly reading the Bible. He is punched by Frenssen when the submarine is trapped at the bottom of the Straits of Gibraltar for praying rather than repairing the boat.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Oliver Stritzel</target></link><space/>as Schwalle: A tall and well-built blond torpedoman who speaks<space/><link><target>Berlinerisch</target><part>Berlin dialect</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>Jean-Claude Hoffmann as Benjamin: A red haired sailor who serves as a diving planes operator and watch officer.</listitem><listitem>Lutz Schnell as Dufte: The sailor who gets jeered at because he is getting married, and for a possible false airplane sighting.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Konrad Becker</target></link><space/>as Bckstiegel: the sailor who is first visited by Hinrich for crab lice. Speaks Austro-Bavarian of the very distinctive<space/><link><target>Vienna</target><part>Viennese</part></link><space/>variation</listitem><listitem><link><target>Otto Sander</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Kapitnleutnant</italics><space/>Philipp Thomsen: An alcoholic and<space/><link><target>combat stress reaction</target><part>shell-shocked</part></link><space/>U-boat commander, who is a member of &quot;The Old Guard&quot;. When he is introduced, he is extremely drunk and briefly mocks both Hitler and Winston Churchill on the stage of a French nightclub. (In the audio commentary of the director's-cut DVD, Petersen says that Sander was really drunk while they were shooting the scene.) Sometime after<space/><italics>U-96</italics><space/>departs, Thomsen is deployed once again and the two submarines meet randomly in the middle of the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target></link><space/>being put off course by the storm. This upsets the captain because it means that there is now a gap in the blockade chain. After failing to make contact later, it becomes apparent that Thomsens boat is missing.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gnter Lamprecht</target></link><space/>as the Captain of the<space/><italics>Weser</italics><space/>(rank:<space/><italics>Kapitn zur See</italics>): An enthusiastic officer aboard the resupply ship<space/><italics>Weser</italics>. He mistakes the I. WO for the Captain as they enter the ship's elegant dining room. An ardent<space/><link><target>Nazi</target></link>, he complains about the frustration of not being able to fight, but boasts about the food that has been prepared for the crew and the ship's &quot;specialities&quot;.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sky du Mont</target></link><space/>as an<space/><italics>Oberleutnant</italics><space/>aboard the<space/><italics>Weser</italics><space/>(uncredited). The II. WO amuses him with a comical demonstration of depth charging, involving a bowl of punch, a ladle and oranges.</listitem></list><paragraph>The film features both Standard German-speakers and<space/><link><target>dialect</target></link><space/>speakers. Petersen states in his DVD audio commentary that young men from throughout Germany and Austria were recruited for the film, as he wanted faces and dialects that would accurately reflect the diversity of the<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target><part>Third Reich</part></link>, around 1941. All of the main actors are bilingual in German and English, and when the film was dubbed into English, each actor recorded his own part (with the exception of Martin Semmelrogge, who only dubbed his own role in the Director's Cut). The German version is dubbed as well, as the film was shot &quot;silent&quot;, because the dialogue spoken on-set would have been drowned out by the<space/><link><target>gyroscope</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the special camera developed for filming.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Production</heading><heading level='3'>Sets and models</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Baselapallice08.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>U-boat pens</target></link><space/>at the harbor of<space/><link><target>La Rochelle</target></link><space/>(2007)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>coord</target><arg>46</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>32</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>1</arg><arg>12</arg><arg>33</arg><arg>W</arg><arg>type:landmark_scale:3000_region:FR</arg><arg name="display">inline</arg></template></part></link><link><target>File:U995 2004 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>U 995</target></link>, a U-boat of the version VII-C/41, at its exhibition in<space/><link><target>Laboe</target></link><space/>in 2004</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 1</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 4</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 5.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 5</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 6.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Bavaria Filmstudio Das Boot 6</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><paragraph>The interior U-boat mock-up was mounted five metres off the floor and was shaken, rocked, and tilted up to 45 degrees by means of a hydraulic apparatus, and was vigorously shaken to simulate depth charge attacks. Petersen was admittedly obsessive about the structural detail of the U-boat set, remarking that &quot;every screw&quot; in the set was an authentic facsimile of the kind used in a<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>U-boat. In this he was considerably assisted by the numerous photographs<space/><link><target>Lothar-Gnther Buchheim</target></link><space/>had taken during his own voyage on the historical<space/><italics>U-96</italics>, some of which had been published in his 1976 book,<space/><xhtml:cite>U-Boot-Krieg</xhtml:cite><space/>(&quot;U-Boat War&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Special camera</heading><paragraph>Most of the interior shots were filmed using a hand-held<space/><link><target>Arriflex</target></link><space/>of cinematographer<space/><link><target>Jost Vacano</target></link>'s design to convey the claustrophobic atmosphere of the boat. It had two gyroscopes to provide stability, a different and smaller scale solution than the<space/><link><target>Steadicam</target></link>, so that it could be carried throughout the interior of the mock-up.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://vimeo.com/19688881'>''SOC 2011 Historical Shot: Das Boot by Jost Vacano''</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Versions</heading><paragraph>Several versions of the film and video releases have been made: The first version to be released was the theatrical 150-minute (2-hour) cut, released to theatres in Germany in 1981, and in the United States in 1982. It was nominated for six<space/><link><target>Academy Award</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(<link><target>Academy Award for Best Cinematography</target><part>Cinematography</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Best Director</target><part>Directing</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Film Editing</target><part>Film Editing</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Best Sound</target><part>Sound</part></link><space/>(<link><target>Milan Bor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Trevor Pyke</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mike Le Mare</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Sound Editing</target><part>Sound Effects Editing</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Writing Adapted Screenplay</target><part>Writing</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oscars1983"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.oscars.org/oscars/ceremonies/1983<space/></arg><arg name="title">The 55th Academy Awards (1983) Nominees and Winners<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-10-09</arg><arg name="work">oscars.org</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The film was partly financed by the German television broadcasters<space/><link><target>Westdeutscher Rundfunk</target><part>WDR</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Sddeutscher Rundfunk</target><part>SDR</part></link>, and much more footage had been shot for the film than was shown in the theatrical version. A version of three 100-minute episodes was transmitted on<space/><link><target>BBC Two</target></link><space/>in the United Kingdom in October 1984, and in Germany and Austria the following year. In 1988 a version comprising six 50-minute episodes was screened. These episodes had additional cutback scenes summarising past episodes.</paragraph><paragraph>Petersen then oversaw the editing of six hours of film, from which was distilled<space/><italics>Das Boot: The Director's Cut</italics>, 209 minutes long (3 hours, 29 minutes). Released in 1997, this cut combines the action sequences seen in the feature-length version with character development scenes contained in the mini-series. This release also provides better sound and video quality.<extension extension_name='ref'>Original Movie Website restoration information --&gt; http://www.dasboot.com/classics.htm</extension><space/>Petersen originally had planned to release this version in 1981, which for commercial reasons was not possible. The Director's Cut was released to cinemas in Germany on 11 December and on 4 April 1997 in the U.S. In addition to the &quot;Director's Cut&quot; DVD, a<space/><link><target>Superbit</target></link><space/>version, with fewer additional DVD features but a higher bit-rate (superior quality), was released by Columbia Pictures.</paragraph><paragraph>An uncut miniseries version, running 293 minutes (four hours, 53 minutes), was released to DVD on 1 June 2004, as<space/><italics>Das Boot: The Original Uncut Version</italics><space/>with enhanced video and audio quality. It omits the cutback scenes of the 1988 television broadcast and is therefore shorter.</paragraph><paragraph>On 14 October 2010, the 208-minute &quot;Director's Cut&quot; was released on a German-language<space/><link><target>Blu-ray Disc</target></link><space/>in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bluray-disc.de/blu-ray-filme/das-boot-blu-ray-disc<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Das Boot (Directors Cut) Blu-ray<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2014-03-16</arg></template></extension><space/>It was released in the United States on 5 July 2011. The shortest version begins an evening in a French nightclub. The longer begins in a car that is driving to the same place, and several drunken sailors are urinating at the car, in which the U-boat commander and the guest reporter are sitting. The commander does not care, but later the new German-Mexican volunteer officer complains about it. This complaint is also cut in the short version, hence the introduction of this officer becomes very short. The long version was released for at least cinemas in Sweden at the time (a long time before 1997).</paragraph><heading level='3'>List</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>150 minutes (1981, 1982) Theatrical</listitem><listitem>209 minutes (1981) unreleased</listitem><listitem>300 minutes (1984, 1988) BBC mini-series</listitem><listitem>208 minutes (1997) Director's Cut</listitem><listitem>293 minutes (2004)<space/><italics>Das Boot: The Original Uncut Version</italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Reception</heading><heading level='3'>Critical response</heading><paragraph>The film drew highest critical acclaim and is seen as<space/><link><target>Films considered the greatest ever#Germany</target><part>one of the greatest of all German films</part></link>. The film currently has a &quot;certified fresh&quot; score of 98% based on 46 reviews with an average rating of 9 out of 10 on<space/><link><target>Rotten Tomatoes</target></link>. The critical consensus states &quot; Taut, breathtakingly thrilling, and devastatingly intelligent, Das Boot is one of the greatest war films ever made.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/das_boot/?search=das%20boot</extension><space/>The film also has a score of 86 out of 100 on<space/><link><target>Metacritic</target></link><space/>based on 15 critics indicating &quot;universal acclaim&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.metacritic.com/movie/das-boot</extension><space/>For its unsurpassed authenticity in tension and realism, it is regarded internationally as pre-eminent among all submarine films. The film was ranked #25 in<space/><italics><link><target>Empire (magazine)</target><part>Empire</part></link></italics><space/>magazine's &quot;The 100 Best Films Of World Cinema&quot; in 2010.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>The 100 Best Films Of World Cinema – 25. Das Boot
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.empireonline.com/features/100-greatest-world-cinema-films/default.asp?film</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Empire
</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>In late 2007, there was an exhibition about the film<space/><italics>Das Boot</italics>, as well as about the real U-Boat<space/><italics>U-96</italics>, at the<space/><link><target>Haus der Geschichte</target></link><space/>(House of German History) in<space/><link><target>Bonn</target></link>. Over 100,000 people visited the exhibition during its four-month run.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Promotion</heading><paragraph>The film was unusual in its North American promotion, since it was referred to both in German as<space/><italics>Das Boot</italics>, and in English as<space/><italics>The Boat</italics>. The lack of drama in the translated title eventually led to its being marginalized, with<space/><italics>Das Boot</italics><space/>becoming the normal title for the film.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Historical accuracy</heading><paragraph>Even though the beginning and the end of the film occur in the port of<space/><link><target>La Rochelle</target></link>, it does not correspond historically. The<space/><link><target>submarine base</target></link><space/>in La Rochelle was not functional before November 1941, and at the time of the film the port was dried up.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://francois.delboca.free.fr/fsbase.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">History of the submarine base of La Rochelle</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Criticism by novelist Buchheim</heading><paragraph>Even though impressed by the technological accuracy of the film's set-design and port construction buildings, novelist<space/><link><target>Lothar-Gnther Buchheim</target></link><space/>expressed great disappointment with Petersen's adaptation in a film review<extension extension_name='ref' name="buchheim">Lothar-Gnter Buchheim (1981).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/~junghans/dasboot/inhalt.html'>''Kommentar - Die Wahrheit blieb auf Tauchstation''</link><space/>(&quot;Commentary: The truth remained hidden under the sea&quot;),<space/><italics>Geo</italics>, no. 10, 1981</extension><space/>published in 1981, especially with Petersen's aesthetic vision for the film and the way the plot and the effects are, according to him, overdone and clichd by the adaptation. He also criticised the hysterical overacting of the cast, which he called highly unrealistic, while acknowledging the cast's acting talent in general. Buchheim, after several attempts for an American adaptation had failed, had provided a script detailing his own narrative, cinematographical and photographical ideas as soon as Petersen was chosen as new director. It would have amounted in full to a complete six-hour epic; however, Petersen turned him down because at the time the producers were aiming for a 90-minute feature for international release. However, today's Director's Cut of<space/><italics>Das Boot</italics><space/>amounts to over 200 minutes, and the complete TV version of the film is 282 minutes long.</paragraph><paragraph>Buchheim, himself a U-boat correspondent, attacked specifically what he called Petersen's sacrificing of both realism and suspense in dialogue, narration, and photography for the sake of cheap dramatic thrills and action effects (for example, in reality one single exploding bolt of the boat's<space/><link><target>Submarine#Pressure hull</target><part>pressure hull</part></link><space/>would have been enough for the whole crew to worry about the U-boat being crushed by water pressure, while Petersen has several bolts loosening in various scenes). Buchheim also criticized depictions of the crew's loud behaviour during patrols as unrealistic and celebrations after achieving a torpedo hit or surviving a bombing as unprofessional. Furthermore, an officereven an outsider like Lt. Wernerwould have commanded special respect and that throwing an oil-drenched towel into his face would not have been tolerated.</paragraph><paragraph>Uttering concerns about the end result, Buchheim felt that unlike his clearly anti-war novel the adaptation was &quot;another re-glorification and re-mystification&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="buchheim"></extension><space/>of the German World War II U-boat war, German heroism and nationalism. He called the film a cross between a &quot;cheap, shallow American action flick&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="buchheim"></extension><space/>and a &quot;contemporary German propaganda newsreel from World War II&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="buchheim"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Soundtrack</heading><paragraph>The characteristic lead melody of the soundtrack, composed and produced by<space/><link><target>Klaus Doldinger</target></link>, took on a life of its own after German<space/><link><target>rave music</target><part>rave</part></link><space/>group<space/><link><target>U96</target></link><space/>created a remixed &quot;techno version&quot; in 1991. The title theme &quot;<link><target>Das Boot (song)</target><part>Das Boot</part></link>&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>discogs master</target><arg>162882</arg><arg>Die Original Titelmelodie: Das Boot (Klaus Doldinger single)</arg></template></extension><space/>later became an international hit.</paragraph><paragraph>The official soundtrack<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>discogs master</target><arg>55391</arg><arg>Das Boot (Die original Filmmusik) (album)</arg></template></extension><space/>features only compositions by Doldinger, except for<space/><italics><link><target>J'attendrai</target></link></italics><space/>sung by<space/><link><target>Rina Ketty</target></link>. The soundtrack (&quot;Filmmusik&quot;) released following the release of<space/><italics>The Director's Cut</italics><space/>version omits<space/><italics>J'attendrai</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Songs heard in the film, but not included on the album are<space/><italics><link><target>La Paloma</target></link></italics><space/>sung by<space/><link><target>Rosita Serrano</target></link>, the<space/><italics><link><target>Erzherzog-Albrecht-Marsch</target></link></italics><space/>(a popular military march),<space/><italics><link><target>It's a Long Way to Tipperary</target></link></italics><space/>performed by the<space/><link><target>MVD Ensemble</target><part>Red Army Chorus</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Heimat, Deine Sterne</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Westerwald#Westerwaldlied</target><part>Westerwald-Marsch</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of successful U-boat commanders</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Submarine films</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of the Atlantic</target></link><space/>(19391945)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Cruel Sea (1953 film)</target><part>The Cruel Sea</part></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>U-Boote westwrts</target></link></italics>, 1941 propaganda film</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Die Brcke (film)</target><part>Die Brcke</part></link></italics>, 1958 anti-war film</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">October 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>IMDb title</target><arg>0082096</arg><arg>Das Boot</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Rotten-tomatoes</target><arg>das_boot</arg><arg>Das Boot</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>AllRovi movie</target><arg>60982</arg><arg>Das Boot</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cosmopolis.ch/english/cosmo8/boot.htm'>Das Boot review in cosmopolis.ch</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>InternationalEmmyAward Drama</target></template><template><target>Wolfgang Petersen</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Boot, Das</target></template><link><target>Category:1981 films</target></link><link><target>Category:1980s war films</target></link><link><target>Category:West German films</target></link><link><target>Category:German war films</target></link><link><target>Category:German-language films</target></link><link><target>Category:Anti-war films about World War II</target></link><link><target>Category:German epic films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films based on German novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Films based on military novels</target></link><link><target>Category:War drama films</target></link><link><target>Category:World War II submarine films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films directed by Wolfgang Petersen</target></link><link><target>Category:Columbia Pictures films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films set in the 1940s</target></link><link><target>Category:German television miniseries</target></link><link><target>Category:World War II television drama series</target></link><link><target>Category:U-boat fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:International Emmy Award for Drama winners</target></link></paragraph></article>