<article title='Circumcision_and_law'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>laws concerning male circumcision</arg><arg>the legal status of female genital mutilation</arg><arg>female genital mutilation</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There exist laws restricting or regulating<space/><link><target>circumcision</target></link>, some dating back to ancient times. In a number of modern states, circumcision is presumed to be legal, but under certain circumstances, more general laws, such as laws about assault or child custody, may sometimes be interpreted as applying to situations involving circumcision. Some countries have placed restrictions on circumcision.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Brit milah</arg></template>There are ancient religious requirements for<space/><link><target>circumcision</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>commands<space/><link><target>Jew</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to circumcise their male children on the eighth day of life, and to circumcise their male slaves (<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Genesis</arg><arg>17:11–12</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>).</paragraph><paragraph>Laws banning circumcision are also ancient. The<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>ancient Greeks</part></link><space/>prized the foreskin and disapproved of the Jewish custom of circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hodges2001"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hodges<space/></arg><arg name="first">Frederick M.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Ideal Prepuce in Ancient Greece and Rome: Male Genital Aesthetics and Their Relation to Lipodermos, Circumcision, Foreskin Restoration, and the Kynodesme<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Bulletin of the History of Medicine<space/></arg><arg name="volume">75<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3</arg><arg name="pages">375–405<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cirp.org/library/history/hodges2/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 January 2008<space/></arg><arg name="quote"></arg><arg name="doi">10.1353/bhm.2001.0119<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">11568485</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>1 Maccabees</target></link>, 1:6061 states that<space/><link><target>Antiochus IV Epiphanes</target><part>King Antiochus IV</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Syria</target></link>, the occupying power of<space/><link><target>Judea</target></link><space/>in 170 BCE, outlawed circumcision on penalty of death.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>1 Maccabees</target></link>, 1:6061</extension><space/>one of the grievances leading to the<space/><link><target>Maccabean Revolt</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Miller"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Miller
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Geoffrey P.
</arg><arg name="date">Spring 2002
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Circumcision: Cultural-Legal Analysis
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Virginia Journal of Social Policy & the Law
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>9
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>497–585
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id</arg><arg name="format"><space/>PDF (free download)
</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 August 2010
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Ritual circumcision of boys is a durable tradition. Jews of ancient times refused to abandon the practice despite enormous pressure to do so. In 167 BCE the Seleucid emperor Antiochus IV, as part of a campaign to Hellenise the Jews, condemned to death every Hebrew who allowed a son to be circumcised. The Jews responded with the Maccabean revolt, a campaign of guerrilla warfare that resulted in major victories for the rebels and, eventually, a peace treaty that restored Jewish ritual prerogatives.
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2139/ssrn.201057
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the<space/><italics><link><target>Historia Augusta</target></link></italics>, the<space/><link><target>Roman empire</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>emperor<space/><link><target>Hadrian</target></link><space/>issued a decree banning circumcision in the empire,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/history/hodges2/'>The Ideal Prepuce in Ancient Greece and Rome</link></extension><space/>and some modern scholars argue that this was a main cause of the Jewish<space/><link><target>Bar Kokhba's revolt</target><part>Bar Kokhba</part></link><space/>revolt of 132 CE.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, e.g., Alfredo M. Rabello, The Ban on Circumcision as a Cause of Bar Kokhba's Rebellion, 29 ISRAEL L. REV. 176 (1995) (Arguing that the Bar Kokhba rebellion against Roman rule was primarily motivated by the superimposition of foreign religious standards, rather than by some important notion of independence or sovereignty).</extension><space/>The Roman historian<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link>, however, made no mention of such a law, and blamed the Jewish uprising instead on Hadrian's decision to rebuild<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Aelia Capitolina</target></link>, a city dedicated to<space/><link><target>Jupiter (god)</target><part>Jupiter</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Antoninus Pius</target></link><space/>permitted Jews to circumcise their own sons. However, he forbade the circumcision of non-Jews that were either foreign-slaves or non-Jewish members of the household, contrary to<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Genesis</arg><arg>17:12</arg><arg>HE</arg></template><space/>He also made it illegal for a man to convert to Judaism.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/bmcr/2004/2004-03-29.html'>Bryn Mawr Classical Review 2004.03.29</link></extension><space/>Antoninus Pius exempted the Egyptian priesthood from the otherwise universal ban on circumcision.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern law</heading><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph>In 1993, a non-binding research paper of the<space/><link><target>Queensland Law Reform Commission</target></link><space/>(<italics>Circumcision of Male Infants</italics>) concluded that &quot;On a strict interpretation of the assault provisions of the<space/><link><target>Queensland</target></link><space/>Criminal Code, routine circumcision of a male infant could be regarded as a criminal act&quot;, and that doctors who perform circumcision on male infants may be liable to civil claims by that child at a later date.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/QLRC/'>QLRC: Circumcision of Male Infants</link></extension><space/>No prosecutions have occurred in Queensland, and circumcisions continue to be performed.</paragraph><paragraph>In a case of<space/><link><target>sexual assault</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Queensland, Australia</target></link><space/>(1997), a district court awarded a man damages for nervous shock after a botched attempt to circumcise him with a broken beer bottle in a drunken attack. Making Australian legal history, the award was made against the assailant for unlawful wounding.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dispatch.co.za/1997/10/09/page%2015.htm'>&quot;Man sues for circumcision&quot;, (9 October 1997) ''Daily Dispatch''</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.dispatch.co.za/1997/10/09/page%2015.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20101110072012<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1999, a<space/><link><target>Perth</target></link><space/>man won A$360,000 in damages after a doctor admitted he botched a circumcision operation at birth which left the man with a badly deformed penis.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/news/perth1/'>Man Receives $360,000 Compensation for Childhood Circumcision</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2002, Queensland police charged a father with grievous bodily harm for having his two sons, then aged nine and five, circumcised without the knowledge and against the wishes of the mother. The mother and father were in a family court dispute. The charges were dropped when the police prosecutor revealed that he did not have all family court paperwork in court and the magistrate refused to grant an adjournment.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/news/thesundaymail08-11-02/'>Mother's Fury as Boys Circumcised</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Cosmetic circumcision for newborn males is currently banned in all Australian public hospitals, South Australia being the last state to adopt the ban in 2007; the procedure was not forbidden from being performed in private hospitals.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Pengelley</arg><arg name="first">J</arg><arg name="title">SA to ban most circumcisions in state hospitals</arg><arg name="url">http://www.news.com.au/national/sa-to-ban-most-circumcisions-in-state-hospitals/story-e6frfkvr-1111114853797</arg><arg name="accessdate">7 April 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Advertiser</arg><arg name="date">12 November 2007</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22744548-5006787,00.html</arg><arg name="title">Public hospitals ban circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 November 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Australian<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg><arg name="bot">RjwilmsiBot</arg></template></extension><space/>In the same year, the Tasmanian President of the<space/><link><target>Australian Medical Association</target></link>, Haydn Walters, stated that they would support a call to ban circumcision for non-medical, non-religious reasons.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/12/09/2113665.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Doctors back call for circumcision ban<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 December 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ABC News</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2009, the Tasmanian Law Reform Institute released its Issues Paper investigating the law relating to male circumcision in Tasmania, it &quot;highlights the uncertainty in relation to whether doctors can legally perform circumcision on infant males&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/malecircumcision.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Male circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Tasmanian Law Reform Institute</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Tasmania Law Reform Institute released its recommendations for reform of Tasmanian law relative to male circumcision on 21 August 2012.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tasmanian Law Reform Institute.<italics><link type='external' href='http://www.law.utas.edu.au/reform/documents/CircumcisionFinal.pdf'>Non Therapeutic Male Circumcision</link></italics>. Report No. 17, August 2012</extension><space/>The report makes fourteen recommendations for reform of Tasmanian law relative to male circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tasmanian Law Reform Institute.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://theconversation.edu.au/tasmanian-report-calls-for-groundbreaking-reform-of-circumcision-law-9105'>Non Therapeutic Male Circumcision</link></italics>. Report No. 17, August 2012</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bulgaria</heading><paragraph>Male circumcision was very strongly discouraged in Bulgaria in the 1980s as part of attempts to pressure the country's Muslim minority but there was no actual legislation against the practice.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Under the Fez and the Foreskin', p113,<space/><italics>The Orient Within</italics><space/>(Cornell University Press, 2004) http://theorientwithin.com/</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph>According to the College of Physicians and Surgeons of British Columbia:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;To date, the legality of infant male circumcision has not been tested in the Courts. It is thus assumed to be legal if it is performed competently, in the childs best interest, and after valid consent has been obtained.&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;At all times the physician must perform the procedure with competence and at all times, the parent and physician must act in the best interests of the child. Signed parental consent for any treatment is assumed to be valid if the parent understands the nature of the procedure and its associated risks and benefits. However, proxy consent by parents is now being questioned. Many believe it should be limited to consent for diagnosis and treatment of medical conditions, and that it is not relevant for non-therapeutic procedures.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="cpsbc"><link type='external' href='https://www.cpsbc.ca/files/u6/Circumcision-Infant-Male.pdf'>Circumcision (Infant Male)</link><space/>In:<space/><italics>Professional Standards and Guidelines</italics>. Vancouver, College of Physicians and Surgeons of British Columbia, 2009.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>England and Wales</heading><paragraph>Male circumcision has traditionally been presumed to be legal under British law,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">English Criminal Law and Ethnic Minority Customs<space/></arg><arg name="last">Poulter<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sebastian<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Butterworths,London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-406-18000-8<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/poulter/</arg><arg name="quote">no amount of parental agreement or support can legitimise the circumcision, excision or infibulation of a young girl in this country, unless the operation is for therapeutic purposes.</arg></template></extension><space/>however some authors have argued that there is no solid foundation for this view in English law.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cirp"><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/UKlaw/fox-thomson2005/'>A covenant with the status quo? Male circumcision and the new BMA guidance to doctors</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cirp.org">Christopher Price M.A.(Oxon), Male Circumcision: An Ethical and Legal Affront, 1997 http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/price/#n18</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The passage of the<space/><link><target>Human Rights Act 1998</target></link><space/>has led to some speculation that the lawfulness of the circumcision of male children is unclear.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/edge1/'>Circumcision After the Human Rights Act 1998</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One 1999 case,<space/><italics>Re &quot;J&quot; (child's religious upbringing and circumcision)</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/Re_J/'>Re J (child's religious upbringing and circumcision)</link></extension><space/>said that circumcision in Britain required the consent of all those with parental responsibility, or the permission of the court, acting for the best interests of the child, and issued an order prohibiting the circumcision of a male child of a non-practicing<space/><link><target>Muslim</target></link><space/>father and non-practicing Christian mother with custody. The reasoning included evidence that circumcision carried some medical risk; that the operation would be likely to weaken the relationship of the child with his mother, who strongly objected to circumcision without<space/><link><target>medical necessity</target></link>; that the child may be subject to ridicule by his peers as the odd one out and that the operation might irreversibly reduce sexual pleasure, by permanently removing some sensory nerves, even though cosmetic foreskin restoration might be possible. The court did not rule out circumcision against the consent of one parent. It cited a hypothetical case of a Jewish mother and an agnostic father with a number of sons, all of whom, by agreement, had been circumcised as infants in accordance with Jewish laws; the parents then have another son who is born after they have separated; the mother wishes him to be circumcised like his brothers; the father refuses his agreement. In such a case, a decision in favor of circumcision was said to be likely.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2001 the General Medical Council had found a doctor who had botched circumcision operations guilty of abusing his professional position and that he had acted &quot;inappropriately and irresponsibly&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/1502729.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Circumcision doctors 'abused position'<space/></arg><arg name="date">21 August 2001<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 April 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>and struck him off the register.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"><link type='external' href='http://archive.thisisthenortheast.co.uk/2003/3/3/101692.html'>Circumcision case GP told he can resume career</link></extension><space/>A doctor who had referred patients to him, and who had pressured a mother into agreeing to the surgery, was also condemned.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2"></extension><space/>He was put on an 18-month period of review and retraining, and was allowed to resume unrestricted practice as a doctor in March 2003, after a committee found that he had complied with conditions it placed on him. According to the<space/><italics>Northern Echo</italics>, he &quot;told the committee he has now changed his approach to circumcision referrals, accepting that most cases can be treated without the need for surgery.&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Fox and Thomson (2005) argue that consent cannot be given for non-therapeutic circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cirp"></extension><space/>They say there is &quot;no compelling legal authority for the common view that circumcision is lawful.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>In 2005 a Muslim man had his son circumcised against the wishes of the child's mother who was the custodial parent. He was found not guilty of assault occasioning actual bodily harm by a majority verdict of the jury.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://icsurreyonline.icnetwork.co.uk/0100news/0400crawley/tm_objectid=15505735&amp;amp;method=full&amp;amp;siteid=50101&amp;amp;headline=father-cleared-of-assault-name_page.html'>icNetwork Local and regional news, sport, entertainment and classifieds across the UK</link><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">July 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.scotsman.com/latest.cfm?id</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20050523125330/http://news.scotsman.com/latest.cfm?id</arg><arg name="archivedate">23 May 2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">Muslim Accused of Assaulting Son Through Circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 May 2005<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="first">James<space/></arg><arg name="last">Tapsfield<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''[[The Scotsman]]''<space/></arg><arg name="location">Edinburgh</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2009 it was reported that a 20-year-old man whose father had him ritually circumcised as a baby is preparing to sue the doctor who circumcised him. This is believed to be the first time a person who was circumcised as an infant has made a claim in the UK. The case is expected to be heard in 2010.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2009/11/17/snip-op-illegal-115875-21828059/</arg><arg name="title">Ritual circumcisions 'illegal'</arg><arg name="work">[[Daily Mirror]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Europe</heading><paragraph>On 1 October 2013, the<space/><link><target>Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe</target></link><space/>adopted a resolution in which they state they are &quot;particularly worried about a category of violation of the physical integrity of children,&quot; and include in this category &quot;circumcision of young boys for religious reasons.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Parliamentary Assembly, Council of Europe.<space/><link type='external' href='http://assembly.coe.int/nw/xml/XRef/X2H-Xref-ViewPDF.asp?FileID=20174&amp;amp;lang=en'>Children's Right to Physical Integrity</link>, Resolution 1952., Adopted at Strasbourg, Tuesday, 1 October 2013.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Finland</heading><paragraph>In August 2006, a Finnish court ruled that the circumcision of a four-year-old boy arranged by his mother, who is Muslim, to be an illegal assault. The boy's father, who had not been consulted, reported the incident to the police. A local prosecutor stated that the prohibition of circumcision is not gender-specific in Finnish law. A lawyer for the Ministry of Social Affairs and Health stated that there is neither legislation nor prohibition on male circumcision, and that &quot;the operations have been performed on the basis of common law.&quot; The case was appealed<extension extension_name='ref' name="Helsingin Sanomat"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Court rules circumcision of four-year-old boy illegal<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Court+rules+circumcision+of+four-year-old+boy+illegal/1135220958830</arg></template></extension><space/>and in October 2008 the Finnish Supreme Court ruled that the circumcision, &quot; carried out for religious and social reasons and in a medical manner, did not have the earmarks of a criminal offence. It pointed out in its ruling that the circumcision of Muslim boys is an established tradition and an integral part of the identity of Muslim men&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://yle.fi/news/id104896.html'>Supreme Court: Male Circumcision Not A Crime | Yle Uutiset | yle.fi</link></extension><space/>In 2008, the Finnish government was reported to be considering a new law to legalise circumcision if the practitioner is a doctor and if the child consents.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yle.fi/news/id97605.html
</arg><arg name="title">Finland Considers Legalising Male Circumcision</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 September 2007
</arg><arg name="date">2 August 2008
</arg><arg name="publisher">Ylesiradio</arg></template></extension><space/>In December 2011, Helsinki District Court said that the Supreme Court's decision does not mean that circumcision is legal for any non-medical reasons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HS"><link type='external' href='http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Circumcision+assault+case+brings+fine+%E2%80%93+conviction+but+no+punishment+for+parents/1135270121491'>Circumcision assault case brings fine conviction but no punishment for parents</link>, Helsingin Sanomat, HS.fi 2 January 2012</extension><space/>The court referred to the Convention on Human rights and Biomedicine of the Council of Europe, which was ratified in Finland in 2010.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HS"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In February 2010, a Jewish couple were fined for causing bodily harm to their then infant son who was circumcised in 2008 by a<space/><link><target>mohel</target></link><space/>brought in from the UK. Normal procedure for persons of Jewish faith in Finland is to have a locally certified mohel who works in Finnish healthcare perform the operation. In the 2008 case, the infant was not anesthetized and developed complications that required immediate hospital care. The parents were ordered to pay 1500 euros in damages to their child.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yle.fi/uutiset/news/2010/02/parents_ordered_to_pay_circumcised_son_1500_euros_1479554.html
</arg><arg name="title">Parents Ordered to Pay Circumcised Son 1,500 Euros</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 February 2010
</arg><arg name="date">24 February 2010
</arg><arg name="publisher">Finnish Broadcasting Corporation</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Germany</heading><paragraph>In October 2006, a Turkish national who performed ritual circumcisions on seven boys was convicted of causing dangerous bodily harm by the state court in<space/><link><target>Dsseldorf</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://rawstory.com/news/2006/Germany_fines_circumciser_for_initi_10172006.html'>The Raw Story | Germany fines circumciser for initiation of 7 boys</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In September 2007, a<space/><link><target>Frankfurt</target><part>Frankfurt am Main</part></link><space/>appeals court found that the circumcision of an 11<template><target>endash</target></template>year<template><target>endash</target></template>old boy without his approval was an unlawful personal injury. The boy, whose parents were divorced, was visiting his Muslim father during a vacation when his father forced him to be ritually circumcised. The boy had planned to sue his father for<space/><template><target>euro</target><arg>10,000</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20071017044733/http://jta.org/cgi-bin/iowa/breaking/104271.html'>Breaking News&amp;nbsp; JTA, Jewish &amp; Israel News</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.lareda.hessenrecht.hessen.de/jportal/portal/t/dz2/page/bslaredaprod.psml?pid=Dokumentanzeige&amp;amp;showdoccase=1&amp;amp;js_peid=Trefferliste&amp;amp;documentnumber=1&amp;amp;numberofresults=1&amp;amp;fromdoctodoc=yes&amp;amp;doc.id=KORE244012007%3Ajuris-r01&amp;amp;doc.part=L&amp;amp;doc.price=0.0&amp;amp;doc.hl=1'>Oberlandesgericht Frankfurt 21 August 2007 4 W 12/07</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In May 2012, the Cologne regional appellate court ruled that religious circumcision of male children amounts to bodily injury, and is a criminal offense in the area under its jurisdiction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="telegraph"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/9358636/Jewish-groups-condemn-courts-definition-of-circumcision-as-grievous-bodily-harm.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jewish groups condemn court's definition of circumcision as grievous bodily harm<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">27 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Daily Telegraph<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>The decision based on the article &quot;Criminal Relevance of Circumcising Boys. A Contribution to the Limitation of Consent in Cases of Care for the Person of the Child&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Holm Putzke:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.holmputzke.de/images/stories/pdf/2008_fs_herzberg_beschneidung.pdf'>''Die strafrechtliche Relevanz der Beschneidung von Knaben. Zugleich ein Beitrag ber die Grenzen der Einwilligung in Fllen der Personensorge''</link>. In: Festschrift fr Rolf Dietrich Herzberg, Tbingen 2008, p. 669709 - Translation:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.holmputzke.de/images/stories/pdf/2008_putzke%20fs%20herzberg%20essay%20on%20circumcision.pdf'>''Criminal Relevance of Circumcising Boys. A Contribution to the Limitation of Consent in Cases of Care for the Person of the Child''</link>, tanslated by Katharina McLarren.</extension><space/>published by<space/><link><target>Holm Putzke</target></link>, a German law professor at the University of Passau.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/'>German verdict aims to delay circumcision, not ban it, jurist says.</link><space/>Retrieved 16 June 2014</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.circinfo.org/Circumcision_and_law.html'>German court rules non-therapeutic circumcision of boys unlawful.</link><space/>Retrieved 16 June 2014</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.intactamerica.org/putzke Intactivist of the month: Holm Putzke</extension><space/>The court arrived at its judgment by application of the human rights provisions of the Basic Law, a section of the Civil Code, and some sections of the Criminal Code to non-therapeutic circumcision of male children.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2012</arg></template><space/>Some observers said it could set a legal precedent that criminalizes the practice.<extension extension_name='ref' name="telegraph"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thelocal.de/opinion/20120626-43385.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Circumcision: religious right or crime?<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">27 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Local|TheLocal.de]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thelocal.de/society/20120627-43409.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Muslims, Jews denounce circumcision ruling<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">27 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Local|TheLocal.de]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Holm Putzke<space/><link type='external' href='http://blogs.reuters.com/faithworld/tag/germany-circumcision-jewish-muslim-law-court-verdict-cologne-putzke-jurist/'>German verdict aims to delay circumcision, not ban it, jurist says.</link><space/>Retrieved 16 June 2014</extension><space/>Jewish and Muslim groups were outraged by the ruling, viewing it as trampling on freedom of religion.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-18604664'>German court rules circumcision is 'bodily harm', BBC News Europe.</link><space/>Retrieved 13 July 2012</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-18793842'>Evans, Stephen. German circumcision ban: Is it a parent's right to choose? BBC News Magazine.</link><space/>Retrieved 13 July 2012</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/9360203/Jewish-and-Muslim-groups-condemn-German-circumcision-ruling.html<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Daily Telegraph<space/></arg><arg name="first">Matthew<space/></arg><arg name="last">Day<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jewish and Muslim groups condemn German circumcision ruling<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 June 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The German ambassador to Israel, Andreas Michaelis, told Israeli lawmakers that Germany was working to resolve the issue and that it doesn't apply at a national level, but instead only to the local jurisdiction of the court in Cologne.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CBS"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Israeli parliament slams German circumcision ban</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-202_162-57468680/israeli-parliament-slams-german-circumcision-ban/</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 July 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">CBS News</arg><arg name="date">9 July 2012</arg><arg name="agency">AP</arg></template></extension><space/>The Council of the Coordination of Muslims in Germany condemned the ruling, stating that it is &quot;a serious attack on religious freedom.&quot; Ali Kizilkaya, a spokesman of the council, stated that, &quot;The ruling does not take everything into account, religious practice concerning circumcision of young Muslims and Jews has been carried out over the millenia on a global level.&quot; The<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/><link><target>archbishop</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Aachen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Heinrich Mussinghoff</target></link>, said that the ruling was &quot;very surprising&quot;, and the contradiction between &quot;basic rights on freedom of religion and the well-being of the child brought up by the judges is not convincing in this very case.&quot; Hans Ulrich Anke, the head of the<space/><link><target>Protestant Church</target></link><space/>in Germany, said the ruling should be appealed since it didn't &quot;sufficiently&quot; consider the religious significance of the rite.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EJP"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Key Muslim group in Germany slams circumcision ruling</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ejpress.org/article/news/germany/59627</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 July 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">European Jewish Press</arg><arg name="date">28 June 2012</arg><arg name="agency">AFP</arg></template></extension><space/>A spokesman, Steffen Seibert, for<space/><link><target>Chancellor of Germany</target><part>German Chancellor</part></link><space/><link><target>Angela Merkel</target></link><space/>stated that Jewish and Muslim communities will be free to practice circumcision responsibly, and the government would find a way around the local ban in Cologne. The spokesman stated &quot;For everyone in the government it is absolutely clear that we want to have Jewish and Muslim religious life in Germany. Circumcision carried out in a responsible manner must be possible in this country without punishment.&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TimesofIsrael1"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Ahren</arg><arg name="first">Raphael</arg><arg name="title">German government looking for quick fix on circumcision ban</arg><arg name="url">http://www.timesofisrael.com/german-government-looking-for-quick-fix-on-circumcision-ban/</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 July 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Times of Israel</arg><arg name="date">13 July 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Guardian"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Angela Merkel intervenes over court ban on circumcision of young boys</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/jul/13/angela-merkel-intervenes-ban-circumcision</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 July 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Guardian</arg><arg name="date">13 July 2012</arg><arg name="agency">Reuters</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July, a group of rabbis, imams, and others said that they view the ruling against circumcision &quot;an affront on our basic religious and human rights.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="HuffPoCirc"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/07/12/rabbis-urge-german-jews-to-continue-circumcisions_n_1667916.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rabbis Urge German Jews To Continue Circumcisions<space/></arg><arg name="work">Huffington Post<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="author">Rising, David</arg></template></extension><space/>The joint statement was signed by leaders of groups including Germany's<space/><link><target>Turkish-Islamic Union for Religious Affairs</target></link>, the Islamic Center Brussels, the Rabbinical Centre of Europe, the European Jewish Parliament and the European Jewish Association, who met with members of<space/><link><target>European Parliament</target></link><space/>from Germany, Finland, Belgium, Italy, and Poland. European rabbis, who urged Jews to continue circumcision, planned further talks with Muslim and Christian leaders to determine how they can oppose the ban together.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HurriyetCirc"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/german-courts-move-to-ban-circumcision-unites-religions.aspx?pageID</arg><arg name="title">German court's move to ban circumcision unites religions<space/></arg><arg name="work">Hurriyet Daily News<space/></arg><arg name="agency">Anatolia News Agency<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 July 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>The Jewish Hospital of Berlin suspended the practice of male circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4249122,00.html'>Jewish Hospital in Berlin suspends circumcisions</link>. YNET News, 1 July 2012.</extension><space/>On 19 July 2012, a joint resolution of the<space/><link><target>CDU/CSU</target></link>,<space/><link><target>SPD</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Free Democratic Party (Germany)</target><part>FDP</part></link><space/>factions in the<space/><link><target>Bundestag</target></link><space/>requesting the executive branch to draft a law permitting circumcision of boys to be performed without unnecessary pain in accordance with best medical practice<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Rechtliche Regelung der Beschneidung minderjähriger Jungen<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://dipbt.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/17/103/1710331.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="language">German</arg></template></extension><space/>carried with a broad majority.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beschneidung minderjähriger Jungen<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bundestag.de/dokumente/textarchiv/2012/39861243_kw29_angenommen_abgelehnt/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="language">German</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The New York Times reported that the<space/><link><target>German Medical Association</target></link><space/>&quot;condemned the ruling for potentially putting children at risk by taking the procedure out of the hands of doctors, but it also warned surgeons not to perform circumcisions for religious reasons until legal clarity was established.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytimes_germany"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/14/world/europe/in-germany-ruling-over-circumcision-sows-anxiety-and-confusion.html?_r</arg><arg name="title">In Germany, Ruling Over Circumcision Sows Anxiety and Confusion<space/></arg><arg name="work">New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 July 2012<space/></arg><arg name="author">Eddy, Melissa</arg></template></extension><space/>The ruling was supported by Deutsche Kinderhilfe, a German child rights organization, which asked for a two-year moratorium to discuss the issue and pointed out that religious circumcision may contravene the<space/><link><target>Convention on the Rights of the Child</target></link><space/>(Article 24.3: &quot;States Parties shall take all effective and appropriate measures with a view to abolishing traditional practices prejudicial to the health of children.&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.themenportal.de/politik/petitionsausschuss-korrigiert-fehlentscheidung-petition-gegen-vorschnelles-gesetz-zur-legalisierung-nicht-therapeutischer-beschneidungen-seit-gestern-vom-bundestag-zur-unterzeichnung-freigeschaltet-16702'>Petitionsausschuss korrigiert Fehlentscheidung: Petition gegen vorschnelles Gesetz zur Legalisierung nicht-therapeutischer Beschneidungen seit gestern vom Bundestag zur Unterz...</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/anlaesslich-des-weltkindertages-fordert-die-deutsche-kinderhilfe-ein-klares-bekenntnis-zu-kinderrechten-statt-festtagsreden-keine-nicht-medizinische-beschneidung-fuer-einwilligungsunfaehige-kinder/'>Anlsslich des Weltkindertages fordert die Deutsche Kinderhilfe ein klares Bekenntnis zu Kinderrechten statt Festtagsreden: keine nicht-medizinische Beschneidung fr einwillig...</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.kinderhilfe.de/blog/artikel/bundestagspetition-zu-beschneidungen)'>Bundestagspetition zu Beschneidungen | Deutsche Kinderhilfe</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The German Academy for Pediatric and Adolescent Medicine (Deutsche Akademie fr Kinder- und Jugendmedizin e.V., DAKJ),<extension extension_name='ref'>http://dakj.de/pages/posts/stellungnahme-zur-beschneidung-von-minderjaehrigen-jungen-123.php , http://dakj.de/media/stellungnahmen/ethische-fragen/2012_Stellungnahme_Beschneidung.pdf</extension><space/>the German Association for Pediatric Surgery (Deutsche Gesellschaft fr Kinderchirurgie, DGKCH)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dgkic.de/index.php/presse/189-pressemitteilung-juli-2012'>Presseerklrung (4. July 2012) (DGKCH).</link></extension><space/>and the Professional Association of Pediatric and Adolescent Physicians (Berufsverband der Kinder- und Jugendrzte)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.kinderaerzte-im-netz.de/bvkj/aktuelles1/show.php3?id=4322&amp;amp;nodeid=26'>http://www.kinderaerzte-im-netz.de</link></extension><space/>took a firm stand against non-medical routine infant circumcision.</paragraph><paragraph>In July, in Berlin, a criminal complaint was lodged against Rabbi Yitshak Ehrenberg for &quot;causing bodily harm&quot; by performing religious circumcision, and for vocal support of the continuation of the practice. In September, the prosecutors dismissed the complaint, concluding that &quot;there is no proof to establish that the rabbi's conduct met the 'condition of a criminal' violation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="JPost_Ehrenberg"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishNews/Article.aspx?id</arg><arg name="title">Berlin prosecutor nixes circumcision complaint<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Jerusalem Post<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 August 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">6 September 2012<space/></arg><arg name="author">WEINTHAL, BENJAMIN</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In September, Reuters reported &quot;Berlin's senate said doctors could legally circumcise infant boys for religious reasons in its region, given certain conditions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reuters_Berlin_2012"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/48914968/ns/world_news-europe/#.UEjj5FLfu5k<space/></arg><arg name="title">Berlin reverses ban on religious circumcisions<space/></arg><arg name="work">MSNBC<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 May 2012<space/></arg><arg name="agency">Reuters<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">6 September 2012<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20120911010141/http://www.msnbc.msn.com:80/id/48914968/ns/world_news-europe<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">11 September 2012<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 12 December 2012, following a series of hearings and consultations, the Bundestag adopted the proposed law explicitly permitting non-therapeutic circumcision to be performed under certain conditions; it is now 1631(d) in the<space/><link><target>Brgerliches Gesetzbuch</target><part>German Civil Code</part></link>. The vote tally was 434 ayes, 100 noes, and 46 abstentions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beschneidung von Jungen jetzt gesetzlich geregelt<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bundestag.de/dokumente/textarchiv/2012/42042381_kw50_de_beschneidung/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="language">German</arg></template></extension><space/>Following approval by the<space/><link><target>Bundesrat of Germany</target><part>Bundesrat</part></link><space/>and signing by the<space/><link><target>President of Germany</target><part>Bundesprsident</part></link>, the new law became effective on 28 December 2012 a day after its publication in the<space/><link><target>Bundesgesetzblatt (Germany)</target><part>Federal Gazette</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Gesetz über den Umfang der Personensorge bei einer Beschneidung des männlichen Kindes<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bgbl.de/Xaver/media.xav?SID</arg><arg name="language">German</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ireland</heading><paragraph>In October 2005 a Nigerian man was cleared of a charge of reckless endangerment over the death of a baby from haemorrhage and shock after he had circumcised the child. The judge directed the jury not to &quot;bring what he called their white western values to bear when they were deciding this case&quot; and after deliberating for an hour and a half they found the defendant not guilty.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.rte.ie/news/2005/1007/igbinediono.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">RTÉ News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Nigerian cleared over circumcision death<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 October 2005</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Israel</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, Jewish circumcision is entirely legal, as is posthumous circumcision. In 1999, the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Israel</target><part>Israeli Supreme Court</part></link><space/>overruled an attempt to have after-death circumcision outlawed.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nocirc.org/publish/ar00.pdf'>NOCIRC NEWSLTTR reordered2</link></extension><space/>Though illegal, female circumcision is still practiced among the<space/><link><target>Negev Bedouin</target></link>, and tribal secrecy among the Bedouin makes it difficult for authorities to enforce the ban.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3568416,00.html</extension><space/>In 2013 Rabbinical court in Israel, ordered a mother, Elinor Daniel to circumcise her son or pay a fine of 500 Israeli Shekel for every day that the child is not circumcised. The mother appealed the Rabbinical court ruling, and her appeal is now pending the Supreme court decision.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Netherlands</heading><paragraph>When<space/><link><target>Ayaan Hirsi Ali</target></link><space/>was a Member of the Netherlands Parliament she asked it to consider making the circumcision of male children unlawful.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/news/radionetherlands10-04-04/'>Dutch MP wants ban on male circumcision</link></extension><space/>In May 2008 a father who had his two sons, aged 3 and 6 circumcised against the will of their mother was found not guilty of causing them serious physical harm but was given a 6-week suspended jail sentence for taking the boys away from their mother against her will.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dutchnews.nl/news/archives/2008/05/father_not_guilty_in_circumcis.php'>DutchNews.nl Father 'not guilty' in circumcision case</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Norway and region</heading><paragraph>In 2012, the<space/><link><target>Senterpartiet</target></link><space/>proposed a ban on circumcision on males under eighteen.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>no icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dagbladet.no/2012/06/19/kultur/debatt/omskjering/helse_bergen/bar_overkropp/22180612/'>Attenrsgrense for omskjring, [[Dagbladet</link>. Retrieved 27 June 2012]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In September 2013, the<space/><link><target>Children's Ombudsman</target><part>Children's ombudsmen</part></link><space/>in all<space/><link><target>Nordic countries</target></link><space/>issued a statement<extension extension_name='ref' name="resolution"><template><target>vcite web</target><arg name="author">Nordic Association of Children's Ombudsmen<space/></arg><arg name="home"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Let the boys decide for themselves<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://www.crin.org/en/library/news-archive/male-circumcision-nordic-ombudspersons-seek-ban-non-therapeutic-male<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 September 2013<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 October 2013<space/></arg></template>[] Tuesday, 1 October 2013</extension><space/>by which they called for a ban on circumcision of minors for non-medical reasons, stating that such circumcisions violate the rights of children after the<space/><link><target>Convention on the Rights of the Child</target></link><space/>to co-determination and protection from harmful traditions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lise Marit Kalstad (2 October 2013):<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vl.no/samfunn/vil-la-gutter-bestemme-omskjaring-selv/'>Vil la gutter bestemme omskjring selv</link><space/><italics><link><target>Vrt Land (Norwegian newspaper)</target><part>Vrt Land</part></link></italics>.<space/><template><target>no icon</target></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Children's Act 2005</target></link><space/>makes the circumcision of male children under 16 unlawful except for religious or medical reasons. In the<space/><link><target>Eastern Cape</target></link><space/>province the Application of Health Standards in Traditional Circumcision Act, 2001, regulates traditional circumcision, which causes the death or mutilation of many youths by traditional surgeons each year.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId</arg><arg name="title">SOUTH AFRICA: Clamping down on botched circumcisions</arg><arg name="date">1 August 2007</arg><arg name="work">IRIN In-Depth</arg><arg name="location">MTHATA</arg></template></extension><space/>Among other provisions, the minimum age for circumcision is age 18.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2004, a 22-year-old Rastafarian convert was forcibly circumcised by a group of<space/><link><target>Xhosa people</target><part>Xhosa</part></link><space/>tribal elders and relatives. When he first fled, two police returned him to those who had circumcised him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rastafarian circumcised against his will
</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 April 2007
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Peters
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Melanie
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>4 July 2004
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>South Africa
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Sunday Tribune]]
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>3
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>22-year-old Cape Town man was taken by force and circumcised against his will this week....He is a Rastafarian convert and strongly opposes Xhosa initiation. The men who forcibly circumcised him also cut off his Rasta dreadlocks.</arg></template></extension><space/>In another case, a medically circumcised Xhosa man was forcibly recircumcised by his father and community leaders. He laid a charge of unfair discrimination on the grounds of his religious beliefs, seeking an apology from his father and the Congress of Traditional Leaders of South Africa. According to South African newspapers, the subsequent trial became &quot;a landmark case around forced circumcision.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.iol.co.za/news/south-africa/forced-circumcision-son-takes-parents-on-1.454711
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Forced circumcision: Son takes parents on
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>11 August 2009
</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IOL: News for South Africa and the World
</arg></template></extension><space/>In October 2009, the<space/><link><target>Eastern Cape High Court, Bhisho</target><part>Eastern Cape High Court at Bhisho</part></link><space/>(sitting as an<space/><link><target>Equality Court</target></link>) clarified that circumcision is unlawful unless done with the full consent of the initiate.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.legalbrief.co.za/article.php?story</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Judgment in forced circumcision case
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>14 October 2009
</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Legalbrief Today
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sweden</heading><paragraph>In 2001, the<space/><link><target>Parliament of Sweden</target></link><space/>enacted a law allowing only persons certified by the National Board of Health to circumcise infants. It requires a medical doctor or an anesthesia nurse to accompany the circumciser and for anaesthetic to be applied beforehand. After the first two months of life circumcisions can only be performed by a physician. The stated purpose of the law was to increase the safety of the procedure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SR"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://sverigesradio.se/sida/artikel.aspx?programid</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Sveriges Radio]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">22 October 2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">Snitt som kostar – om omskärelse av pojkar<space/></arg><arg name="language">Swedish</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Swedish Jews and Muslims objected to the law,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1572483.stm
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sweden restricts circumcisions
</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 October 2006
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1 October 2001
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[BBC|BBC Europe]]
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Swedish Jews and Muslims object to the new law, saying it violates their religious rights.
</arg></template></extension><space/>and in 2001, the<space/><link><target>World Jewish Congress</target></link><space/>called it &quot;the first legal restriction on Jewish religious practice in Europe since the Nazi era.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Jews protest Swedish circumcision restriction<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.hrwf.net/religiousfreedom/news/sweden2001.html#JewsprotestSwedish<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Reuters<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>7 June 2001</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>A WJC spokesman said, "This is the first legal restriction placed on a Jewish rite in Europe since the Nazi era. This new legislation is totally unacceptable to the Swedish Jewish community."</arg></template></extension><space/>The requirement for an anaesthetic to be administered by a medical professional is a major issue,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Hofvander Y<space/></arg><arg name="title">New law on male circumcision in Sweden<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Lancet<space/></arg><arg name="volume">359<space/></arg><arg name="issue">9306<space/></arg><arg name="page">630<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 2002<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">11867150<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)07737-1</arg></template></extension><space/>and the low degree of availability of certified professionals willing to conduct circumcision has also been subject to criticism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://uppsalademokraten.etc.se/28460/lang-koetid-foer-omskaerelse/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lång kötid för omskärelse<space/></arg><arg name="language">Swedish<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">UppsalaDemokraten<space/></arg><arg name="author">Malin Beeck<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 March 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>According to a survey, two out of three paediatric surgeons said they refuse to perform non-therapeutic circumcision, and less than half of all<space/><link><target>County Councils of Sweden</target><part>county councils</part></link><space/>offer it in their hospitals.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Swedish doctors refuse to circumcise boys<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.thelocal.se/20900/20090725/<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Local]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">25 July 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>However, in 2006, the U.S. State Department stated, in a report on Sweden, that most Jewish<space/><link><target>mohel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>had been certified under the law and 3000 Muslim and 4050 Jewish boys were circumcised eachyear. An estimated 2000 of these are performed by persons who are neither physicians nor have officially recognised certification.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holender2009"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.dn.se/nyheter/manga-lakare-vagrar-utfora-omskarelse-av-unga-pojkar-1.918069<space/></arg><arg name="title">Många läkare vägrar utföra omskärelse av unga pojkar<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Dagens Nyheter]]<space/></arg><arg name="language">Swedish<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 July 2009<space/></arg><arg name="author">Robert Holender</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare reviewed the law in 2005 and recommended that it be maintained,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71410.htm
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sweden
</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 July 2007
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>15 September 2006
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>International Religious Freedom Report 2006
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>US Department of State
</arg></template></extension><space/>but found that the law had failed with regard to the intended consequence of increasing the safety of circumcisions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Soc2007"></extension><space/>A later report by the Board criticised the low level of availability of legal circumcisions, partly due to reluctance among health professionals.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Soc2007"></extension><space/>To remedy this, the report suggested a new law obliging all county councils to offer non-therapeutic circumcision in their hospitals,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Soc2007"><template><target>Cite report</target><arg name="title">Omskärelse av pojkar<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/publikationer2007/2007-107-7<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Board of Health and Welfare (Sweden)|National Board of Health and Welfare]]<space/></arg><arg name="language">Swedish<space/></arg><arg name="docket">2007-107-7<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20120222063038/http://www.socialstyrelsen.se/publikationer2007/2007-107-7<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">22 February 2012<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>but this was later abandoned in favour of a non-binding recommendation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holender2009"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph>Circumcision of adults who grant personal informed consent for the surgical operation is not at issue and is unquestionably lawful.</paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, non-therapeutic circumcision of male children has long been assumed to be lawful in every jurisdiction provided that one parent grants surrogate informed consent. Adler (2013) has recently challenged the validity of this assumption.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Peter W. Adler.<space/><link type='external' href='http://rjolpi.richmond.edu/archive/Adler_Formatted.pdf'>Is Circumcision Legal?</link><space/>16(3) Richmond J. L. &amp; Pub. Int. 439 (2013).</extension><space/>As with every country, doctors who circumcise children must take care that all applicable rules regarding informed consent and safety are satisfied.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Steven Svoboda, Robert S. Van Howe, James G. Dwyer,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/conundrum/'>Informed Consent for Neonatal Circumcision: An Ethical and Legal Conundrum</link>. 17 J Contemporary Health Law Policy 61 (2000)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While anti-circumcision groups have occasionally proposed legislation banning non-therapeutic child circumcision, it has not been supported in any legislature.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://edition.cnn.com/2005/LAW/04/08/colb.circumcision/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="author">Colb, Sherry<space/></arg><arg name="title">A proposed bill to ban male circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="date">8 April 2005<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CNN</arg></template></extension><space/>After a failed attempt to adopt a local ordinance banning circumcision on a San Francisco ballot, the state of California enacted in October 2011 a law protecting circumcision from local attempts to ban the practice.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f</arg><arg name="title">Circumcision law blocks local bans<space/></arg><arg name="author">Evangelista, Benny<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">San Francisco Chronicle<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 October 2011<space/></arg><arg name="pages">C–2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2012, New York City required those performing<space/><italics><link><target>metzitzah b'peh</target></link></italics>, a part of circumcision required by some<space/><link><target>Hasidim</target></link>, to obey stringent consent requirements, including documentation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">N.Y. Board Orders Forms for Circumcision Rite</arg><arg name="url">http://forward.com/articles/162762/ny-board-orders-forms-for-circumcision-rite/?p</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 December 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Jewish Daily Forward]]</arg><arg name="date">13 September 2012</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Agudath Israel of America</target></link><space/>and other Jewish groups have planned to sue the city in response.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Exclusive: Agudah Preparing To Sue City Over Metzitza Informed Consent</arg><arg name="url">http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/breaking-news/exclusive-agudah-preparing-sue-city-over-metzitza-informed-consent</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 December 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Jewish Week]]</arg><arg name="date">11 September 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Disputes between parents</bold></paragraph><paragraph>Occasionally the courts are asked to make a ruling when parents cannot agree on whether or not to circumcise a child.</paragraph><paragraph>In January 2001 a dispute between divorcing parents in New Jersey was resolved when the mother, who sought to have the boy circumcised withdrew her request. The boy had experienced two instances of foreskin inflammation and she wanted to have him circumcised. The father, who had experienced a traumatic circumcision as a child objected and they turned to the courts for a decision. The Medical Society of New Jersey and the Urological Society of New Jersey both opposed any court ordered medical treatment. As the parties came to an agreement, no precedent was set.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/news/star-ledger01-25-01/'>Accord Not To Circumcise Son Still Leaves Heated Legal Debate</link></extension><space/>In June 2001 a Nevada court settled a dispute over circumcision between two parents but put a strict gag order on the terms of the settlement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.reviewjournal.com/cgi-bin/printable.cgi?/lvrj_home/2001/Jun-25-Mon-2001/news/16387263.html</arg><arg name="title">Gag order issued</arg><arg name="last">Thevemot</arg><arg name="first">Carri Geer</arg><arg name="date">25 June 2001</arg><arg name="work">[[Las Vegas Review-Journal]]</arg></template></extension><space/>In July 2001 a dispute between parents in<space/><link><target>Kansas</target></link><space/>over circumcision was resolved when the mother's request to have the infant circumcised was withdrawn. In this case the father opposed circumcision while the mother asserted that not circumcising the child was against her religious beliefs. (The woman's pastor had stated that circumcision was &quot;important&quot; but was not necessary for salvation.) On 24 July 2001 the parents reached agreement that the infant would not be circumcised.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cirp.org/news/wichitaeagle07-24-01<space/></arg><arg name="title">Agreement reached in circumcision case<space/></arg><arg name="date">25 July 2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Wichita Eagle<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 August 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cirp.org/news/wichitaeagle07-13-01/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Wichitans fight over their son's circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="author">Alex Branch<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 July 2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Wichita Eagle</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 14 July 2004 a mother appealed to the<space/><link><target>Missouri Supreme Court</target></link><space/>to prevent the circumcision of her son after a county court and the Court of Appeals had denied her a writ of prohibition.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20041226064014/http://examiner.net/stories/071504/new_071504018.shtml'>The Examiner: Parents in court over son's circumcision 07/15/04</link></extension><space/>However, in early August 2004, before the Supreme Court had given its ruling, the father, who had custody of the boy, had him circumcised.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.kansascity.com/mld/kansascity/news/local/9359979.htm</arg><arg name="title">Despite mother's protest, father has boy circumcised</arg><arg name="date">10 August 2004</arg><arg name="work">Kansas City Star</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20041029070148/http://www.kansascity.com/mld/kansascity/news/local/9359979.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate">29 October 2004</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In October 2006 a judge in Chicago granted an injunction blocking the circumcision of a 9-year-old boy. In granting the injunction the judge stated that &quot;the boy could decide for himself whether to be circumcised when he turns 18.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reut06"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/N24253813.htm
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>US judge rules 9-year-old need not get circumcised
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>24 October 2006
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Reuters
</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 August 2010
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>In a decision cheered by foes of routine circumcision for boys, a judge ruled on Tuesday that a 9-year-old need not be circumcised as his mother wanted....In granting the boy's father an injunction blocking the procedure, the judge said the boy could decide for himself whether to be circumcised when he turns 18.
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 2007, the<space/><link><target>Oregon Supreme Court</target></link><space/>heard arguments from a divorced<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link><space/>couple over the circumcision of their son. The father wanted his son, who turned 13 on 2 March 2008, to be circumcised in accordance with the father's religious views; the child's mother opposes the procedure. The parents dispute whether the boy is in favor of the procedure. A group opposed to circumcision filed briefs in support of the mother's position, while some Jewish groups filed a brief in support of the father.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Gerstein<space/></arg><arg name="first">Josh<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ore. Court Mulls Circumcision Case<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nysun.com/article/65997?page_no</arg><arg name="work">The New York Sun<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 December 2007</arg></template></extension><space/>On 25 January 2008, the Court returned the case to the trial court with instructions to determine whether the child agrees or objects to the proposed circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.publications.ojd.state.or.us/S054714.htm'>Oregon Judicial Department Appellate Court Opinions</link></extension><space/>The father appealed to the US Supreme Court to allow him to have his son circumcised<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://blog.oregonlive.com/breakingnews/2008/05/dad_appeals_teen_sons_circumci.html</arg><arg name="title">Dad appeals teen son's circumcision to U.S. Supreme Court</arg><arg name="date">May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[The Oregonian]]</arg></template></extension><space/>but his appeal was rejected. The case then returned to the trial court.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/oregonian/index.ssf?/base/news/1223344525313320.xml&coll</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Supreme Court rejects Oregon's circumcision, abortion cases</arg><arg name="work">[[The Oregonian]]<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ashbel S.</arg><arg name="last">Green</arg><arg name="date">7 October 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>When the trial court interviewed the couple's son, now 14 years old, the boy stated that he did not want to be circumcised. This also provided the necessary circumstances to allow the boy to change residence to live with his mother. The boy was not circumcised.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Other disputes</bold></paragraph><paragraph>In September 2004 the<space/><link><target>North Dakota Supreme Court</target></link><space/>rejected a mother's attempt to prosecute her doctor for circumcising her child without fully informing her of the consequences of the procedure. The judge and jury found that the defendants were adequately informed of possible complications, and the jury further found that it is not incumbent on the doctors to describe every &quot;insignificant&quot; risk.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FargoForum2004"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Hawley mother loses appeal
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Janelle
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Cole
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cirp.org/news/theforum09-04-04/
</arg><arg name="format"><space/>[[WP:CONV|convenience link]]
</arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>[[The Forum of Fargo-Moorhead]]
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Forum Communications]]
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>4 September 2004
</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 November 2011
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>The mother who unsuccessfully sued MeritCare Hospital and one of its doctors over her infant son's circumcision won't get a new trial, the North Dakota Supreme Court said Friday. Anita Flatt of Hawley, Minn., also will have to pay more than $58,000 in costs the doctor and hospital incurred defending themselves, the court ruled. The justices rejected Flatt's argument that she received inadequate information before consenting to her son's circumcision shortly after his birth in 1997. If she had had more information, she would not have consented, she said....Jurors agreed with defense attorneys' arguments that Flatt had been told of the possible complications and that there is no need for doctors to outline every possible "insignificant" risk.
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In March 2009 a<space/><link><target>Fulton County, Georgia</target><part>Fulton County, Ga.</part></link>, State Court jury awarded $2.3 million in damages to a 4-year-old boy and his mother for a botched circumcision in which too much tissue was removed causing permanent disfigurement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.com/jsp/article.jsp?id</arg><arg name="author">Katheryn Hayes Tucker<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jury Awards $2.3 Million for Botched Circumcision<space/></arg><arg name="date">31 March 2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Law.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In August 2010 an eight-day-old boy was circumcised in a Florida hospital against the stated wishes of the parents. The hospital admitted that the boy was circumcised by mistake; the mother has sued the hospital and the doctor involved in the case.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/09/15/1826768/moms-sues-hospital-over-babys.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Accidental circumcision leads to lawsuit, protest<space/></arg><arg name="author">Fred Tasker<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 August 2010<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Miami Herald<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MiamiHerald.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>USSR</heading><paragraph>Before<space/><link><target>glasnost</target></link>, according to an article in<space/><link><target>The Jewish Press</target></link>, Jewish ritual circumcision was forbidden in the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>USSR</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barbara Oka,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.russianjewry.org/about/media/jp9.php'>&quot;Soviet Jews Of All Ages Seek Circumcision&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The Jewish Press</italics>, 14 March 1991.</extension><space/>However, David E. Fishman, professor of Jewish History at the<space/><link><target>Jewish Theological Seminary of America</target></link>, states that, whereas the<space/><italics><link><target>Cheder</target><part>heder</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>yeshiva</target></link></italics>, the organs of Jewish education, &quot;were banned by virtue of the law separating church and school, and subjected to tough police and administrative actions,&quot; circumcision was not proscribed by law or suppressed by executive measures.<extension extension_name='ref'>David E. Fishman, &quot;Judaism in the USSR, 19171930: The Fate of Religious Education,&quot; in: Yaacov Ro'i, ed.,<space/><italics>Jews and Jewish Life in Russia and the Soviet Union</italics><space/>(Cummings Center Series; London: Cass, 1995), 251262; pp. 251252.</extension>Jehoshua A. Gilboa writes that while circumcision was not officially or explicitly banned, pressure was exerted to make it difficult.<space/><italics><link><target>Mohel</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics><space/>in particular were concerned that they could be punished for any health issue that might develop, even if it arose some time after the circumcision.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;There was no official prohibition of circumcision and, on the whole, even the propaganda attacks on it were relatively restrained, apparently out of consideration for the presence of many millions of Moslems [...] in the Soviet Union. But at the same time numerous pressures were exerted to make observance of this precept [i.e., circumcision] difficult. Needless to say, Jewish members of the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Communist Party</part></link><space/>were in an embarrassing situation when they personally faced the question whether to circumcise their sons [...] And the uncertainty weighed heaviest on the<space/><italics>mohalim</italics><space/>themselves [...] Any health problem developing in the baby some time after circumcision could serve to incriminate the<space/><italics>mohel</italics>. It is easy to imagine, for example, the impact of news items on the death of children because of [...] circumcision (and the punishments imposed on<space/><italics>mohalim</italics>), even if there were no explicit legal bans on circumcision.&quot; Jehoshua A. Gilboa,<space/><italics>A Language Silenced: The Suppression of Hebrew Literature and Culture in the Soviet Union</italics><space/>(London: Associated University Press, 1982), pp. 3435.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Forced circumcision</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>William E. Brigman.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/brigman/'>Circumcision as Child Abuse: The Legal and Constitutional Issues.</link><space/>23 J Fam Law 337 (1985).</listitem><listitem>Rich Winkel.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.math.missouri.edu/~rich/MGM/primer.html'>Male Circumcision in the USA: A Human Rights Primer</link></listitem><listitem>Ross Povenmire.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/povenmire/'>Do Parents Have the Legal Authority to Consent to the Surgical Amputation of Normal, Healthy Tissue From Their Infant Children?: The Practice of Circumcision in the United States.</link><space/>7 Journal of Gender, Social Policy &amp; the Law 87 (19981999).</listitem><listitem>Gregory J Boyle, J. Steven Svoboda, Christopher P Price, J Neville Turner.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cirp.org/library/legal/boyle1/'>Circumcision of Healthy Boys: Criminal Assault?</link><space/>7 Journal of Law and Medicine 301 (2000). The authors are leading anti-circumcision campaigners.</listitem><listitem>Peter W. Adler.<space/><link type='external' href='http://rjolpi.richmond.edu/archive/Adler_Formatted.pdf'>Is Circumcision Legal?</link><space/>16(3) Richmond J. L. &amp; Pub. Int. 439 (2013).</listitem><listitem>Amicus curiae briefs filed in Oregon circumcision case:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.doctorsopposingcircumcision.org/pdf/2007-04BoldtReview.pdf'>Amicus Brief without attachments (Doctors Opposing Circumcision)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.doctorsopposingcircumcision.org/pdf/2007-07BoldtMerits.pdf'>Amicus Brief on the Merits (Doctors Opposing Circumcision)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ouradio.org/images/uploads/Oregon_Circumcision.pdf'>Amicus Brief on the Merits (American Jewish Congress, American Jewish Committee, Anti-Defamation League, and Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America)</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Circumcision series</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Circumcision And Law</target></template><link><target>Category:Circumcision debate</target></link><link><target>Category:Tort law</target></link><link><target>Category:Common law</target></link><link><target>Category:Children's rights</target><part></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>fr:Circoncision#Aspects juridiques</target></link></paragraph></article>