<article title='Dagger'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the weapon</arg></template><link><target>File:Fs-dagger.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>FairbairnSykes fighting knife</target></link>, a modern-day dagger</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>dagger</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>knife</target></link><space/>with a very sharp point designed or capable of being used as a thrusting or stabbing weapon.<extension extension_name='ref'>State v. Martin, 633 S.W.2d 80 (Mo. 1982): This is the dictionary or popular-use definition of a dagger, which has been used to describe everything from an ice pick to a folding knife with pointed blade as a 'dagger'. The Missouri Supreme Court used the popular definition of 'dagger' found in Webster's New Universal Dictionary (&quot;a short weapon with a sharp point used for stabbing&quot;) to rule that an ordinary pointed knife with four-to-five inch blade constitutes a 'dagger' under the Missouri criminal code.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>California Penal Code 12020(a)(24):&quot;dagger&quot; means a<space/><italics>knife or other instrument</italics><space/>with or without a handguard that is<space/><italics>capable of ready use as a stabbing weapon</italics><space/>that may inflict great bodily injury or death. The State of California and other jurisdictions have seized upon the popular-use definition of a dagger to classify items ranging from a pointed kitchen knife to a tent stake as a 'dagger' under the law.</extension><space/>The design dates to human prehistory, and daggers have been used throughout human experience to the modern day in<space/><link><target>close combat</target></link><space/>confrontations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burton, Walter E.,<space/><italics>Knives For Fighting Men</italics>, Popular Science, July 1944, Vol. 145 No. 1, p. 150: The dagger is classified as a type of<space/><bold>fighting knife</bold>, while a<space/><italics><link><target>combat knife</target></link></italics><space/>is a knife<space/><bold>specifically designed for military use</bold>, and is thus only certain types of daggers designed for military use are considered to be combat knives. Thus, an ordinary dagger designed for civilian sale and use is only a fighting knife, while the U.S. Army M3 trench knife is both a combat knife<space/><italics>and</italics><space/>a fighting knife.</extension><space/>Many ancient cultures used adorned daggers in ritual and ceremonial purposes, a trend which continues to the present time in the form of art knives. The distinctive shape and historic usage of the dagger have made it iconic and symbolic.</paragraph><paragraph>Over the years, the term has been used to describe a wide variety of thrusting knives, including knives that feature only a single cutting edge, such as the European<space/><link><target>rondel dagger</target></link><space/>or the Persian<space/><link><target>pesh-kabz</target></link>, or, in some instances, no cutting edge at all, such as the<space/><link><target>stiletto</target></link><space/>of the Renaissance. However, over the last hundred years or so, authorities have recognized that the dagger, in its contemporary or mature form, has certain definable characteristics, including a short blade with a sharply tapered point, a central<space/><link><target>Knife#Materials, features, and construction</target><part>spine</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>fuller (weapon)</target><part>fuller</part></link>, and (usually) two cutting edges sharpened the full length of the blade, or nearly so.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EME">Emerson, Robert L.,<space/><italics>Legal Medicine and Toxicology</italics>, New York: D. Appleton &amp; Co. (1909), p. 80</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cas">Cassidy, William L.,<space/><italics>The Complete Book Of Knife Fighting</italics>, ISBN 0-87364-029-2, ISBN 978-0-87364-029-9 (1997), pp. 918, 2736</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="DRA">Draper, Frank W.,<space/><italics>A Text-book of Legal Medicine</italics>, Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders &amp; Co. (1905), pp. 341343</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gross, Hans,<space/><italics>Criminal Investigation: A Practical Textbook for Magistrates, Police Officers and Lawyers</italics>, London: Sweet &amp; Maxwell (1949), p. 185</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Harding, David, and Cann, Jefferson (eds.),<space/><italics>Weapons: An International Encyclopedia from 5000 B.C. to 2000 A.D.</italics>, The Diagram Visual Group, New York: St. Martin's Press/Macmillan, ISBN 0-312-03950-6, ISBN 978-0-312-03950-9 (1990), pp. 3233</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Goddard, Wayne,<space/><italics>The Wonder of Knifemaking</italics>, Iola, WI: Krause Publications, ISBN 1-4402-1684-3, ISBN 978-1-4402-1684-8 (2011), pp. 50, 131132</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most daggers also feature a full crossguard to keep the hand from riding forwards onto the sharpened blade edges. Another distinctive feature of the modern dagger is that it is designed to position the blade horizontally when using a conventional<space/><link><target>Knife fight#Basic knife fighting techniques</target><part>palm grip</part></link>, enabling the user to slash right or left as well as thrust the blade between an opponent's ribs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cas"></extension><space/>The twin full-length edges enable the user to make broad slashes (cuts) using either a forehand or backhand arm movement, while the sharp, acutely pointed tip makes the knife an effective thrusting or stabbing weapon.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cas"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="WER"><italics>The New Werner Twentieth Century edition of the Encyclopaedia Britannica</italics>, Volume 6, Akron, OH: The Werner Co. (1907), p. 669</extension><space/>This versatility distinguishes the modern dagger from more specialized thrusting knives, like the stiletto.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WER"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://definitions.uslegal.com/d/dagger/'>Dagger Law &amp; Legal Definition</link></italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early history</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Poignard 0.188.1 2 fond.jpg</target><part>150px</part><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>Neolithic</target></link><space/>dagger from the<space/><link><target>Musum de Toulouse</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Pual bero de frontn (M.A.N.) 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=.5</part><part>left</part><part>Pre-Roman Iberian iron dagger forged between the middle of the 5th century BCE and the 3rd century BCE</part></link><link><target>File:Bronze age, Kurdistan, Sine.jpg</target><part>150px</part><part>thumbnail</part><part>Bronze age swords,<space/><link><target>Kurdistan</target></link>, museum of Sanandaj</part></link><link><target>File:Pual bero antenas atrofiadas (M.A.N.) 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=.5</part><part>right</part><part>Iberian triangular iron dagger</part></link>Much like<space/><link><target>battle axe</target><trail>s</trail></link>, daggers evolved out of<space/><link><target>prehistoric</target></link><space/><link><target>tool</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In<space/><link><target>Neolithic</target></link><space/>times, daggers were made of materials such as<space/><link><target>flint</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ivory</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>bone</target></link><space/>and were used as weapons since the earliest periods of human civilization. The earliest metal daggers are of copper and appear in the early<space/><link><target>Bronze Age</target></link>, in the 3rd millennium BCE, predating the<space/><link><target>Bronze Age sword</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sheridan, Alison,<space/><italics>A Beaker Period Copper Dagger Blade from the Silees River near Ross Lough, Co. Fermanagh</italics>, Ulster Journal of Archaeology, Vol. 56 (1993), pp. 6162</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From<space/><link><target>pre-dynastic Egypt</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Iorwerth Eiddon Stephen Edwards, Cyril John Gadd, Nicholas Geoffrey Lemprire Hammond, 1970</extension><space/>daggers were adorned as<space/><link><target>ceremonial weapon</target><part>ceremonial objects</part></link><space/>with golden hilts and later even more ornate and varied construction. One early silver dagger was recovered with midrib design. Traditionally, some military and naval officers wore dress daggers as symbols of power, and modern soldiers are still equipped with<space/><link><target>combat knife</target><part>combat knives</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>knife bayonet</target><trail>s</trail></link>.Copper daggers of<space/><link><target>Early Minoan III</target></link><space/>were recovered at<space/><link><target>Knossos</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>C. Michael Hogan,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.themodernantiquarian.com/site/10854/knossos.html#fieldnotes'>''Knossos fieldnotes'', Modern Antiquarian (2007)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In ancient Egypt, daggers were usually made of copper or bronze, while royalty had gold weapons. The 1924 opening of the<space/><link><target>Tutankhamun's mummy</target><part>tomb of Tutankhamun</part></link><space/>revealed two daggers, one with a gold blade, and one of smelted iron. Iron ore was not found in Egypt, making the iron dagger rare, and the context suggests that the iron dagger was valued on a level equal to that of its ceremonial gold counterpart.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Tutankhamun's armies: battle and conquest during ancient Egypt's late eighteenth dynasty</arg><arg name="author">Jay Cassell</arg><arg name="editor">Peter J. Fiduccia</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="page">77<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN">978-0-471-74358-3</arg></template></extension><space/>The iron dagger is actually a majority iron content alloy that is considered to be of meteoric origin.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.incose-cc.org/2010/03/king-tutankhamuns-dagger/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of the earliest objects made of smelted iron dates is a dagger dating to before 2000 BCE, found in a context that suggests it was treated as an ornamental object of great value. Found in a Hattic royal tomb dated about 2500 BCE, at Alaca Hyk in northern Anatolia, the dagger has a smelted iron blade and a gold handle.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Out of the fiery furnace: the impact of metals on the history of mankind<space/></arg><arg name="author">Robert Raymond<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penn State Press</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="page">61<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN">978-0-271-00441-9<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Antiquity</heading><paragraph>The artisans and blacksmiths of<space/><link><target>Iberia</target></link><space/>in what is now southern Spain and southwestern France produced various iron daggers and swords of high quality from the 5th to the 3rd century BCE, in ornamentation and patterns influenced by Greek, Punic (Carthaginian), and Phoenician culture.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WIS">Wise, Terence,<space/><italics>Armies of the Carthaginian Wars, 265146 BCE</italics>, London: Osprey Publishing Ltd., ISBN 0-85045-430-1, ISBN 978-0-85045-430-7 (1982), pp. 2021</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Keay, Simon (Prof.),<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.swanhellenic.com/library/phoenicians-carthaginians-and-romans-in-southern-iberia-13715.html'>Phoenicians, Carthaginians and Romans in Southern Iberia</link></italics>, Swan Hellenic's Online Library &amp; Archive, 30 June 2011, retrieved 2 August 2011</extension><space/>The exceptional purity of<space/><link><target>Iberians</target><part>Iberian</part></link><space/>iron and the sophisticated method of forging, which included cold hammering, produced double-edged weapons of excellent quality.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WIS"></extension><space/>One can find technologically advanced designs such as folding knives rusted among the artifacts of many Second Iberian Iron Age cremation burials or in Roman Empire excavations all around Spain and the Mediterranean.<extension extension_name='ref'>De Fontcuberta, Eduardo A.,<space/><italics>Bandolero Blades</italics>, Tactical-Life.com, Tactical Knives (September 2010), retrieved 13 August 2011</extension><space/>Iberian infantrymen carried several types of iron daggers, most of them based on shortened versions of double-edged swords, but the true Iberian dagger had a triangular-shaped blade. Iberian daggers and swords were later adopted by Hannibal and his Carthaginian armies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WIS"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Lusitanians</target><part>Lusitanii</part></link>, a pre-Celtic people dominating the lands northwest of Iberia (most of modern Portugal) successfully held off the Roman Empire for many years with a variety of innovative tactics and light weapons, including iron-bladed short spears and daggers modeled after Iberian patterns.</paragraph><paragraph>During the Roman Empire, legionaries were issued a<space/><italics><link><target>pugio</target></link></italics><space/>(from the Latin<space/><italics>pugn</italics>, or fight), a double-edged iron thrusting dagger with a blade of 712 inches. The design and fabrication of the<space/><italics>pugio</italics><space/>was taken directly from Iberian daggers and short swords; the Romans even adopted the triangular-bladed Iberian dagger, which they called the<space/><italics>parazonium</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WIS"></extension><space/>Like the<space/><italics><link><target>gladius</target></link></italics>, the<space/><italics>pugio</italics><space/>was most often used as a thrusting (stabbing weapon). As an extreme close-quarter combat weapon, the<space/><italics>pugio</italics><space/>was the Roman soldier's last line of defense. When not in battle, the<space/><italics>pugio</italics><space/>served as a convenient utility knife.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">A concise dictionary of Greek and Roman antiquities<space/></arg><arg name="author">Sir William Smith<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Murray</arg><arg name="year">1898</arg><arg name="page">66<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Francis Warre Cornish<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Middle Ages</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Misericorde (weapon)</arg><arg>Rondel dagger</arg></template>The term<space/><italics><link><target>:wikt:dagger</target><part>dagger</part></link></italics><space/>appears only in the<space/><link><target>Late Middle Ages</target></link>, reflecting the fact that while the dagger had been known in antiquity, it had disappeared during the Early Middle Ages, replaced by the hewing knife or<space/><link><target>seax</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Underwood, Richard (1999)<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Weapons and Warfare</italics><space/>Stroud, England: Tempus, ISBN 0-7524-1910-2 p70.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gale, David (1989)<space/><italics>The Seax</italics><space/>in<space/><italics>Weapons and Warfare in Anglo-Saxon England</italics><space/>Oxford, England: Oxbow ISBN 0-947816-21-6</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:De Fechtbuch Talhoffer 169.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Depiction of combat with the dagger (''degen'') in<space/><link><target>Hans Talhoffer</target></link><space/>(1467)</part></link>The dagger reappeared in the 12th century as the &quot;knightly dagger&quot;, or more properly cross-hilt or quillon dagger,<extension extension_name='ref'>Capwell, p. 28 and Thompson, p. 25. Note that the term quillon is a modern invention, though it is commonly used</extension><space/>and was developed into a common arm and tool for civilian use by the late medieval period.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Knight<space/></arg><arg name="author">Christopher Gravett<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin,</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="page">17</arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0-7566-6762-7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:ReproMedievalDaggers.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Modern reproductions of three of the four main types of Medieval dagger. From left to right: Ballock Dagger (a copy of Wallace Collection A732 by Arms &amp; Armor, US), a typical later style of rondel dagger (by English Cutler, UK) and a sword-hilt dagger made by the photographer, based on an original 14th century dagger in the Museum of London (formerly in the Guildhall Museum).</part></link>The earliest known depiction of a cross-hilt dagger is the so-called &quot;Guido relief&quot; inside the<space/><link><target>Grossmnster</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Zrich</target></link><space/>(c. 1120).<extension extension_name='ref'>Daniel Gutscher,<space/><italics>Das Grossmnster in Zrich</italics><space/>(1983), 120121, 214215.</extension><space/>A number of depictions of the fully developed cross-hilt dagger are found in the<space/><link><target>Morgan Bible</target></link><space/>(c. 1240). Many of these cross-hilt daggers resemble miniature swords, with cross guards and pommels very similar in form to swords of the period.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Thompson, p. 10 and Peterson, plate 25, for good examples of this type in the Museum of London</extension><space/>Others, however, are not an exact match to known sword designs, having for example pommel caps, large hollow star shaped pommels on so-called Burgundian Heraldic daggers or antenna style cross and pommel, reminiscent of Hallstatt era daggers.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Capwell pp. 28, 122-123, Thompson pp. 24-25, and Peterson plates 26-29</extension>The cross-hilt type persisted well into the Renaissance<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Peterson plate 46 and Dean p.96, No. 100</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Old French</target></link><space/>term<space/><italics><link><target>:wikt:dague</target><part>dague</part></link></italics><space/>appears to have referred to these weapons in the 13th century, alongside other terms such as<space/><italics>poignal</italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>basilard</target></link></italics>. The<space/><link><target>Late Middle English</target><part>Middle English</part></link><space/><italics>dagger</italics><space/>is used from the 1380s.</paragraph><paragraph>During this time, the dagger was often employed in the role of a<space/><link><target>companion weapon</target><part>secondary defense weapon</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>close combat</target></link>. The knightly dagger evolved into the larger<space/><link><target>baselard</target></link><space/>knife in the 14th century. The baselard was considered an intermediate between a short sword and a long dagger, and became popular also as a civilian weapon.<space/><link><target>Sloane MS</target></link>. 2593 (c. 1400) records a song satirizing the use of oversized baselard knives as fashion accessories.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>prenegarde prenegarde, thus bere I myn baselard</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=s9iobZUO8nUC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>ed. Pickering 1836</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the Late Middle Ages, knives with blade designs that emphasized thrusting attacks, such as the<space/><link><target>stiletto</target></link>, became increasingly popular, and some thrusting knives commonly referred to as 'daggers' ceased to have a cutting edge. This was a response to the deployment of heavy armor, such as<space/><link><target>maille</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>plate armour</target></link>, where cutting attacks were ineffective and focus was on thrusts with narrow blades to punch through mail or aim at armour plate intersections (or the eye slits of the helmet visor). These late medieval thrusting weapons are sometimes classed by the shape of their hilt as either<space/><link><target>roundel dagger</target><part>roundel</part></link>,<space/><link><target>bollock dagger</target><part>bollock</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Ear dagger</target><part>ear</part></link><space/>daggers.The term<space/><italics>dagger</italics><space/>is coined in this time, as are the<space/><link><target>Early Modern German</target></link><space/>equivalents<space/><italics><link><target>:wikt:Dolch</target><part>dolch</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>tolch</italics>) and<space/><italics><link><target>:wikt:Degen#Etymology 2</target><part>degen</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>tegen</italics>).In the<space/><link><target>German school of fencing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Johannes Liechtenauer</target></link><space/>(<link><target>3227a</target><part>Ms. 3227a</part></link>) and his successors (specifically Andres Lignizer in<space/><link><target>Cod. 44 A 8</target></link>) taught fighting with the dagger.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Schools and Masters of Fencing: From the Middle Ages to the Eighteenth Century<space/></arg><arg name="author">Egerton Castle</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="page">246</arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0-486-42826-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>These techniques in some respects resemble modern<space/><link><target>knife fighting</target></link>, but emphasized thrusting strokes almost exclusively, instead of slashes and cuts. When used offensively, a standard attack frequently employed the reverse or<space/><link><target>icepick grip</target></link>, stabbing downward with the blade to increase thrust and penetrative force. This was done primarily because the blade point frequently had to penetrate or push apart an opponent's steel<space/><link><target>chain mail</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>plate armor</target></link><space/>in order to inflict an injury. The disadvantage of employing the medieval dagger in this manner was that it could easily be blocked by a variety of techniques, most notably by a block with the weaponless arm while simultaneously attacking with a weapon held in the right hand. Another disadvantage was the reduction in effective blade reach to the opponent when using a reverse grip. As the wearing of armor fell out of favor, dagger fighting techniques began to evolve which emphasized the use of the dagger with a conventional or forward grip, while the reverse or icepick grip was retained when attacking an unsuspecting opponent from behind, such as in an assassination.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Renaissance and Early Modern era</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Stiletto</arg><arg>Parrying dagger</arg><arg>Dirk</arg></template><link><target>File:Dagger horse head Louvre OA7892 full.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=.5</part><part><link><target>Mughal Empire</target><part>Mughal</part></link><space/>dagger,<space/><link><target>Louvre</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The dagger was very popular as a fencing and personal defense weapon in 17th- and 18th-century Spain, where it was referred to as the<space/><italics>daga</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>pual</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Blade's Guide to Knives & Their Values<space/></arg><arg name="author">Steve Shackleford</arg><arg name="publisher">Krause Publications</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="page">246</arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-1-4402-0387-9<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>During the Renaissance Age the dagger was used as part of everyday dress, and daggers were the only weapon commoners were allowed to carry on their person.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Medieval and Renaissance Dagger Combat</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Jason Vail<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Paladin Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="page">16</arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-1-58160-517-4<space/></arg></template></extension>In English, the terms<space/><italics>poniard</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>dirk</italics><space/>are loaned during the late 16th to early 17th century, the latter in the spelling<space/><italics>dork, durk</italics><space/>(presumably via Low German, Dutch or Scandinavian<space/><italics>dolk, dolch</italics>, ultimately from a West Slavic<space/><italics>tulich</italics>), the modern spelling<space/><italics>dirk</italics><space/>dating to 18th-century<space/><link><target>Scots language</target><part>Scots</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Beginning with the 17th century, another form of daggerthe plug<space/><link><target>bayonet</target></link><space/>and later the socket bayonetwas used to convert<space/><link><target>musket</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other<space/><link><target>long gun</target><part>longarms</part></link><space/>into<space/><link><target>spear</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>by mounting them on the barrel.</paragraph><paragraph>During the same time, highly elaborate and richly decorated daggers were produced in<space/><link><target>India</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern (1815 to 2000s)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Combat knife</arg></template><link><target>File:Ek knives.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Daggers from the 20th century made by<space/><link><target>Ek Commando Knife Co.</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>WW1 trench warfare caused daggers and fighting knives to come back in play. They also replaced the sabres worn by officers, which were too long and clumsy for trench warfare. They were worn with pride as a sign of having served front line duty.</paragraph><paragraph>Daggers achieved public notoriety in the 20th century as ornamental uniform regalia during the Fascist dictatorships of Mussolini's Italy and Hitler's Germany. The resurgence of these dress daggers and accoutrements in post-World War I Germany gave a much needed boost to the flagging fortunes of the metalworking center Solingen. Dress daggers were used by several other countries as well, including Japan, but never to the same extent as those worn by the military and political bodies of the Third Reich or Fascist Italy. As combat equipment they were carried by many infantry and<space/><link><target>commando</target></link><space/>forces during the<space/><link><target>World War II</target><part>Second World War</part></link>. British Commando and other elite units were issued an especially slender dagger, the<space/><link><target>Fairbairn-Sykes fighting knife</target></link>, developed by<space/><link><target>William E. Fairbairn</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eric A. Sykes</target></link><space/>from real-life close-combat experiences gained while serving on the Shanghai Municipal Police Force.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cas"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Chambers, John W.,<space/><italics>OSS Training in the National Parks and Service Abroad in World War II,</italics><space/>Washington, D.C., U.S. National Park Service (2008), p. 191: Fairbairn reportedly engaged in hundreds of street fights in his twenty-year career in Shanghai, where he organized and headed a special anti-riot squad. Much of his body arms, legs, torso, and even the palms of his hands was covered with scars from knife wounds from those fights.</extension><space/>The F-S dagger proved very popular with the commandos, who used it primarily for sentry elimination. Some units of the<space/><link><target>Marine Raiders</target><part>U.S. Marine Corps Raiders</part></link><space/>in the Pacific were issued a similar fighting dagger, the<space/><link><target>United States Marine Raider Stiletto</target><part>Marine Raider Stiletto</part></link>.,<extension extension_name='ref'>Walker, Greg,<space/><italics>Battle Blades: A Professional's Guide to Combat/Fighting Knives</italics>, Boulder, Colo.: Paladin Press, ISBN 0-87364-732-7 (1993), p. 77</extension><space/>though this modified design proved less than successful when used in the type of knife combat encountered in the Pacific theater<extension extension_name='ref'>Alexander, Joseph H.,<space/><italics>Edson's Raiders: The 1st Marine Raider Battalion in World War II</italics>, Annapolis MD: Naval Institute Press, ISBN 1-55750-020-7 (2001), p. 67</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Sledge, E.B.,<space/><italics>With The Old Breed: At Peleleiu and Okinawa</italics>, Presidio Press, ISBN 978-0-89141-919-8 (2007), pp. 2122</extension><space/>due to this version using inferior materials and manufacturing techniques.<extension extension_name='ref'>McCarthy, John (2008). &quot;WWII Marine Raider Stiletto Reborn&quot;. Raider Patch (U.S. Marine Raider Association).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the Vietnam War, the<space/><link><target>Gerber Mark II</target></link>, designed by US Army Captain Bud Holzman and Al Mar, was a popular fighting knife pattern that was privately purchased by many U.S. soldiers and marines serving in that conflict.</paragraph><paragraph>Aside from military forces, most daggers are no longer carried openly, but concealed in clothing. One of the more popular forms of the concealable dagger is the<space/><italics><link><target>boot knife</target></link></italics>. The boot knife is nothing more than a shortened dagger that is compact enough to be worn on the lower leg, usually by means of a sheath clipped or strapped to a boot or other footwear.<extension extension_name='ref' name="des"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Steele</arg><arg name="first"><space/>David</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Boot Knife Fighting</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Black Belt</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4</arg><arg name="pages">48–51<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Active Interest Media, Inc.</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988<space/></arg></template></extension><template><target>-</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Cultural symbolism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:US Army Special Operations Command SSI.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=.5</part><part>right</part><part>U.S. Army emblem with dagger</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The dagger is symbolically ambiguous. Daggers are commonly used as part of the insignias of elite military units or special forces, such as the US Army Airborne Special Operations unit or the Commando Dagger patch for those who have completed the British<space/><link><target>All Arms Commando Course</target></link>. Daggers may be associated with deception, stealth, and/or treachery due to the ease of concealment and surprise that someone could inflict with one on an unsuspecting victim, and indeed many<space/><link><target>assassinations</target></link><space/>have been carried out with the use of a dagger, including that of<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The History That Was Never Spoken<space/></arg><arg name="author">David Gray<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Lulu</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="page">87</arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-1-4116-1703-2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>A<space/><link><target>cloak and dagger</target></link><space/>attack is one in which a deceitful, traitorous, or concealed enemy attacks a person.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Dickens<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Charles<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Barnaby Rudge: A Tale of the Riots of 'Eighty<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1841<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Chapman & Hall<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-14-043728-2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>203</arg></template></extension><space/>On the other hand, for some cultures and military organizations the dagger symbolizes courage and daring in combat.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The illustrated encyclopedia of military insignia of the 20th century: a comprehensive A-Z guide to the badges, patches, and embellishments of the world's armed forces<space/></arg><arg name="author">Guido Rosignoli<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Stanley Paul</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="page">44<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0-09-172670-6<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Art knives</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Art Knives by Buster Warenski.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Buster Warenski dagger</part></link>Daggers are a popular form of what is known as the &quot;art knife&quot;, due in part to the symmetry of the blade.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Images of Steel</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ethen<space/></arg><arg name="last">Edwards</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Blade Magazine</arg><arg name="pages">40–43</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="volume">27<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>One of the most famous examples is knifemaker<space/><link><target>Buster Warenski</target></link>'s replication of the gold dagger found in<space/><link><target>Tutankhamun</target></link>'s tomb. Warenski's dagger was made with a cast gold blade and the knife contained 32 ounces of pure gold in its construction.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Winter</arg><arg name="first">Butch</arg><arg name="title">The Art of the Knife</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Popular Mechanics</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg><arg name="pages">86–88</arg><arg name="volume">166</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Hearst Magazines</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-03-10</arg></template></extension><space/>One of the knives required of an<space/><link><target>American Bladesmith Society</target></link><space/>Mastersmith is the construction of an &quot;art knife&quot; or a &quot;European style&quot; dagger.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">ABS Testing Rules and Guidelines for the Master Smith Rating</arg><arg name="url">http://www.americanbladesmith.com/uploads/file/Testing/MS%20Test%20FINAL%204-24-2010.pdf</arg><arg name="format">pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-03-12</arg></template></extension><template><target>-</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Blade</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dagger (typography)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Knife</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Knife fight</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of daggers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Push dagger</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of blade materials</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Capwell, Dr. Tobias.<space/><italics>The World Encyclopedia of Knives, Daggers, and Bayonets</italics>. Hermes House. Leicestershire. 2011.<space/></listitem><listitem>Dean, Bashford.<space/><italics>Catalogue of European Daggers 13001800</italics>. Metropolitan Museum of Art. New York. 1929.</listitem><listitem>Edge, David and Paddock, John Miles.<space/><italics>Arms &amp; Armor of the Medieval Knight - An Illustrated History of Weapons in the Middle Ages</italics>. Crescent Books. New York. 1988.</listitem><listitem>Iorwerth Eiddon Stephen Edwards, Cyril John Gadd, Nicholas Geoffrey Lemprire Hammond.<space/><italics>The Cambridge Ancient History</italics>. Cambridge University Press. 1970. (ISBN 0-521-07051-1)</listitem><listitem>Peterson, Harold L.<space/><italics>Daggers &amp; Fighting Knives of the Western World</italics>. Bonanza Books. New York. 1970.</listitem><listitem>Thompson, Logan.<space/><italics>Daggers and Bayonets - A History</italics>. Paladin Press. Boulder. 1999.</listitem><listitem>Vail, Jason.<space/><italics>Medieval and Renaissance Dagger Combat</italics>. Paladin Press. Boulder. 2006.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Daggers</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Knives</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Daggers</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Blade weapons</target></link></paragraph></article>