<article title='Alexander_Jannaeus'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox monarch</target><arg name="name"><space/>Alexander Jannaeus
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>King and High Priest of Judea 
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>File:Alexander Jannaeus.jpg</arg><arg>center</arg><arg>thumb</arg><arg>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Alexander Jannaeus, woodcut designed by [[Guillaume Rouillé]]. From ''[[Promptuarii Iconum Insigniorum]].''
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>c. 103 — 76 BC
</arg><arg name="predecessor">[[Aristobulus I]]
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Salome Alexandra]]
</arg><arg name="royal house">
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[John Hyrcanus I]]
</arg><arg name="mother">
</arg><arg name="birth_date">
</arg><arg name="birth_place">
</arg><arg name="death_date">
</arg><arg name="death_place">
</arg><arg name="buried">
</arg></template><link><target>Image:Judea Alexander Jannes.PNG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Hasmonean Kingdom under Alexander Jannaeus<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>legend</target><arg>lime</arg><arg>situation in 103 BC</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>fuchsia</arg><arg>area conquered</arg></template></part></link><bold>Alexander Jannaeus</bold><space/>(also known as<space/><bold>Alexander Jannai/Yannai</bold>;<space/><link><target>Hebrew</target></link>: ) was king of<space/><link><target>Judea</target></link><space/>from 103&amp;nbsp;BC to 76&amp;nbsp;BC. The son of<space/><link><target>John Hyrcanus</target></link>, he inherited the throne from his brother<space/><link><target>Aristobulus I</target></link>, and appears to have married his brother's widow,<space/><italics>Shlomtzion</italics><space/>or &quot;Shelomit&quot;, also known as<space/><link><target>Salome Alexandra</target></link>, according to the Biblical law of<space/><link><target>Yibbum</target></link><space/>(&quot;levirate marriage&quot;), although<space/><link><target>Josephus</target></link><space/>is inexplicit on that point. Since Alexander Jannaeus was a high priest, he was technically breaking Jewish law according to the<space/><link><target>Priestly Code</target><part>laws in Leviticus</part></link>. The laws in Leviticus state that a Jewish high priest is forbidden to marry a widow. The Law in Leviticus would have taken precedence over the biblical law in Deuteronomy that allowed the marriage of a non-high priest individual to a childless brother's widow.</paragraph><paragraph>His likely full Hebrew name was &quot;Jonathan&quot;; he may have been the High Priest Jonathan, rather than his great-uncle of the same name, who established the<space/><link><target>Masada</target></link><space/>fortress. Under the name &quot;King Yannai&quot; he appears as a wicked tyrant in the<space/><link><target>Talmud</target></link>, reflecting his conflict with the<space/><link><target>Pharisee</target></link><space/>party. He is among the more colorful historical figures, despite being little known outside specialized history. He and his widow (who became<space/><link><target>queen regnant</target></link><space/>after his death) had a substantial impact on the subsequent development of Judaism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="DGRBM"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last"><space/>Mason<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles Peter<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alexander, Jannaeus<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]]<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia"><space/>[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>117<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Little, Brown and Company]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1867<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Family</heading><paragraph>Alexander Jannaeus was the third son of John Hyrcanus, by his second wife. When Aristobulus I, Hyrcanus' son by his first wife, became king, he deemed it necessary for his own security to imprison his half-brother. Aristobulus died after a reign of one year. Upon his death, his widow,<space/><link><target>Salome Alexandra</target></link><space/>had Alexander and his brothers released from prison.<extension extension_name='ref' name="je"><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/1144-alexander-jannaeus-jonathan'>&quot;Alexander Jannaeus&quot;, ''Jewish encyclopedia''</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexander, as the oldest living brother, had the right not only to the throne but also to Salome, the widow of his deceased brother, who had died childless; and, although she was thirteen years older than he, he married her. By her, he had two sons, the eldest,<space/><link><target>Hyrcanus II</target></link><space/>became high-priest in 62&amp;nbsp;BC and<space/><link><target>Aristobulus II</target></link><space/>who was high-priest from 66 - 62&amp;nbsp;BC and started a bloody civil war with his brother, ending in his capture by<space/><link><target>Pompey the Great</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite Josephus</target><arg name="text">wars</arg><arg name="bookno">1</arg><arg name="Wchapter"></arg><arg name="chunkid">107</arg><arg name="NorW">N</arg><arg name="pace">1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Conquests</heading><paragraph>During the twenty-seven year reign of Alexander Jannaeus, he was almost constantly involved in military conflict. International factors at the time created an environment suitable for Jannaeus' conquests. First, Jannaeus received support from<space/><link><target>Cleopatra III of Egypt</target></link>. This support was particularly crucial during the war with Ptolemy Lathyrus (discussed later). Ultimately, conflict in the<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target></link><space/>was the greatest outside influence on Judean military campaigns. Political instability in Rome led to a<space/><link><target>Sulla's first civil war</target><part>Civil War</part></link><space/>beginning in 88&amp;nbsp;BC. With Rome chiefly concerned with a tumultuous domestic predicament, Jannaeus was free to expand the Judean state.</paragraph><heading level='3'>War with Ptolemy Lathyrus</heading><paragraph>Alexander's first expedition was against the<space/><link><target>polis</target></link><space/>of Ptolemais (<link><target>Akko</target><part>Acre</part></link>). This campaign seems to have been well timed politically as the weak<space/><link><target>Seleucid Empire</target></link><space/>was unable to intervene. Help came to the citizens of Ptolemais from<space/><link><target>Ptolemy Lathyrus</target></link>, who had been cast out by his mother, Cleopatra III, and had founded a kingdom in<space/><link><target>History of Cyprus</target><part>Cyprus</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Ptolemy landed a large army for the relief of the town; but Alexander met him with treachery, arranging an alliance with him openly while secretly he sought to obtain the help of his mother against him. As soon as Ptolemy learned of this intrigue, he marched against<space/><link><target>Asochis</target></link>, near Sepphoris, which he captured, together with 10,000 prisoners and much plunder. A similar attack upon<space/><link><target>Sepphoris</target></link><space/>failed; but in a later battle at Azophon on the Jordan, Alexander with his whole army suffered a defeat at the hands of a much smaller force. Alexander allowed the enemy to cross the river unimpeded, in order that, as he thought, he might more easily catch it between his army and the stream. He saw his error only when it was too late. The enemy fell upon the Jewish camp, women and children were struck down, their corpses were hacked to pieces, flung into caldrons and boiled, so that the people thought they were dealing with cannibals. This act was used to terrify the Judean people and their military.</paragraph><paragraph>Alexander might easily have lost his crown and Judea its independence as the result of this battle, had it not been for the assistance extended by Egypt. Cleopatra's two Jewish generals, Helkias and Ananias, persuaded the queen of the dangers of allowing her banished son Ptolemy to remain victorious and she entrusted them with an army against him. As a result, Ptolemy was forced to withdraw to Cyprus, and Alexander was saved. The Egyptians, as compensation for their aid, desired to annex Judea to their country, but considerations touching the resident Egyptian Jews, who were the main support of her throne, induced Cleopatra to modify her longings for conquest. The Egyptian army withdrawn, Alexander found his hands free; and forthwith he planned new campaigns.<extension extension_name='ref' name="je"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Later campaigns</heading><paragraph>Alexander captured<space/><link><target>Gadara</target></link><space/>and the strong fortress<space/><link><target>Amathus (Transjordan)</target><part>Amathus</part></link><space/>on the Jordan; but, in an ambush set for him by Theodorus, ruler of Amathus, he lost the whole of the rear-guard of his army10,000 men together with his baggage. He was more successful in his expedition against the Hellenized coastal cities (what had once been<space/><link><target>Philistia</target></link>), capturing<space/><link><target>Rafah</target><part>Raphia</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Anthedon (Palestine)</target><part>Anthedon</part></link>. Finally, in 96 BC<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Archaeological encyclopedia of the Holy Land By Avraham Negev, Shimon Gibson<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Books.google.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-06</arg></template></extension><space/>Jannaeus outlasted the inhabitants of<space/><link><target>Gaza City</target><part>Gaza</part></link><space/>in a year-long siege, which he occupied through treachery, and gave up to be pillaged and burned by his soldiery. This victory gained Judean control over the Mediterranean outlet for the<space/><link><target>Nabataean kingdom</target><part>Nabatean</part></link><space/>trade routes.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.mfa.gov.il/mfa/israelexperience/history/pages/hasmonean-rule-extended-to-negev-10-dec-2009.aspx'>&quot;Hasmonean rule extended to Negev highlands&quot;, Israel Ministry of Foreign Affairs, December 10, 2009</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>High Priesthood</heading><paragraph>The relations between Alexander and the Pharisees were probably never very cordial; though, according to the statement of the Talmud,<space/><link><target>Simeon ben Shetach</target></link>, the head of the party, was a brother of the queen and a frequent guest at the palace.<extension extension_name='ref' name="je"></extension>The rival Sadducees were avid supporters of Jannaeus (see 4Q448). Furthermore, Jannaeus established himself as a ruler concerned mainly with conquests rather than his religious obligations.</paragraph><paragraph>One year during the Jewish holiday of<space/><link><target>Sukkot</target><part>Sukkot or Feast of Tabernacles</part></link>, Alexander Jannaeus, while officiating as the<space/><link><target>High Priest (Judaism)</target><part>High Priest</part></link><space/>(<italics>Kohen Gadol</italics>) at the Temple in Jerusalem, demonstrated his support of the<space/><link><target>Sadducees</target></link><space/>by refusing to perform the water<space/><link><target>libation</target></link><space/>ceremony properly: instead of pouring it on the altar, he poured it on his feet. The crowd responded with shock at his mockery and showed their displeasure by pelting Alexander with the<space/><link><target>etrog</target><trail>im</trail></link><space/>(<link><target>citron</target><trail>s</trail></link>) that they were holding in their hands. Unwittingly, the crowd had played right into Alexander's hands. He had intended to incite the people to riot and his soldiers fell upon the crowd at his command. The soldiers slew more than 6,000 people in the Temple courtyard.</paragraph><paragraph>This incident during the Feast of Tabernacles was a major factor leading up to the Judean Civil War by igniting popular opponents of Jannaeus. A Qumran document sheds further light on another opponent of Jannaeus. The scroll 4Q390 was written by an adversary of Jannaeus seeking popular support to overthrow the Hasmonean king. The author called for an end to the dispute between Jannaeus and the Pharisees. According to the author, the only acceptable solution was an end to the Hasmonean priesthood and secular control. This opposition culminated in the Judean Civil War.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Judean Civil War and the Crucifixion of the 800</heading><paragraph>The Judean Civil War initially began after the conquest of Gaza by Jannaeus. Due to Jannaeus' victory at Gaza, the Nabatean kingdom no longer controlled their main<space/><link><target>trade route</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>. Therefore, Nabatean king<space/><link><target>Obodas I</target></link><space/>launched an attack on Judea in the<space/><link><target>Golan Heights</target></link>. After Jannaeus was defeated in battle against Obodas, he returned to fierce Jewish opposition in Jerusalem. A civil war broke out between Pharisee-supported Jewish rebels and Jannaeus.</paragraph><paragraph>Overall, the war lasted six years and left 50,000 Judeans dead. After Jannaeus succeeded early in the war, the rebels asked for Seleucid assistance. Judean insurgents joined forces with<space/><link><target>Demetrius III Eucaerus</target></link><space/>to fight against Jannaeus. The Seleucid forces defeated Jannaeus at<space/><link><target>Schechem</target></link><space/>and forced him to take refuge in the mountains. However, these Judean rebels ultimately decided that it was better to live under a terrible Jewish king than backtrack to a Seleucid ruler. After 6,000 Jews returned to Jannaeus, Demetrius was defeated. The end of the Civil War brought a sense of national solidarity against Seleucid influence. Nevertheless, Jannaeus was uninterested in reconciliation within the Judean State.</paragraph><paragraph>The aftermath of the Judean Civil War consisted of popular unrest, poverty and grief over the fallen soldiers on both sides. The greatest impact of the war was the victor's revenge. Josephus reports that Jannaeus brought 800 rebels to Jerusalem and had them crucified, and had the throats of the rebel's wives and children cut before their eyes as Jannaeus ate with his concubines.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Coinage</heading><paragraph>The coinage of Alexander Jannaeus is characteristic of the early Jewish coinage in that it avoided human or animal representations, in opposition to the surrounding Greek, and later Roman types of the period. Jewish coinage instead focused on symbols, either natural, such as the<space/><link><target>palm tree</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>pomegranate</target></link><space/>or the star, or man-made, such as the<space/><link><target>Temple in Jerusalem</target><part>Temple</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Menorah (Temple)</target><part>Menorah</part></link>, trumpets or<space/><link><target>cornucopia</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>[[Image:JanaeusCoinPhoto.jpg|thumb|300px|Coin of Alexander Jannaeus (103 BC to 76 BC).<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><bold>Obv:</bold><space/><link><target>Seleucid</target></link><space/>anchor and Greek Legend: BASILEOS ALEXANDROU &quot;King Alexander&quot;.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><bold>Rev:</bold><space/>Eight-spoke wheel or star within diadem. Hebrew legend inside the spokes: &quot;Yehonatan the King&quot;.]]Alexander Jannaeus was the first of the Jewish kings to introduce the &quot;eight-ray star&quot; or &quot;eight-spoked wheel&quot; symbol, in his<space/><link><target>bronze</target></link><space/>&quot;Widow's mite&quot; coins, in combination with the widespread<space/><link><target>Seleucid</target></link><space/>numismatic symbol of the anchor. Depending on the make, the star symbol can be shown with straight spokes connected to the outside circle, in a style rather indicative of a wheel. On others, the spokes can have a more &quot;flame-like&quot; shape, more indicative of the representation of a star within a diadem.</paragraph><paragraph>It is not clear what the wheel or star may exactly symbolize, and interpretations vary, from the morning star, to the sun or the heavens. The influence of some<space/><link><target>Persia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>symbols of a star within a diadem, or the eight-spoked<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target></link><space/>wheel (see the coins of the<space/><link><target>Indo-Greek</target></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Menander I</target></link><space/>with this symbol) have also been suggested. The eight-spoked Macedonian star (a variation of which is the<space/><link><target>Vergina Sun</target></link>), emblem of the royal<space/><link><target>Argead dynasty</target></link><space/>and the ancient kingdom of<space/><link><target>Macedon</target><trail>ia</trail></link>, within a Hellenistic<space/><link><target>Diadem (personal wear)</target><part>diadem</part></link><space/>symbolizing royalty (many of the coins depict a small knot with two ends on top of the diadem), seem to be the most probable source for this symbol.</paragraph><paragraph>The most likely explanation is that the symbol is a star encased in a diadem and it is a religious explanation. Biblical law forbids the making of graven images (especially see Deuteronomy 4:16,23), yet the image of a monarch is a staple of Hellenistic coins. In place of an image of himself, therefore, it is likely that Alexander Jannaeus chose a star, in keeping with Numbers 24:17, &quot;A star rises from Jacob, a scepter comes forth from Israel.&quot; This verse generally was seen as a biblical support for monarchy (and specifically as support for a Davidic monarchy). Jannaeus, however, could have seen it as an image of his achievements, if not his own rule. This is how the rest of Numbers 24:17 and verses 18 and 19 continue: The star, it says, &quot;smashes the brow of Moab, the foundation of all children of Seth. Edom becomes a possession, yea, Seir a possession of its enemies; but Israel is triumphant. A victor issues from Jacob to wipe out what is left of Ir.&quot; Considering Jannaeus' conquestscreating a kingdom that rivaled those of David and Solomon and may have even exceeded thosethe &quot;star&quot; envisioned in the prophecy of Balaam in Numbers was a perfect match for him.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In literature</heading><paragraph>Alexander Jannaeus is the main character of the novel<space/><italics><link><target>The King of Flesh and Blood</target></link></italics>, ( ) by Israeli novelist<space/><link><target>Moshe Shamir</target></link><space/>- a novel including many hints to the politics of 1950s<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, when it was written.</paragraph><paragraph>As the husband of Queen<space/><link><target>Salome Alexandra</target></link>, he is also a character in the novel<space/><link><target>Queen of the Jews</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Judy Petsonk</target></link><space/>(2012).</paragraph><paragraph>Alexander Jannaeus and his wife Queen Alexandra are the main characters of Constantine Cavafy's poem<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://www.cavafy.com/poems/content.asp?id</arg><arg name="title">Alexander Jannaios and Alexandra</arg><arg name="author">C. P. Cavafy</arg><arg name="authorlink">Constantine P. Cavafy</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Collected Poems</arg><arg name="others"><space/>Edited by George Savidis. Translated by [[Edmund Keeley]] and [[Philip Sherrard]].</arg><arg name="editor"></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Revised<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton University Press</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg></template></extension><space/>bearing their names. In the poem Cavafy notes the Hellenistic influence on the behavior of the couple.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Coins of Alexander Jannaeus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hashmonean coinage</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Shachar, Ilan, &quot;The Historical and Numismatic Significance of Alexander Jannaeus's Later Coinage as Found in Archaeological Excavations,&quot;<space/><italics>Palestine Exploration Quarterly</italics>,<space/><bold>136</bold>(1) (April 2004), 533.</listitem><listitem>Paul Romanoff,<space/><italics>Jewish symbols on ancient Jewish coins</italics>, New York American Israel Numismatic Association, 1971.</listitem><listitem>This article incorporates some content from the public domain 1911 edition of<space/><italics>The New Century Book of Facts</italics><space/>published by the King-Richardson Company, Springfield, Massachusetts. (This reference gives a death date of 78 BC, but consensus seems to be 76 BC.)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thewidowsmite.net'>Christian Jewelry with Coins of Alexander Yannai (Alexander Jannaeus)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblicalmites.com'>Leptons and Prutahs of Alexander Jannaeus</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://dougsmith.ancients.info/feac47wid.html'>Coinage of King Alexander Jannaeus, &quot;Widow's Mites&quot;.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://images.google.co.jp/images?q=Alexander%20Jannaeus%20coins&amp;amp;hl=ja&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;sa=N&amp;amp;tab=wi'>Coins of King Alexander Jannaeus</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.macedonian-heritage.gr/HellenicMacedonia/en/img_A1a.html'>Miniature 'shield' showing the 8-spoked star of the Argead</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.judypetsonk.com'>Information on Salome Alexandra and Alexander Jannaeus by the author of Queen of the Jews</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://people.duke.edu/~goranson/jannaeus.pdf'>&quot;Jannaeus, His Brother Absalom,and Judah the Essene,&quot; By Stephen Goranson. Jannaeus as the Qumran text's &quot;Wicked Priest.&quot;</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Hasmonean|Hasmonean Dynasty]]</arg><arg>103 BC</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg>76 BC</arg><arg name="name">Alexander Jannaeus of Judea</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="rows">2</arg><arg name="before">[[Aristobulus I]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Judean rulers|King of Judea]]</arg><arg name="years">103 BC &ndash; 76 BC</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Salome Alexandra]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of High Priests of Israel|High Priest of Judea]]</arg><arg name="years">103 BC – 76 BC</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Hyrcanus II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>IsraeliteKings</target></template><template><target>High Priests of Judaism</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Jannaeus, Alexander</target></template><link><target>Category:1st-century BC monarchs in the Middle East</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century BC Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:2nd-century BC monarchs in the Middle East</target></link><link><target>Category:2nd-century BC clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:2nd-century BC Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century BC clergy</target></link><link><target>Category:2nd-century BC births</target></link><link><target>Category:76 BC</target></link><link><target>Category:Hasmonean dynasty</target></link><link><target>Category:70s BC deaths</target></link></paragraph></article>