<article title='Boris_Pasternak'><paragraph><template><target>Eastern Slavic name</target><arg>Leonidovich</arg><arg>Pasternak</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="name"><space/>Boris Pasternak
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Boris Pasternak cropped.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Pasternak at the first Congress of the [[USSR Union of Writers|Union of Soviet Writers]] in 1934.
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>250px
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Boris Leonidovich Pasternak
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{OldStyleDate|10 February|1890|29 January}}
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Moscow|Moscow, Russian Empire]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Peredelkino|Peredelkino, USSR]]
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>Russian
</arg><arg name="ethnicity"><space/>[[Jewish]]
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Russian Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodoxy]]
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Poet, writer
</arg><arg name="notableworks"><space/>''My Sister, Life'', ''The Second Birth'', ''[[Doctor Zhivago (novel)|Doctor Zhivago]]''
</arg><arg name="awards"><space/>{{awd|[[Nobel Prize in Literature]]|1958}}
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Boris Leonidovich Pasternak</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>p</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>ər</arg><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>k</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/pasternak'>&quot;Pasternak&quot;</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Random House Webster's Unabridged Dictionary</target></link></italics>.</extension><space/><template><target>lang-rus</target><arg>Бори́с Леони́дович Пастерна́к</arg><arg name="p">bɐˈrʲis lʲɪɐˈnʲidəvʲɪtɕ pəstɛrˈnak</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>F.L. Ageenko and M.V. Zarva,<space/><italics>Slovar' udarenii</italics><space/>(Moscow: Russkii yazyk), p. 686.</extension>) (<template><target>OldStyleDate</target><arg>10 February</arg><arg>1890</arg><arg>29 January</arg></template><template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>30 May 1960) was a Russian poet, novelist, and literary translator. In his native Russian, Pasternak's first book of poems,<space/><italics>My Sister, Life</italics><space/>(1917), is one of the most influential collections ever published in the<space/><link><target>Russian language</target></link>. Pasternak's translations of<space/><link><target>stage play</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</target><part>Goethe</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Friedrich Schiller</target><part>Schiller</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Pedro Caldern de la Barca</target><part>Calderon</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>William Shakespeare</target><part>Shakespeare</part></link><space/>remain very popular with Russian audiences.</paragraph><paragraph>Outside Russia, Pasternak is best known as the author of<space/><italics><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (novel)</target><part>Doctor Zhivago</part></link></italics><space/>(1957), a novel which takes place between the<space/><link><target>Russian Revolution of 1905</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>First World War</target></link>. Due to the novel's independent-minded stance on the<space/><link><target>socialist state</target></link>,<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was rejected for publication in the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>USSR</part></link>. At the instigation of<space/><link><target>Giangiacomo Feltrinelli</target></link>,<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was smuggled to<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>and published in 1957. Pasternak was awarded the<space/><link><target>Nobel Prize for Literature</target></link><space/>in 1958, an event which both humiliated and enraged the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></link>, which forced him to decline the prize, though his descendants were later to accept it in his name in 1988.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pasternak boris alex.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Boris (left) with his brother Alex; painting by their father,<space/><link><target>Leonid Pasternak</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak was born in Moscow on 10 February, (Gregorian), 1890 (Julian 29 January) into a wealthy assimilated<space/><link><target>History of the Jews in Russia</target><part>Russian Jewish</part></link><space/>family.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/Pasternak.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Boris Leonidovich Pasternak Biography<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Jewishvirtuallibrary.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 January 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>His father was the<space/><link><target>Post-Impressionist</target></link><space/>painter,<space/><link><target>Leonid Pasternak</target></link>, professor at the<space/><link><target>Moscow School of Painting, Sculpture and Architecture</target><part>Moscow School of Painting, Sculpture, and Architecture</part></link>. His mother was<space/><link><target>Rosa Kaufman</target></link>, a concert pianist and the daughter of<space/><link><target>Odessa</target></link><space/>industrialist Isadore Kaufman and his wife. Pasternak had a younger brother Alex and sisters<space/><link><target>Lydia Pasternak Slater</target><part>Lydia</part></link><space/>and Josephine.</paragraph><paragraph>In a 1959 letter to<space/><link><target>Jacqueline de Proyart</target></link>, Pasternak recalled,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>I was baptized as a child by my [[nanny]], but because of the restrictions imposed on Jews, particularly in the case of a family which was exempt from them and enjoyed a certain reputation in view of my father's standing as an artist, there was something a little complicated about this, and it was always felt to be half-secret and intimate, a source of rare and exceptional inspiration rather than being calmly taken for granted. I believe that this is at the root of my distinctiveness. Most intensely of all my mind was occupied by Christianity in the years 1910–12, when the main foundations of this distinctiveness – my way of seeing things, the world, life – were taking shape...<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), p 137.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Shortly after his birth, Pasternak's parents had joined the<space/><link><target>Tolstoyan</target></link><space/>Movement. Novelist<space/><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link><space/>was a close family friend, as Pasternak recalled, &quot;my father illustrated his books, went to see him, revered him, and ...the whole house was imbued with his spirit.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Pasternak (1959) p 25</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a 1956 essay, Pasternak recalled his father's feverish work creating illustrations for Tolstoy's novel<space/><italics><link><target>Resurrection (novel)</target><part>Resurrection</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Past28"></extension><space/>The novel was serialized in the journal<space/><italics><link><target>Niva (magazine)</target><part>Niva</part></link></italics><space/>by the publisher<space/><link><target>Adolf Marks</target><part>Fyodor Marx</part></link>, based in St Petersburg. The sketches were drawn from observations in such places as courtrooms, prisons and on trains, in a spirit of realism. To ensure that the sketches met the journal deadline, train conductors were enlisted to personally collect the illustrations. Pasternak wrote,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="My childish imagination was struck by the sight of a train conductor in his formal railway uniform, standing waiting at the door of the kitchen as if he were standing on a railway platform at the door of a compartment that was just about to leave the station. Joiner's glue was boiling on the stove. The illustrations were hurriedly wiped dry, fixed, glued on pieces of cardboard, rolled up, tied up. The parcels, once ready, were sealed with sealing wax and handed to the conductor.<ref name">"Past28">Pasternak (1959) pp 27–28.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Max Hayward</target></link>, &quot;In November 1910, when Tolstoy fled from his home and died in the stationmaster's house at<space/><link><target>Astapovo</target></link>, Leonid Pasternak was informed by telegram and he went there immediately, taking his son Boris with him, and made a drawing of Tolstoy on his deathbed.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p<space/><italics>xvi</italics>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Regular visitors to the Pasternak's home also included<space/><link><target>Sergei Rachmaninoff</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Alexander Scriabin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lev Shestov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rainer Maria Rilke</target></link>. Pasternak aspired first to be a musician.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pasternak (1967)</extension><space/>Inspired by Scriabin, Pasternak briefly was a student at the<space/><link><target>Moscow Conservatory</target></link>. In 1910 he abruptly left for the<space/><link><target>Imperial Germany</target><part>German</part></link><space/><link><target>University of Marburg</target></link>, where he studied under<space/><link><target>Neo-Kantian</target></link><space/>philosophers<space/><link><target>Hermann Cohen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nicolai Hartmann</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Natorp</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Career</heading><paragraph><template><target>Empty section</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early career</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Uni Marburg 05.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The University of Marburg, where Pasternak studied Philosophy 1912</part></link><link><target>File:BORIS BESIDE THE BALTIC AT MEREKULE, 1910 by L.Pasternak.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''Boris Pasternak in 1910,'' by his father Leonid Pasternak</part></link>Pasternak fell in love with Ida Wissotzkaya, a girl from a notable Moscow family of tea merchants, whose company<space/><link><target>Wissotzky Tea</target></link><space/>was the largest tea company in the world. Pasternak had tutored her in the final class of high school. He helped her prepare for finals. They met in Marburg during the summer of 1912 when Boris' father,<space/><link><target>Leonid Pasternak</target></link>, painted her portrait.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978 p 395">Ivinskaya (1978) p 395.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Professor Cohen encouraged him to remain in Germany and to pursue a Philosophy doctorate, Pasternak decided against it. He returned to Moscow upon the outbreak of World War I. His first book of poems was published later that year. In the aftermath, Pasternak proposed marriage to Ida. However, the Wissotzky family was disturbed by Pasternak's poor prospects and persuaded Ida to refuse him. She turned him down and he told of his love and rejection in the poem &quot;Marburg&quot; (1917).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978 p 395"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;I quivered. I flared up, and then was extinguished.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>I shook. I had made a proposal - but late,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Too late. I was scared, and she had refused me.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>I pity her tears, am more blessed than a saint.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Another failed love affair in 1917 inspired the poems in his first book,<space/><italics><link><target>My Sister, Life</target></link></italics>. His early verse cleverly dissimulates his preoccupation with<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>'s philosophy. Its fabric includes striking alliterations, wild rhythmic combinations, day-to-day vocabulary, and hidden allusions to his favourite poets such as<space/><link><target>Rilke</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lermontov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pushkin</target></link><space/>and German-language Romantic poets.</paragraph><paragraph>During World War I, Pasternak taught and worked at a chemical factory in<space/><link><target>Vsevolodovo-Vilve</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Perm</target></link>, which undoubtedly provided him with material for<space/><italics>Dr. Zhivago</italics><space/>many years later. Unlike the rest of his family and many of his closest friends, Pasternak chose not to leave Russia after the<space/><link><target>October Revolution</target></link><space/>of 1917. According to<space/><link><target>Max Hayward</target></link>,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Pasternak remained in Moscow throughout the [[Russian Civil War|Civil War]] (1918–1920), making no attempt to escape abroad or to the [[White Movement|White-occupied]] south, as a number of other Russian writers did at the time. No doubt, like Yuri Zhivago, he was momentarily impressed by the "splendid surgery" of the Bolshevik seizure of power in October 1917, but – again to judge by the evidence of the novel, and despite a personal admiration for [[Vladimir Lenin]], whom he saw at the [[Ninth party Congress|9th Congress of Soviets]] in 1921 – he soon began to harbor profound doubts about the claims and credentials of the regime, not to mention its style of rule. The terrible shortages of food and fuel, and the depredations of the [[Red Terror]], made life very precarious in those years, particularly for the "[[bourgeois]]" [[intelligentsia]]. In a letter written to Pasternak from abroad in the twenties, [[Marina Tsvetayeva]] reminded him of how she had run into him in the street in 1919 as he was on the way to sell some valuable books from his library in order to buy bread. He continued to write original work and to translate, but after about the middle of 1918 it became almost impossible to publish. The only way to make one's work known was to declaim it in the several "literary" cafes which then sprang up, or – anticipating [[samizdat]] – to circulate it in manuscript. It was in this way that ''My Sister, Life'' first became available to a wider audience.<ref>Ivinskaya (1978) p xxiii.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Mayakovsky Pasternak.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Pasternak (second from left) in 1924, with friends including<space/><link><target>Lilya Brik</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sergei Eisenstein</target></link><space/>(third from left) and<space/><link><target>Vladimir Mayakovsky</target></link><space/>(centre)</part></link>When it finally was published in 1921, Pasternak's<space/><italics>My Sister, Life</italics><space/>revolutionised Russian poetry. It made Pasternak the model for younger poets, and decisively changed the poetry of<space/><link><target>Osip Mandelshtam</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Marina Tsvetayeva</target></link><space/>and others.</paragraph><paragraph>Following<space/><italics>My Sister, Life</italics>, Pasternak produced some hermetic pieces of uneven quality, including his masterpiece, the lyric cycle<space/><italics>Rupture</italics><space/>(1921). Both Pro-Soviet writers and their<space/><link><target>White emigre</target></link><space/>equivalents applauded Pasternak's poetry as pure, unbridled inspiration.</paragraph><paragraph>In the late 1920s, he also participated in the much celebrated tripartite correspondence with<space/><link><target>Rilke</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Tsvetayeva</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bayley</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Big Three</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nybooks.com/articles/5268</arg><arg name="journal">[[The New York Review of Books]]</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>32</arg><arg name="date"><space/>5 December 1985</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 September 2007</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension><space/>As the 1920s wore on, however, Pasternak increasingly felt that his colourful style was at odds with a less educated readership. He attempted to make his poetry more comprehensible by reworking his earlier pieces and starting two lengthy poems on the<space/><link><target>Russian Revolution of 1905</target></link>. He also turned to prose and wrote several autobiographical stories, notably &quot;The Childhood of Luvers&quot; and &quot;Safe Conduct&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1922 Pasternak married Evgeniya Lurye ( ), a student at the Art Institute. The following year they had a son, Evgenii.</paragraph><paragraph>Evidence of Pasternak's support of still-revolutionary members of the leadership of the Communist Party as late as 1926 is indicated by his worshipful poem &quot;In Memory of Reissner&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.marxists.org/subject/women/authors/reissner/works/hamburg/app3.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">In Memory of Reissner<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Pasternak<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Boris<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/></arg><arg name="date">1926(?)<space/></arg><arg name="website">http://www.marxists.org<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">various<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>presumably written upon the shockingly premature death from typhus of legendary Bolshevik leader<space/><link><target>Larisa Reisner</target></link><space/>at age 30 in February of that year.</paragraph><paragraph>By 1927, Pasternak's close friends<space/><link><target>Vladimir Mayakovsky</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nikolai Aseyev</target></link><space/>were advocating the complete subordination of the Arts to the needs of the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Boris Pasternak: Family Correspondence, 19211960,</italics><space/>p 78.</extension><space/>In a letter to his sister Josephine, Pasternak wrote of his intentions to, &quot;break off relations,&quot; with both of them. Although he expressed that it would be deeply painful, Pasternak explained that it could not be prevented. He explained,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>They don't in any way measure up to their exalted calling. In fact, they've fallen short of it but – difficult as it is for me to understand – a modern [[sophist]] might say that these last years have actually demanded a reduction in conscience and feeling in the name of greater intelligibility. Yet now the very spirit of the times demands great, courageous purity. And these men are ruled by trivial routine. Subjectively, they're sincere and conscientious. But I find it increasingly difficult to take into account the personal aspect of their convictions. I'm not out on my own – people treat me well. But all that only holds good up to a point. It seems to me that I've reached that point.<ref>Nicholas Pasternak Slater, ''Boris Pasternak: Family Correspondence 1921–1960'', p 80.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By 1932, Pasternak had strikingly reshaped his style to make it more understandable to the general public and printed the new collection of poems, aptly titled<space/><italics>The Second Birth</italics>. Although its Caucasian pieces were as brilliant as the earlier efforts, the book alienated the core of Pasternak's refined audience abroad, which was largely composed of anti-communist emigres.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1932 Pasternak fell in love with Zinaida Neigauz, the wife of the pianist<space/><link><target>Heinrich Neuhaus</target><part>Genrikh Neigauz</part></link>. They both got divorces and married two years later.</paragraph><paragraph>He continued to change his poetry, simplifying his style and language through the years, as expressed in his next book,<space/><italics>Early Trains</italics><space/>(1943).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Stalin Epigram</heading><paragraph>After<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target></link><space/>was acclaimed as leader of the<space/><link><target>CPSU</target></link><space/>in 1929, Pasternak became further disillusioned with the Party's tightening censorship of literature. Still unwilling to conform, Pasternak remained a close friend of<space/><link><target>Anna Akhmatova</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Osip Mandelstam</target></link>. Mandelstam recited his searing indictment of Stalin, the &quot;<link><target>Stalin Epigram</target></link>,&quot; to Pasternak soon after its composition in late April 1934. After listening, Pasternak told Mandelstam:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="I didn't hear this, you didn't recite it to me, because, you know, very strange and terrible things are happening now: they've begun to pick people up. I'm afraid the walls have ears and perhaps even these benches on the boulevard here may be able to listen and tell tales. So let's make out that I heard nothing.<ref name">"Ivin61">Ivinskaya (1978) pp 61–63</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On the night of 14 May 1934, Mandelstam was arrested at his home based on a warrant signed by<space/><link><target>NKVD</target></link><space/>boss<space/><link><target>Genrikh Yagoda</target></link>. Devastated, Pasternak went immediately to the offices of<space/><italics><link><target>Izvestia</target></link></italics><space/>and begged<space/><link><target>Nikolai Bukharin</target></link><space/>to intercede on Mandelstam's behalf.</paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link>, later Pasternak's lover, Pasternak was deeply upset by Mandelstam's arrest. He was concerned for his friend but he also worried that he might be blamed for betraying Mandelstam to the secret police. Ivinskaya writes that Pasternak &quot;raced frantically all over town, telling everybody that he was not to blame and denying responsibility for Mandelstam's disappearance, which for some reason he thought might be laid at his door.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin61"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Soon after his meeting with Bukharin, the telephone rang in Pasternak's Moscow apartment. A voice from<space/><link><target>Moscow Kremlin</target><part>The Kremlin</part></link><space/>said, &quot;Comrade<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target><part>Stalin</part></link><space/>wishes to speak with you.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin61"></extension><space/>According to Ivinskaya, Pasternak was struck dumb. &quot;He was totally unprepared for such a conversation. But then he heard<space/><italics>his</italics><space/>voice, the voice of Stalin, coming over the line. The Leader addressed him in a rather bluff uncouth fashion, using the familiar<space/><italics>thou</italics><space/>form: 'Tell me, what are they saying in your literary circles about the arrest of Mandelstam?'&quot; Flustered, Pasternak denied that there was any discussion or that there were any literary circles left in Soviet Russia. Stalin went on to ask him for his own opinion of Mandelstam. In an &quot;eager fumbling manner&quot; Pasternak explained that he and Mandelstam each had a completely different philosophy about poetry. Ivinskaya writes that he:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="…went on for quite a time in this vein. Stalin gave him no encouragement whatsoever, not interjecting, or uttering a sound of any kind. At last B[oris] L[eonidovich] came to a halt. Stalin then said, in a mocking tone of voice: "I see, you just aren't able to stick up for a comrade," and put down the receiver.<ref name">"Ivin61"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Years later, Pasternak recalled that he was horrified at how the conversation had ended. He repeatedly telephoned the Kremlin's number, begging to be reconnected to Stalin. Instead, Pasternak was told, &quot;Comrade Stalin is busy.&quot; Pasternak became frantic, pacing around his apartment repeating over and over that he must write to Stalin to explain what he had meant and to also say that injustices were being committed in the name of the Leader. Pasternak later did write and send just such a letter.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin61"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>If ever the conversation turned to Mandelstam, [Boris Leonidovich] would always hark back to the same thing: that he was not to blame for his misfortunes, and that if he had not written to Bukharin and in general made a great fuss about his arrest, then perhaps Mandelstam would not even have had the respite, brief as it was, which was granted to him – with the result that the ''Voronezh Notebooks'' might never have been written. It was clear, however, that [Boris Leonidovich] himself felt he had not come as well as he should out of his unexpected conversation with the Leader. He had done something not quite right...<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 156–157.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Great Purge</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Great Purge</arg></template>According to Pasternak, during the 1937<space/><link><target>Case of Trotskyist Anti-Soviet Military Organization</target><part>show trial</part></link><space/>of General<space/><link><target>Iona Yakir</target></link><space/>and Marshal<space/><link><target>Mikhail Tukhachevsky</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Union of Soviet Writers</target></link><space/>requested all members to add their names to a statement supporting the death penalty for the defendants. They demanded Pasternak's signature as well, but he refused to give it. Vladimir Stavski, the chairman of the Union, was terrified that he would be punished for Pasternak's dissent. The leadership of the Union travelled to Pasternak's dacha at<space/><link><target>Peredelkino</target></link><space/>and severely threatened the writer, who refused to sign the statement and returned to his<space/><link><target>dacha</target></link>. Hearing this, Zinaida Pasternak, who was pregnant, was terribly upset, accusing him of risking the destruction of their family. Pasternak went to bed. He and Zinaida expected to be arrested that evening. They later learned that an<space/><link><target>NKVD</target></link><space/>agent was hiding in the bushes outside their window and wrote down every word they said to each other.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978 pp 132-133">Ivinskaya (1978) pp 132133</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Soon after, Pasternak appealed directly to Stalin. He wrote about his family's strong<space/><link><target>Tolstoyan</target></link><space/>convictions, which he still held dear. He declared that his own life was at the Leader's disposal. He said, that he could not stand as a self-appointed judge of life and death. Pasternak was certain that he would be instantly arrested, but he was not.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978 pp 132-133"></extension><space/>Stalin is said to have crossed Pasternak's name off an execution list during the<space/><link><target>Great Purge</target></link>. According to Pasternak, Stalin declared, &quot;Do not touch this cloud dweller&quot; (or, in another version, &quot;Leave that holy fool alone!&quot;)<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 133.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Pasternak was never arrested by the<space/><link><target>Soviet secret police</target></link>, his close friend<space/><link><target>Titsian Tabidze</target></link><space/>fell victim to the Great Purge. In an autobiographical essay published in the 1950s, Pasternak described the execution of Tabidze and the<space/><link><target>suicides</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Marina Tsvetaeva</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paolo Iashvili</target></link><space/>as the greatest heartbreaks of his entire life.</paragraph><paragraph>Ivinskaya wrote, &quot;I believe that between Stalin and Pasternak there was an incredible, silent<space/><link><target>duel</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 135.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>World War II</heading><paragraph>Pasternak was elated by the outbreak of war between<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target></link><space/>and the Soviet Union. When the<space/><link><target>Luftwaffe</target></link><space/>began bombing Moscow, Pasternak immediately began to serve as a fire warden on the roof of the writer's building on Lavrushinski Street. According to Ivinskaya, he repeatedly helped to dispose of German bombs which fell on it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin72">Ivinskaya (1978) pp 7273.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1943, Pasternak was finally granted permission to visit the soldiers at the front. He bore up well, considering the hardships of the journey (he had a weak leg from an old injury), and he wanted to go to the most dangerous places. He read his poetry and talked extensively with the active and injured troops.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin72"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>With the end of the war in 1945, the Soviet people expected to see the end of the devastation of<space/><link><target>Nazism</target></link>, and hoped for the end of Stalin's Purges. But, sealed trains began carrying large numbers of prisoners to the Soviet<space/><link><target>Gulag</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Some were<space/><link><target>Nazi collaborator</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who had fought under General<space/><link><target>Andrey Vlasov</target></link>, but most were ordinary Soviet officers and men. Pasternak watched as ex-POWs were directly transferred from Nazi Germany to Soviet<space/><link><target>concentration camp</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><link><target>White emigre</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who had returned due to pledges of<space/><link><target>amnesty</target></link><space/>were also sent directly to the Gulag, as were Jews from the<space/><link><target>Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee</target><part>Anti-Fascist Committee</part></link><space/>and other organizations. Many thousands of innocent people were incarcerated in connection with the<space/><link><target>Leningrad Affair</target></link><space/>and the so-called<space/><link><target>Doctor's Plot</target></link>, while whole ethnic groups were<space/><link><target>Population transfer in the Soviet Union</target><part>deported to Siberia</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 75.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak later said, &quot;If, in a bad dream, we had seen all the horrors in store for us after the war, we should not have been sorry to see Stalin fall, together with<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target><part>Hitler</part></link>. Then, an end to the war in favour of our<space/><link><target>Western Allies</target><part>allies</part></link>, civilized countries with democratic traditions, would have meant a hundred times less suffering for our people than that which Stalin again inflicted on it after his victory.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 80.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Olga Ivinskaya</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Olga Ivinskaia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link><space/>(19121995)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In October 1946, the married Pasternak met<space/><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link>, a single mother employed by<space/><italics><link><target>Novy Mir</target></link></italics>. Deeply moved by her resemblance to his first love Ida Vysotskaya,<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) pp 12, 395, footnote 3.</extension><space/>Pasternak gave Ivinskaya several volumes of his poetry and literary translations. Although Pasternak never left his wife Zinaida, he started an extramarital relationship with Ivinskaya that would last for the remainder of Pasternak's life. Ivinskaya later recalled, &quot;He phoned almost every day and, instinctively fearing to meet or talk with him, yet dying of happiness, I would stammer out that I was &quot;busy today.&quot; But almost every afternoon, toward the end of working hours, he came in person to the office and often walked with me through the streets, boulevards, and squares all the way home to Potapov Street. 'Shall I make you a present of this square?' he would ask.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>She gave him the phone number of her neighbour Olga Volkova who resided below. In the evenings, Pasternak would phone and Volkova would signal by Olga banging on the water pipe which connected their apartments.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When they first met, Pasternak was translating the verse of the Hungarian<space/><link><target>List of national poets</target><part>national poet</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Sndor Petfi</target></link>. Pasternak gave his lover a book of Petfi with the inscription, &quot;Petfi served as a code in May and June 1947, and my close translations of his lyrics are an expression, adapted to the requirements of the text, of my feelings and thoughts for you and about you. In memory of it all, B.P., 13 May 1948.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak later noted on a photograph of himself, &quot;Petfi is magnificent with his descriptive lyrics and picture of nature, but you are better still. I worked on him a good deal in 1947 and 1948, when I first came to know you. Thank you for your help. I was translating both of you.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 27.</extension><space/>Ivinskaya would later describe the Petfi translations as, &quot;a first declaration of love.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 28.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya, Zinaida Pasternak was infuriated by her husband's infidelity. Once, when his younger son Leonid fell seriously ill, Zinaida extracted a promise from her husband, as they stood by the boy's sickbed, that he would end his affair with Ivinskaya. Pasternak asked Luisa Popova, a mutual friend, to tell Ivinskaya about his promise. Popova told him that he must do it himself. Soon after, Ivinskaya happened to be ill at Popova's apartment, when suddenly Zinaida Pasternak arrived and confronted her.</paragraph><paragraph>Ivinskaya later recalled,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>But I became so ill through loss of blood that she and Luisa had to get me to the hospital, and I no longer remember exactly what passed between me and this heavily built, strong-minded woman, who kept repeating how she didn't give a damn for our love and that, although she no longer loved [Boris Leonidovich] herself, she would not allow her family to be broken up. After my return from the hospital, Boris came to visit me, as though nothing had happened, and touchingly made his peace with my mother, telling her how much he loved me. By now she was pretty well used to these funny ways of his.<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), p 23.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1948, Pasternak advised Ivinskaya to resign her job at<space/><italics>Novy Mir</italics>, which was becoming extremely difficult due to their relationship. In the aftermath, Pasternak began to instruct her in translating poetry. In time, they began to refer to her apartment on Potapov Street as, &quot;Our Shop.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>On the evening of 6 October 1949, Ivinskaya was arrested at her apartment by the<space/><link><target>KGB</target></link>. Ivinskaya relates in her memoirs that, when the agents burst into her apartment, she was at her typewriter working on translations of the<space/><link><target>Korean poetry</target><part>Korean poet</part></link><space/><link><target>Won Tu-Son</target></link>. Her apartment was ransacked and all items connected with Pasternak were piled up in her presence. Ivinskaya was taken to the<space/><link><target>Lubyanka (KGB)</target><part>Lubyanka Prison</part></link><space/>and repeatedly interrogated, where she refused to say anything incriminating about Pasternak. At the time, she was pregnant with Pasternak's child and had a miscarriage early in her ten-year sentence in the<space/><link><target>GULAG</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Upon learning of his<space/><link><target>Mistress (lover)</target><part>mistress</part></link>' arrest, Pasternak telephoned Liuisa Popova and asked her to come at once to<space/><link><target>Gogol Boulevard</target></link>. She found him sitting on a bench near the<space/><link><target>Kropotkinskaya</target><part>Palace of Soviets Metro Station</part></link>. Weeping, Pasternak told her, &quot;Everything is finished now. They've taken her away from me and I'll never see her again. It's like death, even worse.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 86">Ivinskaya (1978), p 86.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya, &quot;After this, in conversation with people he scarcely knew, he always referred to Stalin as a 'murderer.' Talking with people in the offices of literary periodicals, he often asked: 'When will there be an end to this freedom for lackeys who happily walk over corpses to further their own interests?' He spent a good deal of time with Akhmatovawho in those years was given a very wide berth by most of the people who knew her. He worked intensively on the second part of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 86"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a 1958 letter to a friend in<space/><link><target>West Germany</target></link>, Pasternak wrote, &quot;She was put in jail on my account, as the person considered by the<space/><link><target>KGB</target><part>secret police</part></link><space/>to be closest to me, and they hoped that by means of a gruelling interrogation and threats they could extract enough evidence from her to put me on trial. I owe my life, and the fact that they did not touch me in those years, to her heroism and endurance.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 109.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Translating Goethe</heading><paragraph>Pasternak's translation of the<space/><link><target>Faust: The First Part of the Tragedy</target><part>first part</part></link><space/>of<space/><italics><link><target>Goethe's Faust</target><part>Faust</part></link></italics><space/>led him to be attacked in the August 1950 edition of<space/><italics><link><target>Novy Mir</target></link></italics>. The critic accused Pasternak of distorting<space/><link><target>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</target><part>Goethe</part></link>'s &quot;progressive&quot; meanings to support &quot;the reactionary theory of 'pure art'&quot;, as well as introducing aesthetic and<space/><link><target>individualist</target></link><space/>values. In a subsequent letter to the daughter of Marina Tsvetaeva, Pasternak explained that the attack was motivated by the fact that the supernatural elements of the play, which<space/><italics>Novy Mir</italics><space/>considered, &quot;irrational,&quot; had been translated as Goethe had written them. Pasternak further declared that, despite the attacks on his translation, his contract for the<space/><link><target>Faust: The Second Part of the Tragedy</target><part>second part</part></link><space/>had not been revoked.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin78"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Khrushchev thaw</heading><paragraph>When Stalin died of a stroke on 5 March 1953, Olga Ivinskaya was still imprisoned in the<space/><link><target>Gulag</target></link>, and Pasternak was in Moscow. Across the nation, there were waves of panic, confusion, and public displays of grief. Pasternak wrote, &quot;Men who are not free... always idealize their bondage.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978) p 144.</extension><extension extension_name='blockquote'><paragraph>After her release, Pasternak's relationship with Ivinskaya picked up where it had left off. Soon after he confided in her, &quot;For so long we were ruled over by a madman and a murderer, and now by a fool and a pig. The madman had his occasional flights of fancy, he had an intuitive feeling for certain things, despite his wild obscurantism. Now we are ruled over by mediocrities.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin142">Ivinskaya (1978) p 142.</extension><space/>During this period, Pasternak delighted in reading a clandestine copy of<space/><link><target>George Orwell</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Animal Farm</target></link></italics><space/>in English. In conversation with Ivinskaya, Pasternak explained that the pig dictator<space/><link><target>Napoleon (Animal Farm)</target><part>Napoleon</part></link>, in the novel, &quot;vividly reminded&quot; him of Soviet Premier<space/><link><target>Nikita Khrushchev</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin142"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Doctor Zhivago-1st ITA edition.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Cover to the Italian first edition of ''Doctor Zhivago'', 1957.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Although it contains passages written in the 1910s and 1920s,<space/><italics><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (novel)</target><part>Doctor Zhivago</part></link></italics><space/>was not completed until 1956. Pasternak submitted the novel to &quot; &quot; (<italics><link><target>Novy Mir</target></link></italics>), which refused publication due to its rejection of<space/><link><target>socialist realism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Doctor Zhivago&quot;: Letter to Boris Pasternak from the Editors of<space/><italics>Novyi Mir</italics>. Daedalus, Vol. 89, No. 3, The Russian Intelligentsia (Summer, 1960), pp.&amp;nbsp;648668</extension><space/>The author, like his<space/><link><target>protagonist</target></link><space/><link><target>Yuri Zhivago</target></link>, showed more concern for the welfare of individual characters than for the &quot;progress&quot; of society. Censors also regarded some passages as<space/><link><target>anti-Soviet</target></link>, especially the novel's criticisms<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2013</arg></template><space/>of<space/><link><target>Stalinism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Collectivisation</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Great Purge</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Gulag</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak's fortunes were soon to change, however. In March 1956, the<space/><link><target>Italian Communist Party</target></link><space/>sent a journalist,<space/><link><target>Sergio d'Angelo</target></link>, to work in the Soviet Union, and his status as a journalist as well as his membership in the Italian Communist Party allowed him to have access to various aspects of the cultural life in Moscow at the time. A Milan publisher, the communist<space/><link><target>Giangiacomo Feltrinelli</target></link>, had also given him a commission to find new works of Soviet literature that would be appealing to Western audiences, and upon learning of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>'s existence, d'Angelo travelled immediately to Peredelkino and offered to submit Pasternak's novel to Feltrinelli's company for publication. At first Pasternak was stunned. Then he brought the manuscript from his study and told d'Angelo with a laugh, &quot;You are hereby invited to watch me face the firing squad.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Lazar Fleishman,<space/><italics>Boris Pasternak: The Poet and His Politics</italics>, p 275.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Lazar Fleishman, Pasternak was aware that he was taking a huge risk. No Soviet author had attempted to deal with Western publishers since the 1920s, when such behavior led the Soviet State to declare war on<space/><link><target>Boris Pilnyak</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Evgeny Zamyatin</target></link>. Pasternak, however, believed that Feltrinelli's Communist affiliation would not only guarantee publication, but might even force the Soviet State to publish the novel in Russia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fleishman, pp 275276.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a rare moment of agreement, both Olga Ivinskaya and Zinaida Pasternak were horrified by the submission of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>to a Western publishing house. Pasternak, however, refused to change his mind and informed an emissary from Feltrinelli that he was prepared to undergo any sacrifice in order to see<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>published.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fleishman, p 276.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1957, Feltrinelli announced that the novel would be published by his company. Despite repeated demands from visiting Soviet emissaries, Feltrinelli refused to cancel or delay publication. According to Ivinskaya, &quot;He did not believe that we would ever publish the manuscript here and felt he had no right to withhold a masterpiece from the world this would be an even greater crime.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 203.</extension><space/>The Soviet government forced Pasternak to cable the publisher to withdraw the manuscript, but he sent separate, secret letters advising Feltrinelli to ignore the telegrams.<template><target>r</target><arg>washingtonpost</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Helped considerably by the Soviet campaign against the novel (as well as by the U.S.<space/><link><target>Central Intelligence Agency</target></link>'s secret purchase of hundreds of copies of the book as it came off the presses around the world see &quot;Nobel Prize&quot; section below),<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>became an instant sensation throughout the non-Communist world upon its release in November 1957. In the<space/><link><target>State of Israel</target></link>, however, Pasternak's novel was sharply criticized for its<space/><link><target>assimilationist</target></link><space/>views towards the<space/><link><target>Jewish people</target></link>. When informed of this, Pasternak responded, &quot;No matter. I am above race...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 136.</extension><space/>According to Lazar Fleishman, Pasternak had written the disputed passages prior to Israeli independence. At the time, Pasternak had also been regularly attending Russian Orthodox<space/><link><target>Divine Liturgy</target></link>. Therefore, he believed that Soviet Jews converting to Christianity was preferable to assimilating into<space/><link><target>atheism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stalinism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fleishman, pp 264266.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first English translation of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was hastily produced by<space/><link><target>Max Hayward</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Manya Harari</target></link><space/>in order to coincide with overwhelming public demand. It was released in August 1958, and remained the only edition available for more than fifty years. Between 1958 and 1959, the English language edition spent 26 weeks at the top of<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics>' bestseller list.</paragraph><paragraph>Ivinskaya's daughter Irina circulated typed copies of the novel in<space/><link><target>Samizdat</target></link>. Although no Soviet critics had read the banned novel,<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was pilloried in the State-owned press. Similar attacks led to a humorous Russian saying, &quot;I haven't read Pasternak, but I condemn him&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 268271.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the aftermath of the Second World War, Pasternak had composed a series of poems on<space/><link><target>Gospel</target></link><space/>themes. According to Ivinskaya, Pasternak had regarded Stalin as a, &quot;giant of the pre-Christian era.&quot; Therefore, Pasternak's Christian-themed poems were, &quot;a form of protest.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 134.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 9 September 1958, the<space/><italics>Literary Gazette</italics><space/>critic Viktor Pertsov retaliated by denouncing, &quot;the decadent religious poetry of Pasternak, which reeks of mothballs from the<space/><link><target>Russian Symbolism</target><part>Symbolist</part></link><space/>suitcase of 190810 manufacture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 231.</extension><space/>Furthermore, the author received much<space/><link><target>hate mail</target></link><space/>from Communists both at home and abroad. According to Ivinskaya, Pasternak continued to receive such letters for the remainder of his life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 230.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a letter written to his sister Josephine, however, Pasternak recalled the words of his friend Ekaterina Krashennikova upon reading<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>. She had said, &quot;Don't forget yourself to the point of believing that it was you who wrote this work. It was the<space/><link><target>Russian people</target></link><space/>and their sufferings who created it. Thank God for having expressed it through your pen.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Boris Pasternak: Family Correspondence 19121960,</italics><space/>p 403.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nobel Prize</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Miniature Volume of Pasternak's Doctor Zhivago - Flickr - The Central Intelligence Agency.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Copy of the original Russian-language edition of ''Doctor Zhivago'', covertly published by the<space/><link><target>Central Intelligence Agency</target><part>CIA</part></link>. The front cover and the binding identify the book in Russian; the back of the book states that it was printed in France.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>According to Yevgeni Borisovich Pasternak, &quot;Rumors that Pasternak was to receive the Nobel Prize started right after the end of<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>. According to the former Nobel Committee head<space/><link><target>Lars Gyllensten</target></link>, his nomination was discussed every year from 1946 to 1950, then again in 1957 (it was finally awarded in 1958). Pasternak guessed at this from the growing waves of criticism in USSR. Sometimes he had to justify his European fame: 'According to the Union of Soviet Writers, some literature circles of the West see unusual importance in my work, not matching its modesty and low productivity'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="english.pravda.ru"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"></arg><arg name="url">http://english.pravda.ru/society/showbiz/18-12-2003/4383-pasternak-0/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Boris Pasternak: Nobel Prize, Son's Memoirs<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">English.pravda.ru<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 December 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 January 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to journalist Ivan Tolstoi, the British<space/><link><target>MI6</target></link><space/>and the American<space/><link><target>CIA</target></link><space/>lent a hand to ensure that<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was submitted to the<space/><link><target>Nobel Committee</target></link><space/>in the original Russian. According to Tolstoi, this was done so that Pasternak could win the Nobel prize and harm the international credibility of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>. He repeats and elaborates upon Feltrinelli's claims that the CIA operatives had photographed a manuscript of the novel and secretly printed a small number of books in the<space/><link><target>Russian language</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="timesonline-292690"><link type='external' href='http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article1292690.ece'>How the CIA won Zhivago a Nobel</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="RFERL.org"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rferl.org/content/Was_Pasternaks_Path_To_The_Nobel_Paved_By_The_CIA/1496794.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Was Pasternak's Path to the Nobel Prize Paved by the CIA?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rferl.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 January 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="washingtonpost"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/26/AR2007012601758.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Plot Thickens A New Book Promises an Intriguing Twist to the Epic Tale of 'Doctor Zhivago'<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Washingtonpost.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 January 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>More recently, Anna Sergeyeva-Klyatis wrote that the first Russian edition of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>, which was a pirated version with numerous typographical errors and omissions, was actually initiated by the Central Association of Postwar migres, in response to a growing demand among Russian migrs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Social sciences"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.eastviewpress.com/Files/SS_FROM%20THE%20CURRENT%20ISSUE_No.%203_2011_small.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Social sciences – A Quarterly Journal of the Russian Academy of Sciences: INTERNATIONAL PROVOCATION: ON BORIS PASTERNAK’S NOBEL PRIZE<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 January 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The issue of whether or not the CIA had a hand in creating the international controversy that led to Pasternak's winning the Nobel Prize was definitively settled on 11 April 2014 when the U.S.<space/><link><target>Central Intelligence Agency</target></link><space/>released &quot;nearly 100 declassified documents&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.foia.cia.gov/search-results?search_api_views_fulltext</arg><arg name="title">Zhivago<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">11 April 2014<space/></arg><arg name="website">www.cia.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">U.S. Central Intelligence Agency<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>confirming that it had, in fact, undertaken a massive propaganda campaign to influence the Nobel Prize committee to consider<space/><italics>Zhivago</italics><space/>for the award, starting as early as 12 December 1957: &quot;<italics>Dr. Zhivago</italics><space/>should be published in a maximum number of foreign editions, for maximum free world discussion and acclaim and consideration for such honor as the Nobel prize&quot; [sic]<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.foia.cia.gov/sites/default/files/document_conversions/1822135/DOC_0005795615.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Document 19571212 MEMORANDUM ON PASTERNAK'S DR. ZHIVAGO<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">12 December 1957<space/></arg><arg name="website">www.cia.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">U.S. Central Intelligence Agency<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>In order to turn Pasternak's novel into an international bestseller worthy of consideration for the Nobel Prize, the CIA purchased thousands of copies of the novel as they came off the presses throughout Europe. When in the summer of 1958 the Dutch publishing house of Mouton brought out an edition of<space/><italics>Zhivago</italics>, the CIA secretly arranged to &quot;obtain first thousand copies of the book off the press and of these send 500 copies to the Brussels Fair&quot; (i.e. the World's Fair held that summer in Brussels, Belgium).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.foia.cia.gov/sites/default/files/document_conversions/1822135/DOC_0005796355.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Document 19590203 NOTE ON THE STORY OF DR. ZHIVAGO<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">3 February 1959<space/></arg><arg name="website">www.cia.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">U.S. Central Intelligence Agency<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>In its announcement of the declassification of the<space/><italics>Zhivago</italics><space/>documents the CIA states that it also published &quot;thousands&quot; of copies of<space/><italics>Zhivago</italics><space/>and gave them out to Soviet tourists on holiday in Western Europe and had them smuggled into the Soviet Union: &quot;After working secretly to publish the Russian-language edition in the Netherlands, the CIA moved quickly to ensure that copies of Doctor Zhivago were available for distribution to Soviet visitors at the 1958 Brussels Worlds Fair. By the end of the Fair, 355 copies of Doctor Zhivago had been surreptitiously handed out, and eventually thousands more were distributed throughout the Communist bloc. [...] Subsequently, the CIA funded the publication of a miniature, lightweight paperback edition of Doctor Zhivago that could be easily mailed or concealed in a jacket pocket. Distribution of the miniature version began in April 1959.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/news-information/press-releases-statements/2014-press-releases-statements/cia-declassifies-agency-role-in-publishing-doctor-zhivago.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">CIA Declassifies Agency Role in Publishing Doctor Zhivago<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">14 April 2014<space/></arg><arg name="website">www.cia.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">U.S. Central Intelligence Agency<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 September 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, Pasternak wrote to Renate Schweitzer<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 220.</extension><space/>and his sister,<space/><link><target>Lydia Pasternak Slater</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Boris Pasternak: Family Correspondence 19211960</italics>,<space/><link><target>Hoover Press</target></link>, 2010. p 402.</extension><space/>In both letters, the author expressed hope that he would be passed over by the Nobel Committee in favour of<space/><link><target>Alberto Moravia</target></link>. Pasternak wrote that he was wracked with torments and anxieties at the thought of placing his loved ones in danger.</paragraph><paragraph>On 23 October 1958, Boris Pasternak was announced as the winner of the Nobel Prize. The citation credited Pasternak's contribution to Russian lyric poetry and for his role in, &quot;continuing the great Russian epic tradition.&quot; On 25 October, Pasternak sent a<space/><link><target>telegram</target></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>Swedish Academy</target></link>: &quot;Infinitely grateful, touched, proud, surprised, overwhelmed.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 221.</extension><space/>That same day, the Literary Institute in Moscow demanded that all its students sign a petition denouncing Pasternak and his novel. They were further ordered to join a &quot;spontaneous&quot; demonstration demanding Pasternak's exile from the Soviet Union.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 223224.</extension><space/>On 26 October, the<space/><italics>Literary Gazette</italics><space/>ran an article by David Zaslavski entitled,<space/><italics><link><target>Reactionary</target></link><space/>Propaganda Uproar over a Literary Weed</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 224.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Solomon Volkov</target></link>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The anti-Pasternak campaign was organized in the worst Stalin tradition: denunciations in ''Pravda'' and other newspapers; publications of angry letters from, "ordinary Soviet workers," who had not read the book; hastily convened meetings of Pasternak's friends and colleagues, at which fine poets like [[Vladimir Soloukin]], [[Leonid Martynov]], and [[Boris Slutsky]] were forced to censure an author they respected. Slutsky, who in his brutal prose-like poems had created an image for himself as a courageous soldier and truth-lover, was so tormented by his anti-Pasternak speech that he later went insane. On October 29, 1958, at the plenum of the Central Committee of the Young Communist League, dedicated to the [[Komsomol]]'s fortieth anniversary, its head, [[Vladimir Semichastny]], attacked Pasternak before an audience of 14,000 people, including Khrushchev and other Party leaders. Semishastny first called Pasternak, "a mangy sheep," who pleased the enemies of the Soviet Union with, "his slanderous so-called work." Then Semichastny (who became head of the KGB in 1961) added that, "this man went and spat in the face of the people." And he concluded with, "If you compare Pasternak to a pig, a pig would not do what he did," because a pig, "never shits where it eats." Khrushchev applauded demonstratively. News of that speech drove Pasternak to the brink of suicide. It has recently come to light that the real author of Semichastny's insults was Khrushchev, who had called the Komsomol leader the night before and dictated his lines about the mangy sheep and the pig, which Semichastny described as a, "typically Khrushchevian, deliberately crude, unceremoniously scolding."<ref>Solomon Volkov, ''The Magical Chorus: A History of Russian Culture from Tolstoy to Solzhenitsyn'', Alfred A. Knopf, 2008. Pages 195–196.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, Pasternak was informed that, if he traveled to<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>to collect his Nobel Medal, he would be refused re-entry to the Soviet Union. As a result, Pasternak sent a second telegram to the Nobel Committee: &quot;In view of the meaning given the award by the society in which I live, I must renounce this undeserved distinction which has been conferred on me. Please do not take my voluntary renunciation amiss.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 232.</extension><space/>The Swedish Academy announced: &quot;This refusal, of course, in no way alters the validity of the award. There remains only for the Academy, however, to announce with regret that the presentation of the Prize cannot take place.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="nobel_lectures"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Literature 1901–1967
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Frenz, Horst (ed.)
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>Nobel Lectures
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1969
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Elsevier
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Amsterdam
</arg></template>(Via<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1958/press.html
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nobel Prize in Literature 1958 – Announcement
</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 May 2007
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Nobel Foundation]]
</arg></template>)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Yevgenii Pasternak, &quot;I couldn't recognize my father when I saw him that evening. Pale, lifeless face, tired painful eyes, and only speaking about the same thing: 'Now it all doesnt matter, I declined the Prize.'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="english.pravda.ru"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Deportation plans</heading><paragraph>Despite his decision to decline the award, the Soviet Union of Writers continued to demonise Pasternak in the State-owned press. Furthermore, he was threatened at the very least with formal exile to the West. In response, Pasternak wrote directly to Soviet Premier<space/><link><target>Nikita Khrushchev</target></link>,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>I am addressing you personally, the C.C. of the C.P.S.S., and the Soviet Government. From Comrade Semichastny's speech I learn that the government, 'would not put any obstacles in the way of my departure from the U.S.S.R.' For me this is impossible. I am tied to Russia by birth, by my life and work. I cannot conceive of my destiny separate from Russia, or outside it. Whatever my mistakes or failings, I could not imagine that I should find myself at the center of such a political campaign as has been worked up round my name in the West. Once I was aware of this, I informed the Swedish Academy of my voluntary renunciation of the Nobel Prize. Departure beyond the borders of my country would for me be tantamount to death and I therefore request you not to take this extreme measure with me. With my hand on my heart, I can say that I have done something for Soviet literature, and may still be of use to it.<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 240–241.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>The Oak and the Calf</italics>,<space/><link><target>Alexander Solzhenitsyn</target></link><space/>sharply criticized Pasternak, both for declining the Nobel Prize and for sending such a letter to Khrushchev. In her own memoirs, Olga Ivinskaya blames herself for pressuring her lover into making both decisions.</paragraph><paragraph>According to Yevgenii Pasternak, &quot;She accused herself bitterly for persuading Pasternak to decline the Prize. After all that had happened, open shadowing, friends turning away, Pasternak's suicidal condition at the time, one can... understand her: the memory of Stalins camps was too fresh, [and] she tried to protect him.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="english.pravda.ru"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 31 October 1958, the<space/><link><target>Union of Soviet Writers</target></link><space/>held a trial behind closed doors. According to the meeting minutes, Pasternak was denounced as an internal<space/><link><target>White emigre</target></link><space/>and a Fascist<space/><link><target>fifth columnist</target></link>. Afterwards, the attendees announced that Pasternak had been expelled from the Union. They further signed a petition to the<space/><link><target>Politburo</target></link>, demanding that Pasternak be stripped of his Soviet citizenship and exiled to, &quot;his Capitalist paradise.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 251261.</extension><space/>According to Yevgenii Pasternak, however, author<space/><link><target>Konstantin Paustovsky</target></link><space/>refused to attend the meeting.<space/><link><target>Yevgeny Yevtushenko</target></link><space/>did attend, but walked out in disgust.<extension extension_name='ref' name="english.pravda.ru"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Yevgenii Pasternak, his father would have been exiled had it not been for Indian Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Jawaharlal Nehru</target></link>, who telephoned Khrushchev and threatened to find a Committee for Pasternak's protection.<extension extension_name='ref' name="english.pravda.ru"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is possible that the 1958 Nobel Prize prevented Pasternak's imprisonment due to the Soviet State's fear of international protests. Yevgenii Pasternak believes, however, that the resulting persecution fatally weakened his father's health.<template><target>r</target><arg>washingtonpost</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile,<space/><link><target>Bill Mauldin</target></link><space/>produced a<space/><link><target>political cartoon</target></link><space/>which won the 1959<space/><link><target>Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Cartooning</target></link>. The cartoon depicts Pasternak and another<space/><link><target>GULAG</target></link><space/>inmate, splitting trees in the snow. The caption reads, &quot;I won the Nobel Prize for literature. What was your crime?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/print/swann/mauldin/mauldin-intro.html'>Bill Mauldin Beyond Willie and Joe</link><space/>(Library of Congress)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Last years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dommuzejpasternak.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Boris Pasternak's<space/><link><target>dacha</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Peredelkino</target></link>, where he lived between 1936 and 1960</part></link>Pasternak's post-<italics>Zhivago</italics><space/>poetry probes the universal questions of love, immortality, and reconciliation with God.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.hoover.org/hila/exhibits/3243901.html'>Hostage of Eternity: Boris Pasternak</link><space/>(Hoover Institution)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news-service.stanford.edu/news/2004/april28/pasternak-428.html'>Conference set on Doctor Zhivago writer</link><space/>(Stanford Report, 28 April 2004)</extension><space/>Boris Pasternak wrote his last complete book,<space/><italics>When the Weather Clears</italics>, in 1959.</paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya, Pasternak continued to stick to his daily writing schedule even during the controversy over<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>. He also continued translating the writings of<space/><link><target>Juliusz Sowacki</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pedro Caldern de la Barca</target></link>. In his work on Calderon, Pasternak received the discreet support of Nikolai Mikhailovich Liubimov, a senior figure in the Party's literary apparatus. Ivinskaya describes Liubimov as, &quot;a shrewd and enlightened person who understood very well that all the mudslinging and commotion over the novel would be forgotten, but that there would always be a Pasternak.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 292.</extension></paragraph></extension><space/>In a letter to his sisters in Oxford, England, Pasternak claimed to have finished translating one of Calderon's plays in less than a week.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p xxxix.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the summer of 1959, Pasternak began writing<space/><italics>The Blind Beauty</italics>, a trilogy of<space/><link><target>stage play</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>set before and after<space/><link><target>Alexander II of Russia</target><part>Alexander II</part></link>'s abolition of<space/><link><target>serfdom in Russia</target></link>. In an interview with<space/><link><target>Olga Carlisle</target></link><space/>from<space/><italics><link><target>The Paris Review</target></link></italics>, Pasternak enthusiastically described the play's plot and characters. He informed Olga Carlisle that, at the end of<space/><italics>The Blind Beauty</italics>, he wished to depict &quot;the birth of an enlightened and affluent middle class, open to occidental influences, progressive, intelligent, artistic&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/4679/the-art-of-fiction-no-25-boris-pasternak'>&quot;The Paris Review&quot; interviews Boris Pasternak</link>.</extension><space/>However, Pasternak fell ill with terminal lung cancer before he could complete the first play of the trilogy.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pasternaks last poem</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>How I remember solstice days<br />
Through many winters long completed!<br />
Each unrepeatable, unique,<br />
And each one countless times repeated.

Of all these days, these only days,<br />
When one rejoiced in the impression<br />
That time had stopped, there grew in years<br />
An unforgettable succession.

Each one of them I can evoke.<br />
The year is to midwinter moving,<br />
The roofs are dripping, roads are soaked,<br />
And on the ice the sun is brooding.

Then lovers hastily are drawn<br />
To one another, vague and dreaming,<br />
And in the heat, upon a tree<br />
The sweating nesting-box is steaming.

And sleepy clock-hands laze away<br />
The clock-face wearily ascending.<br />
Eternal, endless is the day,<br />
And the embrace is never-ending.<ref>[http://jewishnews.com.ua/en/publication/is_it_easy_to_be_a_jew" Is it easy to be a Jew? Jewish News]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Death</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pasternak grave landscape.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Boris Pasternak's grave in<space/><link><target>Peredelkino</target></link><space/>in October 1983</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Boris Pasternak died of lung cancer in his<space/><link><target>dacha</target></link><space/>in Peredelkino on the evening of 30 May 1960. He first summoned his sons, and in their presence said, &quot;Who will suffer most because of my death? Who will suffer most? Only Oliusha will, and I haven't had time to do anything for her. The worst thing is that she will suffer.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin323">Ivinskaya (1978), pp 323326</extension><space/>Pasternak's last words were, &quot;I can't hear very well. And there's a mist in front of my eyes. But it will go away, won't it? Don't forget to open the window tomorrow.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin323"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Shortly before his death, a priest of the<space/><link><target>Russian Orthodox Church</target></link><space/>had given Pasternak the<space/><link><target>last rites</target></link>. Later, in the strictest secrecy, a<space/><link><target>Russian Orthodox Church#Liturgy</target><part>Russian Orthodox funeral liturgy</part></link>, or<space/><link><target>Panikhida</target></link>, was offered in the family's dacha.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 332">Ivinskaya (1978), p 332.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Funeral demonstration</heading><paragraph>Despite only a small notice appearing in the<space/><italics>Literary Gazette</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin323"></extension><space/>handwritten notices carrying the date and time of the funeral were posted throughout the Moscow subway system.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin323"></extension><space/>As a result, thousands of admirers braved Militia and KGB surveillance to attend Pasternak's funeral in Peredelkino.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 326327.</extension>&lt;/blockquote&gt;</paragraph><paragraph>Before Pasternak's civil funeral, Olga Ivinskaya had a conversation with<space/><link><target>Konstantin Paustovsky</target></link>. According to Ivinskaya,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>He began to say what an authentic event the funeral was—an expression of what people really felt, and so characteristic of the Russia which stoned its prophets and did its poets to death as a matter of longstanding tradition. At such a moment, he continued indignantly, one was bound to recall the funeral of Pushkin and the Tsar's courtiers – their miserable hypocrisy and false pride. "Just think how rich they are, how many Pasternaks they have—as many as there were Pushkins in the Russia of Tsar Nicholas... Not much has changed. But what can one expect? They are afraid..."<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), p 328.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Then, in the presence of a large number of foreign journalists, the body of Pasternak was removed to the cemetery. According to Ivinskaya,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The graveside service now began. It was hard for me in my state to make out what was going on. Later, I was told that Paustovski had wanted to give the funeral address, but it was in fact Professor Asmus who spoke. Wearing a light colored suit and a bright tie, he was dressed more for some gala occasion than for a funeral. "A writer has died," he began, "who, together with Pushkin, Dostoevsky, and Tolstoy, forms part of the glory of Russian literature. Even if we cannot agree with him in everything; we all none the less owe him a debt of gratitude for setting an example of unswerving honesty, for his incorruptible conscience, and for his heroic view of his duty as a writer." Needless to say, he mentioned [Boris Leonidovich]'s, "mistakes and failings," but hastened to add that, "they do not, however, prevent us from recognizing the fact that he was a great poet." "He was a very modest man," Asmus said in conclusion, "and he did not like people to talk about him too much, so with this I shall bring my address to a close."<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 330–331.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>To the horror of the assembled Party officials, however, someone with, &quot;a young and deeply anguished voice,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 331">Ivinskaya (1978), p 331.</extension><space/>began reciting Pasternak's banned poem<space/><italics>Hamlet</italics>.</paragraph><table><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>quote</target><arg>
Гул затих. Я вышел на подмостки.<br>
Прислонясь к дверному косяку,<br>
Я ловлю в далеком отголоске,<br>
Что случится на моем веку.

На меня наставлен сумрак ночи<br>
Тысячью биноклей на оси.<br>
Если только можно, Aвва Отче,<br>
Чашу эту мимо пронеси.

Я люблю твой замысел упрямый<br>
И играть согласен эту роль.<br>
Но сейчас идет другая драма,<br>
И на этот раз меня уволь.

Но продуман распорядок действий,<br>
И неотвратим конец пути.<br>
Я один, все тонет в фарисействе.<br>
Жизнь прожить – не поле перейти.</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>quote</target><arg>
The murmurs ebb; onto the stage I enter.<br>
I am trying, standing at the door,<br>
To discover in the distant echoes<br>
What the coming years may hold in store.

The nocturnal darkness with a thousand<br>
Binoculars is focused onto me.<br>
Take away this cup, O Abba, Father,<br>
Everything is possible to Thee.

I am fond of this Thy stubborn project,<br>
And to play my part I am content.<br>
But another drama is in progress,<br>
And, this once, O let me be exempt.

But the plan of action is determined,<br>
And the end irrevocably sealed.<br>
I am alone; all round me drowns in falsehood:<br>
Life is not a walk across a field.<ref>Lydia Pasternak Slater, ''Pasternak: Fifty Poems'', Barnes & Noble Books, 1963. p 57.</ref></arg></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="At this point, the persons stage-managing the proceedings decided the ceremony must be brought to an end as quickly as possible, and somebody began to carry the lid toward the coffin. For the last time, I bent down to kiss Boria on the forehead, now completely cold... But now something unusual began to happen in the cemetery. Someone was about to put the lid on the coffin, and another person in gray trousers... said in an agitated voice: "That's enough, we don't need any more speeches! Close the coffin!" But people would not be silenced so easily. Someone in a colored, open-necked shirt who looked like a worker started to speak: "Sleep peacefully, dear Boris Leonidovich! We do not know all your works, but we swear to you at this hour: the day will come when we shall know them all. We do not believe anything bad about your book. And what can we say about all you others, all you brother writers who have brought such disgrace upon yourselves that no words can describe it. Rest in peace, Boris Leonidovich!" The man in gray trousers seized hold of other people who tried to come forward and pushed them back into the crowd: "The meeting is over, there will be no more speeches!" A foreigner expressed his indigation in broken Russian: "You can only say the meeting is over when no more people wish to speak!"<ref name">"Ivinskaya 1978, p 331"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The final speaker at the graveside service said,</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>God marks the path of the elect with thorns, and Pasternak was picked out and marked by God. He believed in eternity and he will belong to it... We excommunicated [[Leo Tolstoy|Tolstoy]], we disowned [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky|Dostoevsky]], and now we disown Pasternak. Everything that brings us glory we try to banish to [[Free world|the West]]... But we cannot allow this. We love Pasternak and we revere him as a poet... Glory to Pasternak!<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), pp 331–332.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As the spectators cheered, the bells of Peredelkino's Church of the Transfiguration began to toll. Written prayers for the dead were then placed upon Pasternak's forehead and the coffin was closed and buried. Pasternak's gravesite would go on to become a major shrine for members of the<space/><link><target>Soviet dissident</target></link><space/>movement.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 332"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:1990 CPA PC 197.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>USSR, 4<space/><link><target>Russian ruble</target><part>kopek</part></link><space/>stamp, 1990</part></link>After Pasternak's death,<space/><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link><space/>was arrested for the second time, with her daughter, Irina Emelyanova. Both were accused of being Pasternak's link with Western publishers and of dealing in hard currency for<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>. All of Pasternak's letters to Ivinskaya, as well as many other manuscripts and documents, were seized by the<space/><link><target>KGB</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>KGB</target></link><space/>quietly released them, Irina after one year, in 1962, and Olga in 1964.<extension extension_name='ref' name="independent"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.independent.co.uk/news/obituaries/obituary-olga-ivinskaya-1600834.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">OBITUARY: Olga Ivinskaya<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Independent<space/></arg><arg name="location">UK<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 September 1995<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 October 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>By this time, Ivinskaya had served four years of an eight-year sentence, in retaliation for her role in<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>s publication.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytimes"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1995/09/13/obituaries/olga-ivinskaya-83-pasternak-muse-for-zhivago.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Olga Ivinskaya, 83, Pasternak Muse for 'Zhivago'<space/></arg><arg name="work">New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 September 1995<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 October 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1978, her memoirs were smuggled abroad and published in Paris. An English translation by<space/><link><target>Max Hayward</target></link><space/>was published the same year under the title<space/><italics>A Captive of Time: My Years with Pasternak</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Ivinskaya was<space/><link><target>Rehabilitation (Soviet)</target><part>rehabilitated</part></link><space/>only in 1988. After the<space/><link><target>dissolution of the Soviet Union</target></link>, Ivinskaya sued for the return of the letters and documents seized by the KGB in 1961. The<space/><link><target>Russian Supreme Court</target></link><space/>ultimately ruled against her, stating that, &quot;there was no proof of ownership,&quot; and that the, &quot;papers should remain in the state archive&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="independent"></extension><space/>Olga Ivinskaya died of cancer on 8 September 1995.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytimes"></extension><space/>A reporter on<space/><link><target>NTV (Russia)</target><part>NTV</part></link><space/>compared her role to that of other famous<space/><link><target>muse</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for Russian poets: &quot;As<space/><link><target>Pushkin</target></link><space/>would not be complete without<space/><link><target>Anna Kern</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Yesenin</target></link><space/>would be nothing without Isadora, so Pasternak would not be Pasternak without<space/><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link>, who was his inspiration for<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>.&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytimes"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, Boris Pasternak continued to be pilloried by the Soviet State until<space/><link><target>Mikhail Gorbachev</target></link><space/>proclaimed<space/><link><target>Perestroika</target></link><space/>during the 1980s.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1988, after decades of circulating in<space/><link><target>Samizdat</target></link>,<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics><space/>was serialized in the literary journal<space/><italics><link><target>Novy Mir</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://magazines.russ.ru/novyi_mi/soder/80-89.html'>Contents</link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Novy Mir</target></link><space/>magazines<space/><template><target>ru icon</target></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In December 1989, Yevgenii Borisovich Pasternak was permitted to travel to Stockholm in order to collect his father's Nobel Medal.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://english.pravda.ru/society/showbiz/18-12-2003/4383-pasternak-0/'>&quot;Boris Pasternak: The Nobel Prize. Son's memoirs&quot;.</link><space/>(<italics>Pravda</italics>, 18 December 2003)</extension><space/>At the ceremony, acclaimed cellist and Soviet dissident<space/><link><target>Mstislav Rostropovich</target></link><space/>performed a<space/><link><target>Johann Sebastian Bach</target><part>Bach</part></link><space/>serenade in honor of his deceased countryman.</paragraph><paragraph>A 2009 book by Ivan Tolstoi reasserts claims that British and American intelligence officers were involved in ensuring Pasternak's Nobel victory however another Russian researcher disagrees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RFERL.org"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Social sciences"></extension><space/>When Yevgeny Borisovich Pasternak was questioned about this, he responded that his father was completely unaware of the actions of Western intelligence services. Yevgeny further declared that the Nobel Prize caused his father nothing but severe grief and harassment at the hands of the Soviet State.<extension extension_name='ref' name="timesonline-292690"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="washingtonpost"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Pasternak family papers are stored at the<space/><link><target>Hoover Institution</target></link><space/>Archives,<space/><link><target>Stanford University</target></link>. They contain correspondence, drafts of<space/><italics><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (novel)</target><part>Doctor Zhivago</part></link></italics><space/>and other writings, photographs, and other material, of Boris Pasternak and other family members.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cultural influence</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>minor planet</target></link><space/>(<link><target>3508 Pasternak</target></link>) discovered by Soviet astronomer<space/><link><target>Lyudmila Georgievna Karachkina</target></link><space/>in 1980 is named after him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Schmadel</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Lutz D.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dictionary of Minor Planet Names</arg><arg name="page"><space/>294</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>5th</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Springer Verlag</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?q</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>3-540-00238-3</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 2014 Spanish-Argentinian anthological film<space/><italics><link><target>Wild Tales (film)</target><part>Relatos Salvajes</part></link></italics><space/>features the story about a failed musician named Pasternak who elaborately conspires to kill himself and a range of acquaintances in his life who he believes has wronged him.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Russian-American</target></link><space/>singer and songwriter<space/><link><target>Regina Spektor</target></link><space/>recites a verse from &quot;Black Spring&quot;, a 1912 poem by Pasternak in her song &quot;Apres Moi&quot; from her album<space/><italics><link><target>Begin to Hope</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Adaptations</heading><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (1965 film)</target><part>screen adaptation</part></link><space/>of<space/><italics>Doctor Zhivago</italics>, adapted by<space/><link><target>Robert Bolt</target></link><space/>and directed by<space/><link><target>David Lean</target></link>, appeared in 1965. The film, which toured in the<space/><link><target>roadshow</target></link><space/>tradition, starred<space/><link><target>Omar Sharif</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Geraldine Chaplin</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Julie Christie</target></link>. Concentrating on the<space/><link><target>love triangle</target></link><space/>aspects of the novel, the film became a worldwide blockbuster, but was unavailable in Russia until<space/><link><target>Perestroika</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2002, the novel was adapted as a<space/><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (TV serial)</target><part>television miniseries</part></link>. Directed by Giacomo Campiotti, the serial starred<space/><link><target>Hans Matheson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Alexandra Maria Lara</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Keira Knightley</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Sam Neill</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Russian TV version of 2006, directed by<space/><link><target>Alexander Proshkin</target></link><space/>and starring<space/><link><target>Oleg Menshikov</target></link><space/>as Zhivago, is considered more faithful to Pasternak's novel than David Lean's 1965 film.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Work</heading><heading level='3'>Poetry</heading><heading level='4'>Thoughts on poetry</heading><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="In Pasternak the 'all-powerful god of detail' always, it seems, revolted against the idea of turning out verse for its own sake or to convey vague personal moods. If 'eternal' themes were to be dealt with yet again, then only by a poet in the true sense of the word – otherwise he should not have the strength of character to touch them at all. Poetry so tightly packed (till it crunched like ice) or distilled into a solution where 'grains of true prose germinated,' a poetry in which realistic detail cast a genuine spell – only such poetry was acceptable to Pasternak; but not poetry for which indulgence was required, or for which allowances had to be made – that is, the kind of ephemeral poetry which is particularly common in an age of literary conformism. [Boris Leonidovich] could weep over the 'purple-gray circle' which glowed above [[Alexander Blok|Blok]]'s tormented muse and he never failed to be moved by the terseness of [[Pushkin]]'s sprightly lines, but rhymed slogans about the production of tin cans in the so-called 'poetry' of [[Surkov]] and his like, as well as the outpourings about love in the work of those young poets who only echo each other and the classics – all this left him cold at best and for the most part made him indignant."<ref name">"Ivinskaya 1978, p 145">Ivinskaya (1978), p 145.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For this reason, Pasternak regularly avoided literary cafes where young poets regularly invited them to read their verse. According to Ivinskaya, &quot;It was this sort of thing that moved him to say: 'Who started the idea that I love poetry? I can't stand poetry.'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivinskaya 1978, p 145"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Also according to Ivinskaya, &quot;'The way they could write!' he once exclaimed by 'they' he meant the Russian classics. And immediately afterward, reading or, rather, glancing through some verse in the<space/><italics>Literary Gazette</italics>: 'Just look how tremendously well they've learned to rhyme! But there's actually nothing there it would be better to say it in a news bulletin. What has poetry got to do with this?' By 'they' in this case, he meant the poets writing today.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ivinskaya (1978), p 146.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Translation</heading><paragraph>Reluctant to conform to<space/><link><target>Socialist Realism</target></link>, Pasternak turned to translation in order to provide for his family. He soon produced acclaimed translations of<space/><link><target>Sndor Petfi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rainer Maria Rilke</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paul Verlaine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Taras Shevchenko</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Nikoloz Baratashvili</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Osip Mandelstam</target></link>, however, privately warned him, &quot;Your collected works will consist of twelve volumes of translations, and only one of your own work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin78">Ivinskaya (1978) pp 7879.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a 1942 letter, Pasternak declared, &quot;I am completely opposed to contemporary ideas about translation. The work of Lozinski, Radlova,<space/><link><target>Samuil Marshak</target><part>Marshak</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Kornei Chukovsky</target><part>Chukovski</part></link><space/>is alien to me, and seems artificial, soulless, and lacking in depth. I share the nineteenth century view of translation as a literary exercise demanding insight of a higher kind than that provided by a merely philological approach.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin78"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya, Pasternak believed in not being too literal in his translations, which he felt could confuse the meaning of the text. He instead advocated observing each poem from afar to plumb its true depths.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin28">Ivinskaya (1978) pp 2829.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak's translations of<space/><link><target>William Shakespeare</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Romeo and Juliet</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Antony and Cleopatra</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Othello</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics>King Henry IV</italics><space/>(Parts I and II),<space/><italics><link><target>Hamlet</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Macbeth</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>King Lear</target></link></italics>)<extension extension_name='ref'>Boris Pasternak,<space/><italics>I Remember: Sketch for an Autobiography</italics>, Pantheon Books, 1959. p 127.</extension><space/>remain deeply popular with Russian audiences because of their colloquial, modernised dialogues. Pasternak's critics, however, accused him of &quot;pasternakizing&quot; Shakespeare. In a 1956 essay, Pasternak wrote, &quot;Translating Shakespeare is a task which takes time and effort. Once it is undertaken, it is best to divide it into sections long enough for the work to not get stale and to complete one section each day. In thus daily progressing through the text, the translator finds himself reliving the circumstances of the author. Day by day, he reproduces his actions and he is drawn into some of his secrets, not in theory, but practically, by experience.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Pasternak, (1959) p 142.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Ivinskaya:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Whenever [Boris Leonidovich] was provided with literal versions of things which echoed his own thoughts or feelings, it made all the difference and he worked feverishly, turning them into masterpieces. I remember his translating [[Paul Verlaine]] in a burst of enthusiasm like this – ''[[:s:fr:Art poétique (Verlaine)|Art poétique (Verlaine)]]'' was after all an expression of his own beliefs about poetry.<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), p 34.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While they were both collaborating on translating<space/><link><target>Rabindranath Tagore</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Bengali language</target><part>Bengali</part></link><space/>into Russian, Pasternak advised Ivinskaya, &quot;1) Bring out the theme of the poem, its subject matter, as clearly as possible; 2) tighten up the fluid, non-European form by rhyming internally, not at the end of the lines; 3) use loose, irregular<space/><link><target>Meter (poetry)</target><part>meters</part></link>, mostly ternary ones. You may allow yourself to use<space/><link><target>assonance</target><trail>s</trail></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ivin28"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Later, while she was collaborating with him on a translation of<space/><link><target>Vtzslav Nezval</target></link>, Pasternak told Ivinskaya:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Use the literal translation only for the ''meaning'', but do not borrow words as they stand from it: they are absurd and not always comprehensible. Don't translate everything, only what you can manage, and by this means try to make the translation more precise than the original – an absolute necessity in the case of such a confused, slipshod piece of work."<ref name">"Ivin28"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Olga Ivinskaya</target></link>, however, translation was not a genuine vocation for Pasternak. She later recalled:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>One day someone brought him a copy of a British newspaper in which there was a double feature under the title, "Pasternak Keeps a Courageous Silence." It said that if Shakespeare had written in Russian he would have written in the same way he was translated by Pasternak... What a pity, the article continued, that Pasternak published nothing but translations, writing his own work for himself and a small circle of intimate friends. "What do they mean by saying that my silence is courageous?" [Boris Leonidovich] commented sadly after reading all this. "I am silent because I am not printed."<ref>Ivinskaya (1978), p 35.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Music</heading><paragraph>Boris Pasternak was also a composer, and had a promising musical career as a musician ahead of him, had he chosen to pursue it. He came from a musical family: his mother was a concert pianist and a student of<space/><link><target>Anton Rubinstein</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Theodor Leschetizky</target></link>, and Pasternak's early impressions were of hearing piano trios in the home. The family had a<space/><link><target>dacha</target></link><space/>country house close to one occupied by<space/><link><target>Alexander Scriabin</target></link>;<space/><link><target>Sergei Rachmaninoff</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rainer Maria Rilke</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link><space/>were all visitors to the family home. His father Leonid was a painter who produced one of the most important portraits of Scriabin, and Pasternak wrote many years later of witnessing with great excitement the creation of Scriabin's<space/><link><target>Symphony No. 3 (Scriabin)</target><part>Symphony No. 3, &quot;The Divine Poem&quot;</part></link>, in 1903.</paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak began to compose at the age of 13. The high achievements of his mother discouraged him from becoming a pianist, but inspired by Scriabin he entered the<space/><link><target>Moscow Conservatory</target></link>, but left abruptly in 1910 at the age of twenty, to study philosophy in<space/><link><target>Marburg University</target></link>. Four years later he returned to Moscow, having finally decided on a career in literature, publishing his first book of poems, influenced by<space/><link><target>Alexander Blok</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Russian Futurists</target></link>, the same year.</paragraph><paragraph>Pasternak's early compositions show the clear influence of Scriabin. His single-movement Piano Sonata of 1909 shows a more mature and individual voice. Nominally in B minor, it moves freely from key to key with frequent changes of key-signature and a chromatic dissonant style that defies easy analysis. Although composed during his time at the Conservatory, the Sonata was composed at Raiki, some 27 miles north-east of Moscow, where Leonid Pasternak had his painting studio and taught his students. (NB. This is not the site of the Pasternak family dacha, now open to the public, in the writers' colony at<space/><link><target>Peredelkino</target></link>, which is about 16 miles south-west of the capital.)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Selected books by Pasternak</heading><heading level='3'>Poetry collections</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Twin in the Clouds</italics><space/>(1914)</listitem><listitem><italics>Over the Barriers</italics><space/>(1916)</listitem><listitem><italics>Themes and Variations</italics><space/>(1917)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>My Sister, Life</target></link></italics><space/>(1922)</listitem><listitem><italics>On Early Trains</italics><space/>(1944)</listitem><listitem><italics>Selected Poems</italics><space/>(1946)</listitem><listitem><italics>Poems</italics><space/>(1954)</listitem><listitem><italics>When the Weather Clears</italics><space/>(1959)</listitem><listitem><italics>In The Interlude: Poems 19451960</italics><space/>(1962)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Books of prose</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Safe Conduct</italics><space/>(1931)</listitem><listitem><italics>Second Birth</italics><space/>(1932)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Last Summer (Pasternak novella)</target><part>The Last Summer</part></link></italics><space/>(1934)</listitem><listitem><italics>Childhood</italics><space/>(1941)</listitem><listitem><italics>Selected Writings</italics><space/>(1949)</listitem><listitem><italics>Collected Works</italics><space/>(1945)</listitem><listitem><italics>Goethe's Faust</italics><space/>(1952)</listitem><listitem><italics>Essay in Autobiography</italics><space/>(1956)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Doctor Zhivago (novel)</target><part>Doctor Zhivago</part></link></italics><space/>(1957)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Novels</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Jewish Nobel laureates</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Boris Pasternak,<space/><italics>I Remember; Sketches for an Autobiography</italics>,<space/><link><target>Pantheon Books</target></link>, 1959.</listitem><listitem>Boris Pasternak. &quot;Sister, My Life&quot; Translated by C. Flayderman. Introduction by Robert Payne. Washington Square Press, 1967.</listitem><listitem>Olga Ivinskaya,<space/><italics>A Captive of Time; My Years with Pasternak</italics>, Doubleday, 1978. Translated by<space/><link><target>Max Hayward</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Peter Finn and Petra Couvee,<space/><italics>The Zhivago Affair: The Kremlin, the CIA, and the Battle Over a Forbidden Book,</italics><space/>New York: Pantheon Books, 2014</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theparisreview.org/viewinterview.php/prmMID/4679'>Read Pasternak's interview with ''The Paris Review''</link><space/>Summer-Fall 1960 No. 24</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://nobelprize.org/literature/laureates/1958/index.html'>1958 Nobel Prize in Literature</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.poets.org/poet.php/prmPID/364'>Pasternak profile at Poets.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/masterpiece/zhivago/ei_pasternak.html'>PBS biography of Pasternak</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf70000535/'>Register of the Pasternak Family Papers at the Hoover Institution Archives</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://pasternak-trust.org/boris/biography/'>profile and images at the Pasternak Trust</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.uni-marburg.de/aktuelles/unijournal/uj39/uj39.pdf'>pp. 3639: Pasternak as a student at Marburg University, Germany</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Nobel Prize in Literature Laureates 19511975</target></template><template><target>Bancarella Prize</target></template><template><target>Soviet dissidents</target></template><template><target>Doctor Zhivago</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Pasternak, Boris
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich; Борис Леонидович Пастернак (Russian)
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Russian poet and writer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>10 February 1890
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Moscow, Russian Empire
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>30 May 1960
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Peredelkino, USSR
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Pasternak, Boris</target></template><link><target>Category:1890 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1960 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Writers from Moscow</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Moscow Governorate</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century English novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century Russian writers</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Antideath penalty activists</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Converts to Eastern Orthodoxy from Judaism</target></link><link><target>Category:EnglishRussian translators</target></link><link><target>Category:FrenchRussian translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Nobel laureates in Literature</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian Nobel laureates</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet Nobel laureates</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian male poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian World War I poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian male novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from lung cancer</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in the Soviet Union</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet dissidents</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet short story writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:Modernist writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Tolstoyans</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Armenian</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Bengali</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Czech</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from French</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Georgian</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from German</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Hungarian</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Polish</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Spanish</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators from Ukrainian</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators of William Shakespeare</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators to Russian</target></link><link><target>Category:UkrainianRussian translators</target></link><link><target>Category:World War II poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Nobel laureates absent at the ceremony</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian male dramatists and playwrights</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian male short story writers</target></link></paragraph></article>