<article title='Book_of_Jeremiah'><paragraph><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Nevi'im</arg><arg>prophetic</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Book of Jeremiah</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-he</target><arg>ספר יִרְמְיָהוּ</arg></template>; abbreviated<space/><bold><link><target>wikt:Jer.</target><part>Jer.</part></link></bold><space/>or<space/><bold><link><target>wikt:Jerem.</target><part>Jerem.</part></link></bold><space/>in citations) is the second of the<space/><link><target>Latter Prophets</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link>, and the second of the Prophets in the Christian<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">81-82</arg></template><space/>The superscription at chapter 1:13 identifies it as &quot;the words of<space/><link><target>Jeremiah</target></link><space/>son of Hilkiah,&quot; and places the prophet historically from the reforms of king<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link><space/>in 627 BC through to the assassination of the Babylonian-appointed governor of Judah in 582.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">81-82</arg></template><space/>Of all the prophets, Jeremiah comes through most clearly as a person, ruminating to his scribe Baruch about his role as a servant of God with little good news for his audience.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kugler</arg><arg>Hartin</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">241</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jeremiah is written in a very complex and poetic Hebrew (apart from verse 10:11, curiously written in<space/><link><target>Biblical Aramaic</target></link>). It has come down in two distinct though related versions, one in Hebrew, the other known from a Greek translation.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Both versions are heavily edited and reflect the perspectives of later ages; both portray Jeremiah as a &quot;second Moses&quot; but in reverse, presiding over Israel's banishment from the Promised land.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">86</arg></template><space/>The book is a representation of the message and significance of the prophet substantially intended for the Jews in Babylonian exile: its purpose is to explain the disaster as God's response to Israel's pagan worship:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">7,14</arg></template><space/>the people, says Jeremiah, are like an unfaithful wife and rebellious children: their infidelity and rebelliousness make judgement inevitable, although restoration and a new covenant are foreshadowed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Biddle</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">1074</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>(Taken from<space/><link><target>Michael D. Coogan</target></link>'s<space/></italics>A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament<italics>; other sources will give slightly different divisions)</italics></listitem></list><paragraph>It is difficult to discern any structure in Jeremiah, probably because the book had such a long and complex composition history.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kugler</arg><arg>Hartin</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">241</arg></template><space/>It can be divided into roughly 6 sections:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">299</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Chapters 125 (The earliest and main core of Jeremiah's message)</listitem><listitem>Chapters 2629 (Biographic material and interaction with other prophets)</listitem><listitem>Chapters 3033 (God's promise of restoration including Jeremiah's &quot;new covenant&quot; which is<space/><link><target>New Covenant#Judaism</target><part>interpreted differently in Judaism</part></link><space/>than it is in<space/><link><target>New Covenant#Christianity</target><part>Christianity</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>Chapters 3445 (Mostly interaction with<space/><link><target>Zedekiah</target></link><space/>and the fall of Jerusalem)</listitem><listitem>Chapters 4651 (Divine punishment to the nations surrounding Israel)</listitem><listitem>Chapter 52 (Appendix that retells<space/><link><target>2 Kings</target></link><space/>24.1825.30)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Summary</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn - Jeremia treurend over de verwoesting van Jeruzalem - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>thumbnail</part><part><link><target>Rembrandt van Rijn</target></link>, &quot;Jeremiah Lamenting the Destruction of Jerusalem&quot;, c. 1630</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Historical background</heading><paragraph>The background to Jeremiah is briefly described in the superscription to the book: Jeremiah began his prophetic mission in the thirteenth year of king Josiah (about 627 BCE) and finished in the eleventh year of king Zedekiah (586), &quot;when Jerusalem went into exile in the sixth month.&quot; During this period, Josiah reformed Judahite religion, Babylon destroyed Assyria, Egypt briefly imposed vassal status on Judah, Babylon defeated Egypt and made Judah a Babylonian vassal (605), Judah revolted but was subjugated again by Babylon (597), and Judah revolted once more. This revolt was the final one: Babylon destroyed Jerusalem and its Temple and exiled its king and many of the leading citizens in 586, ending Judah's existence as an independent or quasi-independent kingdom and inaugurating the<space/><link><target>Babylonian exile</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brettler</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">173</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Overview</heading><paragraph>The book can be conveniently divided into biographical, prose and poetic strands, each of which can be summarised separately. The biographical material is to be found in chapters 2629, 32, and 3444, and focuses on the events leading up to and surrounding the fall of Jerusalem to the Babylonians in 587; it provides precise dates for the prophet's activities beginning in 609 BCE. The non-biographical prose passages, such as the Temple sermon in chapter 7 and the covenant passage in 11:117, are scattered throughout the book; they show clear affinities with the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomist</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the school of writers and editors who shaped the series of history books from<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Books of Kings</target><part>Kings</part></link>, and while it is unlikely they come directly from Jeremiah, they may well have their roots in traditions about what he said and did.The poetic material found is found largely in chapters 125 and consists of oracles in which the prophet speaks as God's messenger. These passages, dealing with Israel's unfaithfulness to God, the call to repentance, and attacks on the religious and political establishment, are mostly undated and have no clear context, but it is widely accepted that they represent the teachings of Jeremiah and are the earliest stage of the book. Allied to them, and also probably a reflection of the authentic Jeremiah, are further poetic passages of a more personal nature, which have been called Jeremiah's confessions or spiritual diary. In these poems the prophet agonises over the apparent failure of his mission, is consumed by bitterness at those who oppose or ignore him, and accuses God of betraying him.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davidson</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">345-346</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><heading level='3'>Overview</heading><paragraph>Jeremiah exists in two versions, Greek (meaning a Greek translation of a text originally written in Hebrew) and Hebrew, with the Greek representing the earlier version.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">7-8</arg></template><space/>The longer text was apparently developed to replace the shorter; the shorter version ultimately became canonical in Greek Orthodox churches, while the longer was adopted in Judaism and in Western Christian churches.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">7-8</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It is generally agreed that the three types of material interspersed through the book poetic, narrative, and biographical come from different sources or circles.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davidson</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">345</arg></template><space/>Authentic oracles of Jeremiah are probably to be found in the poetic sections of chapters 125, but the book as a whole has been heavily edited and added to by followers (including perhaps the prophet's companion, the scribe Baruch) and later generations of Deuteronomists.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">300</arg></template><space/>The date of the final versions of the book (Greek and Hebrew) can be suggested by the fact that the Greek shows concerns typical of the early Persian period, while the<space/><link><target>Masoretic</target></link><space/>(i.e., Hebrew) shows perspectives which, although known in the Persian period, did not reach their realisation until the 2nd century BCE.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">94</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Texts and manuscripts</heading><paragraph>Jeremiah exists in two versions, a Greek translation, called the Septuagint, dating from the last few centuries before Christ and found in the earliest Christian manuscripts, and the<space/><link><target>Masoretic</target></link><space/>Hebrew text of traditional Jewish bibles the Greek version is shorter than the Hebrew by about one eighth, and arranges the material differently. Equivalents of both versions were found among the<space/><link><target>Dead Sea Scrolls</target></link>, so that is clear that the differences mark important stages in the transmission of the text.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Blenkinsopp</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">130</arg></template><space/>Most scholars hold that the Hebrew text underlying the Septuagint version is older than the Masoretic text, and that the Masoretic evolved either from this or from a closely related version.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Williamson</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">168</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Literary development</heading><paragraph>The Book of Jeremiah grew over a long period of time. The Greek stage, looking forward to the fall of Babylon and aligning in places with Second<space/><link><target>Book of Isaiah</target><part>Isaiah</part></link>, had already seen major redaction (editing) in terms of overall structure, the superscriptions (sentences identifying following passages as the words of God or of Jeremiah), the assignment of historical settings, and arrangement of material, and may have been completed by the late Exilic period (last half of the 6th century BCE); the initial stages of the Masoretic Hebrew version may have been written not long afterwards, although chapter 33:1426 points to a setting in post-exilic times.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Jeremiah and Baruch</heading><paragraph>According to its opening verses the book records the prophetic utterances of the priest<space/><link><target>Jeremiah</target></link><space/>son of Hilkiah, &quot;to whom the word of<space/><link><target>YHWH</target></link><space/>came in the days of king Josiah&quot; and after. Jeremiah lived during a turbulent period, the final years of the kingdom of Judah, from the death of king<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link><space/>(609 BCE) and the loss of independence that followed, through the destruction of Jerusalem by the Babylonians and the exile of much its population (587/586).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">86</arg></template><space/>The book depicts a remarkably introspective prophet, impetuous and often angered by the role into which he has been thrust, alternating efforts to warn the people with pleas to God for mercy, until he is ordered to &quot;pray no more for this people.&quot; He engages in extensive<space/><link><target>performance art</target></link>, walking about in the streets with a yoke about his neck and engaging in other efforts to attract attention. He is taunted and retaliates, is thrown in jail as the result, and at one point is thrown into a pit to die.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Jeremiah and the Deuteronomists</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Deuteronomist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were a school or movement who edited the books of Joshua, Judges, Samuel and Kings into a more or less unified history of Israel (the so-called Deuteronomistic History) during the Jewish exile in Babylon (6th century BCE).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knight</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">65-66</arg></template><space/>It is generally accepted that the Deuteronomists played an important role in the production of the book of Jeremiah; for example, there is clear Deuteronomistic language in chapter 25, in which the prophet looks back over twenty-three years of unheeded prophecy. From the Deuteronomistic perspective the prophetic role implied, more than anything else, concern with law and covenant after the manner of Moses. On this reading Jeremiah was the last of a long line of prophets sent to warn Israel of the consequences of infidelity to God; unlike the Deuteronomists, for whom the call for repentance was always central, Jeremiah seems at some point in his career to have decided that further intercession was pointless, and that Israel's fate was sealed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Blenkinsopp</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">132, 135–136</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Jeremiah as a new Moses</heading><paragraph>The book's superscription claims that Jeremiah was active for forty years, from the thirteenth year of Josiah (627 BCE) to the fall of Jerusalem in 587. It is clear from the last chapters of the book, however, that he continued to speak in Egypt after the assassination of Gedaliah, the Babylonian-appointed governor of Judah, in 582. This suggests that the superscription is trying to make a theological point about Jeremiah by comparing him to<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link><space/>where Moses spent forty years leading Israel from slavery in Egypt to the Promised Land, Jeremiah's forty years saw Israel exiled from the land and Jeremiah himself ultimately in exile in Egypt.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sweeney</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">87-88</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><heading level='3'>Covenant</heading><paragraph><template><target>seealso</target><arg>Covenant (biblical)</arg></template>Much of Jeremiah's prophetic preaching is based on the theme of the covenant between God and Israel (God would protect the people in return for their exclusive worship of him): Jeremiah insists that the covenant is conditional, and can be broken by Israel's apostasy (worship of gods other than<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, the god of Israel). The people, says Jeremiah, are like an unfaithful wife and rebellious children: their infidelity and rebelliousness makes judgement inevitable. Interspersed with this are references to repentance and renewal, although it is unclear whether Jeremiah thought that repentance could ward off judgement or whether it would have to follow judgement. The theme of restoration is strongest in chapter 31:32, which looks to a future in which a new covenant made with Israel and Judah, one which will not be broken.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Biddle</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">1074</arg></template><space/>This is the theme of the &quot;new covenant&quot; passage at chapter 31:3134, drawing on Israel's past relationship with God through the covenant at Sinai to foresee a new future in which Israel will be obedient to God.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davidson</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">347</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The &quot;Confessions&quot; of Jeremiah</heading><paragraph>Scholars have identified several passages in Jeremiah that can be understood as &quot;confessions;&quot; they occur in the first section of the book (chapters 125) and are 11:1812.6, 15:1021, 17:1418, 18:1823, and 20:718. In these passages, Jeremiah expresses his discontent with the message he is to deliver, but also his steadfast commitment to the divine call despite the fact that he had not sought it out. Additionally, in several of these &quot;confessions,&quot; Jeremiah prays that the Lord will take revenge on his persecutors (for example, Jeremiah 12.3).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">303</arg></template><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Jeremiah's &quot;confessions&quot; are a type of individual<space/><link><target>lament</target></link>. Such laments are found elsewhere in the psalms and the<space/><link><target>Book of Job</target></link>. Like Job, Jeremiah curses the day of his birth (Jer. 20:1418 and Job 3:310). Likewise, Jeremiah's exclamation &quot;For I hear the whispering of many: Terror is all around!&quot; (Jer. 20:10) matches Psalm 31:13 exactly. However, Jeremiah's laments are made unique by his insistence that he has been called by Yahweh to deliver his messages.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">303</arg></template><space/>These laments &quot;provide a unique look at the prophet's inner struggle with faith, persecution, and human suffering&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Perdue</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">1021</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Prophetic gestures</heading><paragraph>Prophetic gestures, also known as sign-acts or symbolic actions, was a form of communication in which a message was delivered by performing symbolic actions.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">303</arg></template><space/>Not unique to the book of Jeremiah, these were often bizarre and violated the cultural norms of the time (e.g. Ezekiel 4:48). They served the purposes of both drawing audience and causing that audience to ask questions, giving a prophet the opportunity to explain the meaning of the behavior. The recorder of the events in the written text (i.e. the author of the text) had neither the same audience nor, potentially, the same intent that Jeremiah had in performing these prophetic gestures.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Friebel</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">13</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The following is a list not exhaustive of noteworthy sign-acts found in Jeremiah:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Friebel</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">88-136</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 13:111</bold><space/>The wearing, burial, and retrieval of a linen waistband.</listitem><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 16:19</bold><space/>The shunning of the expected customs of marriage, mourning, and general celebration.</listitem><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 19:113</bold><space/>the acquisition of a clay jug and the breaking of said jug in front of the religious leaders of Jerusalem.</listitem><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 2728</bold><space/>The wearing of an oxen yoke and its subsequent breaking by a false prophet, Hananiah.</listitem><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 32:6-15</bold><space/>The purchase of a field in Anathoth for the price of seventeen silver shekels.</listitem><listitem><bold>Jeremiah 35:119</bold><space/>The offering of wine to the Rechabites, a tribe known for living in tents and refusing to drink wine. This was done in the Temple, which is an important part of the breaking of societal norms.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Later interpretation and influence</heading><heading level='3'>Judaism</heading><paragraph>The influence of Jeremiah during and after the Exile was considerable in some circles, and three additional books, the<space/><link><target>Book of Baruch</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Lamentations</target><part>Lamentations</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Letter of Jeremiah</target></link>, were attributed to him in<space/><link><target>Second Temple Judaism</target></link><space/>(Judaism in the period between the building of the Second Temple in about 515 BCE and its destruction in 70 CE); in the Greek<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link><space/>they stand between Jeremiah and the<space/><link><target>Book of Ezekiel</target></link>, but only Lamentations is included in modern Jewish or Protestant bibles (the Letter of Jeremiah appears in Catholic bibles as the sixth chapter of Baruch).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Redditt</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">132-133</arg></template><space/>Jeremiah is mentioned by name in<space/><link><target>Books of Chronicles</target><part>Chronicles</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Book of Ezra</target></link>, both dating from the later<space/><link><target>Yehud medinata</target><part>Persian period</part></link>, and his prophecy that the<space/><link><target>Babylonian exile</target></link><space/>would last 70 years was taken up and reapplied by the author of the<space/><link><target>Book of Daniel</target></link><space/>in the 2nd century BCE.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Christianity</heading><paragraph>The understanding of the<space/><link><target>early Christians</target></link><space/>that<space/><link><target>Jesus</target></link><space/>represented a &quot;<link><target>new covenant</target></link>&quot; (see 1 Corinthians 11:25 and Hebrews 8:613) is based on Jeremiah 31:3134, in which a future Israel will repent and give God the obedience he demands.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davidson</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">347</arg></template><space/>The Gospel's portrayal of Jesus as a persecuted prophet owes a great deal to the account of Jeremiah's sufferings in chapters 3744, as well as to the &quot;<link><target>Songs of the Suffering Servant</target></link>&quot; in<space/><link><target>Book of Isaiah</target><part>Isaiah</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Blenkinsopp</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">134</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nebo-Sarsekim Tablet</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">20em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Allen
</arg><arg name="first">Leslie C. 
</arg><arg name="title">Jeremiah: A Commentary
</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press
</arg><arg name="year">2008
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">
9780664222239</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Bandstra
</arg><arg name="first">Barry L.
</arg><arg name="title">Reading the Old Testament: an introduction to the Hebrew Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher">Wadsworth
</arg><arg name="year">2004
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780495391050
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Biddle
</arg><arg name="first">Mark E.
</arg><arg name="chapter">Jeremiah
</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Coogan
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Michael D.
</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Brettler
</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Mark Zvi
</arg><arg name="editor3-last">Newsom
</arg><arg name="editor3-first">Carol Ann 
</arg><arg name="title">The New Oxford Annotated Bible with the Apocryphal/Deuterocanonical Books: New Revised Standard Version
</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="year">2007
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">
9780199743919</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Blenkinsopp
</arg><arg name="first">Joseph
</arg><arg name="title">A history of prophecy in Israel
</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press
</arg><arg name="year">1996
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664256395
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brettler
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Marc Zvi
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>How to read the Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Jewish Publication Society
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8276-0775-0
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Brueggemann
</arg><arg name="first">Walter
</arg><arg name="title">Reverberations of faith: a theological handbook of Old Testament themes
</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox
</arg><arg name="year">2002
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664222314
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Coogan
</arg><arg name="first">Michael D.
</arg><arg name="title">A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: The Hebrew Bible in Its Context
</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="year">2009
</arg><arg name="url">
</arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Davidson
</arg><arg name="first">Robert
</arg><arg name="chapter">Jeremiah, Book of
</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Metzger
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Bruce M.
</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Coogan
</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Michael D.
</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford Companion to the Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="year">1993
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">
9780199743919</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Diamond
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>A.R.Pete
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Jeremiah
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Dunn
</arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>James D. G.
</arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Rogerson
</arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>John William
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780802837110
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Friebel
</arg><arg name="first">Kelvin G. 
</arg><arg name="title">Jeremiah's and Ezekiel's Sign-Acts: Rhetorical Nonverbal Communication
</arg><arg name="publisher">Continuum
</arg><arg name="year">1999
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">
9781850759195</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight
</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A
</arg><arg name="chapter">Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists
</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Mays 
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">James Luther
</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Petersen
</arg><arg name="editor2-first">David L.
</arg><arg name="editor3-last">Richards
</arg><arg name="editor3-first">Harold 
</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation
</arg><arg name="publisher">T&T Clark
</arg><arg name="year">1995
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg><arg name="isbn">9780567292896
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">Kugler
</arg><arg name="first1">Robert
</arg><arg name="last2">Hartin
</arg><arg name="first2">Patrick
</arg><arg name="title">The Old Testament between theology and history: a critical survey
</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans
</arg><arg name="year">2009
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802846365
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Perdue
</arg><arg name="first">Leo G.
</arg><arg name="chapter">Jeremiah
</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Attridge 
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Harold W.
</arg><arg name="title">HarperCollins Study Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher">HarperCollins
</arg><arg name="year">2006
</arg><arg name="url">
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Redditt
</arg><arg name="first">Paul L.
</arg><arg name="title">Introduction to the Prophets
</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans
</arg><arg name="year">2008
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802828965
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Sweeney
</arg><arg name="first">Marvin A.
</arg><arg name="title">The Prophetic Literature
</arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon Press
</arg><arg name="year">2010
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Sweeney
</arg><arg name="first">Marvin A.
</arg><arg name="chapter">The Latter Prophets
</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Steven L. McKenzie, Matt Patrick Graham
</arg><arg name="title">The Hebrew Bible today: an introduction to critical issues
</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press
</arg><arg name="year">1998
</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664256524
</arg><arg name="ref">harvref
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Williamson
</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>H.G.M.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Do We Need A New Bible? Reflections on the Proposed Oxford Hebrew Bible
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Biblia
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>90
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>168
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>BSW
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bsw.org/Biblica/Vol-90-2009/Do-We-Need-A-New-Bible-Reflections-On-The-Proposed-Oxford-Hebrew-Bible/13/article-p168.html
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Book of Jeremiah</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Original Hebrew text:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt1101.htm'><space/>''Yirmiyahu'' Jeremiah</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link>)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Translations into English<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Judaism</target><part>Jewish</part></link><space/>translations:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et1101.htm'>Jeremiah at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society translation)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15756'>Yirmiyahu Jeremiah (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Christian</target></link><space/>translations:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Jeremiah+1'>''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20061011002610/http://www.anova.org/sev/htm/hb/24_jeremiah.htm'>Jeremiah at The Great Books</link><space/>(New Revised Standard Version) (via archive.org)</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Commentary<list type='bullet'><listitem>Jewish Commentary<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15756'>Jeremiah (Judaica Press)</link><space/>[with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><link><target>Abraham Joshua Heschel</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Prophets</italics>. HarperCollins Paperback, 1975. ISBN 0-06-131421-8</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>(Jewish Encyclopedia)<space/><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=225&amp;amp;letter=J&amp;amp;search=Jeremiah'>Book of Jeremiah article</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Farrell Till]]
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.infidels.org/library/magazines/tsr/1990/4/4jerem90.html
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Jeremiah Dilemma
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The Skeptical Review
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990
</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Major prophet]]s</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Ezekiel|Ezekiel]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Lamentations|Lamentations]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Jeremiah, Book Of</target></template><link><target>Category:Nevi'im</target></link><link><target>Category:Year of work unknown</target></link><link><target>Category:Septuagint</target></link><link><target>Category:Jeremiah</target></link><link><target>Category:Book of Jeremiah</target></link></paragraph></article>