<article title='Ecclesiastes'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Ketuvim<space/></arg><arg>WP</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Ecclesiastes</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ɨ</arg><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>z</arg><arg>i</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>z</arg></template>;<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link>: ,<space/><italics>Ekklesiastes</italics>,<space/><template><target>lang-he-n</target><arg>קֹהֶלֶת</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Qoheleth</italics>,<space/><italics>Koheleth</italics>) is one of 24 books of the<space/><link><target>Tanakh</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link>, where it is classified as one of the<space/><italics><link><target>Ketuvim</target></link></italics><space/>(or &quot;Writings&quot;). It is among the canonical<space/><link><target>Sapiential books</target><part>Wisdom Books</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link><space/>of most<space/><link><target>Christian denominations</target><part>denominations of Christianity</part></link>. The title<space/><italics>Ecclesiastes</italics><space/>is a Latin<space/><link><target>transliteration</target></link><space/>of the Greek translation of the Hebrew<space/><bold>Koheleth</bold><space/>(meaning &quot;Gatherer&quot;, but traditionally translated as &quot;Teacher&quot; or &quot;Preacher&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Seow</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">944</arg></template>), the<space/><link><target>pseudonym</target></link><space/>used by the author of the book.</paragraph><paragraph>The book is an anonymous<space/><link><target>treatise</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The New American Bible</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="pages">649</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>critical study belives it was composed in the last part of the 3rd century BC.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Rudman</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">13</arg></template><space/>The author &quot;Koheleth&quot; uses a literary device to introduce himself as &quot;son of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, king in<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link>&quot; (i.e.,<space/><link><target>Solomon</target></link>), which dates the book itself to the 10th century BC. It proceeds to discuss the<space/><link><target>meaning of life</target></link><space/>and the best way of life. He proclaims all the actions of man to be inherently<space/><italics>hevel</italics>, meaning &quot;vain&quot;, &quot;futile&quot;, &quot;empty&quot;, &quot;meaningless&quot;, &quot;temporary&quot;, &quot;transitory&quot;, &quot;fleeting&quot;, or &quot;mere breath,&quot; as the lives of both wise and foolish people end in death. While Koheleth clearly endorses wisdom as a means for a well-lived earthly life, he does not ascribe eternal meaning to it. In light of this senselessness, one should enjoy the simple pleasures of daily life, such as eating, drinking, and taking enjoyment in one's work, which are gifts from the hand of God. The book concludes with the injunction: &quot;Fear God, and keep his commandments; for that is the whole duty of everyone&quot; (12:13).</paragraph><paragraph>Ecclesiastes has had a deep influence on Western literature. It contains several phrases that have resonated in British and American culture, such as &quot;nothing new under the sun,&quot; &quot;a time to be born and a time to die,&quot; and &quot;vanity of vanities; all is vanity.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hirsch</arg><arg name="first">E.D.</arg><arg name="title">The New Dictionary of Cultural Literacy</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</arg><arg name="pages">8</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>American novelist<space/><link><target>Thomas Wolfe</target></link><space/>wrote: &quot;[O]f all I have ever seen or learned, that book seems to me the noblest, the wisest, and the most powerful expression of man's life upon this earthand also the highest flower of poetry, eloquence, and truth. I am not given to dogmatic judgments in the matter of literary creation, but if I had to make one I could say that Ecclesiastes is the greatest single piece of writing I have ever known, and the wisdom expressed in it the most lasting and profound.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Christianson</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template><space/>The book is even popular among<space/><link><target>atheists</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph>Ecclesiastes is a treatise<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The New American Bible</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="pages">649</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>presented as an autobiography of &quot;Koheleth.&quot; Koheleth's story is framed by voice of the narrator, who refers to Koheleth in the third person, praises his wisdom, but reminds the reader that wisdom has its limitations and is not man's main concern. Koheleth reports what he planned, did, experienced and thought. His journey to knowledge is, in the end, incomplete. The reader is not only to hear Koheleth's wisdom, but to observe his journey towards understanding and acceptance of life's frustrations and uncertainties: the journey itself is important.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">xiii</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Few of the many attempts to uncover an underlying structure to Ecclesiastes have met with widespread acceptance; among them, the following is one of the more influential:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">xvi</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Title (1:1)</listitem><listitem>Initial poem (1:211)</listitem><listitem>I: Koheleth's investigation of life (1:126:9)</listitem><listitem>II: Koheleth's conclusions (6:1011:6)<list type='bullet'><listitem>Introduction (6:1012)</listitem><listitem>A: Man cannot discover what is good for him to do (7:18:17)</listitem><listitem>B: Man does not know what will come after him (9:111:6)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Concluding poem (11:712:8)</listitem><listitem>Epilogue (12:914)</listitem></list><paragraph>(The outline begins at verse 1:2 because verse 1:1 is a superscription, the ancient equivalent of a title page: it introduces the book as &quot;the words of Koheleth, son of David, king in Jerusalem.&quot;)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Longman</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">57–59</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Most, though not all, modern commentators regard the epilogue (12:914) as an addition by a later scribe. Some have identified certain other statements as further additions intended to make the book more religiously orthodox (e.g., the affirmations of God's justice and the need for piety).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">xvii</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Summary</heading><paragraph>The ten-verse introduction in verses 1:211 are the words of the frame narrator; they set the mood for what is to follow: Koheleth's message is that all is meaningless.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Longman</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">57–59</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>After the introduction come the words of Koheleth. As king he has experienced everything and done everything, but nothing is ultimately reliable. Death levels all. The only good is to partake of life in the present, for enjoyment is from the hand of God. Everything is ordered in time and people are subject to time in contrast to God's eternal character. The world is filled with injustice, which only God will adjudicate. God and humans do not belong in the same realm and it is therefore necessary to have a right attitude before God. People should enjoy, but should not be greedy; no-one knows what is good for humanity; righteousness and wisdom escape us. Koheleth reflects on the limits of human power: all people face death, and death is better than life, but we should enjoy life when we can. The world is full of risk: he gives advice on living with risk, both political and economic. Mortals should take pleasure when they can, for a time may come when no one can. Koheleth's words finish with imagery of nature languishing and humanity marching to the grave.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Seow</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">946–957</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The frame narrator returns with an epilogue: the words of the wise are hard, but they are applied as the shepherd applies goads and pricks to his flock. The original ending of the book was probably the words: &quot;The end of the matter&quot; (12:13:) but the text we have continues: &quot;Fear God&quot; (a phrase used often in Koheleth's speech) &quot;and keep his commandments&quot; (which he never uses), &quot;for God will bring every deed to judgement.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Seow</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">957–958</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><heading level='3'>Title, date and author</heading><paragraph>The book takes its name from the Greek<space/><italics>ekklesiastes</italics>, a translation of the title by which the central figure refers to himself:<space/><italics>Koheleth</italics>, meaning something like &quot;one who convenes or addresses an assembly&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gilbert</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">124–125</arg></template><space/>According to rabbinic tradition, Ecclesiastes was written by<space/><link><target>Solomon</target></link><space/>in his old age.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template><space/>(An alternative tradition that &quot;<link><target>Hezekiah</target></link><space/>and his colleagues wrote<space/><link><target>Isaiah</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Proverbs</target><part>Proverbs</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Song of Songs</target></link><space/>and Ecclesiastes&quot; probably means simply that the book was edited under Hezekiah.)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">692</arg></template><space/>Nevertheless, critical scholars have long rejected the idea of a pre-exilic origin.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">x</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">50–52</arg></template><space/>The presence of Persian loan-words and Aramaisms points to a date no earlier than about 450 BCE,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Seow</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">944</arg></template><space/>while the latest possible date for its composition is 180 BCE, when another Jewish writer,<space/><link><target>Ben Sira</target></link>, quotes from it.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">xiv</arg></template><space/>The dispute as to whether Ecclesiastes belongs to the Persian or the Hellenistic periods (i.e., the earlier or later part of this period) revolves around the degree of Hellenization (influence of Greek culture and thought) present in the book. Scholars arguing for a Persian date (c. 450330 BCE) hold that there is a complete lack of Greek influence;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Seow</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">944</arg></template><space/>those who argue for a Hellenistic date (c. 330180 BCE) argue that it shows internal evidence of Greek thought and social setting.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">54–55</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Also unresolved is whether the author and narrator of Koheleth are one and the same person. Some scholars have argued that the third-person narrative structure is an artificial literary device along the lines of<space/><link><target>Uncle Remus</target></link>, although the description of the Teacher in 12:814 seems to favour a historical person whose thoughts are presented by the narrator.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">48</arg></template><space/>The question, however, has no theological importance,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">48</arg></template><space/>and one scholar (Roland Murphy) has commented that Koheleth himself would have regarded the time and ingenuity put into interpreting his book as &quot;one more example of the futility of human effort&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ingram</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">45</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Genre and setting</heading><paragraph>Ecclesiastes has taken its literary form from the Middle Eastern tradition of the fictional autobiography, in which a character, often a king, relates his experiences and draws lessons from them, often self-critical: Koheleth likewise identifies himself as a king, speaks of his search for wisdom, relates his conclusions, and recognises his limitations.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">xiii</arg></template><space/>It belongs to the category of<space/><link><target>wisdom literature</target></link>, the body of biblical writings which give advice on life, together with reflections on its problems and meaningsother examples include the<space/><link><target>Book of Job</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Proverbs</target><part>Proverbs</part></link>, and some of the<space/><link><target>Book of Psalms</target><part>Psalms</part></link>. Ecclesiastes differs from the other biblical Wisdom books in being deeply skeptical of the usefulness of Wisdom itself.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brettler</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">721</arg></template><space/>Ecclesiastes in turn influenced the<space/><link><target>deuterocanonical</target></link><space/>works,<space/><link><target>Wisdom of Solomon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sirach</target></link>, both of which contain vocal rejections of the Ecclesiastical philosophy of futility.</paragraph><paragraph>Wisdom was a popular genre in the ancient world, where it was cultivated in scribal circles and directed towards young men who would take up careers in high officialdom and royal courts; there is strong evidence that some of these books, or at least sayings and teachings, were translated into Hebrew and influenced the Book of Proverbs, and the author of Ecclesiastes was probably familiar with examples from Egypt and Mesopotamia.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">x–xi</arg></template><space/>He may also have been influenced by Greek philosophy, specifically the schools of<space/><link><target>Stoicism</target></link>, which held that all things are fated, and<space/><link><target>Epicureanism</target></link>, which held that happiness was best pursued through the quiet cultivation of life's simpler pleasures.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gilbert</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">125</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canonicity</heading><paragraph>The presence of Ecclesiastes in the Bible is something of a puzzle, as the common themes of the Hebrew canona God who reveals and redeems, who elects and cares for a chosen peopleare absent from it, which gives it tone that Koheleth had lost his faith in his old age. The problem to understand the book has been there from the earliest recorded discussions (the hypothetical<space/><link><target>Council of Jamnia</target></link><space/>in the 1st century CE). One argument advanced then was that the name of Solomon carried enough authority to ensure its inclusion, but other works which appeared with Solomon's name were excluded despite being more orthodox than Ecclesiastes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Diderot</arg><arg name="first1">Denis</arg><arg name="title">Canon</arg><arg name="date">1752</arg><arg name="pages">601–604</arg><arg name="url">http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.did2222.0000.566</arg></template></extension><space/>Another was that the words of the epilogue, in which the reader is told to fear God and keep his commands, made it orthodox; but all later attempts to find anything in the rest of the book which would reflect this orthodoxy have failed. A modern suggestion has been to treat the book as a dialogue in which different statements belong to different voices, with Koheleth himself answering and refuting unorthodox opinions, but there are no explicit markers for this in the book, as there are, for example in the<space/><link><target>Book of Job</target></link>. Yet another suggestion is that Ecclesiastes is simply the most extreme example of a tradition of skepticism, but none of the proposed examples match Ecclesiastes for a sustained denial of faith and doubt in the goodness of God. &quot;In short, we do not know why or how this book found its way into such esteemed company&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shields</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">1-5</arg></template><space/>And fundamental point of view sees it as book from the perspective of the person who lost his faith.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>Scholars disagree about the themes of Ecclesiastes. Is it positive and life-affirming or deeply pessimistic?<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template><space/>Is Koheleth coherent or incoherent, insightful or confused, orthodox or heterodox? Is the ultimate message of the book to copy Koheleth, the wise man, or to avoid his errors?<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Enns</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">21</arg></template><space/>Some passages of Ecclesiastes seem to contradict other portions of the Old Testament, and even itself.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bartholomew</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template><space/>One suggestion for resolving the contradictions is to read the book as the record of Koheleth's quest for knowledge: opposing judgments (e.g., &quot;the dead are better off than the living&quot; (4:2) vs. &quot;a living dog is better off than a dead lion&quot; (9:4)) are therefore provisional, and it is only at the conclusion that the verdict is delivered (1112:7). On this reading, Koheleth's sayings are goads, designed to provoke dialogue and reflection in his readers, rather than to reach premature and self-assured conclusions.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">17-18</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The subject of Ecclesiastes is the pain and frustration engendered by observing and meditating on the distortions and inequities pervading the world, the uselessness of human deeds, the limitations of wisdom and righteousness and the phrase &quot;under the sun&quot; appears thirty times in connection with these observations; all this coexists with a firm belief in God, whose power, justice and unpredictability are sovereign.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fox</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">ix</arg></template><space/>History and nature move in cycles, so that all events are predetermined and unchangeable, and life has no meaning or purpose: the wise man and the man who does not study wisdom will both die and be forgotten: man should be reverent (&quot;Fear God&quot;), but in this life it is best to simply enjoy God's gifts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gilbert</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">125</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Traditional Judaism</heading><paragraph>In traditional Judaism, Ecclesiastes is read either on<space/><link><target>Shemini Atzeret</target></link><space/>(by Yemenites, Italians, some<space/><link><target>Sepharadim</target></link>, and the mediaeval French Jewish rite) or on the<space/><link><target>Shabbat</target></link><space/>of the Intermediate Days of<space/><link><target>Sukkot</target></link><space/>(by<space/><link><target>Ashkenazim</target></link>). If there is no Intermediate Sabbath of<space/><link><target>Sukkot</target></link>, even the Ashkenazim read it on<space/><link><target>Shemini Atzeret</target></link><space/>(or, for Ashkenazim in the Land of Israel, on the first<space/><link><target>Shabbat</target></link><space/>of Sukkot). It is read on Sukkot as a reminder to not get too caught up in the festivities of the holiday, as well as to carry over the happiness of Sukkot to the rest of the year by telling the listeners that, without God, life is meaningless. When the listeners take this to heart, then true happiness can be achieved throughout the year.</paragraph><paragraph>The final poem of Koheleth (<template><target>Bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Ecclesiastes</arg><arg>12:1–8</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>) has been interpreted in the<space/><link><target>Targum</target></link>, Talmud and<space/><link><target>Midrash</target></link>, and by the rabbis<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rashbam</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Abraham ibn Ezra</target><part>ibn Ezra</part></link>, as an allegory of old age.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Catholicism</heading><paragraph>Like most of the Bible, Ecclesiastes has been cited in the writings of past and current<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target><part>Catholic Church</part></link><space/>leaders. For example,<space/><link><target>doctors of the Church</target></link><space/>have cited Ecclesiastes.<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target><part>St. Augustine of Hippo</part></link><space/>cited Ecclesiastes in Book XX of<space/><italics><link><target>City of God (book)</target><part>City of God</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Augustine,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/120120.htm'>The City of God, Book XX</link>. Accessed 2015-06-28.</extension><space/><link><target>St. Jerome</target></link><space/>wrote a commentary on Ecclesiastes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jerome,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.paulistpress.com/Products/0601-1/66-st-jerome-commentary-on-ecclesiastes.aspx'>Commentary on Ecclesiastes</link>. Accessed 2015-09-09.</extension><space/><link><target>St. Thomas Aquinas</target></link><space/>cited Ecclesiastes (&quot;The number of fools is infinite.&quot;) in his<space/><italics><link><target>Summa Theologica</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas Aquinas,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/chr/aquinas/summa/sum071.htm#FP_Q63_A9-p3.1'>Summa Theologica</link>. Accessed 2015-09-09.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The book continues to be cited by recent<space/><link><target>pope</target><trail>s</trail></link>, including<space/><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pope Francis</target></link>. Pope John Paul II, in his general audience of October 20, 2004, called the author of Ecclesiastes &quot;an ancient biblical sage&quot; whose description of death &quot;makes frantic clinging to earthly things completely pointless.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Manhardt</arg><arg name="first">Laurie</arg><arg name="title">Come and See: Wisdom of the Bible</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Emmaus Road Publishing</arg><arg name="pages">115</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>Pope Francis cited Ecclesiastes on his address on September 9, 2014. Speaking of vain people, he said, &quot;How many Christians live for appearances? Their life seems like a<space/><link><target>soap bubble</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Pope Francis,<space/><link type='external' href='http://en.radiovaticana.va/news/2014/09/25/pope_francis_vain_christians_are_like_soap_bubbles/1107284'></link>. Accessed 2015-09-09.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Atheism</heading><paragraph><link><target>Atheists</target></link><space/>often name Ecclesiastes as their favorite book of the Bible.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.alternet.org/belief/bible-verses-atheists-love<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bible Verses That Atheists Love<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Tarico<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Valerie<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 6, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="website">AlterNet<space/></arg><arg name="access-date">4 September 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>antitheist</target></link><space/>author<space/><link><target>Christopher Hitchens</target></link>, who considered<space/><link><target>George Orwell</target></link><space/>an atheist, wrote approvingly of Orwell's use of Ecclesiastes at his funeral.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2011/05/hitchens-201105?currentPage</arg><arg name="title">When the King Saved God<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Hitchens<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2011<space/></arg><arg name="website">Vanity Fair<space/></arg><arg name="access-date">4 September 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>The atheist biologist<space/><link><target>Richard Dawkins</target></link><space/>called the King James Bible translation of Ecclesiastes &quot;one of the glories of English literature.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.theguardian.com/science/2012/may/19/richard-dawkins-king-james-bible<space/></arg><arg name="title">Why I want all our children to read the King James Bible<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Dawkins<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2012<space/></arg><arg name="website">The Guardian<space/></arg><arg name="access-date">4 September 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Other atheists that have voiced support for Ecclesiastes include<space/><link><target>Greta Christina</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hemant Mehta</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dale McGowan</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Pippa Evans</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.alternet.org/belief/bible-verses-atheists-love<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bible Verses That Atheists Love<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Tarico<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Valerie<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 6, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="website">AlterNet<space/></arg><arg name="access-date">4 September 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bible</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tanakh</target></link></listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Turn! Turn! Turn!</target></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>Pete Seeger</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vanitas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wisdom of Sirach</target></link>, also known as &quot;Ecclesiasticus&quot;</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>A Rose for Ecclesiastes</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Roger Zelazny</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Q (novel)</target><part>Q</part></link></italics>, novel by<space/><link><target>Luther Blissett (nom de plume)</target><part>Luther Blissett</part></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Vier ernste Gesnge</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Johannes Brahms</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">15em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bartholomew
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Craig
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Baker Academic Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.de/books?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780801026911
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brettler
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark Zvi
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Poetical and Wisdom Books
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Coogan
</arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Michael D.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The New Oxford Annotated Bible (3rd ed.)
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780195288803
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brown
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>William P.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes: Interpretation: A Bible Commentary for Teaching and Preaching
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Westminster John Knox Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780664238247
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Christianson
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eric S.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes Through the Centuries
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Wiley-Blackwell]]
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.de/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780631225294
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Coogan
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael D.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Old Testament: A Very Short Introduction
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780199719464
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Diderot
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Denis
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1752
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Canon
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://hdl.handle.net/2027/spo.did2222.0000.566
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Eaton
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IVP Academic
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://isbndb.com/d/book/ecclesiastes_an_introduction_and_commentary.html
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Enns
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780802866493
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fredricks
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.C.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ecclesiastes and Song of Songs
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IVP Academic
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ivpress.com/cgi-ivpress/book.pl/code</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fox
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael V.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The JPS Bible Commentary: Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Jewish Publication Society
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780827609655
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gilbert
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Christopher
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Complete Introduction to the Bible: A Literary and Historical Introduction to the Bible
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Paulist Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780809145522
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ingram
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Doug
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ambiguity in Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Continuum
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Longman
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tremper
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Tremper Longman
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Book of Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.de/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780802823663
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Rudman
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dominic
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Determinism in the Book of Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sheffield Academic Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780567215635
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Seow
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>C.L.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Coogan
</arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Michael D.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The New Oxford Annotated Bible (3rd ed.)
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780195288803
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shields
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Martin A.
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The End of Wisdom: A Reappraisal of the Historical and Canonical Function of Ecclesiastes
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Eisenbrauns]]
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.de/?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781575061023
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smith
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Wisdom Literature and Psalms
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>College Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.amazon.com/Wisdom-Literature-Psalms-Testament-Survey/dp/0899004393
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780899004396
</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ranston, Harry (1925).<space/><italics>Ecclesiastes and the Early Greek Wisdom Literature</italics>. First ed. Epworth Press.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Ecclesiastes (Bible)</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Book of Ecclesiastes</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15779'>Kohelet Ecclesiastes (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bible.oremus.org/?passage=Ecclesiastes'>Ecclesiastes: New Revised Standard Version</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.drbo.org/chapter/23001.htm'>Ecclesiastes: Douay Rheims Bible Version</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>s:Bible, King James, Ecclesiastes</target><part>''Ecclesiastes'' at Wikisource</part></link><space/>(Authorised King James Version)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/#ecclesiastes'>''Ecclesiastes'' at United States Conference of Catholic Bishops</link><space/>(New American Bible)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?book_id=25&amp;amp;chapter=1&amp;amp;version=50'>''Ecclesiastes'' at Bible Gateway</link><space/>(New King James Version)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/stg40003.htm'>''A Metaphrase of the Book Of Ecclesiastes''</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Gregory Thaumaturgus</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Wisdom literature]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Lamentations|Lamentations]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Esther|Esther]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Proverbs|Proverbs]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Song of Songs]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template><template><target>Sukkot</target></template><template><target>Solomon</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Ecclesiastes</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Solomon</target></link><link><target>Category:Sukkot</target></link><link><target>Category:Ketuvim</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Middle Eastern wisdom literature</target></link></paragraph></article>