<article title='Code_division_multiple_access'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>a channel access method</arg><arg>the mobile phone technology referred to as CDMA</arg><arg>IS-95</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>CDMA2000</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Multiplex_techniques</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Code division multiple access</bold><space/>(<bold>CDMA</bold>) is a<space/><link><target>channel access method</target></link><space/>used by various<space/><link><target>radio</target></link><space/>communication technologies.</paragraph><paragraph>CDMA is an example of<space/><link><target>multiple access</target></link>, where several transmitters can send information simultaneously over a single communication channel. This allows several users to share a band of frequencies (see<space/><link><target>bandwidth (signal processing)</target><part>bandwidth</part></link>). To permit this without undue interference between the users, CDMA employs<space/><link><target>spread-spectrum</target></link><space/>technology and a special coding scheme (where each transmitter is assigned a code).</paragraph><paragraph>CDMA is used as the access method in many<space/><link><target>List of mobile phone standards</target><part>mobile phone standards</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>IS-95</target><part>cdmaOne</part></link>,<space/><link><target>CDMA2000</target></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>3G</target></link><space/>evolution of cdmaOne), and<space/><link><target>WCDMA</target></link><space/>(the 3G standard used by<space/><link><target>GSM</target></link><space/>carriers), which are often referred to as simply<space/><italics>CDMA</italics>.<link><target>File:CDMA_Cell_antenna.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>CDMA Cell tower antenna cable</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The technology of code division multiple access channels has long been known. In the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>(USSR), the first work devoted to this subject was published in 1935 by professor<space/><link><target>:ru:,</target><part>Dmitriy V. Ageev</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Ageev</arg><arg name="first">D. V.</arg><arg name="title">Bases of the Theory of Linear Selection. Code Demultiplexing</arg><arg name="journal">Proceedings of the Leningrad Experimental Institute of Communication</arg><arg name="year">1935</arg><arg name="pages">3–35</arg></template></extension><space/>It was shown that through the use of linear methods, there are three types of signal separation: frequency, time and compensatory. The technology of CDMA was used in 1957, when the young military radio engineer<space/><link><target>Leonid Kupriyanovich</target></link><space/>in Moscow, made an experimental model of a wearable automatic mobile phone, called LK-1 by him, with a base station. LK-1 has a weight of 3&amp;nbsp;kg, 2030&amp;nbsp;km operating distance, and 2030 hours of battery life.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Nauka i Zhizn</target></link></italics><space/>8, 1957, p. 49</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Yuniy technik</italics><space/>7, 1957, p. 4344</extension><space/>The base station, as described by the author, could serve several customers. In 1958, Kupriyanovich made the new experimental &quot;pocket&quot; model of mobile phone. This phone weighed 0.5&amp;nbsp;kg. To serve more customers, Kupriyanovich proposed the device, named by him as correllator.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Nauka i Zhizn</italics><space/>10, 1958, p. 66</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Tekhnika Molodezhi</target></link></italics><space/>2, 1959, p. 1819</extension><space/>In 1958, the USSR also started the development of the &quot;<link><target>Altai (mobile telephone system)</target><part>Altai</part></link>&quot; national civil mobile phone service for cars, based on the Soviet MRT-1327 standard. The phone system weighed<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>11</arg><arg>kg</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. It was placed in the trunk of the vehicles of high-ranking officials and used a standard handset in the passenger compartment. The main developers of the Altai system were VNIIS (Voronezh Science Research Institute of Communications) and GSPI (State Specialized Project Institute). In 1963 this service started in Moscow and in 1970 Altai service was used in 30 USSR cities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://englishrussia.com/2006/09/18/first-russian-mobile-phone/</arg><arg name="title">First Russian Mobile Phone</arg><arg name="date">September 18, 2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Uses</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Au CDMA 1X WIN W31SAII gravelly silver expansion.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A CDMA2000<space/><link><target>mobile phone</target></link></part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>One of the early applications for code division multiplexing is in the<space/><link><target>Global Positioning System</target></link><space/>(GPS). This predates and is distinct from its use in<space/><link><target>mobile phone</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Qualcomm</target></link><space/>standard<space/><link><target>IS-95</target></link>, marketed as cdmaOne.</listitem><listitem>The Qualcomm standard<space/><link><target>IS-2000</target></link>, known as CDMA2000, is used by several mobile phone companies, including the<space/><link><target>Globalstar</target></link><space/><link><target>satellite phone</target></link><space/>network.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>UMTS</target></link><space/>3G mobile phone standard, which uses<space/><link><target>W-CDMA</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>CDMA has been used in the<space/><bold>OmniTRACS</bold><space/>satellite system for transportation<space/><link><target>logistics</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Steps in CDMA modulation</heading><paragraph>CDMA is a spread-spectrum multiple access<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Valeri
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Ipatov
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Spread Spectrum and CDMA
<space/></arg><arg name="edition">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Wiley & Sons, Ltd
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg></template></extension><space/>technique. A spread spectrum technique spreads the bandwidth of the data uniformly for the same transmitted power. A spreading code is a pseudo-random code that has a narrow<space/><link><target>ambiguity function</target></link>, unlike other narrow pulse codes. In CDMA a locally generated code runs at a much higher rate than the data to be transmitted. Data for transmission is combined via bitwise<space/><link><target>XOR#Bitwise operation</target><part>XOR</part></link><space/>(exclusive OR) with the faster code. The figure shows how a spread spectrum signal is generated. The data signal with pulse duration of<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_{b}</extension><space/>(symbol period) is XORed with the code signal with pulse duration of<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_{c}</extension><space/>(chip period). (Note:<space/><link><target>Bandwidth (signal processing)</target><part>bandwidth</part></link><space/>is proportional to<space/><extension extension_name='math'>1/T</extension>, where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T</extension><space/>= bit time.) Therefore, the bandwidth of the data signal is<space/><extension extension_name='math'>1/T_{b}</extension><space/>and the bandwidth of the spread spectrum signal is<space/><extension extension_name='math'>1/T_{c}</extension>. Since<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_{c}</extension><space/>is much smaller than<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_{b}</extension>, the bandwidth of the spread spectrum signal is much larger than the bandwidth of the original signal. The ratio<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_{b}/T_{c}</extension><space/>is called the spreading factor or processing gain and determines to a certain extent the upper limit of the total number of users supported simultaneously by a base station.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Vern A.
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Dubendorf
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Wireless Data Technologies
<space/></arg><arg name="edition">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Wiley & Sons, Ltd
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Generation of CDMA.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>500px</part><part>center</part><part>Generation of a CDMA signal</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Each user in a CDMA system uses a different code to modulate their signal. Choosing the codes used to modulate the signal is very important in the performance of CDMA systems. The best performance will occur when there is good separation between the signal of a desired user and the signals of other users. The separation of the signals is made by<space/><link><target>Cross-correlation</target><part>correlating</part></link><space/>the received signal with the locally generated code of the desired user. If the signal matches the desired user's code then the correlation function will be high and the system can extract that signal. If the desired user's code has nothing in common with the signal the correlation should be as close to zero as possible (thus eliminating the signal); this is referred to as<space/><link><target>cross-correlation</target></link>. If the code is correlated with the signal at any time offset other than zero, the correlation should be as close to zero as possible. This is referred to as auto-correlation and is used to reject multi-path interference.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">
<space/></arg><arg name="first">
<space/></arg><arg name="title">CDMA Spectrum
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">
<space/></arg><arg name="year">
<space/></arg><arg name="work">
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.activexperts.com/asmssrvr/cellular/cdmaspectrum/
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-29
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An analogy to the problem of multiple access is a room (channel) in which people wish to talk to each other simultaneously. To avoid confusion, people could take turns speaking (time division), speak at different pitches (frequency division), or speak in different languages (code division). CDMA is analogous to the last example where people speaking the same language can understand each other, but other languages are perceived as<space/><link><target>noise</target></link><space/>and rejected. Similarly, in radio CDMA, each group of users is given a shared code. Many codes occupy the same channel, but only users associated with a particular code can communicate.</paragraph><paragraph>In general, CDMA belongs to two basic categories: synchronous (orthogonal codes) and asynchronous (pseudorandom codes).</paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>SYNC-CDMA</arg></template>Code division multiplexing (synchronous CDMA)</heading><paragraph>The digital modulation method is analogous to those used in simple radio transceivers. In the analog case, a low frequency data signal is time multiplied with a high frequency pure sine wave carrier, and transmitted. This is effectively a frequency convolution (Weiner-Kinchin Theorem) of the two signals, resulting in a carrier with narrow sidebands. In the digital case, the sinusoidal carrier is replaced by<space/><link><target>Walsh function</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These are binary square waves that form a complete orthonormal set. The data signal is also binary and the time multiplication is achieved with a simple XOR function. This is usually a<space/><link><target>Gilbert cell</target></link><space/>mixer in the circuitry.</paragraph><paragraph>Synchronous CDMA exploits mathematical properties of<space/><link><target>orthogonality</target></link><space/>between<space/><link><target>coordinate vector</target><part>vectors</part></link><space/>representing the data strings. For example, binary string<space/><italics>1011</italics><space/>is represented by the vector (1, 0, 1, 1). Vectors can be multiplied by taking their<space/><link><target>dot product</target></link>, by summing the products of their respective components (for example, if u = (a, b) and v = (c, d), then their dot product uv = ac + bd). If the dot product is zero, the two vectors are said to be<space/><italics>orthogonal</italics><space/>to each other. Some properties of the dot product aid understanding of how<space/><link><target>W-CDMA</target></link><space/>works. If vectors<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>b</italics><space/>are orthogonal, then<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\scriptstyle\mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{b} \,=\, 0</extension><space/>and:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>
\mathbf{a}\cdot(\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{b}) = \|\mathbf{a}\|^2 \quad\mathrm{since}\quad \mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{b} = \|\mathbf{a}\|^2+0 
</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>
\mathbf{a}\cdot(-\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{b}) = -\|\mathbf{a}\|^2 \quad\mathrm{since}\quad -\mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{b} = -\|\mathbf{a}\|^2+0 
</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>
\mathbf{b}\cdot(\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{b}) = \|\mathbf{b}\|^2 \quad\mathrm{since}\quad \mathbf{b}\cdot\mathbf{a}+\mathbf{b}\cdot\mathbf{b} = 0+\|\mathbf{b}\|^2 
</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>
\mathbf{b}\cdot(\mathbf{a}-\mathbf{b}) = -\|\mathbf{b}\|^2 \quad\mathrm{since}\quad \mathbf{b}\cdot\mathbf{a}-\mathbf{b}\cdot\mathbf{b} = 0-\|\mathbf{b}\|^2
</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Each user in synchronous CDMA uses a code orthogonal to the others' codes to modulate their signal. An example of four mutually orthogonal digital signals is shown in the figure. Orthogonal codes have a cross-correlation equal to zero; in other words, they do not interfere with each other. In the case of IS-95 64 bit<space/><link><target>Walsh code</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are used to encode the signal to separate different users. Since each of the 64 Walsh codes are orthogonal to one another, the signals are channelized into 64 orthogonal signals. The following example demonstrates how each user's signal can be encoded and decoded.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Example</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cdma orthogonal signals.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>An example of four mutually orthogonal digital signals.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Start with a set of vectors that are mutually<space/><link><target>orthogonality</target><part>orthogonal</part></link>. (Although mutual orthogonality is the only condition, these vectors are usually constructed for ease of decoding, for example columns or rows from<space/><link><target>Walsh matrix</target><part>Walsh matrices</part></link>.) An example of orthogonal functions is shown in the picture on the right. These vectors will be assigned to individual users and are called the<space/><italics>code</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>chip (CDMA)</target><part>chip</part></link><space/>code</italics>, or<space/><italics>chipping code</italics>. In the interest of brevity, the rest of this example uses codes,<space/><bold>v</bold>, with only two bits.</paragraph><paragraph>Each user is associated with a different code, say<space/><bold>v</bold>. A 1 bit is represented by transmitting a positive code,<space/><bold>v</bold>, and a 0 bit is represented by a negative code,<space/><bold>v</bold>. For example, if<space/><bold>v</bold><space/>= (v<xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>) = (1, 1) and the data that the user wishes to transmit is (1, 0, 1, 1), then the transmitted symbols would be<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<bold>v</bold>,<space/><bold>v</bold>,<space/><bold>v</bold>,<space/><bold>v</bold>) = (v<xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub>, v<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>) = (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1). For the purposes of this article, we call this constructed vector the<space/><italics>transmitted vector</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Each sender has a different, unique vector<space/><bold>v</bold><space/>chosen from that set, but the construction method of the transmitted vector is identical.</paragraph><paragraph>Now, due to physical properties of interference, if two signals at a point are in phase, they add to give twice the amplitude of each signal, but if they are out of phase, they subtract and give a signal that is the difference of the amplitudes. Digitally, this behaviour can be modelled by the addition of the transmission vectors, component by component.</paragraph><paragraph>If sender0 has code (1, 1) and data (1, 0, 1, 1), and sender1 has code (1, 1) and data (0, 0, 1, 1), and both senders transmit simultaneously, then this table describes the coding steps:</paragraph><table style="border: 1px #aaaaaa solid; background-color: #f7f8ff; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><tablerow><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Step</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Encode sender0</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Encode sender1</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top">0</tablecell><tablecell>code0 = (1, 1), data0 = (1, 0, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>code1 = (1, 1), data1 = (0, 0, 1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top">1</tablecell><tablecell>encode0 = 2(1, 0, 1, 1) (1, 1, 1, 1) = (1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>encode1 = 2(0, 0, 1, 1) (1, 1, 1, 1) = (1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top">2</tablecell><tablecell>signal0 = encode0 code0<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>= (1, 1, 1, 1) (1, 1)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>= (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>signal1 = encode1 code1<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>= (1, 1, 1, 1) (1, 1)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>= (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Because signal0 and signal1 are transmitted at the same time into the air, they add to produce the raw signal:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>(1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1) + (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1) = (0, 2, 2, 0, 2, 0, 2, 0)</listitem></list><paragraph>This raw signal is called an interference pattern. The receiver then extracts an intelligible signal for any known sender by combining the sender's code with the interference pattern, the receiver combines it with the codes of the senders. The following table explains how this works and shows that the signals do not interfere with one another:</paragraph><table style="border: 1px #aaaaaa solid; background-color: #f7f8ff; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><tablerow><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Step</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Decode sender0</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Decode sender1</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>code0 = (1, 1), signal = (0, 2, 2, 0, 2, 0, 2, 0)</tablecell><tablecell>code1 = (1, 1), signal = (0, 2, 2, 0, 2, 0, 2, 0)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = pattern.vector0</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = pattern.vector1</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = ((0, 2), (2, 0), (2, 0), (2, 0)).(1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = ((0, 2), (2, 0), (2, 0), (2, 0)).(1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = ((0 + 2), (2 + 0), (2 + 0), (2 + 0))</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = ((0 2), (2 + 0), (2 + 0), (2 + 0))</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>data0=(2, 2, 2, 2), meaning (1, 0, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>data1=(2, 2, 2, 2), meaning (0, 0, 1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Further, after decoding, all values greater than 0 are interpreted as 1 while all values less than zero are interpreted as 0. For example, after decoding, data0 is (2, 2, 2, 2), but the receiver interprets this as (1, 0, 1, 1). Values of exactly 0 means that the sender did not transmit any data, as in the following example:</paragraph><paragraph>Assume signal0 = (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1) is transmitted alone. The following table shows the decode at the receiver:</paragraph><table style="border: 1px #aaaaaa solid; background-color: #f7f8ff; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><tablerow><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Step</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Decode sender0</tablecell><tablecell align="center" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Decode sender1</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>code0 = (1, 1), signal = (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>code1 = (1, 1), signal = (1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = pattern.vector0</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = pattern.vector1</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = ((1, 1), (1, 1), (1, 1), (1, 1)).(1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = ((1, 1), (1, 1), (1, 1), (1, 1)).(1, 1)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>decode0 = ((1 + 1), (1 1),(1 + 1), (1 + 1))</tablecell><tablecell>decode1 = ((1 1), (1 + 1),(1 1), (1 1))</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>data0 = (2, 2, 2, 2), meaning (1, 0, 1, 1)</tablecell><tablecell>data1 = (0, 0, 0, 0), meaning no data</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>When the receiver attempts to decode the signal using sender1's code, the data is all zeros, therefore the cross correlation is equal to zero and it is clear that sender1 did not transmit any data.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Asynchronous CDMA</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Direct-sequence spread spectrum</arg><arg>near-far problem</arg></template>When mobile-to-base links cannot be precisely coordinated, particularly due to the mobility of the handsets, a different approach is required. Since it is not mathematically possible to create signature sequences that are both orthogonal for arbitrarily random starting points and which make full use of the code space, unique &quot;pseudo-random&quot; or &quot;pseudo-noise&quot; (PN) sequences are used in<space/><italics>asynchronous</italics><space/>CDMA systems. A PN code is a binary sequence that appears random but can be reproduced in a deterministic manner by intended receivers. These PN codes are used to encode and decode a user's signal in Asynchronous CDMA in the same manner as the orthogonal codes in synchronous CDMA (shown in the example above). These PN sequences are statistically uncorrelated, and the sum of a large number of PN sequences results in<space/><italics>multiple access interference</italics><space/>(MAI) that is approximated by a Gaussian noise process (following the<space/><link><target>central limit theorem</target></link><space/>in statistics).<space/><link><target>Gold code</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are an example of a PN suitable for this purpose, as there is low correlation between the codes. If all of the users are received with the same power level, then the variance (e.g., the noise power) of the MAI increases in direct proportion to the number of users. In other words, unlike synchronous CDMA, the signals of other users will appear as noise to the signal of interest and interfere slightly with the desired signal in proportion to number of users.</paragraph><paragraph>All forms of CDMA use<space/><link><target>spread spectrum</target></link><space/><link><target>process gain</target></link><space/>to allow receivers to partially discriminate against unwanted signals. Signals encoded with the specified PN sequence (code) are received, while signals with different codes (or the same code but a different timing offset) appear as wideband noise reduced by the process gain.</paragraph><paragraph>Since each user generates MAI, controlling the signal strength is an important issue with CDMA transmitters. A CDM (synchronous CDMA), TDMA, or FDMA receiver can in theory completely reject arbitrarily strong signals using different codes, time slots or frequency channels due to the orthogonality of these systems. This is not true for Asynchronous CDMA; rejection of unwanted signals is only partial. If any or all of the unwanted signals are much stronger than the desired signal, they will overwhelm it. This leads to a general requirement in any asynchronous CDMA system to approximately match the various signal power levels as seen at the receiver. In CDMA cellular, the base station uses a fast closed-loop power control scheme to tightly control each mobile's transmit power.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Advantages of asynchronous CDMA over other techniques</heading><heading level='4'>Efficient practical utilization of the fixed frequency spectrum</heading><paragraph>In theory CDMA, TDMA and FDMA have exactly the same spectral efficiency but practically, each has its own challenges power control in the case of CDMA, timing in the case of TDMA, and frequency generation/filtering in the case of FDMA.</paragraph><paragraph>TDMA systems must carefully synchronize the transmission times of all the users to ensure that they are received in the correct time slot and do not cause interference. Since this cannot be perfectly controlled in a mobile environment, each time slot must have a guard-time, which reduces the probability that users will interfere, but decreases the spectral efficiency. Similarly, FDMA systems must use a guard-band between adjacent channels, due to the unpredictable<space/><link><target>doppler shift</target></link><space/>of the signal spectrum because of user mobility. The guard-bands will reduce the probability that adjacent channels will interfere, but decrease the utilization of the spectrum.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Flexible allocation of resources</heading><paragraph>Asynchronous CDMA offers a key advantage in the flexible allocation of resources i.e. allocation of a PN codes to active users. In the case of CDM (synchronous CDMA), TDMA, and FDMA the number of simultaneous orthogonal codes, time slots and frequency slots respectively are fixed hence the capacity in terms of number of simultaneous users is limited. There are a fixed number of orthogonal codes, time slots or frequency bands that can be allocated for CDM, TDMA, and FDMA systems, which remain underutilized due to the bursty nature of telephony and packetized data transmissions. There is no strict limit to the number of users that can be supported in an asynchronous CDMA system, only a practical limit governed by the desired bit error probability, since the SIR (Signal to Interference Ratio) varies inversely with the number of users. In a bursty traffic environment like mobile telephony, the advantage afforded by asynchronous CDMA is that the performance (bit error rate) is allowed to fluctuate randomly, with an average value determined by the number of users times the percentage of utilization. Suppose there are 2N users that only talk half of the time, then 2N users can be accommodated with the same<space/><italics>average</italics><space/>bit error probability as N users that talk all of the time. The key difference here is that the bit error probability for N users talking all of the time is constant, whereas it is a<space/><italics>random</italics><space/>quantity (with the same mean) for 2N users talking half of the time.</paragraph><paragraph>In other words, asynchronous CDMA is ideally suited to a mobile network where large numbers of transmitters each generate a relatively small amount of traffic at irregular intervals. CDM (synchronous CDMA), TDMA, and FDMA systems cannot recover the underutilized resources inherent to bursty traffic due to the fixed number of<space/><link><target>orthogonal</target></link><space/>codes, time slots or frequency channels that can be assigned to individual transmitters. For instance, if there are N time slots in a TDMA system and 2N users that talk half of the time, then half of the time there will be more than N users needing to use more than N time slots. Furthermore, it would require significant overhead to continually allocate and deallocate the orthogonal code, time slot or frequency channel resources. By comparison, asynchronous CDMA transmitters simply send when they have something to say, and go off the air when they don't, keeping the same PN signature sequence as long as they are connected to the system.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spread-spectrum characteristics of CDMA</heading><paragraph>Most modulation schemes try to minimize the bandwidth of this signal since bandwidth is a limited resource. However, spread spectrum techniques use a transmission bandwidth that is several orders of magnitude greater than the minimum required signal bandwidth. One of the initial reasons for doing this was military applications including guidance and communication systems. These systems were designed using spread spectrum because of its security and resistance to jamming. Asynchronous CDMA has some level of privacy built in because the signal is spread using a pseudo-random code; this code makes the spread spectrum signals appear random or have noise-like properties. A receiver cannot demodulate this transmission without knowledge of the pseudo-random sequence used to encode the data. CDMA is also resistant to jamming. A jamming signal only has a finite amount of power available to jam the signal. The jammer can either spread its energy over the entire bandwidth of the signal or jam only part of the entire signal.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Bernard
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Skylar
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Digital Communications: Fundamentals and Applications
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Second
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Prentice-Hall PTR.
<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN">
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>CDMA can also effectively reject narrow band interference. Since narrow band interference affects only a small portion of the spread spectrum signal, it can easily be removed through notch filtering without much loss of information.<space/><link><target>Convolution encoding</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>forward error correction#Interleaving</target><part>interleaving</part></link><space/>can be used to assist in recovering this lost data. CDMA signals are also resistant to multipath fading. Since the spread spectrum signal occupies a large bandwidth only a small portion of this will undergo fading due to multipath at any given time. Like the narrow band interference this will result in only a small loss of data and can be overcome.</paragraph><paragraph>Another reason CDMA is resistant to multipath interference is because the delayed versions of the transmitted pseudo-random codes will have poor correlation with the original pseudo-random code, and will thus appear as another user, which is ignored at the receiver. In other words, as long as the multipath channel induces at least one chip of delay, the multipath signals will arrive at the receiver such that they are shifted in time by at least one chip from the intended signal. The correlation properties of the pseudo-random codes are such that this slight delay causes the multipath to appear uncorrelated with the intended signal, and it is thus ignored.</paragraph><paragraph>Some CDMA devices use a<space/><link><target>rake receiver</target></link>, which exploits multipath delay components to improve the performance of the system.A rake receiver combines the information from several correlators, each one tuned to a different path delay, producing a stronger version of the signal than a simple receiver with a single correlation tuned to the path delay of the strongest signal.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Theodore S.
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Rapporteur
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Wireless Communications, Principles and Practice
<space/></arg><arg name="edition">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Prentice-Hall, Inc
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Frequency reuse is the ability to reuse the same radio channel frequency at other cell sites within a cellular system. In the FDMA and TDMA systems frequency planning is an important consideration. The frequencies used in different cells must be planned carefully to ensure signals from different cells do not interfere with each other. In a CDMA system, the same frequency can be used in every cell, because channelization is done using the pseudo-random codes. Reusing the same frequency in every cell eliminates the need for frequency planning in a CDMA system; however, planning of the different pseudo-random sequences must be done to ensure that the received signal from one cell does not correlate with the signal from a nearby cell.<extension extension_name='ref' name="xtsphp"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Lawrence, Richard, Romans
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Harte, Levine, Kikta
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>3G Wireless Demystified
<space/></arg><arg name="edition">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGowan-Hill
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since adjacent cells use the same frequencies, CDMA systems have the ability to perform soft hand offs. Soft hand offs allow the mobile telephone to communicate simultaneously with two or more cells. The best signal quality is selected until the hand off is complete. This is different from hard hand offs utilized in other cellular systems. In a hard hand off situation, as the mobile telephone approaches a hand off, signal strength may vary abruptly. In contrast, CDMA systems use the soft hand off, which is undetectable and provides a more reliable and higher quality signal.<extension extension_name='ref' name="xtsphp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Collaborative CDMA</heading><paragraph>In a recent study, a novel collaborative multi-user transmission and detection scheme called Collaborative CDMA<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first"><space/>Indu L.
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Shakya
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>High User Capacity Collaborative CDMA
<space/></arg><arg name="edition">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IET Communications
</arg></template></extension><space/>has been investigated for the uplink that exploits the differences between users fading channel signatures to increase the user capacity well beyond the spreading length in multiple access interference (MAI) limited environment. The authors show that it is possible to achieve this increase at a low complexity and high<space/><link><target>bit error rate</target></link><space/>performance in at fading channels, which is a major research challenge for overloaded CDMA systems. In this approach, instead of using one sequence per user as in conventional CDMA, the authors group a small number of users to share the same spreading sequence and enable group spreading and despreading operations. The new collaborative multi-user receiver consists of two stages: group multi-user detection (MUD) stage to suppress the MAI between the groups and a low complexity maximum-likelihood detection stage to recover jointly the co-spread users data using minimum Euclidean distance measure and users channel gain coefcients. In CDMA, signal security is high.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>CDMA</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Div col</target><arg></arg><arg>25em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>IS-95</target><part>cdmaOne</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>CDMA2000</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>W-CDMA</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Orthogonal variable spreading factor</target></link><space/>(OVSF), an implementation of CDMA</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pseudo-random noise</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Spread spectrum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>CDMA Spectral Efficiency</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Comparison of mobile phone standards</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Andrew J.
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Viterbi
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Andrew Viterbi
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>CDMA: Principles of Spread Spectrum Communication
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>1st
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Prentice Hall PTR
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-201-63374-4
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">
<space/></arg><arg name="first">
<space/></arg><arg name="title">CDMA Spectrum
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">
<space/></arg><arg name="year">
<space/></arg><arg name="work">
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.activexperts.com/asmssrvr/cellular/cdmaspectrum/
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-29
</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cdg.org/'>CDMA Development Group</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://video.ias.edu/goresky-lecture-4-13'>Talk at Princeton Institute for Advanced Study on Solomon Golomb's work on pseudorandom sequences</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>cdma</target><arg name="state">uncollapsed</arg></template><template><target>Channel access methods</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Code Division Multiple Access</target></template><link><target>Category:Code division multiple access</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Multiplexing</target></link><link><target>Category:Radio resource management</target></link><link><target>Category:Media access control</target></link></paragraph></article>