<article title='Athanasian_Creed'><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Athanasius I.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Athanasius of Alexandria</target></link><space/>was traditionally thought to be the author of the Athanasian Creed, and gives his name to its common title.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Athanasian Creed</bold>, or<space/><bold><italics>Quicunque Vult</italics></bold><space/>(also<space/><italics>Quicumque Vult</italics>), is a<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/><link><target>Creed</target><part>statement of belief</part></link><space/>focused on<space/><link><target>Trinity</target><part>Trinitarian</part></link><space/>doctrine and<space/><link><target>Christology</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>name of the creed,<space/><italics>Quicunque vult</italics>, is taken from the<space/><link><target>Incipit</target><part>opening words</part></link>, &quot;Whosoever wishes&quot;. The creed has been used by Christian churches since the sixth century. It is the first creed in which the equality of the three persons of the Trinity is explicitly stated. It differs from the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target><part>Nicene-Constantinopolitan</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Apostles' Creed</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the inclusion of<space/><link><target>anathema</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or condemnations of those who disagree with the creed (like the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed#The original Nicene Creed of 325</target><part>original Nicene Creed</part></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>Widely accepted among<space/><link><target>Western Christianity</target><part>Western Christians</part></link>, including the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target><part>Roman Catholic Church</part></link><space/>and some<space/><link><target>Anglican Communion</target><part>Anglican churches</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lutheran church</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>(it is considered part of the Lutheran confessions in the<space/><link><target>Book of Concord</target></link>), and ancient,<space/><link><target>liturgical</target></link><space/>churches generally, the Athanasian Creed has been used in public worship less and less frequently, but part of it can be found as an &quot;Authorized Affirmation of Faith&quot; in the recent (2000) Common Worship liturgy of the Church of England [Main Volume page 145].<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Morin</arg><arg>1911</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kantorowicz1957"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Kantorowicz</arg><arg>1957</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template></extension><space/>The creed has never gained much acceptance in liturgy among<space/><link><target>Eastern Christianity</target><part>Eastern Christians</part></link>. It was designed to distinguish<space/><link><target>Nicene Christianity</target></link><space/>from the heresy of<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link>. Liturgically, this Creed was recited at the<space/><link><target>Sunday Office of Prime</target></link><space/>in the Western Church; it is not in common use in the Eastern Church. Today, the Athanasian Creed is rarely used even in the Western Church. When used, one common practice is to use it once a year on<space/><link><target>Trinity Sunday</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://orthodoxwiki.org/Athanasian_Creed</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origin</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Shield-Trinity-Scutum-Fidei-compact.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Shield of the Trinity</target></link>, a visual representation of the doctrine of the Trinity, derived from the Athanasian Creed. The Latin reads: &quot;The Father is God, The Son is God, The Holy Spirit is God; God is the Father, God is the Son, God is the Holy Spirit; The Father is not the Son, The Son is not the Father, The Father is not the Holy Spirit, The Holy Spirit is not the Father, The Son is not the Holy Spirit, The Holy Spirit is not the Son.&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A medieval account credited<space/><link><target>Athanasius of Alexandria</target></link>, the famous defender of<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target><part>Nicene theology</part></link>, as the author of the Creed. According to this account, Athanasius composed it during his exile in<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Rome</part></link><space/>and presented it to<space/><link><target>Pope Julius I</target></link><space/>as a witness to his orthodoxy. This traditional attribution of the Creed to Athanasius was first called into question in 1642 by Dutch Protestant theologian<space/><link><target>Gerhard Johann Vossius</target><part>G.J. Voss</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>O'Carroll</arg><arg>1987</arg></template></extension><space/>and it has since been widely accepted by modern scholars that the creed was not authored by Athanasius,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norris1997"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Norris</arg><arg>1997</arg></template></extension><space/>that it was not originally called a creed at all,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Richardson</arg><arg>Hopkins</arg><arg>1967</arg><arg name="p">483</arg></template></extension><space/>nor was Athanasius' name originally attached to it.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Faulkner</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg name="p">427</arg></template></extension><space/>Athanasius' name seems to have become attached to the creed as a sign of its strong declaration of Trinitarian faith. The reasoning for rejecting Athanasius as the author usually relies on a combination of the following:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The creed originally was most likely written in Latin, while Athanasius composed in Greek.</listitem><listitem>Neither Athanasius nor his contemporaries ever mention the Creed.</listitem><listitem>It is not mentioned in any records of the<space/><link><target>ecumenical councils</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>It appears to address theological concerns that developed after Athanasius died (including the<space/><link><target>filioque</target></link>).</listitem><listitem>It was most widely circulated among<space/><link><target>Western Christianity</target><part>Western Christians</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kantorowicz1957"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Bente</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg>p13</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The use of the creed in a sermon by<space/><link><target>Caesarius of Arles</target></link>, as well as a theological resemblance to works by<space/><link><target>Vincent of Lrins</target></link>, point to Southern<space/><link><target>Gaul</target></link><space/>as its origin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norris1997"></extension><space/>The most likely time frame is in the late fifth or early sixth century AD at least 100 years after Athanasius. The<space/><link><target>Christian theology</target><part>theology</part></link><space/>of the creed is firmly rooted in the<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target><part>Augustinian tradition</part></link>, using exact terminology of Augustine's<space/><italics>On the Trinity</italics><space/>(published 415 AD).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Schaff</arg><arg>1990</arg></template></extension><space/>In the late 19th century, there was a great deal of speculation about who might have authored the creed, with suggestions including<space/><link><target>Ambrose of Milan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Venantius Fortunatus</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Hilary of Poitiers</target></link>, among others.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Jackson</arg><arg>1966</arg></template><space/>for examples of various theories of authorship.</extension><space/>The 1940 discovery of a lost work by<space/><link><target>Vincent of Lrins</target></link>, which bears a striking similarity to much of the language of the Athanasian Creed, have led many to conclude that the creed originated either with Vincent or with his students.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Mahajan</arg><arg>Sampaolo</arg><arg>2012</arg></template></extension><space/>For example, in the authoritative modern monograph about the creed,<space/><link><target>J.N.D. Kelly</target></link><space/>asserts that Vincent of Lrin was not its author, but that it may have come from the same milieu, namely the area of Lrins in southern Gaul.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Kelly</arg><arg>1964</arg></template></extension><space/>The oldest surviving manuscripts of the Athanasian Creed date from the late 8th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Chazelle</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">1056</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Content</heading><paragraph><template><target>listen</target><arg name="title">Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="filename">Athanasian Creed.ogg</arg><arg name="description">Recording of the Athanasian Creed in English</arg></template>The Athanasian Creed is usually divided into two sections: lines 128 addressing the doctrine of the<space/><link><target>Trinity</target></link>, and lines 2944 addressing the doctrine of<space/><link><target>Christology</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Schaff</arg><arg>1877a</arg></template><space/>for an example of this division.</extension><space/>Enumerating the three persons of the Trinity (i.e.,<space/><link><target>God the Father#Christianity</target><part>Father</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Christian views of Jesus</target><part>Son</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link>), the first section of the creed ascribes the<space/><link><target>divine attribute</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to each individually. Thus, each person of the Trinity is described as uncreated (<italics>increatus</italics>), limitless (<italics>Immensus</italics>), eternal (<italics>ternus</italics>), and omnipotent (<italics>omnipotens</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Athanasian Creed, lines 8,9,10, and 13, respectively. See the side by side English and Latin in<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Schaff</arg><arg>1877b</arg><arg name="pp">66–71</arg></template></extension><space/>While ascribing the divine attributes and divinity to each person of the Trinity, thus avoiding<space/><link><target>subordinationism</target></link>, the first half of the Athanasian Creed also stresses the unity of the three persons in the one Godhead, thus avoiding a theology of<space/><link><target>tritheism</target></link>. Furthermore, although one God, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are distinct from each other. For the Father is neither made nor begotten; the Son is not made but is begotten from the Father; the Holy Spirit is neither made nor begotten but proceeds from the Father and the Son (<link><target>filioque</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>The text of the Athanasian Creed is as follows:</paragraph><table class="wikitable" style="width:75%; margin: 1em auto 1em auto"><tablerow><tablehead>in Latin</tablehead><tablehead>English translation<extension extension_name='ref'>This is Schaff's emendation of the<space/><link><target>Book of Common Prayer</target></link><space/>translation. See<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Schaff</arg><arg>1877b</arg><arg name="pp">66–71</arg></template></extension></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow valign="top"><tablecell style="width:48.6%;cellpadding:15"><paragraph><italics>Quicumque vult salvus esse, ante omnia opus est, ut teneat catholicam fidem: Quam nisi quisque integram inviolatamque servaverit, absque dubio in aeternum peribit. Fides autem catholica haec est: ut unum Deum in Trinitate, et Trinitatem in unitate veneremur. Neque confundentes personas, neque substantiam separantes. Alia est enim persona Patris alia Filii, alia Spiritus Sancti: Sed Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti una est divinitas, aequalis gloria, coeterna maiestas. Qualis Pater, talis Filius, talis [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Increatus Pater, increatus Filius, increatus [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Immensus Pater, immensus Filius, immensus [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Aeternus Pater, aeternus Filius, aeternus [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Et tamen non tres aeterni, sed unus aeternus. Sicut non tres increati, nec tres immensi, sed unus increatus, et unus immensus. Similiter omnipotens Pater, omnipotens Filius, omnipotens [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Et tamen non tres omnipotentes, sed unus omnipotens. Ita Deus Pater, Deus Filius, Deus [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Et tamen non tres dii, sed unus est Deus. Ita Dominus Pater, Dominus Filius, Dominus [et] Spiritus Sanctus. Et tamen non tres Domini, sed unus [est] Dominus. Quia, sicut singillatim unamquamque personam Deum ac Dominum confiteri christiana veritate compellimur: Ita tres Deos aut [tres] Dominos dicere catholica religione prohibemur. Pater a nullo est factus: nec creatus, nec genitus. Filius a Patre solo est: non factus, nec creatus, sed genitus. Spiritus Sanctus a Patre et Filio: non factus, nec creatus, nec genitus, sed procedens. Unus ergo Pater, non tres Patres: unus Filius, non tres Filii: unus Spiritus Sanctus, non tres Spiritus Sancti. Et in hac Trinitate nihil prius aut posterius, nihil maius aut minus: Sed totae tres personae coaeternae sibi sunt et coaequales. Ita, ut per omnia, sicut iam supra dictum est, et unitas in Trinitate, et Trinitas in unitate veneranda sit. Qui vult ergo salvus esse, ita de Trinitate sentiat.</italics></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Sed necessarium est ad aeternam salutem, ut incarnationem quoque Domini nostri Iesu Christi fideliter credat. Est ergo fides recta ut credamus et confiteamur, quia Dominus noster Iesus Christus, Dei Filius, Deus [pariter] et homo est. Deus [est] ex substantia Patris ante saecula genitus: et homo est ex substantia matris in saeculo natus. Perfectus Deus, perfectus homo: ex anima rationali et humana carne subsistens. Aequalis Patri secundum divinitatem: minor Patre secundum humanitatem. Qui licet Deus sit et homo, non duo tamen, sed unus est Christus. Unus autem non conversione divinitatis in carnem, sed assumptione humanitatis in Deum. Unus omnino, non confusione substantiae, sed unitate personae. Nam sicut anima rationalis et caro unus est homo: ita Deus et homo unus est Christus. Qui passus est pro salute nostra: descendit ad inferos: tertia die resurrexit a mortuis. Ascendit ad [in] caelos, sedet ad dexteram [Dei] Patris [omnipotentis]. Inde venturus [est] judicare vivos et mortuos. Ad cujus adventum omnes homines resurgere habent cum corporibus suis; Et reddituri sunt de factis propriis rationem. Et qui bona egerunt, ibunt in vitam aeternam: qui vero mala, in ignem aeternum. Haec est fides catholica, quam nisi quisque fideliter firmiterque crediderit, salvus esse non poterit.</italics></paragraph></tablecell><tablecell style="width:51.4%"><paragraph>Whosoever will be saved, before all things it is necessary that he hold the catholic faith.Which faith except every one do keep whole and undefiled; without doubt he shall perish everlastingly.And the catholic faith is this: That we worship one God in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity; Neither confounding the Persons; nor dividing the Essence.For there is one Person of the Father; another of the Son; and another of the Holy Ghost.But the Godhead of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, is all one; the Glory equal, the Majesty coeternal.Such as the Father is; such is the Son; and such is the Holy Ghost.The Father uncreated; the Son uncreated; and the Holy Ghost uncreated.The Father unlimited; the Son unlimited; and the Holy Ghost unlimited.The Father eternal; the Son eternal; and the Holy Ghost eternal.And yet they are not three eternals; but one eternal.As also there are not three uncreated; nor three infinites, but one uncreated; and one infinite.So likewise the Father is Almighty; the Son Almighty; and the Holy Ghost Almighty.And yet they are not three Almighties; but one Almighty.So the Father is God; the Son is God; and the Holy Ghost is God.And yet they are not three Gods; but one God.So likewise the Father is Lord; the Son Lord; and the Holy Ghost Lord.And yet not three Lords; but one Lord.For like as we are compelled by the Christian verity; to acknowledge every Person by himself to be God and Lord;So are we forbidden by the catholic religion; to say, There are three Gods, or three Lords.The Father is made of none; neither created, nor begotten.The Son is of the Father alone; not made, nor created; but begotten.The Holy Ghost is of the Father and of the Son; neither made, nor created, nor begotten; but proceeding.So there is one Father, not three Fathers; one Son, not three Sons; one Holy Ghost, not three Holy Ghosts.And in this Trinity none is before, or after another; none is greater, or less than another.But the whole three Persons are coeternal, and coequal.So that in all things, as aforesaid; the Unity in Trinity, and the Trinity in Unity, is to be worshipped.He therefore that will be saved, let him thus think of the Trinity.</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore it is necessary to everlasting salvation; that he also believe faithfully the Incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ.For the right Faith is, that we believe and confess; that our Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of God, is God and Man;God, of the Essence of the Father; begotten before the worlds; and Man, of the Essence of his Mother, born in the world.Perfect God; and perfect Man, of a reasonable soul and human flesh subsisting.Equal to the Father, as touching his Godhead; and inferior to the Father as touching his Manhood.Who although he is God and Man; yet he is not two, but one Christ.One; not by conversion of the Godhead into flesh; but by assumption of the Manhood by God.One altogether; not by confusion of Essence; but by unity of Person.For as the reasonable soul and flesh is one man; so God and Man is one Christ;Who suffered for our salvation; descended into hell; rose again the third day from the dead.He ascended into heaven, he sitteth on the right hand of the God the Father Almighty, from whence he will come to judge the living and the dead.At whose coming all men will rise again with their bodies; And shall give account for their own works.And they that have done good shall go into life everlasting; and they that have done evil, into everlasting fire.This is the catholic faith; which except a man believe truly and firmly, he cannot be saved.</paragraph></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>The Christology of the second section is more detailed than that of the Nicene Creed, and reflects the teaching of the<space/><link><target>First Council of Ephesus</target></link><space/>(431) and the definition of the<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target></link><space/>(451). The 'Athanasian' Creed uses the Nicene term<space/><italics><link><target>homoousios</target></link></italics>' ('one substance', 'one in Being') not only with respect to the relation of the Son to the Father according to his divine nature, but that the Son is<space/><italics>homoousios</italics><space/>with his mother Mary, according to his human nature.</paragraph><paragraph>The Creed's wording thus excludes not only<space/><link><target>Sabellianism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link>, but the Christological heresies of<space/><link><target>Nestorianism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eutychianism</target></link>. A need for a clear confession against Arianism arose in western Europe when the<space/><link><target>Ostrogoths</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Visigoths</target></link>, who had Arian beliefs, invaded at the beginning of the 5th century.</paragraph><paragraph>The final section of this Creed also moved beyond the Nicene (and Apostles') Creeds in making negative statements about the people's fate: &quot;They that have done good shall go into life everlasting: and they that have done evil into everlasting fire.&quot; This caused considerable debate in England in the mid-nineteenth century, centred on the teaching of<space/><link><target>Frederick Denison Maurice</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Uses</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Trinity knight shield.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Detail of a manuscript illustration depicting a knight carrying the &quot;Shield of the Trinity.&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Composed of 44 rhythmic lines, the Athanasian Creed appears to have been intended as a liturgical document that is, the original purpose of the creed was to be spoken or sung as a part of worship. The creed itself uses the language of public worship, speaking of the worship of God rather than the language of belief (&quot;Now this is the catholic faith: We worship one God&quot;). In the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>in medieval times, this creed was recited following the Sunday sermon or at the Sunday Office of<space/><link><target>Prime (liturgy)</target><part>Prime</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pfatteicher1990"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Pfatteicher</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">444</arg></template></extension><space/>The creed was often set to music and used in the place of a Psalm.</paragraph><paragraph>Early<space/><link><target>Protestant</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>inherited the late medieval devotion to the Athanasian Creed, and it was considered to be authoritative in many Protestant churches. The statements of Protestant belief (confessional documents) of various Reformers commend the Athanasian Creed to their followers, including the<space/><link><target>Augsburg Confession</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Formula of Concord</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Second Helvetic Confession</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Belgic Confession</target></link>, the Bohemian Confession and the<space/><link><target>Thirty-nine Articles</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Melanchthon</arg><arg>1530</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Andreä</arg><arg>Chemnitz</arg><arg>Selnecker</arg><arg>Chytraeus</arg><arg>1577</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Bullinger</arg><arg>1564</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>de Bres</arg><arg>Junius</arg><arg>1562</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Church of England</arg><arg>1563</arg></template></extension><space/>A<space/><link><target>meter (hymn)</target><part>metric</part></link><space/>version titled &quot;Quicumque vult&quot;, with a musical setting, was published in<space/><italics>The Whole Booke of Psalmes</italics><space/>printed by<space/><link><target>John Day (printer)</target><part>John Day</part></link><space/>in 1562. Among modern Lutheran and Reformed churches adherence to the Athanasian Creed is prescribed by the earlier confessional documents, but the creed does not receive much attention outside of occasional use especially on<space/><link><target>Trinity Sunday</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pfatteicher1990"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Reformed circles, it is included (for example) in the Christian Reformed Churches of Australia's Book of Forms (publ. 1991). However, it is rarely recited in public worship.</paragraph><paragraph>In the successive Books of Common Prayer of the reformed Church of England, from 1549 to 1662, its recitation was provided for on 19 occasions each year, a practice which continued until the nineteenth century, when vigorous controversy regarding its statement about 'eternal damnation' saw its use gradually decline. It remains one of the three Creeds approved in the Thirty-Nine Articles, and is printed in several current Anglican prayer books (e.g. A Prayer Book for Australia (1995)). As with Roman Catholic practice, its use is now generally only on Trinity Sunday or its octave. The Episcopal Church based in the United States has never provided for its use in worship, but added it to its Book of Common Prayer for the first time in 1979, where it is included in small print in a reference section entitled &quot;Historical Documents of the Church.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>=&quot;Hatchett 1980, p. 584&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Roman Catholic churches, it was traditionally said at<space/><link><target>Prime (liturgy)</target><part>Prime</part></link><space/>on Sundays after Epiphany and Pentecost, except when a Double feast or day within an octave occurred, and on Trinity Sunday. In the 1960 reforms, it was reduced to once a year on<space/><link><target>Trinity Sunday</target></link>. It has been effectively dropped from the Catholic liturgy since the<space/><link><target>Second Vatican Council</target></link>. It is however maintained in the<space/><italics>Forma Extraordinaria</italics>, per the decree<space/><link><target>Summorum Pontificum</target></link>, and also in the rite of exorcism, both in the<space/><italics>Forma Ordinaria</italics><space/>and the<space/><italics>Forma Extraordinaria</italics><space/>of the Roman Rite.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target></link>, the Athanasian Creed isalong with the<space/><link><target>Apostles' Creed</target><part>Apostles'</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target><trail>s</trail></link>one of the three<space/><link><target>ecumenical creeds</target></link><space/>placed at the beginning of the 1580<space/><link><target>Book of Concord</target></link>, the historic collection of authoritative doctrinal statements (confessions) of the Lutheran Church. It is still used in the liturgy on<space/><link><target>Trinity Sunday</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A common visualisation of the first half of the Creed is the<space/><link><target>Shield of the Trinity</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Church of England</arg><arg name="authorlink">Church of England</arg><arg name="title">Thirty-Nine Articles</arg><arg name="year">1563</arg><arg name="url">http://www.reformed.org/documents/articles_39_1572.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg><arg name="archivedate">2011-06-29</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20110629034023/http://www.reformed.org/documents/articles_39_1572.html</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Andreä</arg><arg name="first1">Jakob</arg><arg name="author1-link">Jakob Andreä</arg><arg name="last2">Chemnitz</arg><arg name="first2">Martin</arg><arg name="author2-link">Martin Chemnitz</arg><arg name="last3">Selnecker</arg><arg name="first3">Nikolaus</arg><arg name="author3-link">Nikolaus Selnecker</arg><arg name="last4">Chytraeus</arg><arg name="first4">David</arg><arg name="author4-link">David Chytraeus</arg><arg name="last5">Musculus</arg><arg name="first5">Andreas</arg><arg name="author5-link">Andreas Musculus</arg><arg name="last6">Körner</arg><arg name="first6">Christoph</arg><arg name="title">Solid Declaration of the Formula of Concord</arg><arg name="year">1577</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds3.iii.iv.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Bente</arg><arg name="first">Friedrich</arg><arg name="title">Historical Introductions to the Symbolical Books of the Evangelical Lutheran Church</arg><arg name="format">txt</arg><arg name="type">eBook</arg><arg name="date">2008-10-13</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/26909/26909.txt</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">de Bres</arg><arg name="first1">Guido</arg><arg name="author1-link">Guido de Bres</arg><arg name="last2">Junius</arg><arg name="first2">Franciscus</arg><arg name="author2-link">Franciscus Junius (the elder)</arg><arg name="title">Belgic Confession</arg><arg name="year">1562</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.ix.iii.iii.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Bullinger</arg><arg name="first">Heinrich</arg><arg name="authorlink">Heinrich Bullinger</arg><arg name="title">Second Helvetic Confession</arg><arg name="year">1564</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/creeds/helvetic.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Chazelle</arg><arg name="first">Celia</arg><arg name="title">Archbishops Ebo and Hincmar of Reims and the Utrecht Psalter</arg><arg name="work">Speculum</arg><arg name="volume">72</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="publication-date">1997</arg><arg name="page">1056</arg><arg name="jstor">2865958</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Faulkner</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">The First Great Christian Creed</arg><arg name="journal">The American Journal of Theology</arg><arg name="date">July 1910</arg><arg name="volume">14</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">426–427</arg><arg name="publisher">The University of Chicago Press</arg><arg name="location">Chicago</arg><arg name="jstor">3154994</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/478939</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Hatchett</arg><arg name="first">Marion J.</arg><arg name="title">Commentary on the American Prayer Book</arg><arg name="year">1980</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper & Row</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8164-0206-X</arg><arg name="authorlink">Hatchett</arg><arg name="page">584</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Mahajan</arg><arg name="first1">Deepti</arg><arg name="last2">Sampaolo</arg><arg name="first2">Marco</arg><arg name="contribution">Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="publication-date">2012</arg><arg name="contribution-url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/40585/Athanasian-Creed</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Jackson</arg><arg name="first">Samuel</arg><arg name="author-link">Samuel Macauley Jackson</arg><arg name="contribution">Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="title">The New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religion</arg><arg name="publisher">Baker Book House</arg><arg name="place">Grand Rapids</arg><arg name="publication-date">1966</arg><arg name="contribution-url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/encyc01.html?term</arg><arg name="oclc">9097284</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Kantorowicz</arg><arg name="first">Ernst</arg><arg name="title">The King's Two Bodies</arg><arg name="year">1957</arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton University Press</arg><arg name="location">Princeton</arg><arg name="isbn">0691017042</arg><arg name="authorlink">Ernst Kantorowicz</arg><arg name="page">17</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Kelly</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="authorlink">John Norman Davidson Kelly</arg><arg name="title">The Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper and Row</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publication-date">1964</arg><arg name="oclc">6914156</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">The Augsburg Confession</arg><arg name="editor-last">Melanchthon</arg><arg name="editor-first">Philip</arg><arg name="editor-link">Philip Melanchthon</arg><arg name="year">1530</arg><arg name="url">http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Augsburg_Confession</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Morin</arg><arg name="first">Germain</arg><arg name="author-link">Germain Morin</arg><arg name="title">L'Origine du Symbole d'Athanase</arg><arg name="trans_title">The Origin of the Symbol of Athanasius</arg><arg name="url">http://jts.oxfordjournals.org/content/os-XII/3/337.full.pdf</arg><arg name="language">French</arg><arg name="year">1911</arg><arg name="volume">XII</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/jts/os-XII.3.337</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg><arg name="journal">The Journal of Theological Studies</arg><arg name="page">337</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Norris</arg><arg name="first">Frederick</arg><arg name="contribution">Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of Early Christianity</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="place">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Ferguson</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Everett</arg><arg name="editor1-link">Everett Ferguson</arg><arg name="isbn">0824057457</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Trinitas</arg><arg name="publisher">Liturgical Press</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="location">Collegeville</arg><arg name="last">O'Carroll</arg><arg name="first">Michael</arg><arg name="isbn">0814655955</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Pfatteicher</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="title">Commentary on the Lutheran Book of Worship</arg><arg name="publisher">Augsburg Fortress</arg><arg name="year">1990</arg><arg name="isbn">0800603923</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Richardson</arg><arg name="first1">Herbert</arg><arg name="last2">Hopkins</arg><arg name="first2">Jasper</arg><arg name="title">On the Athanasian Creed</arg><arg name="journal">The Harvard Theological Review</arg><arg name="date">October 1967</arg><arg name="volume">60</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pages">483–484</arg><arg name="jstor">1509257</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/S0017816000003953</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Schaff</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="authorlink">Philip Schaff</arg><arg name="title">The Creeds of Christendom</arg><arg name="volume">1</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper Brothers</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1877a</arg><arg name="oclc">2589524</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.iv.v.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Schaff</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="authorlink">Philip Schaff</arg><arg name="title">The Creeds of Christendom</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper Brothers</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1877b</arg><arg name="oclc">2589524</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds2.iv.i.iv.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Schaff</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="authorlink">Philip Schaff</arg><arg name="title">History of the Christian Church</arg><arg name="year">1981</arg><arg name="publisher">Wm. B. Eerdmans</arg><arg name="location">Grand Rapids</arg><arg name="volume">3</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/hcc3.iii.xii.xvi.html</arg><arg name="isbn">0802880495</arg><arg name="edition">5th Revised</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-09-08</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Catholic Prayers</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Book of Concord</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Prayers in the Lutheran Church</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Theology</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Book of Concord</target></link><link><target>Category:Ecumenical creeds</target></link><link><target>Category:5th-century Christian texts</target></link><link><target>Category:Latin texts</target></link><link><target>Category:Trinitarianism</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian statements of faith</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link></paragraph></article>