<article title='Deconstruction'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg></arg><arg>deconstruction of buildings</arg><arg>Deconstruction (building)</arg><arg>the approach to post-modern architecture</arg><arg>Deconstructivism</arg><arg>other uses</arg></template><template><target>pp-semi</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><template><target>Technical</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Deconstruction</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-fr</target><arg>déconstruction</arg></template>) is a critical outlook concerned with the relationship between text and meaning.<space/><link><target>Jacques Derrida</target><part>Jacque Derridas</part></link><space/>1967 work Of Grammatology introduced the majority of ideas influential within deconstruction.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derrida first used the term &quot;Deconstruction&quot; in his work &quot;Of Grammatology&quot;, French version, p.&amp;nbsp;25 (Les ditions de Minuit, 1967, ISBN 978-2-7073-0012-6). On this page Derrida states that the occidental history of sign is essentially theological with reference to Logocentrism. Derrida starts a<space/><link><target>Metaphysics</target><part>metaphysical</part></link><space/>approach of<space/><link><target>semiology</target></link>. He states that the concept of sign and deconstruction work are always exposed to misunderstanding. He uses the term &quot;mconnaissance&quot; probably in reference to<space/><link><target>Jacques Lacan</target></link><space/>who rejected the belief that reality can be captured in language. In the same page Derrida states that he will try to demonstrate that there is no linguistic sign without writing.</extension><space/>According to Derrida and taking inspiration from the work of<space/><link><target>Ferdinand de Saussure</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Saussure 1916 trans. 1959 12122"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Saussure<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ferdinand de<space/></arg><arg name="title">Course in General Linguistics [trans. 1959]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1916<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Philosophical Library<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="pages">121–2<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://faculty.smu.edu/dfoster/cf3324/saussure.htm<space/></arg><arg name="quote">In language there are only differences. Even more important: a difference generally implies positive terms between which the difference is set up; but in language there are only differences without positive terms. Whether we take the signified or the signifier, language has neither ideas nor sounds that existed before the linguistic system, but only conceptual and phonic differences that have issued from the system.</arg></template></extension><space/>language is a system of signs and words only have meaning because of the contrast between these signs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rorty et al 1995-2"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Rorty<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="title">From Formalism to Poststructuralism<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Deconstructionist Theory<space/></arg><arg name="volume">8<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://prelectur.stanford.edu/lecturers/derrida/rorty.html<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Derrida says of the logocentric philosophers who hold out this hope of immediacy: 'Univocity is the essence, or better, the telos of language. No philosophy has ever renounced this Aristotelian ideal. This ideal is philosophy.' (Margins, p.&nbsp;247) To succeed in twisting free of the logocentric tradition would be to write, and to read, in such a way as to renounce this ideal. To destroy the tradition would be to see all the texts of that tradition as self-delusive, because using language to do what language cannot do. Language itself, so to speak, can be relied upon to betray any attempt to transcend it (see Derrida, Writing, pp.&nbsp;278-81).</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1997p12"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated by Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak<space/></arg><arg name="title">Of Grammatology<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Corrected<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Johns Hopkins University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Baltimore<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0801858305<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 1 The End of the Book and the Beginning of Writing<space/></arg><arg name="page">12<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">We already have a foreboding that phonocentrism merges with the historical determination of the meaning of being in general as presence, with all the subdeterminations which depend on this general form and which organize within it their system and their historical sequence (presence of the thing to the sight as eidos, presence as substance/essence/existence ousia, temporal presence as point [stigme] of the now or of the moment [nun], the self-presence of the cogito, consciousness, subjectivity, the co-presence of the other and of the self, intersubjectivity as the intentional phenomenon of the ego, and so forth). Logocentrism would thus support the determination of the being of the entity as presence. To the extent that such a Logocentrism is not totally absent from Heidegger's thought, perhaps it still holds that thought within the epoch of onto-theology, within the philosophy of presence, that is to say within philosophy itself.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1997p7"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated by Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak<space/></arg><arg name="title">Of Grammatology<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Corrected<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Johns Hopkins University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Baltimore<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0801858305<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 1 The End of the Book and the Beginning of Writing<space/></arg><arg name="page">7<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">The secondarity that it seemed possible to ascribe to writing alone affects all signifieds in general, affects them always already, the moment they enter the game. There is not a single signified that escapes the play of differance.</arg></template></extension><space/>As<space/><link><target>Richard Rorty</target><part>Rorty</part></link><space/>contends &quot;words have meaning only because of contrast-effects with other words...no word can acquire meaning in the way in which philosophers from<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link><space/>have hoped it mightby being the unmediated expression of something non-linguistic (e.g., an emotion, a sense-datum, a physical object, an idea, a<space/><link><target>Platonic Form</target></link>)&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rorty et al 1995"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Rorty<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="title">From Formalism to Poststructuralism<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Deconstructionist Theory<space/></arg><arg name="volume">8<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://prelectur.stanford.edu/lecturers/derrida/rorty.html<space/></arg><arg name="quote">That is, words have meaning only because of contrast-effects with other words. 'Red' means what it does only by contrast with 'blue', 'green', etc. 'Being' also means nothing except by contrast, not only with 'beings' but with 'Nature', 'God', 'Humanity', and indeed every other word in the language. No word can acquire meaning in the way in which philosophers from Aristotle to Bertrand Russell have hoped it might -- by being the unmediated expression of something non-linguistic (e.g., an emotion, a sense-datum, a physical object, an idea, a Platonic Form) (...) If this is so, Derrida contends, it means that any given concept is constituted in terms of its oppositions, e.g. being/nothing, one/multiple, truth/false, fair/unfair, beauty/ugly, essence/existence, receptivity/spontaneity, autonomous/heteronomous, transcendental/empirical, transcendent/immanent, mind/body, normal/abnormal, sovereign/beast, speech/writing, nature/culture, bachelor/married, etc..This is not, of course, to say that there is no such thing as linguistic reference to non-language. But merely to repeat Wittgenstein's point that ostensive definition requires a lot of 'stage-setting'. The common-sense claim that 'There's a rabbit' is typically uttered in the presence of rabbits is undermined neither by Wittgenstein's point, nor by Quine's arguments about the inscrutability of reference, nor by Derrida's about the tendency of the signifier to slip away from the signified. For the impact of such arguments on the notion of meaning, see Stout, 'Meaning', and Wheeler, 'Extension'.<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>As a consequence meaning is never present, but rather is deferred to other signs. Derrida refers to the, in this view, mistaken belief that there is a self-sufficient, non-deferred meaning as metaphysics of presence. A concept then must be understood in the context of its opposite, such as being/nothingness, normal/abnormal, speech/writing, etc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 2005p276"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated, with an introduction and additional notes, by Alan Bass<space/></arg><arg name="title">Writing and Difference<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Taylor & Francis e-Library<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0203991788<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 7: Freud and the Scene of Writing<space/></arg><arg name="page">276<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">The model of hieroglyphic writing assembles more strikingly—though we find it in every form of writing—the diversity of the modes and functions of signs in dreams. Every sign—verbal or otherwise—may be used at different levels, in configurations and functions which are never prescribed by its "essence," but emerge from a play of differences.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1981p133"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated and annotated by Alan Bass<space/></arg><arg name="title">Positions<space/></arg><arg name="edition">1st<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The University of Chicago Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Chicago<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0226143317<space/></arg><arg name="page">26<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">At the point at which the concept of differance, and the chain attached to it, intervenes, all the conceptual oppositions of metaphysics (signifier/signified; sensible/intelligible; writing/speech; passivity/activity; etc.)- to the extent that they ultimately refer to the presence of something present (for example, in the form of the identity of the subject who is present for all his operations, present beneath every accident or event, self-present in its "living speech," in its enunciations, in the present objects and acts of its language, etc.)- become non pertinent. They all amount, at one moment or another, to a subordination of the movement of differance in favor of the presence of a value or a meaning supposedly antecedent to differance, more original than it, exceeding and governing it in the last analysis. This is still the presence of what we called above the "transcendental signified.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, Derrida argues that it is not enough to expose and deconstruct the way oppositions work and then stop there in a nihilistic or cynical position, &quot;thereby preventing any means of intervening in the field effectively&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1981p42"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated and annotated by Alan Bass<space/></arg><arg name="title">Positions<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Interview with Jean-Louis Houdebine and Guy Scarpetta<space/></arg><arg name="edition">1st<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The University of Chicago Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Chicago<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0226143317<space/></arg><arg name="page">41<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">Therefore one might not proceed too quickly to a neutralization that in practice would leave the previous field untouched, leaving one no hold on the previous opposition, thereby preventing any means of intervening in the field effectively. We know what always have been the practical (particularly political) effects of Immediately jumping beyond oppositions, and of protests in the simple form of neither this nor that.</arg></template></extension><space/>To be effective, deconstruction needs to create new terms, not to synthesize the concepts in opposition, but to mark their difference and eternal interplay. This explains why Derrida always proposes new terms in his deconstruction, not as a free play but as a pure necessity of analysis, to better mark the intervals. Derrida called undecidables, that is, unities of simulacrum, &quot;false&quot; verbal properties (nominal or semantic) that can no longer be included within philosophical (binary) opposition: but which, however, inhabit philosophical oppositions, resisting and organizing it, without ever constituting a third term, without ever leaving room for a solution in the form of Hegelian dialectics (e.g.<space/><link><target>diffrance</target></link>,<space/><link><target>archi-writing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pharmakon (philosophy)</target><part>pharmakon</part></link>, supplement, hymen, gram, spacing).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1981 p43"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated and annotated by Alan Bass<space/></arg><arg name="title">Positions<space/></arg><arg name="edition">1st<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The University of Chicago Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Chicago<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0226143317<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Interview with Jean-Louis Houdebine and Guy Scarpetta<space/></arg><arg name="page">19<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">I have called undecidables, that is, unities of simulacrum, "false" verbal properties (nominal or semantic) that can no longer be included within philosophical (binary) opposition, but which, however, inhabit philosophical oppositions, resisting and disorganizing it, without ever constituting a third term, without ever leaving room for a solution in the form of speculative dialectics (the pharmakon is neither remedy nor poison, neither good nor evil, neither the inside nor the outside, neither speech nor writing; the supplement is neither a plus nor a minus, neither an outside nor the complement of an inside, neither accident nor essence, etc.; the hymen is neither confusion nor distinction (neither identity nor difference, neither consummation nor virginity, neither the veil nor unveiling, neither the inside nor the outside, etc.; the gram is neither a signifier nor a signified, neither a sign nor a thing, neither a presence nor an absence, neither a position nor a negation, etc.; spacing is neither space nor time; the incision is neither the incised integrity of a beginning, or of a simple cutting into, nor simple secondarity. Neither/nor: that is simultaneously either or; the mark is also the marginal limit, the march, etc.). In fact, I attempt to bring the critical operation to bear against the unceasing reappropriation of this work of the simulacrum by a dialectics of the Hegelian type (Which even idealizes and "semantizes" the value of work), for Hegelian idealism consists precisely of a releve of the binary oppositions of classical idealism, a resolution of contradiction into a third term that comes in order to aufheben, to deny while raising up, while idealizing, while sublimating into an anamnesic interiority (Errinnerung), while interning difference in a self-presence."...</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1980s, deconstruction was being put to use in a range of theoretical enterprises in the humanities and social sciences,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/155306/deconstruction<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Encyclopaedia Brittanica<space/></arg><arg name="title">Deconstruction (Criticism)</arg></template></extension><space/>including law<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida 1992pp3-67"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="others">translated by Mary Quaintance, eds., Drucilla Cornell, Michael Rosenfeld, and David Gray Carlson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Deconstruction and the Possibility of Justice<space/></arg><arg name="edition">1st<space/></arg><arg name="year">1992<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0810103974<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Force of Law<space/></arg><arg name="pages">3–67<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="quote">A decision that did not go through the ordeal of the undecidable would not be a free decision, it would only be the programmable application or unfolding of a calculable process (...) deconstructs from the inside every assurance of presence, and thus every criteriology that would assure us of the justice of the decision.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/bridge/CriticalTheory/critical2.htm'>&quot;Critical Legal Studies Movement&quot;</link><space/>in &quot;The Bridge&quot;</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.germanlawjournal.com/index.php?pageID=13&amp;amp;vol=6&amp;amp;no=1'>GERMAN LAW JOURNAL, SPECIAL ISSUE: A DEDICATION TO JACQUES DERRIDA</link>, Vol. 6 No. 1 Pages 1 - 243 1 January 2005</extension><space/>anthropology,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Legacies of Derrida: Anthropology&quot;, Rosalind C. Morris,<space/><italics>Annual Review of Anthropology</italics>, Volume: 36, pages: 35589, 2007</extension><space/>historiography,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Deconstructing History&quot;, published 1997, 2nd. Edn. Routledge, 2006</extension><space/>linguistics,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Busch 2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Busch<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Brigitt<space/></arg><arg name="title">Linguistic Repertoire Revisited<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Applied Linguistics<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://applij.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2012/10/04/applin.ams056.full</arg></template></extension><space/>sociolinguistics,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The sociolinguistics of schooling: the relevance of Derrida's Monolingualism of the Other or the Prosthesis of Origin&quot;, Michael Evans, 01/2012; ISBN 978-3-0343-1009-3 In book: The Sociolinguistics of Language Education in International Contexts, Publisher: Peter Lang, Editors: Edith Esch and Martin Solly, pp.&amp;nbsp;3146</extension><space/>psychoanalysis, feminism, and LGBT studies. In the continental philosophy tradition, debates surrounding ontology, epistemology, ethics, aesthetics, hermeneutics, and philosophy of language still refer to it today. Within architecture it has inspired deconstructivism, and it remains important in general within art,<extension extension_name='ref'>E.g., &quot;Doris Salcedo&quot;, Phaidon (2004), &quot;Hans Haacke&quot;, Phaidon (2000)</extension><space/>music,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Deconstruction in Music - The Jacques Derrida&quot;, Gerd Zacher Encounter, Rotterdam, The Netherlands, 2002</extension><space/>and literary criticism.<extension extension_name='ref'>E.g. &quot;The return of the real&quot;, Hal Foster, October - MIT Press (1996); &quot;Kant after Duchamp&quot;, Thierry de Duve, October - MIT Press (1996); &quot;Neo-Avantgarde and Cultural Industry - Essays on European and American Art from 1955 to 1975&quot;, Benjamin H.D. Buchloh, October - MIT Press (2000); &quot;Perpetual Inventory&quot;, Rosalind E. Krauss, October - MIT Press, 2010</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>Derrida's original use of the word &quot;deconstruction&quot; was a translation of<space/><italics><link><target>Destruktion</target></link></italics>, a concept from the work of<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link><space/>that Derrida sought to apply to textual reading. Heidegger's term referred to a process of exploring the categories and concepts that tradition has imposed on a word, and the history behind them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heidegger27S21-23"><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link><space/>(1927)<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Time</target></link></italics>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=S57m5gW0L-MC'>Introduction</link>, part II.5, 21-23</extension><space/>Derrida opted for<space/><italics>deconstruction</italics><space/>over the literal translation<space/><italics>destruction</italics><space/>to suggest precision rather than violence.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Deconstruction according to Derrida</heading><heading level='3'>Basic philosophical concerns</heading><paragraph>Derrida's concerns flow from a consideration of several issues:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>A desire to contribute to the re-valuation of all western values, built on the 18th century Kantian critique of reason, and carried forward to the 19th century, in its more radical implications, by<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target><part>Kierkegaard</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target><part>Nietzsche</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>An assertion that texts outlive their authors, and become part of a set of cultural habits equal to, if not surpassing, the importance of authorial intent.</listitem><listitem>A re-valuation of certain classic western dialectics: poetry vs. philosophy, reason vs. revelation, structure vs. creativity,<space/><link><target>episteme</target></link><space/>vs.<space/><link><target>techne</target></link>, etc.</listitem></list><paragraph>To this end, Derrida follows a long line of modern philosophers, who look backwards to Plato and his influence on the western metaphysical tradition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PostModernPlatos"><italics>Post-Modern Platos</italics><space/>by Catherine H. Zuckert, Chigago: University of Chicago Press, 1996, chapter 7.</extension><space/>Like Nietzsche, Derrida suspects Plato of dissimulation in the service of a political project, namely the education, through critical reflections, of a class of citizens more strategically positioned to influence the polis. However, like Nietzsche, Derrida is not satisfied merely with such a political interpretation of Plato, because of the particular dilemma modern humans find themselves stuck in. His Platonic reflections are inseparably part of his critique of modernity, hence the attempt to be something beyond the modern, because of this Nietzschian sense that the modern has lost its way and become mired in nihilism.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Diffrance</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Différance</arg></template>Diffrance is an important idea within deconstruction, it is the observation that the meanings of words come from their<space/><link><target>Synchrony and diachrony</target><part>synchronity</part></link><space/>with other words within the language and their<space/><link><target>Synchrony and diachrony</target><part>diachrony</part></link><space/>between contemporary and historical definitions of a word. Understanding language according Derrida required an understanding of both viewpoints of linguistic analysis. The focus on diachronity has led to accusations against Derrida of engaging in the<space/><link><target>Etymological fallacy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Soskice, Janet M (1987), Metaphor and Religious Language, Oxford University Press, ISBN 978-0198249825, pp.&amp;nbsp;80-82.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There is one statement by Derrida which has been of great interest to his opponents, and which appeared in an essay on<space/><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target><part>Rousseau</part></link><space/>(part of the highly influential<space/><italics><link><target>Of Grammatology</target></link></italics>, 1967),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida67p158"></extension><space/>It is the assertion that &quot;there is no outside-text&quot; (<italics>il n'y a pas de hors-texte</italics>),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Derrida67p158">Derrida (1967)<space/><italics>Of Grammatology</italics>, Part II &quot;Introduction to the &quot;Age of Rousseau,&quot; section 2 &quot;...That Dangerous Supplement...&quot;, title: &quot;The Exorbitant. Question of Method:, pp.&amp;nbsp;15859, 163</extension><space/>which is often mistranslated as &quot;there is nothing outside of the text&quot;. The mistranslation is often used to suggest Derrida believes that nothing exists but words.<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link>, for instance, famously misattributed to Derrida the very different phrase &quot;Il n'y a rien en dehors du text&quot; for this purpose.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;<italics>Mon corps, ce papier, ce feu</italics>,&quot; in the 1972 edition of Foucault's<space/><link><target>Madness and Civilization</target><part>''Histoire de la folie l'ge classique''</part></link><space/>(Paris: Gallimard, p.&amp;nbsp;602)</extension><space/>According to Derrida, his statement simply refers to the unavoidability of context that is at the heart of diffrance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Afterword88P136">Derrida (1988),<space/><italics>Afterword</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;136.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For example, the word &quot;house&quot; derives its meaning more as a function of how it differs from &quot;shed&quot;, &quot;mansion&quot;, &quot;hotel&quot;, &quot;building&quot;, etc. (Form of Content, that<space/><link><target>Louis Hjelmslev</target></link><space/>distinguished from Form of Expression) than how the word &quot;house&quot; may be tied to a certain image of a traditional house (i.e. the relationship between<space/><link><target>Sign (linguistics)</target><part>signifier</part></link><space/>and signified) with each term being established in reciprocal determination with the other terms than by an ostensive description or definition: when can we talk about a &quot;house&quot; or a &quot;mansion&quot; or a &quot;shed&quot;? The same can be said about verbs, in all the languages in the world: when should we stop saying &quot;walk&quot; and start saying &quot;run&quot;? The same happens, of course, with adjectives: when must we stop saying &quot;yellow&quot; and start saying &quot;orange&quot;, or exchange &quot;past&quot; for &quot;present? Not only are the topological differences between the words relevant here, but the differentials between what is signified is also covered by diffrance.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus, complete meaning is always &quot;differential&quot; and<space/><italics>postponed</italics><space/>in language; there is never a moment when meaning is complete and total. A simple example would consist of looking up a given word in a dictionary, then proceeding to look up the words found in that word's definition, etc., also comparing with older dictionaries from different periods in time, and such a process would never end.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Metaphysics of presence</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Metaphysics of presence</arg></template>Derrida describe the task of deconstruction as the identification of metaphysics of presence or<space/><italics>logocentrism</italics><space/>in western philosophy. Metaphysics of presence is the desire for immediate access to meaning, the privileging of presence over absence. This means that there is an assumed bias in certain binary oppositions where one side is placed in a position of one over another, such as good over bad, speech over the written word, male over female among other oppositions. Derrida writes, &quot;Without a doubt, Aristotle thinks of time on the basis of ousia as parousia, on the basis of the now, the point, etc. And yet an entire reading could be organized that would repeat in Aristotle's text both this limitation and its opposite.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Ousia and Gramm: Note on a Note from 'Being and Time,'&quot; in &quot;Margins of Philosophy,&quot; 29-67: 61</extension><space/>To Derrida the central bias of logocentrism was the now being placed as more important than the future or past. This argument is largely based on the earlier work of Heidegger, who in<space/><italics>Being and Time</italics><space/>claimed that the theoretical attitude of pure presence is parasitical upon a more originary involvement with the world in concepts such as the<space/><link><target>ready-to-hand</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>being-with</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Related works by Derrida</heading><paragraph>Derrida published a number of works directly relevant to the concept of deconstruction,<space/><italics><link><target>Of Grammatology</target></link></italics><space/>was the book that introduced the idea of Deconstruction. Derrida went on to write many other books showing deconstruction in action or defining it more completely such as<space/><italics><link><target>Diffrance</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Speech and Phenomena</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Writing and Difference</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Application of deconstruction</heading><paragraph>Derrida's observation have had a large influence on literary criticism and post-structuralism.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Literary criticism</heading><paragraph>Derrida's method consisted in demonstrating all the forms and varieties of the originary complexity of<space/><link><target>semiotics</target></link>, and their multiple consequences in many fields. His way of achieving this was by conducting thorough, careful, sensitive, and yet transformational readings of philosophical and literary texts, with an ear to what in those texts runs counter to their apparent systematicity (structural unity) or intended sense (authorial genesis). By demonstrating the<space/><link><target>aporia</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and ellipses of thought, Derrida hoped to show the infinitely subtle ways that this originary complexity, which by definition cannot ever be completely known, works its structuring and destructuring effects.<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph><link><target>Rodolphe Gasch</target></link>, &quot;Infrastructures and Systematicity,&quot; in<space/><link><target>John Sallis</target></link><space/>(ed.),<space/><italics>Deconstruction and Philosophy</italics><space/>(Chicago &amp; London: University of Chicago Press, 1987), pp.&amp;nbsp;34:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>One of the more persistent misunderstandings that has thus far forestalled a productive debate with Derrida's philosophical thought is the assumption, shared by many philosophers as well as literary critics, that within that thought just anything is possible. Derrida's philosophy is more often than not construed as a license for arbitrary free play in flagrant disregard of all established rules of argumentation, traditional requirements of thought, and ethical standards binding upon the interpretative community. Undoubtedly, some of the works of Derrida may not have been entirely innocent in this respect, and may have contributed, however obliquely, to fostering to some extent that very misconception. But deconstruction which for many has come to designate the content and style of Derrida's thinking, reveals to even a superficial examination, a well-ordered procedure, a step-by-step type of argumentation based on an acute awareness of level-distinctions, a marked thoroughness and regularity. [...] Deconstruction must be understood, we contend, as the attempt to "account," in a certain manner, for a heterogeneous variety or manifold of nonlogical contradictions and discursive equalities of all sorts that continues to haunt and fissure even the ''successful'' development of philosophical arguments and their systematic exposition.</arg></template></paragraph></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Deconstruction denotes the<space/><link><target>Hermeneutics</target><part>pursuing of the meaning</part></link><space/>of a text to the point of exposing the supposed contradictions and internal oppositions upon which it is foundedsupposedly showing that those foundations are irreducibly complex, unstable, or impossible. It is an approach that may be deployed in philosophy, in<space/><link><target>literary analysis</target></link>, and even in the analysis of scientific writings.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marian Hobson,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=Kl146cNpzNQC&amp;amp;pg=PA51'>''Jacques Derrida: Opening Lines''</link>, Routledge, 2012, p.&amp;nbsp;51.</extension><space/>Deconstruction generally tries to demonstrate that any text is not a discrete whole but contains several irreconcilable and contradictory meanings; that any text therefore has more than one interpretation; that the text itself links these interpretations inextricably; that the incompatibility of these interpretations is irreducible; and thus that an interpretative reading cannot go beyond a certain point. Derrida refers to this point as an &quot;aporia&quot; in the text; thus, deconstructive reading is termed &quot;aporetic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Mark Currie,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=i3ecdVgknGkC&amp;amp;pg=PA80'>''The Invention of Deconstruction''</link>, Palgrave Macmillan, 2013, p.&amp;nbsp;80.</extension><space/>He insists that meaning is made possible by the relations of a word to other words within the network of structures that language is.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ramberg, Bjrn and Kristin Gjesdal,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/hermeneutics/#Semiotics'>&quot;Hermeneutics&quot;</link>, Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, 2003, 2005.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Derrida initially resisted granting to his approach the overarching name &quot;deconstruction,&quot; on the grounds that it was a precise technical term that could not be used to characterize his work generally. Nevertheless, he eventually accepted that the term had come into common use to refer to his textual approach, and Derrida himself increasingly began to use the term in this more general way.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Critique of structuralism</heading><paragraph>Derrida's lecture at<space/><link><target>Johns Hopkins University</target></link>, &quot;<link><target>Structure, Sign, and Play in the Discourse of the Human Sciences</target><part>Structure, Sign, and Play in the Human Sciences</part></link>,&quot; often appears in collections as a manifesto against structuralism. Derrida's essay was one of the earliest to propose some theoretical limitations to structuralism, and to attempt to theorize on terms that were clearly no longer structuralist. Structuralism viewed language as a number of signs, composed of a signified (the meaning) and a signifier (the word itself). Derrida proposed that signs always referred to other signs, existing only in relation to each other, and there was therefore no ultimate foundation or centre, this is the basis of<space/><link><target>diffrance</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derrida, &quot;Structure, Sign, and Play&quot; (1966), as printed/translated by Macksey &amp; Donato (1970)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Development after Derrida</heading><heading level='4'>The Yale School</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Yale school</arg></template>Between the late 1960s and the early 1980s many thinkers were influenced by deconstruction, including<space/><link><target>Paul de Man</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Hartman</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>J. Hillis Miller</target></link>. This group came to be known as the<space/><link><target>Yale school (deconstruction)</target><part>Yale school</part></link><space/>and was especially influential in<space/><link><target>literary criticism</target></link>. Several of these theorists were subsequently affiliated with the<space/><link><target>University of California Irvine</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Miller has described deconstruction this way: &quot;Deconstruction is not a dismantling of the structure of a text, but a demonstration that it has already dismantled itself. Its apparently solid ground is no rock, but thin air.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Hillis Miller, &quot;Stevens' Rock and Criticism as Cure,&quot;<space/><italics>Georgia Review</italics><space/>30 (1976), p.&amp;nbsp;34.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Critical legal studies movement</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Critical legal studies</arg></template>Arguing that law and politics cannot be separated, the founders of &quot;Critical Legal Studies Movement&quot; found necessary to criticize its absence at the level of theory. To demonstrate the<space/><link><target>Indeterminacy (philosophy)</target><part>indeterminacy</part></link><space/>of legal doctrine, these scholars often adopts a method, such as<space/><link><target>structuralism</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>linguistics</target></link><space/>or deconstruction in<space/><link><target>Continental philosophy</target></link>, to make explicit the deep structure of categories and tensions at work in legal texts and talk. The aim was to deconstruct the tensions and procedures by which they are constructed, expressed, and deployed.</paragraph><paragraph>For example,<space/><link><target>Duncan Kennedy (legal philosopher)</target><part>Duncan Kennedy</part></link>, in explicit reference to semiotics and deconstruction procedures, maintains that various legal doctrines are constructed around the binary pairs of opposed concepts, each of which with a claim upon intuitive and formal forms of reasoning that must be made explicit, not only in their meaning but also its relative value, and criticized. Self and other, private and public, subjective and objective, freedom and control are examples of such pairs demonstrating the influence of this opposing concepts on the development of legal doctrines through history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Critical Legal Studies Movement">&quot;<link type='external' href='http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/bridge/CriticalTheory/critical2.htm'>Critical Legal Studies Movement</link>&quot; in &quot;The Bridge&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Deconstructing History</italics></heading><paragraph>Deconstructive readings of history and sources have changed the entire discipline of history. In &quot;Deconstructing History&quot;,<space/><link><target>Alun Munslow</target></link><space/>examines history in what he argues is a postmodern age. He provides an introduction to the debates and issues of postmodernist history. He also surveys the latest research into the relationship between the past, history, and historical practice, as well as forwarding his own challenging theories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Edn. Routledge 2006">&quot;Deconstructing History&quot;, published 1997, 2nd. Edn. Routledge, 2006)</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>The Inoperative Community</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>Jean-Luc Nancy</target></link><space/>argues in his 1982 book<space/><italics>The Inoperative Community</italics><space/>for an understanding of community and society that is undeconstructable because it is prior to conceptualisation. Nancy's work is an important development of deconstruction because it takes the challenge of deconstruction seriously and attempts to develop an understanding of political terms that is undeconstructable and therefore suitable for a philosophy after Derrida.</paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>The Ethics of Deconstruction</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>Simon Critchley</target></link><space/>argues in his 1992 book (2nd edition: 1999; 3rd edition: 2014)<space/><italics>The Ethics of Deconstruction</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Critchley<space/></arg><arg name="first">Simon<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Ethics of Deconstruction: Derrida and Levinas, 3rd Edition<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.euppublishing.com/book/9780748689323<space/></arg><arg name="location">Edinburgh<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Edinburgh University Press<space/></arg><arg name="page">352<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780748689323</arg></template></extension><space/>that Derrida's deconstruction is an intrinsically ethical practice. Critchley argues that deconstruction involves an openness to the<space/><link><target>Other</target></link><space/>that makes it ethical in the<space/><link><target>Emmanuel Levinas</target><part>Levinasian</part></link><space/>understanding of the term.</paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Derrida and the Political</italics></heading><paragraph>Jacques Derrida has had a huge influence on contemporary political theory and political philosophy. Derrida's thinking has inspired Slavoj Zizek, Richard Rorty, Ernesto Laclau, Judith Butler and many more contemporary theorists developed a deconstructive approach to politics. Because deconstruction examines the internal logic of any given text or discourse it helped many authors to analyse the contradictions inherent in all schools of thought, and as such it has proved revolutionary in political analysis, particularly ideology critiques.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Politics of Deconstruction: Jacques Derrida and the Other of Philosophy [Paperback] Martin McQuillan (Editor)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Richard Beardsworth, developing on Critchley's<space/><italics>Ethics of Deconstruction</italics>, argues in his 1996<space/><italics>Derrida and the Political</italics><space/>that deconstruction is an intrinsically political practice. He further argues that the future of deconstruction faces a choice (perhaps an undecidable choice) between a<space/><link><target>deconstruction-and-religion</target><part>theological</part></link><space/>approach and a technological approach represented first of all by the work of<space/><link><target>Bernard Stiegler</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Difficulty of definition</heading><paragraph>There have been problems defining deconstruction. Derrida claimed that all of his essays were attempts to define what deconstruction is,<extension extension_name='ref'>Derrida, 1985, p.&amp;nbsp;4</extension><space/>and that deconstruction is necessarily complicated and difficult to explain since it actively criticises the very language needed to explain it.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Deconstruction and dialectics</heading><paragraph>In the deconstruction procedure, one of the main concerns of Derrida is not to collapse into Hegel's dialectic where these oppositions would be reduced to contradictions in a dialectic that has the purpose of resolving it into a synthesis.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. Jacques Derrida, &quot;Interview with Jean-Louis Houdebine and Guy Scarpetta,&quot; in &quot;Positions&quot; (The University of Chicago Press, 1981), p.&amp;nbsp;43:<template><target>quotation</target><arg><space/>If there were a definition of ''differance'', it would be precisely the limit, the interruption, the destruction of the Hegelian ''releve'' wherever it operates. What is at stake here is enormous. I emphasize the Hegelian ''Aufhebung'', such as it is interpreted by a certain Hegelian discourse, for it goes without saying that the double meaning of Aufhebung could be written otherwise. Whence its proximity to all the operations conducted against Hegel's dialectical speculation.<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The presence of Hegelian dialectics was enormous in the intellectual life of France during the second half of the 20th century with the influence of Kojve and Hyppolite, but also with the impact of dialectics based on contradiction developed by Marxists, and including the existentialism from Sartre, etc. This explains Derrida's concern to always distinguish his procedure from Hegel's,<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. Jacques Derrida, &quot;Interview with Jean-Louis Houdebine and Guy Scarpetta,&quot; in &quot;Positions&quot; (The University of Chicago Press, 1981), p.&amp;nbsp;43.</extension><space/>since Hegelianism believes binary oppositions would produce a synthesis, while Derrida saw binary oppositions as incapable of collapsing into a synthesis free from the original contradiction.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Derrida's &quot;negative&quot; descriptions</heading><paragraph>Derrida has been more forthcoming with negative (<link><target>wikt:apophatic</target><part>apophatic</part></link>) than positive descriptions of deconstruction. When asked by<space/><link><target>Toshihiko Izutsu</target></link><space/>some preliminary considerations on how to translate &quot;deconstruction&quot; in Japanese, in order to at least prevent going contrary to its actual meaning, Derrida therefore began his response by saying that such question amounts to &quot;what deconstruction is not, or rather<space/><italics>ought</italics><space/>not to be.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP1">Derrida [1983], p.&amp;nbsp;1</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Derrida states that deconstruction is not an analysis, a critique, or a method<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3">Derrida [1983], p.&amp;nbsp;3</extension><space/>in the traditional sense that philosophy understands these terms. In these negative descriptions of deconstruction Derrida is seeking to &quot;multiply the cautionary indicators and put aside all the traditional philosophical concepts.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>This does not mean that deconstruction has absolutely nothing in common with an analysis, a critique, or a method because while Derrida distances deconstruction from these terms, he reaffirms &quot;the necessity of returning to them, at least under erasure.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>Derrida's necessity of returning to a term<space/><link><target>sous rature</target><part>under erasure</part></link><space/>means that even though these terms are problematic we must use them until they can be effectively reformulated or replaced. The relevance of the tradition of negative theology to Derrida's preference for negative descriptions of deconstruction is the notion that a positive description of deconstruction would over-determine the idea of deconstruction and that this would be a mistake because it would close off the openness that Derrida wishes to preserve for deconstruction. This means that if Derrida were to positively define deconstruction as, for example, a critique then this would put the concept of critique for ever outside the possibility of deconstruction. Some new philosophy beyond deconstruction would then be required in order to surpass the notion of critique.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Not a method</heading><paragraph>Derrida states that &quot;Deconstruction is not a method, and cannot be transformed into one.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>This is because deconstruction is not a mechanical operation. Derrida warns against considering deconstruction as a mechanical operation when he states that &quot;It is true that in certain circles (university or cultural, especially in the United States) the technical and methodological &quot;metaphor&quot; that seems necessarily attached to the very word &quot;deconstruction&quot; has been able to seduce or lead astray.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>Commentator Richard Beardsworth explains that:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Derrida is careful to avoid this term [method] because it carries connotations of a procedural form of judgement. A thinker with a method has already decided<space/><italics>how</italics><space/>to proceed, is unable to give him or herself up to the matter of thought in hand, is a functionary of the criteria which structure his or her conceptual gestures. For Derrida [...] this is irresponsibility itself. Thus, to talk of a method in relation to deconstruction, especially regarding its ethico-political implications, would appear to go directly against the current of Derrida's philosophical adventure.<extension extension_name='ref'>Beardsworth, R. 1996.<space/><italics>Derrida and the Political</italics>. London and New York: Routledge, p.&amp;nbsp;4.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Beardsworth here explains that it would be irresponsible to undertake a deconstruction with a complete set of rules that need only be applied as a method to the object of deconstruction because this understanding would reduce deconstruction to a thesis of the reader that the text is then made to fit. This would be an irresponsible act of reading because it becomes a prejudicial procedure that only finds what it sets out to find.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Not a critique</heading><paragraph>Derrida states that deconstruction is not a<space/><link><target>critique</target></link><space/>in the Kantian sense.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>This is because<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link><space/>defines the term critique as the opposite of<space/><link><target>dogmatism</target></link>. For Derrida it is not possible to escape the dogmatic baggage of the language we use in order to perform a pure critique in the Kantian sense. For Derrida language is dogmatic because it is inescapably<space/><link><target>Metaphysics</target><part>metaphysical</part></link>. Derrida argues that language is inescapably metaphysical because it is made up of<space/><link><target>Sign (linguistics)</target><part>signifiers</part></link><space/>that only refer to that which transcends them the signified.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>In addition Derrida asks rhetorically &quot;Is not the idea of knowledge and of the acquisition of knowledge in itself metaphysical?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Derrida, J., 1973.<space/><italics>Speech and Phenomena</italics>. Trans. D.B. Allison. Evanston: Northwestern UP, p.&amp;nbsp;5.</extension><space/>By this Derrida means that all claims to know something necessarily involve an assertion of the metaphysical type that something<space/><italics>is</italics><space/>the case somewhere. For Derrida the concept of neutrality is suspect and dogmatism is therefore involved in everything to a certain degree. Deconstruction can challenge a particular dogmatism and hence desediment dogmatism in general, but it cannot escape all dogmatism all at once.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Not an analysis</heading><paragraph>Derrida states that deconstruction is not an<space/><link><target>analysis</target></link><space/>in the traditional sense.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>This is because the possibility of analysis is predicated on the possibility of breaking up the text being analysed into elemental component parts. Derrida argues that there are no self-sufficient units of meaning in a text. This is because individual words or sentences in a text can only be properly understood in terms of how they fit into the larger structure of the text and language itself. For more on Derrida's theory of meaning see the page on<space/><link><target>diffrance</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Not post-structuralist</heading><paragraph>Derrida states that his use of the word deconstruction first took place in a context in which &quot;<link><target>structuralism</target></link><space/>was dominant&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat">Derrida [1983], p.&amp;nbsp;2</extension><space/>and its use is related to this context. Derrida states that deconstruction is an &quot;antistructuralist gesture&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat"></extension><space/>because &quot;Structures were to be undone, decomposed, desedimented.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat"></extension><space/>At the same time for Derrida deconstruction is also a &quot;structuralist gesture&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat"></extension><space/>because it is concerned with the structure of texts. So for Derrida deconstruction involves &quot;a certain attention to structures&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat"></extension><space/>and tries to &quot;understand how an 'ensemble' was constituted.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>As both a structuralist and an antistructuralist gesture deconstruction is tied up with what Derrida calls the &quot;structural problematic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="xbkhat"></extension><space/>The structural problematic for Derrida is the tension between genesis, that which is &quot;in the essential mode of creation or movement,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="mcoctr"></extension><space/>and structure, &quot;systems, or complexes, or static configurations.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="mcoctr">Derrida, J., 1978. &quot;'Genesis and Structure' and Phenomenology&quot; from<space/><italics>Writing and Difference</italics><space/>trans. Alan Bass. London &amp; New York: Routledge, p.&amp;nbsp;194.</extension><space/>An example of genesis would be the<space/><link><target>sense</target><part>sensory</part></link><space/><link><target>idea</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from which knowledge is then derived in the<space/><link><target>empirical</target></link><space/><link><target>epistemology</target></link>. An example of structure would be a<space/><link><target>binary opposition</target></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>good and evil</target></link><space/>where the meaning of each element is established, at least partly, through its relationship to the other element.</paragraph><paragraph>It is for this reason that Derrida distances his use of the term deconstruction from<space/><link><target>post-structuralism</target></link>, a term that would suggest philosophy could simply go beyond structuralism. Derrida states that &quot;the motif of deconstruction has been associated with &quot;post-structuralism&quot; but that this term was &quot;a word unknown in France until its &quot;return&quot; from the United States.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LetterToIzutsuP3"></extension><space/>Derrida's deconstruction of Husserl Derrida actually argues<space/><italics>for</italics><space/>the contamination of pure origins by the structures of language and temporality and<space/><link><target>Manfred Frank</target></link><space/>has even referred to Derrida's work as &quot;Neostructuralism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Frank, M., 1989. What is Neostructuralism? Trans. S. Wilke &amp; R. Gray. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Alternative definitions</heading><paragraph>The popularity of the term deconstruction combined with the technical difficulty of Derrida's primary material on deconstruction and his reluctance to elaborate his understanding of the term has meant that many secondary sources have attempted to give a more straightforward explanation than Derrida himself ever attempted. Secondary definitions are therefore an interpretation of deconstruction by the person offering them rather than a direct summary of Derrida's actual position.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paul de Man</target></link><space/>was a member of the<space/><link><target>Yale School</target></link><space/>and a prominent practitioner of deconstruction as he understood it. His definition of deconstruction is that, &quot;[i]t's possible, within text, to frame a question or undo assertions made in the text, by means of elements which are in the text, which frequently would be precisely structures that play off the rhetorical against grammatical elements.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>De Man, in Moynihan 1986, p.&amp;nbsp;156.</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Rorty</target></link><space/>was a prominent interpreter of Derrida's philosophy. His definition of deconstruction is that, &quot;the term 'deconstruction' refers in the first instance to the way in which the 'accidental' features of a text can be seen as betraying, subverting, its purportedly 'essential' message.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rorty 1995<template><target>page needed</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>(The word<space/><italics>accidental</italics><space/>is used here in the sense of<space/><italics>incidental</italics>.)</listitem><listitem><link><target>John D. Caputo</target></link><space/>attempts to explain deconstruction in a nutshell by stating:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;Whenever deconstruction finds a nutshella secure axiom or a pithy maximthe very idea is to crack it open and disturb this tranquility. Indeed, that is a good rule of thumb in deconstruction.<space/><italics>That</italics><space/>is what deconstruction is all about, its very meaning and mission, if it has any. One might even say that cracking nutshells is what deconstruction<space/><italics>is</italics>. In a nutshell. ...Have we not run up against a paradox and an<space/><link><target>aporia</target></link><space/>[something contradictory]...the paralysis and impossibility of an aporia is just what impels deconstruction, what rouses it out of bed in the morning...&quot; (Caputo 1997, p.32)</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Niall Lucy</target></link><space/>points to the impossibility of defining the term at all, stating:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;While in a sense it<space/><italics>is</italics><space/>impossibly difficult to define, the impossibility has less to do with the adoption of a position or the assertion of a choice on deconstruction's part than with the impossibility of every 'is' as such. Deconstruction begins, as it were, from a refusal of the authority or determining power of every 'is', or simply from a refusal of authority in general. While such refusal may indeed count as a position, it is not the case that deconstruction holds this as a sort of 'preference'&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Niall Lucy,<space/><italics>A Derrida Dictionary</italics><space/>(Oxford: Blackwell, 2004).</extension></extension></listitem><listitem>David B. Allison is an early translator of Derrida and states in the introduction to his translation of<space/><italics>Speech and Phenomena</italics>:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>[Deconstruction] signifies a project of critical thought whose task is to locate and 'take apart' those concepts which serve as the axioms or rules for a period of thought, those concepts which command the unfolding of an entire epoch of metaphysics. 'Deconstruction' is somewhat less negative than the Heideggerian or Nietzschean terms 'destruction' or 'reversal'; it suggests that certain foundational concepts of metaphysics will never be entirely eliminated...There is no simple 'overcoming' of metaphysics or the language of metaphysics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Introduction by Allison, in Derrida, 1973, p.&amp;nbsp;xxxii, n. 1.</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Ricur</target></link><space/>defines deconstruction as a way of uncovering the questions behind the answers of a text or tradition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Klein 1995<template><target>page needed</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Richard Ellmann defines 'deconstruction' as the systematic undoing of understanding.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>A survey of the secondary literature reveals a wide range of heterogeneous arguments. Particularly problematic are the attempts to give neat introductions to deconstruction by people trained in literary criticism who sometimes have little or no expertise in the relevant areas of philosophy that Derrida is working in relation to. These secondary works (e.g.<space/><italics>Deconstruction for Beginners</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="powell/lee">Powell, James and Lee, Joe,<space/><italics>Deconstruction for Beginners</italics><space/>(Writers &amp; Readers Publishing, 2005)</extension><space/>and<space/><italics>Deconstructions: A User's Guide</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="royle">Royle, Nicholas,<space/><italics>Deconstructions: A User's Guide</italics><space/>(Palgrave Macmillan, 2000)</extension>) have attempted to explain deconstruction while being academically criticized as too far removed from the original texts and Derrida's actual position.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>In an effort to clarify the rather muddled reception of the term deconstruction Derrida specifies what deconstruction<space/><italics>is not</italics><space/>through a number of negative definitions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Influences</heading><paragraph>Derrida's theories on deconstruction were themselves influenced by the work of linguists such as<space/><link><target>Ferdinand de Saussure</target></link><space/>(whose writings on<space/><link><target>semiotics</target></link><space/>also became a cornerstone of structuralist theory in the mid-20th century) and literary theorists such as<space/><link><target>Roland Barthes</target></link><space/>(whose works were an investigation of the logical ends of structuralist thought). Derrida's views on deconstruction stood opposed to the theories of structuralists such as psychoanalytic theorist<space/><link><target>Jacques Lacan</target></link>, linguist<space/><link><target>Claude Lvi-Strauss</target></link>, and political and social theorist<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link>. However, Derrida resisted attempts to label his work as &quot;<link><target>Post-structuralism</target><part>post-structuralist</part></link>&quot;.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">Correct but this entire paragraph needs references</arg><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Influence of Nietzsche</heading><paragraph>In order to understand Derrida's motivation, one must refer to Nietzsche's philosophy.</paragraph><paragraph>Nietzsche's project began with Orpheus, the man underground. This foil to Platonic light was deliberately and self-consciously lauded in<space/><italics>Daybreak</italics>, when Nietzsche announces, albeit retrospectively, &quot;In this work you will discover a subterranean man at work,&quot; and then goes on to map the project of unreason: &quot;All things that live long are gradually so saturated with reason that their origin in unreason thereby becomes improbable. Does not almost every precise history of an origination impress our feelings as paradoxical and wantonly offensive? Does the good historian not, at bottom, constantly contradict?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Daybreak: Thoughts on the Prejudices of Morality</italics>. Friedrich Nietzsche, translated by R.J. Hollisdale. Cambridge University Press, 1997.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nietzsche's point in<space/><italics>Daybreak</italics><space/>is that standing at the end of modern history, modern thinkers know too much to be deceived by the illusion of reason any more. Reason, logic, philosophy and science are no longer solely sufficient as the royal roads to truth. And so Nietzsche decides to throw it in our faces, and uncover the truth of Plato, that he unlike Orpheus just happened to discover his true love in the light instead of in the dark. This being merely one historical event amongst many, Nietzsche proposes that we revisualize the history of the west as the history of a series of political moves, that is, a manifestation of the will to power, that at bottom have no greater or lesser claim to truth in any noumenal (absolute) sense. By calling our attention to the fact that he has assumed the role of Orpheus, the man underground, in dialectical opposition to Plato, Nietzsche hopes to sensitize us to the political and cultural context, and the political influences that impact authorship. For example, the political influences that led one author to choose philosophy over poetry (or at least<space/><italics>portray</italics><space/>himself as having made such a choice), and another to make a different choice.</paragraph><paragraph>The problem with Nietzsche, as Derrida sees it, is that he did not go far enough. That he missed the fact that this will to power is itself but a manifestation of the operation of writing. And so Derrida wishes to help us step beyond Nietzsche's penultimate revaluation of all western values, to the ultimate, which is the final appreciation of &quot;the role of writing in the production of knowledge.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="PostModernPlatos"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Influence of Saussure</heading><paragraph>Derrida approaches all texts as constructed around elemental oppositions which all<space/><link><target>discourse</target></link><space/>has to articulate if it intends to make any sense whatsoever. This is so because identity is viewed in<space/><link><target>Non-essentialism</target><part>non-essentialist</part></link><space/>terms as a construct, and because constructs only produce meaning through the interplay of<space/><link><target>differences</target><part>difference</part></link><space/>inside a &quot;system of distinct signs&quot;. This approach to text is influenced by the<space/><link><target>semiology</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ferdinand de Saussure</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Royle04p62"><link><target>Nicholas Royle</target><part>Royle, Nicholas</part></link><space/>(2004)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=nNaSdb9VMTwC&amp;amp;pg=PA62'>''Jacques Derrida''</link>, Routledge, 2003, pp.&amp;nbsp;6263</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferraris97p76"><paragraph>Derrida and Ferraris (1997), p.&amp;nbsp;76:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>I take great interest in questions of language and rhetoric, and I think they deserve enormous consideration; but there is a point where the authority of final jurisdiction is neither rhetorical nor linguistic, nor even discursive. The notion of trace or of text is introduced to mark the limits of the linguistic turn. This is one more reason why I prefer to speak of 'mark' rather than of language. In the first place the mark is not anthropological; it is prelinguistic; it is the possibility of language, and it is every where there is a relation to another thing or relation to an other. For such relations, the mark has no need of language.</arg></template></paragraph></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Saussure is considered one of the fathers of<space/><link><target>structuralism</target></link><space/>when he explained that terms get their meaning in reciprocal determination with other terms inside language:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>In language there are only differences. Even more important: a difference generally implies positive terms between which the difference is set up; but in language there are only differences without positive terms. Whether we take the signified or the signifier, language has neither ideas nor sounds that existed before the linguistic system, but only conceptual and phonic differences that have issued from the system. The idea or phonic substance that a sign contains is of less importance than the other signs that surround it. [...] A linguistic system is a series of differences of sound combined with a series of differences of ideas; but the pairing of a certain number of acoustical signs with as many cuts made from the mass thought engenders a system of values.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Saussure 1916 trans. 1959 12122"></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Saussure explicitly suggested that linguistics was only a branch of a more general semiology, of a science of signs in general, being human codes only one among others. Nevertheless, in the end, as Derrida pointed out, he made of linguistics &quot;the regulatory model&quot;, and &quot;for essential, and essentially metaphysical, reasons had to privilege speech, and everything that links the sign to phone&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. Jacques Derrida, &quot;Interview with Julia Kristeva&quot; in &quot;Positions&quot; (The University of Chicago Press, 1981), p.&amp;nbsp;21:<template><target>quotation</target><arg>Although Saussure recognized the necessity of putting the phonic substance between brackets ("What is essential in language, we shall see, is foreign to the phonic character of the linguistic sign" [p.&nbsp;21]. "In its essence it [the linguistic signifier] is not at all phonic" [p.&nbsp;164]), Saussure, for essential, and essentially metaphysical, reasons had to privilege speech, everything that links the sign to phone. He also speaks of the "natural link" between thought and voice, meaning and sound (p.&nbsp;46). He even speaks of "thought-sound" (p.&nbsp;156). I have attempted elsewhere to show what is traditional in such a gesture, and to what necessities it submits. In any event, it winds up contradicting the most interesting critical motive of the Course, making of linguistics the regulatory model, the "pattern" for a general semiology of which it was to be, by all rights and theoretically, only a part. The theme of the arbitrary, thus, is turned away from its most fruitful paths (formalization) toward a hierarchizing teleology: "Thus it can be said that entirely arbitrary signs realize better than any others the ideal of the semiological process; this is why language, the most complex and most widespread of the systems of expression, is also the most characteristic one of them all; in this sense linguistics can become the general pattern for all semiology, even though language is only a particular system" (p.&nbsp;101). One finds exactly the same gesture and the same concepts in Hegel. The contradiction between these two moments of the Course is also marked by Saussure's recognizing elsewhere that "it is not spoken language that is natural to man, but the faculty of constituting a language, that is, a system of distinct signs ... ," that is, the possibility of the code and of articulation, independent of any substance, for example, phonic substance.</arg></template></extension><space/>Derrida will prefer to follow the more &quot;fruitful paths (formalization)&quot; of a general semiotics without falling in what he considered &quot;a hierarchizing teleology&quot; privileging linguistics, and speak of 'mark' rather than of language, not as something restricted to mankind, but as prelinguistic, as the pure possibility of language, working every where there is a relation to something else.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticisms</heading><paragraph>Derrida has been involved in a number of high profile disagreements with prominent philosophers including<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Searle</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Willard Van Orman Quine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Peter Kreeft</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Jrgen Habermas</target></link>. Most of the criticism of deconstruction were first articulated by these philosophers and repeated elsewhere.</paragraph><heading level='3'>John Searle</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Limited Inc</arg></template>In the early 1970s, Searle had a brief exchange with<space/><link><target>Jacques Derrida</target></link><space/>regarding speech-act theory. The exchange was characterized by a degree of mutual hostility between the philosophers, each of whom accused the other of having misunderstood his basic points.<extension extension_name='ref' name="limitedinc">Derrida, Jacques.<space/><italics>Limited, Inc.</italics><space/>Northwestern University Press, 1988. p.&amp;nbsp;29: &quot;...I have read some of his [Searle's] work (more, in any case, than he seems to have read of mine)&quot;</extension><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2012</arg></template><space/>Searle was particularly hostile to Derrida's deconstructionist framework and much later refused to let his response to Derrida be printed along with Derrida's papers in the 1988 collection<space/><italics><link><target>Limited Inc</target></link></italics>. Searle did not consider Derrida's approach to be legitimate philosophy or even intelligible writing and argued that he did not want to legitimize the deconstructionist point of view by dedicating any attention to it. Consequently, some critics<extension extension_name='ref'>Maclean, Ian. 2004. &quot;<italics>un dialogue de sourds?</italics><space/>Some implications of the AustinSearleDerrida debate&quot;, in<space/><italics>Jacques Derrida: critical thought</italics>. Ian Maclachlan (ed.) Ashgate Publishing, 2004</extension><space/>have considered the exchange to be a series of elaborate misunderstandings rather than a debate, while others<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alfino">&quot;Another Look at the Derrida-Searle Debate&quot;. Mark Alfino. Philosophy &amp; Rhetoric , Vol. 24, No. 2 (1991), pp.&amp;nbsp;143-52<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/40237667'></link></extension><space/>have seen either Derrida or Searle gaining the upper hand. The level of hostility can be seen from Searle's statement that &quot;It would be a mistake to regard Derrida's discussion of Austin as a confrontation between two prominent philosophical traditions&quot;, to which Derrida replied that that sentence was &quot;the only sentence of the &quot;reply&quot; to which I can subscribe&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Simon Glendinning</target></link>. 2001.<space/><italics>Arguing with Derrida</italics>. Wiley-Blackwell. p.&amp;nbsp;18</extension><space/>Commentators have frequently interpreted the exchange as a prominent example of a confrontation between<space/><link><target>Analytical philosophy</target><part>analytical</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>continental philosophy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The debate began in 1972, when, in his paper &quot;Signature Event Context&quot;, Derrida analyzed J. L. Austin's theory of the illocutionary act. While sympathetic to Austin's departure from a purely denotational account of language to one that includes &quot;force&quot;, Derrida was sceptical of the framework of normativity employed by Austin. He argued that Austin had missed the fact that any speech event is framed by a &quot;structure of absence&quot; (the words that are left unsaid due to contextual constraints) and by &quot;iterability&quot; (the constraints on what can be said, given by what has been said in the past). Derrida argued that the focus on<space/><link><target>intentionality</target></link><space/>in speech-act theory was misguided because intentionality is restricted to that which is already established as a possible intention. He also took issue with the way Austin had excluded the study of fiction, non-serious or &quot;parasitic&quot; speech, wondering whether this exclusion was because Austin had considered these speech genres governed by different structures of meaning, or simply due to a lack of interest. In his brief reply to Derrida, &quot;Reiterating the Differences: A Reply to Derrida&quot;, Searle argued that Derrida's critique was unwarranted because it assumed that Austin's theory attempted to give a full account of language and meaning when its aim was much narrower. Searle considered the omission of parasitic discourse forms to be justified by the narrow scope of Austin's inquiry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gregor Campbell. 1993. &quot;John R. Searle&quot; in Irene Rima Makaryk (ed). Encyclopedia of contemporary literary theory: approaches, scholars, terms. University of Toronto Press, 1993</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>John Searle, &quot;Reiterating the Diffrences: A Reply to Derrida&quot;, Glyph 2 (Baltimore MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1977).</extension><space/>Searle agreed with Derrida's proposal that intentionality presupposes iterability, but did not apply the same concept of intentionality used by Derrida, being unable or unwilling to engage with the continental conceptual apparatus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alfino"></extension><space/>This, in turn, caused Derrida to criticize Searle for not being sufficiently familiar with<space/><link><target>wikt:phenomenological</target><part>phenomenological</part></link><space/>perspectives on intentionality.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hobson">Marian Hobson. 1998. Jacques Derrida: opening lines. Psychology Press. pp.&amp;nbsp;95-97</extension><space/>Searle also argued that Derrida's disagreement with Austin turned on his having misunderstood Austin's<space/><link><target>typetoken distinction</target></link><space/>and his failure to understand Austin's concept of failure in relation to<space/><link><target>performativity</target></link>. Some critics<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hobson"></extension><space/>have suggested that Searle, by being so grounded in the analytical tradition that he was unable to engage with Derrida's continental phenomenological tradition, was at fault for the unsuccessful nature of the exchange.</paragraph><paragraph>Derrida, in his response to Searle (<template><target>nowrap</target><arg>"a b c ..."</arg></template><space/>in<space/><italics>Limited Inc</italics>), ridiculed Searle's positions. Claiming that a clear sender of Searle's message could not be established, he suggested that Searle had formed with Austin a<space/><italics>socit responsabilit limite</italics><space/>(a &quot;<link><target>limited liability company</target></link>&quot;) due to the ways in which the ambiguities of authorship within Searle's reply circumvented the very speech act of his reply. Searle did not reply. Later in 1988, Derrida tried to review his position and his critiques of Austin and Searle, reiterating that he found the constant appeal to &quot;normality&quot; in the analytical tradition to be problematic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alfino"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Afterwordsp133"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Farrell, F. B. (1988), Iterability and meaning: the Searle&amp;ndash;Derrida debate.<space/><italics>Metaphilosophy</italics>, 19: 5364. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-9973.1988.tb00701<space/><link type='external' href='http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-9973.1988.tb00701.x/abstract'></link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/1343193'>&quot;With the Compliments of the Author: Reflections on Austin and Derrida&quot;</link>. Stanley E. Fish.<space/><italics>Critical Inquiry</italics>, Vol. 8, No. 4 (Summer 1982), pp.&amp;nbsp;693-721.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/468793'>&quot;Derrida, Searle, Contexts, Games, Riddles&quot;</link>. Edmond Wright.<space/><italics><link><target>New Literary History</target></link></italics>, Vol. 13, No. 3 (&quot;Theory: Parodies, Puzzles, Paradigms&quot;), Spring 1982, pp.&amp;nbsp;463-77.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/468640'>&quot;Convention and Meaning: Derrida and Austin&quot;</link>. Jonathan Culler.<space/><italics>New Literary History</italics>, Vol. 13, No. 1 (&quot;On Convention: I&quot;), Autumn 1981, pp.&amp;nbsp;15-30.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.springerlink.com/content/dwu9j5cx8ft1jum8/'>&quot;Language, philosophy and the risk of failure: rereading the debate between Searle and Derrida&quot;</link>. Hagi Kenaan.<space/><italics>Continental Philosophy Review</italics>. Volume 35, Number 2, 117-133, DOI: 10.1023/A:1016583115826.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.springerlink.com/content/x16m6724k5513827/fulltext.pdf'>&quot;Understanding Each Other: The Case of the Derrida-Searle Debate&quot;</link>. Stanley Raffel.<space/><italics>Human Studies</italics>, Volume 34, Number 3, 277-292, DOI: 10.1007/s10746-011-9189-6 Theoretical/Philosophical Paper.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the debate, Derrida praises Austin's work, but argues that he is wrong to banish what Austin calls &quot;infelicities&quot; from the &quot;normal&quot; operation of language. One &quot;infelicity,&quot; for instance, occurs when it cannot be known whether a given speech act is &quot;sincere&quot; or &quot;merely citational&quot; (and therefore possibly ironic, etc.). Derrida argues that every iteration is necessarily &quot;citational,&quot; due to the graphematic nature of speech and writing, and that language could not work at all without the ever-present and ineradicable possibility of such alternate readings. Derrida takes Searle to task for his attempt to get around this issue by grounding final authority in the speaker's inaccessible &quot;intention&quot;. Derrida argues that intention cannot possibly govern how an iteration signifies, once it becomes hearable or readable. All speech acts borrow a language whose significance is determined by historical-linguistic context, and by the alternate possibilities that this context makes possible. This significance, Derrida argues, cannot be altered or governed by the whims of intention.</paragraph><paragraph>He would also argue about the problem he found in the constant appeal to &quot;normality&quot; in the analytical tradition from which Austin and Searle were only paradigmatic examples.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Afterwordsp133"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg><space/>In the description of the structure called "normal," "normative," "central," "ideal,"this possibility must be integrated as an essential possibility. The possibility cannot be treated as though it were a simple accident-marginal or parasitic. It cannot be, and hence ought not to be, and this passage from can to ought reflects the entire difficulty. In the analysis of so-called normal cases, one neither can nor ought, in all theoretical rigor, to exclude the possibility of transgression. Not even provisionally, or out of allegedly methodological considerations. It would be a poor method, since this possibility of transgression tells us immediately and indispensably about the structure of the act said to be normal as well as about the structure of law in general.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He continued arguing how problematic was establishing the relation between &quot;nonfiction or standard discourse&quot; and &quot;fiction,&quot; defined as its &quot;parasite, &quot;for part of the most originary essence of the latter is to allow fiction, the simulacrum, parasitism, to take place-and in so doing to &quot;de-essentialize&quot; itself as it were&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Afterwordsp133">Jacques Derrida, &quot;Afterwords&quot; in<space/><italics>Limited, Inc.</italics><space/>(Northwestern University Press, 1988), p.&amp;nbsp;133</extension><space/>He would finally argue that the indispensable question would then become:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Afterwordsp133"></extension><template><target>quotation</target><arg>what is "nonfiction standard discourse," what must it be and what does this name evoke, once its fictionality or its fictionalization, its transgressive "parasitism," is always possible (and moreover by virtue of the very same words, the same phrases, the same grammar, etc.)? 
<br><space/>This question is all the more indispensable since the rules, and even the statements of the rules governing the relations of "nonfiction standard discourse" and its fictional"parasites," are not things found in nature, but laws, symbolic inventions, or conventions, institutions that, in their very normality as well as in their normativity, entail something of the fictional.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1995, Searle gave a brief reply to Derrida in<space/><italics>The Construction of Social Reality</italics>. He called Derrida's conclusion &quot;preposterous&quot; and stated that &quot;Derrida, as far as I can tell, does not have an argument. He simply declares that there is nothing outside of texts...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Searle<space/><italics>The Construction of Social Reality</italics><space/>(1995) p.157-160.</extension><space/>Searle's reference here is not to anything forwarded in the debate, but to a mistranslation of the phrase &quot;<italics>il n'y a pas dehors du texte</italics>,&quot; (&quot;There is no outside-text&quot;) which appears in Derrida's<space/><italics><link><target>Of Grammatology</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tr. by<space/><link><target>Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak</target></link>. Johns Hopkins University Press. Baltimore, 1976, 158-59</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Jrgen Habermas</heading><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>The Philosophical Discourse of Modernity</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Jrgen Habermas</target></link><space/>criticized what he considered Derrida's opposition to<space/><link><target>Rationality</target><part>rational discourse</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jrgen Habermas (1987),<space/><italics>The Philosophical Discourse of Modernity</italics><space/>(trans. Frederick Lawrence), MIT Press, ISBN 0-7456-0830-2, pp.&amp;nbsp;185210.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Further, in an essay on religion and religious language, Habermas criticized Derrida's insistence on<space/><link><target>etymology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>philology</target></link><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><space/>(see<space/><italics><link><target>Etymological fallacy</target></link></italics>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Walter A. Davis</heading><paragraph>The American philosopher<space/><link><target>Walter A. Davis</target></link>, in<space/><italics>Inwardness and Existence: Subjectivity in/and Hegel, Heidegger, Marx and Freud</italics>, argues that both deconstruction and structuralism are prematurely arrested moments of a dialectical movement that issues in Hegelian &quot;unhappy consciousness.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Walter A. Davis</target><part>Davis, Walter A.</part></link><space/><italics>Inwardness and Existence: Subjectivity in/and Hegel, Heidegger, Marx and Freud</italics>. Madison: The University of Wisconsin Press, 1989.<template><target>page needed</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In popular media</heading><paragraph>Popular criticism of deconstruction also intensified following the<space/><link><target>Sokal affair</target></link>, which many people took as an indicator of the quality of deconstruction as a whole, despite the absence of Derrida from Sokal's follow-up book<space/><italics><link><target>Impostures Intellectuelles</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html
<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 3, 2007
<space/></arg><arg name="last">Sokal
<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alan D.
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Alan Sokal
<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Lingua Franca (magazine)|Lingua Franca]]
<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 1996
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Deconstruction and religion</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hermeneutics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of deconstructionists</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Post-structuralism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Postmodernism</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Derrida, Jacques [1967] (1978).<space/><italics>Of Grammatology</italics>, trans. by Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak. Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins University Press. ISBN 978-0-8018-5830-7</listitem><listitem>Derrida, Jacques.<space/><italics>Speech and Phenomena and Other Essays on Husserl's Theory of Signs</italics>. Trans. David B. Allison. Evanston: Northwestern UP, 1973. ISBN 978-0-8101-0590-4.</listitem><listitem>Derrida, Jacques.<space/><italics>Positions</italics>. Trans. Alan Bass. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1981. ISBN 978-0-226-14331-6</listitem><listitem>Derrida [1980],<space/><italics>The time of a thesis: punctuations</italics>, first published in:</listitem><listitem>Derrida [1988],<space/><italics>Limited Inc</italics></listitem><listitem>Derrida [1990],<space/><italics><link><target>Eyes of the University: Right to Philosophy 2</target></link></italics>, pp.&amp;nbsp;113128</listitem><listitem>Derrida, Jacques [1983],<space/><link type='external' href='http://lucy.ukc.ac.uk/Simulate/Derrida_deconstruction.html'>''Letter to A Japanese Friend''</link>, in<space/><link><target>David Wood (philosopher)</target><part>Wood, David</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Robert Bernasconi</target><part>Bernasconi, Robert</part></link><space/>(eds., 1988)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=kHFkwQOBjPYC'>''Derrida and Diffrance''</link>, Warwick: Parousia, 1985</listitem><listitem>Klein, Anne Carolyn (1995),<space/><italics>Meeting the Great Bliss Queen: Buddhists, Feminists, and the Art of the Self</italics>. Boston: Beacon, 1995. ISBN 978-0-8070-7306-3.</listitem><listitem>Montefiore, Alan (ed., 1983),<space/><italics>Philosophy in France Today</italics><space/>Cambridge: Cambridge UP, pp.&amp;nbsp;3450</listitem><listitem>Moynihan, Robert (1986),<space/><italics>Recent Imagining: Interviews with Harold Bloom, Geoffrey Hartman, Paul De Man, J. Hillis Miller</italics>. Shoe String, 1986. ISBN 978-0-208-02120-5.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Rorty</target><part>Rorty, Richard</part></link>, &quot;From Formalism to Poststructuralism&quot;.<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of Literary Criticism</italics>, vol. 8. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Breckman, Warren, &quot;Times of Theory: On Writing the History of French Theory,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of the History of Ideas</italics>, vol. 71, no. 3 (July 2010), 339361 (<link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/jhi/'>online</link>).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Simon Critchley</target><part>Critchley, Simon</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Ethics of Deconstruction: Derrida and Levinas</italics>, Third Edition, 2014. ISBN 978-0-7486-8932-3.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jonathan Culler</target><part>Culler, Jonathan</part></link>.<space/><italics>On Deconstruction: Theory and Criticism after Structuralism</italics>, Cornell University Press, 1982. ISBN 978-0-8014-1322-3.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Eagleton, Terry</target></link>.<space/><italics>Literary Theory: An Introduction</italics>, University of Minnesota Press, 1996. ISBN 978-0-8166-1251-2</listitem><listitem>Ellis, John M..<space/><italics>Against Deconstruction</italics>, Princeton: Princeton UP, 1989. ISBN 978-0-691-06754-4.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Barbara Johnson</target><part>Johnson, Barbara</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Critical Difference: Essays in the Contemporary Rhetoric of Reading</italics>. Johns Hopkins University Press, 1981. ISBN 978-0-801-82458-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>Simon Reynolds</target><part>Reynolds, Simon</part></link>,<space/><italics>Rip It Up and Start Again</italics>, New York: Penguin, 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;316. ISBN 978-0-143-03672-2.<space/><xhtml:small>(Source for the information about Green Gartside, Scritti Politti, and deconstructionism.)</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem>Stocker, Barry,<space/><italics>Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Derrida on Deconstruction</italics>, Routledge, 2006. ISBN 978-1-134-34381-2</listitem><listitem>Wortham, Simon Morgan,<space/><italics>The Derrida Dictionary</italics>, Continuum, 2010. ISBN 978-1-847-06526-1</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Wiktionary-inline</target></template></listitem><listitem>Video of<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vgwOjjoYtco'>Jacques Derrida attempting to define &quot;Deconstruction&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/derrida/#Dec'>&quot;Deconstruction&quot; in Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://prelectur.stanford.edu/lecturers/derrida/deconstruction.html'>&quot;Deconstruction&quot; in Stanford Presidential Lectures in the Humanities and Arts</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/155306/deconstruction'>&quot;Deconstruction&quot; in Encyclopedia Britannica&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://sas-space.sas.ac.uk/4397/1/Deconstructing_History_by_Alun_Munslow___Institute_of_Historical_Research.pdf'>&quot;Deconstructing History&quot; by Alun Munslow</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/derrida/#H2'>&quot;Deconstruction&quot; in &quot;Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://prelectur.stanford.edu/lecturers/derrida/rorty.html'>&quot;Deconstructionist Theory&quot;</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Richard Rorty</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.germanlawjournal.com/index.php?pageID=13&amp;amp;vol=6&amp;amp;no=1'>&quot;German Law Journal special number about Derrida and Deconstruction&quot;<space/></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/bridge/CriticalTheory/critical2.htm'>&quot;Critical Legal Studies Movement&quot; and the use of Deconstruction&quot;<space/></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.brocku.ca/english/courses/4F70/deconstruction.php'>&quot;Deconstruction: Some Assumptions&quot;</link><space/>by John Lye</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.unizar.es/departamentos/filologia_inglesa/garciala/bibliography.html'>A Bibliography of Literary Theory, Criticism, and Philology</link><space/>by Jos ngel Garca Landa (Deconstruction found under: Authors &amp; Schools - Critics &amp; Schools - Poststructuralism - On Deconstruction)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.alansondheim.org/old/DECON'>Ten ways of thinking about deconstruction</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Willy Maley</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://lacoue-labarthe.cjb.cc/'>Archive of the international conference &quot;Deconstructing Mimesis - Philippe Lacoue-Labarthe&quot;</link><space/>about the work of Lacoue-Labarthe and his mimetic version of deconstruction, held at the<space/><link><target>University of Paris IV: Paris-Sorbonne</target><part>Sorbonne</part></link><space/>in January 2006</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fudco.com/chip/deconstr.html'>How To Deconstruct Almost Anything - My Postmodern Adventure</link><space/>by Chip Morningstar; a cynical introduction to 'deconstruction' from the perspective of a<space/><link><target>software engineer</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sens-public.org/article.php3?id_article=312'>Jacques Derrida: The Perchance of a Coming of the Otherwoman. The Deconstruction of Phallogocentrism from Duel to Duo</link><space/>by Carole Dely, English translation by Wilson Baldridge, at<space/><italics>Sens Public</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.elupton.com/index.php?id=11'>Ellen Lupton on deconstruction in Graphic Design</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.enfocarte.com/5.26/moda.html'>Deconstruction of fashion; La moda en la posmodernidad</link><space/>by Adolfo Vasquez Rocca</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.academia.edu/9934425/DERRIDA_DECONSTRUCCI%C3%93N_DIFF%C3%89RANCE_Y_DISEMINACI%C3%93N_UNA_HISTORIA_DE_PAR%C3%81SITOS_HUELLAS_Y_ESPECTROS'>Derrida: Deconstruccin, diffrance y diseminacin; una historia de parsitos, huellas y espectros<space/></link><space/>Academia.Edu<space/></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Navboxes</target><arg name="list">
{{Litcrit}}
{{philosophy of language}}
{{continental philosophy}}
{{Philosophy topics}}
{{Human geography}}
{{Jacques Derrida}}
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Deconstruction</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of language</target></link><link><target>Category:Literary criticism</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophical movements</target></link><link><target>Category:Postmodern theory</target></link></paragraph></article>