<article title='Biological_membrane'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>various membranes in living things</arg><arg>the membranes surrounding cells<space/></arg><arg>cell membrane</arg></template><template><target>one source</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Phospholipids aqueous solution structures.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>Cross-section view of the structures that can be formed by phospholipids in an aqueous solution</part></link>A<space/><bold>biological membrane</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>biomembrane</bold><space/>is an enclosing or separating<space/><link><target>membrane</target></link><space/>that acts as a<space/><link><target>Semipermeable membrane</target><part>selectively permeable</part></link><space/>barrier within living things. Biological membranes, in the form of<space/><link><target>cell membrane</target><trail>s</trail></link>, often consist of a<space/><link><target>phospholipid bilayer</target></link><space/>with embedded,<space/><link><target>Integral membrane protein</target><part>integral</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>peripheral membrane protein</target><part>peripheral proteins</part></link><space/>used in communication and transportation of chemicals and<space/><link><target>ion</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Bulk<space/><link><target>lipid</target></link><space/>in membrane provides a fluid matrix for proteins to rotate and laterally diffuse for physiological functioning. Proteins are adapted to high<space/><link><target>membrane fluidity</target></link><space/>environment of<space/><link><target>lipid bilayer</target></link><space/>with the presence of an<space/><link><target>annular lipid shell</target></link>, consisting of lipid molecules bound tightly to surface of<space/><link><target>integral membrane proteins</target></link>. The cellular membranes should not be confused with isolating tissues formed by layers of cells, such as<space/><link><target>mucous membrane</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>basement membrane</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Function</heading><paragraph>The phospholipid bilayer contains charged<space/><link><target>hydrophilic</target></link><space/>headgroups, which interact with polar<space/><link><target>Properties of water</target><part>water</part></link>. The lipids also contain<space/><link><target>hydrophobic</target></link><space/>tails, which meet with the hydrophobic tails of the complementary layer. The<space/><link><target>Intermolecular force</target><part>interactions</part></link><space/>of lipids, especially the hydrophobic tails, determine the<space/><link><target>Lipid bilayer phase behavior</target><part>lipid bilayer physical properties</part></link><space/>such as fluidity.</paragraph><paragraph>Membranes in cells typically define enclosed spaces or compartments in which cells may maintain a chemical or biochemical environment that differs from the outside. For example, the membrane around<space/><link><target>peroxisome</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>shields the rest of the cell from peroxides, chemicals that can be toxic to the cell, and the cell membrane separates a cell from its surrounding medium. Peroxisomes are one form of vacuole found in the cell that contain by-products of chemical reactions within the cell. Most organelles are defined by such membranes, and are called &quot;membrane-bound&quot; organelles.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Selective Permeability</heading><paragraph>Probably the most important feature of a biomembrane is that it is a selectively permeable structure. This means that the size, charge, and other chemical properties of the atoms and molecules attempting to cross it will determine whether they succeed in doing so. Selective permeability is essential for effective separation of a cell or organelle from its surroundings. Biological membranes also have certain mechanical or elastic properties that allow them to change shape and move as required.</paragraph><paragraph>Generally, small hydrophobic molecules can readily cross phospholipid bilayers by simple<space/><link><target>diffusion</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brown</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Particles that are required for cellular function but are unable to diffuse freely across a membrane enter through a membrane transport protein or are taken in by means of endocytosis, where the membrane allows for a vacuole to join onto it and push its contents into the cell. Many types of specialized plasma membranes can separate cell from external environment: apical, basolateral, presynaptic and postsynaptic ones, membranes of flagella, cilia, microvillus, filopodia and lamellipodia, the sarcolemma of muscle cells, as well as specialized myelin and dendritic spine membranes of neurons. Plasma membranes can also form different types of &quot;supramembrane&quot; structures such as caveola, postsynaptic density, podosome, invadopodium, desmosome, hemidesmosome, focal adhesion, and cell junctions. These types of membranes differ in lipid and protein composition.</paragraph><paragraph>Distinct types of membranes also create intracellular organelles: endosome; smooth and rough endoplasmic reticulum; sarcoplasmic reticulum; Golgi apparatus; lysosome; mitochondrion (inner and outer membranes); nucleus (inner and outer membranes); peroxisome; vacuole; cytoplasmic granules; cell vesicles (phagosome, autophagosome, clathrin-coated vesicles, COPI-coated and COPII-coated vesicles) and secretory vesicles (including synaptosome, acrosomes, melanosomes, and chromaffin granules).Different types of biological membranes have diverse lipid and protein compositions. The content of membranes defines their physical and biological properties. Some components of membranes play a key role in medicine, such as the efflux pumps that pump drugs out of a cell.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Membrane lipids</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Membrane protein</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Annular lipid shell</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lipid bilayer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Membrane fluidity</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Osmosis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Membrane biology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Membrane models</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>General</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">von Heijne G, Rees D<space/></arg><arg name="title">Membranes: reading between the lines<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.<space/></arg><arg name="volume">18<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">403–5<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 2008<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">18634876<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.sbi.2008.06.003<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0959-440X(08)00091-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brown</arg><arg name="first">Bernard</arg><arg name="title">Biological Membranes</arg><arg name="date">1996</arg><arg name="publisher">The Biochemical Society</arg><arg name="location">London, U.K.</arg><arg name="isbn">0904498328</arg><arg name="page">21</arg><arg name="url">http://www.biochemistry.org/Portals/0/Education/Docs/BASC08_full.pdf</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>MeSH name</target><arg>Membranes</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Biological Membrane</target></template><link><target>Category:Membrane biology</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Biological matter</target><part>membrane</part></link></paragraph></article>