<article title='Carl_Barks'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Duck Man</arg><arg>the cartoon</arg><arg>Duckman</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox comics creator</target><arg name="name"><space/>Carl Barks
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Carl barks.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Carl Barks at the 1982 San Diego Comic Con
</arg><arg name="alt">
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1901|3|27|mf</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Merrill, Oregon|Merrill]], [[Oregon]], [[United States|U.S.]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|2000|8|25|1901|3|27|mf</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Grants Pass, Oregon|Grants Pass]], [[Oregon]], [[United States|U.S.]]
</arg><arg name="death_cause"><space/>[[Leukemia]]
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>American
</arg><arg name="cartoonist"><space/>y
</arg><arg name="influenced"><space/>[[Jeff Smith (cartoonist)|Jeff Smith]],<ref name</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Cartoonist, author, painter
</arg><arg name="years_active"><space/>1936–2000
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>Pearl Turner<br>(1923–1929; divorced)<br>Clara Balken<br>(1932–1951; divorced)<br>Garé Williams<br>(1954–1993; her death)
</arg><arg name="children"><space/>2
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Carl Barks</bold><space/>(March 27, 1901&amp;nbsp; August 25, 2000) was an American<space/><link><target>cartoonist</target></link>, author, and painter. He is best known for his comics about<space/><link><target>Donald Duck</target></link><space/>and as the creator of<space/><link><target>Scrooge McDuck</target></link>. He worked anonymously until late in his career; fans dubbed him<space/><bold>The Duck Man</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>The Good Duck Artist</bold>. In 1987, Barks was one of the three inaugural inductees of the<space/><link><target>List of Eisner Award winners#The Will Eisner Award Hall of Fame</target><part>Will Eisner Comic Book Hall of Fame</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Barks worked for the<space/><link><target>The Walt Disney Company</target><part>Disney Studio</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Western Publishing</target></link><space/>where he created<space/><link><target>Duckburg</target></link><space/>and many of its inhabitants, such as<space/><link><target>Scrooge McDuck</target></link><space/>(1947),<space/><link><target>Gladstone Gander</target></link><space/>(1948), the<space/><link><target>Beagle Boys</target></link><space/>(1951),<space/><link><target>The Junior Woodchucks</target></link><space/>(1951),<space/><link><target>Gyro Gearloose</target></link><space/>(1952),<space/><link><target>Duck family (Disney)#Cornelius Coot</target><part>Cornelius Coot</part></link><space/>(1952),<space/><link><target>Flintheart Glomgold</target></link><space/>(1956),<space/><link><target>John D. Rockerduck</target></link><space/>(1961) and<space/><link><target>Magica De Spell</target></link><space/>(1961). Cartoonist<space/><link><target>Will Eisner</target></link><space/>called him &quot;the<space/><link><target>Hans Christian Andersen</target></link><space/>of comic books.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="tegneserier.no-Barks"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Morten Harper<space/></arg><arg name="title">Den gode tegneren, quote TEGN, 1994<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">tegneserier.no<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.tegneserier.no/default.asp?lib</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20071015143405/http://www.tegneserier.no/default.asp?lib</arg><arg name="archivedate">2007-10-15<space/></arg><arg name="language">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><paragraph>Barks was born in<space/><link><target>Merrill, Oregon</target><part>Merrill</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link><space/>to William Barks and his wife Arminta Johnson. He had an older brother named Clyde. Barks once stated that his paternal ancestors were Dutch and his maternal ancestors were Scottish.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2012</arg></template><space/>His paternal grandparents were David Barks and his wife Ruth Shrum. His maternal grandparents were Carl Johnson and his wife Suzanna Massey, but little else is known about his ancestors. Barks was the descendant of Jacob Barks who came to Missouri from North Carolina around 1800. They lived in Marble Hill in Bollinger County. Jacob Barks' son Isaac was the father of the David Barks noted above.<extension extension_name='ref'>Source: 1850 census;<space/><italics>Goodspeed's History of Southeast Missouri</italics>, Southern Historical Press, 1888.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Childhood</heading><paragraph>According to Barks' description of his childhood, he was a rather lonely child. His parents owned one square mile (2.6&amp;nbsp;km) of land that served as their farm. The nearest neighbor lived half a mile (800 m) away, but he was more an acquaintance to Barks' parents than a friend. The closest school was about two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) away and Barks had to walk that distance every day. The rural area had few children, though, and Barks later remembered that his school had only about eight or ten students including him. He had high praise for the quality of the education he received in that small school. &quot;Schools were good in those days,&quot; he used to say.The lessons lasted from nine o'clock in the morning to four o'clock in the afternoon and then he had to return to the farm. There he remembered not having anybody to talk to, as his parents were busy and he had little in common with his brother.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1908, William Barks (in an attempt to increase the family income) moved with his family to<space/><link><target>Midland, Oregon</target><part>Midland</part></link>, Oregon, some miles north of Merrill, to be closer to the new railway lines. He established a new stock-breeding farm and sold his produce to the local slaughterhouses.</paragraph><paragraph>Nine-year-old Clyde and seven-year-old Carl worked long hours there. But Carl later remembered that the crowd which gathered at Midland's market place made a strong impression on him. This was expected, as he was not used to crowds up until then. According to Barks, his attention was mostly drawn to the<space/><link><target>cowboy</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that frequented the market with their revolvers, strange nicknames for each other and sense of humor.</paragraph><paragraph>By 1911, they had been successful enough to move to<space/><link><target>Santa Rosa, California</target><part>Santa Rosa</part></link>,<space/><link><target>California</target></link>. There they started cultivating vegetables and set up some orchards. Unfortunately, the profits were not as high as William expected and they started having financial difficulties. William's anxiety over them was probably what caused his first nervous breakdown.</paragraph><paragraph>As soon as William recovered, he made the decision to move back to Merrill. The year was 1913, and Barks was already 12 years old; but, due to the constant moving, he had not yet managed to complete grade school. He resumed his education at this point and finally managed to graduate in 1916.</paragraph><paragraph>1916 served as a turning point in Barks' life for various reasons. First, Arminta, his mother, died in this year. Second, his hearing problems, which had already appeared earlier, had at the time become severe enough for him to have difficulties listening to his teachers talking. His hearing would continue to get worse later, but at that point he had not yet acquired a hearing aid. Later in life, he couldn't do without one. Third, the closest high school to their farm was five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) away and even if he did enroll in it, his bad hearing was likely to contribute to his learning problems. He had to decide to stop his school education, much to his disappointment.</paragraph><heading level='3'>From job to job</heading><paragraph>Barks started taking various jobs but had little success in such occupations as a farmer, woodcutter, turner, mule driver, cowboy and printer. From his jobs he learned, he later averred, how eccentric, stubborn and unpredictable men, animals and machines can be. At the same time he interacted with colleagues, fellow breadwinners who had satirical disposition towards even their worst troubles. Barks later declared that he was sure that if not for a little humor in their troubled lives, they would certainly go insane. It was an attitude towards life that Barks would adopt. Later he would say it was natural for him to satirize the secret yearnings and desires, the pompous style and the disappointments of his characters. According to Barks, this period of his life would later influence his best known fictional characters:<space/><link><target>Walt Disney</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Donald Duck</target></link><space/>and his own<space/><link><target>Scrooge McDuck</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Donald's drifting from job to job was reportedly inspired by Barks' own experiences. So was his usual lack of success. And even in those that he was successful this would be temporary, just until a mistake or chance event caused another failure, another disappointment for the frustrated duck. Barks also reported that this was another thing he was familiar with.</paragraph><paragraph>Scrooge's main difference to Donald, according to Barks, was that he too had faced the same difficulties in his past but through intelligence, determination and hard work, he was able to overcome them. Or, as Scrooge himself would say to<space/><link><target>Huey, Dewey and Louie</target></link>: by being &quot;tougher than the toughies and smarter than the smarties.&quot; Even in the present of his stories Scrooge would work to solve his many problems, even though the stories would often point out that his constant efforts seemed futile at the end. In addition, Scrooge was quite similar to his creator in appearing often to be as melancholic, introspective and secretive as he was.</paragraph><paragraph>Through both characters Barks would often exhibit his rather sarcastic sense of humor. It seems that this difficult period for the artist helped shape many of his later views in life that were expressed through his characters.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Professional artist</heading><paragraph>At the same time Barks had started thinking about turning a hobby that he always enjoyed into a profession: that of drawing. Since his early childhood he spent his free time by drawing on any material he could find. He had attempted to improve his style by copying the drawings of his favorite<space/><link><target>comic strip</target></link><space/>artists from the newspapers where he could find them. As he later said, he wanted to create his own facial expressions, figures and comical situations in his drawings but wanted to study the master comic artists' use of the pen and their use of color and shading.</paragraph><paragraph>Among his early favorites were<space/><link><target>Winsor McCay</target></link><space/>(mostly known for<space/><italics><link><target>Little Nemo</target></link></italics>) and<space/><link><target>Frederick Burr Opper</target></link><space/>(mostly known for<space/><italics><link><target>Happy Hooligan</target></link></italics>) but he would later study any style that managed to draw his attention.</paragraph><paragraph>At 16 he was mostly self-taught but at this point he decided to take some lessons through correspondence. He only followed the first four lessons and then had to stop because his working left him with little free time. But as he later said, the lessons proved very useful in improving his style.</paragraph><paragraph>By December 1918, he left his father's home to attempt to find a job in<space/><link><target>San Francisco</target></link>, California. He worked for a while in a small publishing house while attempting to sell his drawings to newspapers and other printed material with little success.</paragraph><heading level='3'>First and second marriages</heading><paragraph>While he continued drifting through various jobs, he met Pearl Turner (19041987). In 1921 they married and had two daughters:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Peggy Barks, born in 1923 and deceased in 1963.</listitem><listitem>Dorothy Barks, born in 1924.</listitem></list><paragraph>In 1923 he returned to his paternal farm in Merrill in an attempt to return to the life of a farmer, but that ended soon. He continued searching for a job while attempting to sell his drawings. He soon managed to sell some of them to<space/><italics>Judge</italics><space/>magazine and then started having success submitting to the Minneapolis-based<space/><italics>Calgary-Eye-Opener</italics>, a racy men's cartoon magazine of the era. He was eventually hired as editor and scripted and drew most of the contents while continuing to sell occasional work to other magazines. His salary of 90 dollars a month was considered respectable enough for the time. A facsimile of one of the racy magazines he did cartoons for in this period,<space/><italics>Coo Coo</italics><space/>#1, was published by Hamilton Comics in 1997.</paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, he had his first divorce. He and Pearl were separated in 1929 and divorced in 1930. After he moved to<space/><link><target>Minneapolis</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Minnesota</target></link>, where<space/><italics>Calgary-Eye-Opener</italics><space/>had its offices he met Clara Balken who in 1938 became his second wife.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Disney</heading><paragraph>In November 1935, when he learned that Walt Disney was seeking more artists for his studio, Barks decided to apply. He was approved for a try-out which entailed a move to<space/><link><target>Los Angeles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>California</target></link>. He was one of two in his class of trainees who was hired. His starting salary was 20 dollars a week. He started at Disney Studios in 1935, more than a year after the debut of Donald Duck on June 9, 1934 in the short animated film<space/><italics><link><target>The Wise Little Hen</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Barks initially worked as an<space/><link><target>animator#Inbetweeners and cleanup artists</target><part>inbetweener</part></link>. This involved being teamed and supervised by one of the head animators who did the key poses of character action (often known as extremes) for which the inbetweeners did the drawings between the extremes to create the illusion of movement. While an inbetweener, Barks submitted gag ideas for cartoon story lines being developed and showed such a knack for creating comical situations that by 1937 he was transferred to the story department. His first story sale was the climax of<space/><link><target>Modern Inventions</target></link>, for a sequence where a robot barber chair gives Donald Duck a haircut on his bottom.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1937 when Donald Duck became the star of his own series of cartoons instead of co-starring with<space/><link><target>Mickey Mouse</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Goofy</target></link><space/>as previously, a new unit of storymen and animators was created devoted solely to this series. Though he originally just contributed gag ideas to some duck cartoons by 1937 Barks was (principally with partner<space/><link><target>Jack Hannah</target></link>) originating story ideas that were storyboarded and (if approved by Walt) put into production. He collaborated on such cartoons as<space/><italics><link><target>Donald's Nephews</target></link></italics><space/>(1938),<space/><italics><link><target>Donald's Cousin Gus</target></link></italics><space/>(1939),<space/><italics><link><target>Mr. Duck Steps Out</target></link></italics><space/>(1940),<italics><link><target>Timber (film)</target><part>Timber</part></link></italics><space/>(1941),<space/><italics><link><target>The Vanishing Private</target></link></italics><space/>(1942) and<space/><italics><link><target>The Plastics Inventor</target></link></italics><space/>(1944).</paragraph><heading level='3'>The Good Duck Artist</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Omelet.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Omelet opening page</part></link>Unhappy at the emerging wartime working conditions at Disney, and bothered by ongoing sinus problems caused by the studio's air conditioning, Barks quit in 1942. Shortly before quitting, he moonlighted as a comic book artist, contributing half the artwork for a one-shot<space/><link><target>comic book</target></link><space/>(the other half of the art being done by story partner<space/><link><target>Jack Hannah</target></link>) titled<space/><italics><link><target>Donald Duck Finds Pirate Gold</target></link></italics>. This 64-page story was adapted by Donald Duck comic strip writer<space/><link><target>Bob Karp</target></link><space/>from an unproduced feature, and published in October 1942 in<space/><link><target>Dell Comics</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Four Color</target><part>Four Color Comics</part></link></italics><space/>#9. It was the first Donald Duck story originally produced for an American comic book and also the first involving Donald and his nephews in a treasure hunting expedition, in this case for the treasure of<space/><link><target>Henry Morgan</target></link>. Barks would later use the treasure hunting theme in many of his stories. This actually was not his first work in comics, as earlier the same year Barks along with Hannah and fellow storyman Nick George scripted<space/><italics><link><target>Pluto Saves the Ship</target></link></italics>, which was among the first original Disney comic book stories published in the United States.</paragraph><paragraph>After quitting the Disney Studio, Barks relocated to the<space/><link><target>Hemet, California</target><part>Hemet</part></link>/<link><target>San Jacinto, California</target><part>San Jacinto</part></link><space/>area in the semi-desert<space/><link><target>Inland Empire (California)</target><part>inland empire</part></link><space/>region east of Los Angeles where he hoped to start a chicken farm.</paragraph><paragraph>When asked which of his stories was a favorite in several interviews Barks cited the ten-pager in<space/><italics>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</italics><space/>#146 (Nov. 1952) in which Donald tells the story of the chain of unfortunate events that took place when he owned a chicken farm in a town which subsequently was renamed Omelet. Likely one reason it was a favorite is that it was inspired by Barks' own experiences in the poultry business.</paragraph><paragraph>But to earn a living in the meantime he inquired whether<space/><link><target>Western Publishing</target></link>, which had published<space/><italics>Pirate Gold</italics>, had any need for artists for Donald Duck comic book stories. He was immediately assigned to illustrate the script for a ten-page Donald Duck story for the monthly<space/><italics><link><target>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</target></link></italics>. At the publisher's invitation he revised the storyline and the improvements impressed the editor sufficiently to invite Barks to try his hand at contributing both the script and the artwork of his follow-up story. This set the pattern for Barks' career in that (with rare exceptions) he provided art (pencil, inking, solid blacks and lettering) and scripting for his stories.</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>The Victory Garden (comic book)</target><part>The Victory Garden</part></link></italics>, that initial ten-page story published in April, 1943 was the first of about 500 stories featuring the Disney ducks Barks would produce for Western Publishing over the next three decades, well into his purported retirement. These can be mostly divided into three categories:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>One-page gag stories like &quot;<link><target>Coffee for Two</target></link>&quot; and &quot;<link><target>Sorry to be Safe</target></link>&quot;. These one-pagers were usually printed in black and white (or black and white and red) on the inside front, inside back, and outside back covers. These stories focused on one joke.<space/></listitem><listitem>Ten-pagers, comedic Donald Duck stories that were the lead for the monthly flagship title<space/><italics>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</italics>, whose circulation peaked in the mid-1950s at 3 million copies sold a month.</listitem><listitem>Humorous adventure stories, usually 24-32 pages in length. In the 1940s these were one-shots in the<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>series (issued 46 times a year) that starred Donald and his nephews. Starting in the early 1950s (and through his retirement) Barks' longer stories were almost exclusively published in Uncle Scrooge's own quarterly title.</listitem></list><paragraph>Barks' artistic growth during his first decade in comics saw a transformation from rather rudimentary storytelling derived from his years as an animation artist and storyman into a virtuoso creator of complex narratives, notably in his longer adventure tales. According to critic Geoffrey Blum, the process that saw its beginnings in 1942's Pirate Gold first bore its full fruit in 1950's '<link><target>Vacation Time</target></link>,' which he describes as 'a visual primer for reading comics and understanding... the form....&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Barks and the Bending Panel"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Blum</arg><arg name="first">Geoffrey</arg><arg name="title">Barks and the Bending Panel</arg><arg name="journal">The Carl Barks Library of Donald Duck Adventures in Color</arg><arg name="year">[199?]</arg><arg name="issue">18</arg><arg name="pages">[46]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He surrounded<space/><link><target>Donald Duck</target></link><space/>and nephews<space/><link><target>Huey, Dewey and Louie</target></link><space/>with a cast of eccentric and colorful characters, such as the aforementioned<space/><link><target>Scrooge McDuck</target></link>, the wealthiest<space/><link><target>duck</target></link><space/>in the world;<space/><link><target>Gladstone Gander</target></link>, Donald's obscenely lucky cousin; inventor<space/><link><target>Gyro Gearloose</target></link>; the persistent<space/><link><target>Beagle Boys</target></link>; the sorceress<space/><link><target>Magica De Spell</target></link>; Scrooge's rivals<space/><link><target>Flintheart Glomgold</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John D. Rockerduck</target></link>; Daisy's nieces<space/><link><target>April, May and June</target></link>; Donald's neighbor Jones, and<space/><link><target>The Junior Woodchucks</target></link><space/>organization.</paragraph><paragraph>Barks's stories (whether humorous adventures or domestic comedies) often exhibited a wry, dark irony born of hard experience. The ten-pagers showcased Donald as everyman, struggling against the cruel bumps and bruises of everyday life with the nephews often acting as a<space/><link><target>Greek chorus</target></link><space/>commenting on the unfolding disasters Donald wrought upon himself. Yet while seemingly defeatist in tone, the humanity of the characters shines through in their persistence despite the obstacles. These stories found popularity not only among young children but adults as well. Despite the fact that Barks had done little traveling his adventure stories often had the duck clan globe-trotting to the most remote or spectacular of places. This allowed Barks to indulge his penchant for elaborate backgrounds that hinted at his thwarted ambitions of doing realistic stories in the vein of<space/><link><target>Hal Foster</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Prince Valiant</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Third marriage</heading><paragraph>As Barks blossomed creatively, his marriage to Clara deteriorated. This is the period referred to in Barks' famed quip that he could feel his creative juices flowing while the whiskey bottles hurled at him by a tipsy Clara flew by his head. They were divorced in 1951, his second and last divorce. In this period Barks dabbled in fine art, exhibiting paintings at local art shows. It was at one of these in 1952 he became acquainted with fellow exhibitor Margaret Wynnfred Williams (1917 March 10, 1993), nicknamed Gar. She was an accomplished landscape artist, some of whose paintings are in the collection of the<space/><link><target>Leanin' Tree Museum of Western Art</target></link>. During her lifetime, and to this day, note cards of her paintings are available from Leanin' Tree. Her nickname appears as a store name in the story &quot;Christmas in Duckburg&quot;, featured on page 1 of Walt Disneys Christmas Parade #9, published in 1958. Soon after they met, she started assisting Barks, handling the solid blacks and lettering, both of which he had found onerous. They married in 1954 and the union lasted until her death.</paragraph><heading level='3'>No longer anonymous</heading><paragraph>People who worked for Disney (and its comic book licensees) generally did so in relative anonymity; stories would only carry Walt Disney's name and (sometimes) a short identification number. Prior to 1960 Barks' identity remained a mystery to his readers. However, many readers recognized Barks' work and drawing stylehe &quot;signed&quot; many stories with a small image of a barking dogand began to call him the Good Duck Artist, a label that stuck even after his true identity was discovered by fans in the late 1950s. Malcolm Willits was the first person to learn Barks's name and address, but two brothers named John and<space/><link><target>Bill Spicer</target></link><space/>became the first fans to contact Barks after independently discovering the same information. After Barks received a 1960 visit from the Spicer brothers and Ron Leonard, he was no longer anonymous, as word of his identity spread through the emerging network of comic book fandom<space/><link><target>fanzine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Fan convention</target><part>conventions</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SpicerLetter"><link type='external' href='http://www.cbarks.dk/thefanletter.htm'>Spicer, John. Letter, April 11, 1960.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Later life</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Carl Barks a Finnland 94.jpg</target><part>Carl Barks visiting<space/><link><target>Finland</target></link><space/>in June, 1994.</part><part>thumb</part></link>Carl Barks retired in 1966, but was persuaded by editor<space/><link><target>Chase Craig</target></link><space/>to continue to script stories for Western. The last new comic book story drawn by Carl Barks was a<space/><link><target>Daisy Duck</target></link><space/>tale (&quot;The Dainty Daredevil&quot;) published in<space/><italics><link><target>Walt Disney Comics Digest</target></link></italics><space/>issue 5 (Nov. 1968). When bibliographer<space/><link><target>Michael Barrier (historian)</target><part>Michael Barrier</part></link><space/>asked Barks why he drew it, Barks' vague recollection was no one was available and he was asked to do it as a favor by Craig.</paragraph><paragraph>He wrote one Uncle Scrooge story, three Donald Duck stories and from 19701974 was the main writer for the<space/><link><target>Junior Woodchucks</target></link><space/>comic book (issues 6 through 25). The latter included environmental themes that Barks first explored in 1957 [&quot;Land of the Pygmy Indians&quot;, Uncle Scrooge #18]. Barks also sold a few sketches to Western that were redrawn as covers. For a time the Barkses lived in<space/><link><target>Goleta, California</target></link><space/>before returning to the Inland Empire by moving to<space/><link><target>Temecula, California</target><part>Temecula</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>To make a little extra money beyond what his pension and scripting earnings brought in, Barks started doing oil paintings to sell at the local art shows where he and Gar exhibited. Subjects included humorous depictions of life on the farm and portraits of Native American princesses. These skillfully rendered paintings encouraged fan Glenn Bray to ask Barks if he could commission a painting of the ducks (&quot;A Tall Ship and a Star to Steer Her By&quot;, taken from the cover of<space/><italics><link><target>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</target></link></italics><space/>#108 by Barks). This prompted Barks to contact<space/><link><target>George Sherman (comics)</target><part>George Sherman</part></link><space/>at Disney's Publications Department to request permission to produce and sell oil paintings of scenes from his stories. In July 1971 Barks was granted a royalty-free license by Disney.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cbarks.dk/thecorrespondence1970s.htm'>TheCorrespondence1970s.com</link></extension><space/>When word spread that Barks was taking commissions from those interested in purchasing an oil of the ducks, much to his astonishment the response quickly outstripped what he reasonably could produce in the next few years.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="title">Ode to the Disney Ducks<space/></arg><arg name="source">— Carl Barks, 1999{{sfn|Blum|2008|page</arg><arg name="width">250px<space/></arg><arg name="fontsize">90%<space/></arg><arg name="bgcolor">#eeffff
</arg><arg name="quote"><poem>They ride tall ships to the far away,
and see the long ago.
They walk where fabled people trod,
and Yetis trod the snow.

They meet the folks who live on stars,
and find them much like us,
With food and love and happiness
the things they most discuss.

The world is full of clans and cults
abuzz as angry bees,
And Junior Woodchucks snapping jeers
at Littlest Chickadees.

The ducks show us that part of life
is to forgive a slight.
That black eyes given in revenge
keep hatred burning bright.

So when our walks in sun or shade
pass graveyards filled by wars,
It's nice to stop and read of ducks
whose battles leave no scars.

To read of ducks who parody
our vain attempts at glory,
They don't exist, but somehow leave
us glad we bought their story.</poem>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When Barks expressed dismay at coping with the backlog of orders he faced, fan/dealers Bruce Hamilton and Russ Cochran suggested Barks instead auction his paintings at conventions and via Cochran's catalog<space/><italics>Graphic Gallery</italics>. By September 1974 Barks had discontinued taking commissions.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://web.archive.org/web/20091028084238/http://www.geocities.com/~jimlowe/barks/images/barkcard.jpg</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At Boston's NewCon convention, in October 1975, the first Carl Barks oil painting auctioned at a comic book convention (&quot;She Was Spangled and Flashy&quot;) sold for $2,500. Subsequent offerings saw an escalation in the prices realized.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1976, Barks and Gar went to Boston for the NewCon show, their first comic convention appearance. Among the other attendees was famed<space/><link><target>Little Lulu</target></link><space/>comic book scripter<space/><link><target>John Stanley (comics)</target><part>John Stanley</part></link>; despite both having worked for<space/><link><target>Western Publishing</target></link><space/>this was the first time they met. The highlight of the convention was the auctioning of what was to that time the largest duck oil painting Barks had done, &quot;July Fourth in Duckburg&quot;, which included depictions of several prominent Barks fans and collectors. It sold for a then record high amount: $6,400.</paragraph><paragraph>Soon thereafter a fan sold unauthorized prints of some of the Scrooge McDuck paintings, leading Disney to withdraw permission for further paintings. To meet demand for new work Barks embarked on a series of paintings of non-Disney ducks and fantasy subjects such as Beowulf and Xerxes. These were eventually collected in the limited-edition book<space/><italics>Animal Quackers</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>As the result of heroic efforts by<space/><italics><link><target>Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope</target><part>Star Wars</part></link></italics><space/>producer<space/><link><target>Gary Kurtz</target></link><space/>and screenwriter<space/><link><target>Edward Summer</target></link>, Disney relented and in 1981, allowed Barks to do a now seminal oil painting called &quot;Wanderers of Wonderlands&quot; for a breakthrough limited edition book entitled<space/><italics><link><target>Uncle Scrooge McDuck: His Life and Times</target></link></italics>. The book collected 11 classic Barks stories of Uncle Scrooge colored by artist<space/><link><target>Peter Ledger</target></link><space/>along with a new Scrooge story by Barks done storybook style with watercolor illustrations, &quot;Go Slowly, Sands of Time&quot;. After being turned down by every major publisher in New York City, Kurtz and Summer published the book through<space/><link><target>Celestial Arts</target></link>, which Kurtz acquired partly for this purpose. The book went on to become the model for virtually every important collection of comic book stories. It was the first book of its kind ever reviewed in<space/><italics><link><target>Time Magazine</target></link><space/></italics>and subsequently in<space/><italics><link><target>Newsweek</target></link></italics>, and the first book review in<space/><italics>Time Magazine</italics><space/>with large color illustrations.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1977 and 1982, Barks attended the San Diego Comic Con. As with his appearance in Boston, the response to his presence was overwhelming, with long lines of fans waiting to meet Barks and get his autograph.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1981, Bruce Hamilton and Russ Cochran, two long-time Disney comics fans, decided to combine forces to bring greater recognition to the works of Carl Barks. Their first efforts went into establishing<space/><link><target>Another Rainbow</target></link><space/>Publishing, the banner under which they produced and issued the award-winning book, &quot;The Fine Art of Walt Disneys Donald Duck by Carl Barks&quot;, a comprehensive collection of the Disney duck paintings of this artist and storyteller. Not long after, the company began producing fine art lithographs of many of these paintings, in strictly limited editions, all signed by Barks, who eventually produced many original works for the series.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1983 Another Rainbow took up the daunting task of collecting the entire Disney comic book ouvr of Barksover 500 stories in allin the ten-set, thirty-volume<space/><italics><link><target>Carl Barks Library</target></link></italics>. These oversized hardbound volumes reproduced Barks pages in pristine black and white line art, as close as possible to the way he would originally drawn them, and included mountains of special features, articles, reminiscences, interviews, storyboards, critiques, and more than a few surprises. This monumental project was finally completed in mid-1990.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1985 a new division was founded,<space/><link><target>Gladstone Publishing</target></link>, which took up the then-dormant Disney comic book license. Gladstone introduced a whole new generation of Disney comic book readers to the wondrous storytelling of such luminaries as Barks, Paul Murry, and Floyd Gottfredson, as well as presenting the first works of modern Disney comics masters Don Rosa and William Van Horn. Seven years after Gladstone's founding, the<space/><italics>Carl Barks Library</italics><space/>was revived as the<space/><italics>Carl Barks Library in Color</italics>, a full-color, high-quality squarebound comic albums (including the first-ever Carl Barks trading cards).</paragraph><paragraph>Barks relocated one last time to Grants Pass, Oregon near where he grew up, partly at the urging of friend and<space/><italics><link><target>Broom Hilda</target></link></italics><space/>artist<space/><link><target>Russell Myers</target></link>, who lived in the area. The move also was motivated, Barks stated in another famous quip, by Temecula being too close to Disneyland and thus facilitating a growing torrent of drop-in visits by vacationing fans. In this period Barks made only one public appearance, at a comic book shop near Grants Pass.</paragraph><paragraph>From 1993 to 1998, Barks' career was managed by the &quot;Carl Barks Studio&quot; (Bill Grandey and Kathy MorbyThey had sold Barks original art since 1979). This involved numerous art projects and activities, including a tour of 11 European countries in 1994, Iceland being the first foreign country he ever visited. Barks appeared at the first of many Disneyana conventions in 1993. Silk screen prints of paintings along with high-end art objects (such as original water colors, bronze figurines and ceramic tiles) were produced based on designs by Barks.</paragraph><paragraph>During the summer of 1994 and until his death, Carl Barks &amp; his studio personally assigned Peter Reichelt, a museum exhibition producer from<space/><link><target>Mannheim</target></link>, Germany, as his agent for Europe. Publisher &quot;Edition 313&quot; put out numerous lithographs. In 1997, tensions between Barks and the Studio eventually resulted in a lawsuit that was settled with an agreement that included the disbanding of the Studio. Barks never traveled to make another Disney appearance. He was represented by Rev. Ed Bergen, as he completed a final project. Gerry Tank and Jim Mitchell were to assist Barks in his final years.</paragraph><paragraph>During his Carl Barks Studio years, Barks created two more stories: the script for the final Uncle Scrooge story &quot;Horsing Around with History&quot;, which was first published in Denmark in 1994 with Bill Van Horn art. The Barks outlines for Barks final Donald Duck story &quot;Somewhere in Nowhere&quot;, were first published in 1997, in Italy, with art by Pat Block.</paragraph><paragraph>Austrian artist<space/><link><target>Gottfried Helnwein</target></link><space/>curated and organized the first solo museum-exhibition of Carl Barks. Between 1994 and 1998 the retrospective was shown in ten European museums and seen by more than 400,000 visitors.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.helnwein.de/kuenstler/bibliografie/artikel_449.html'>Gottfried Helnwein &quot;Wer ist Carl Barks?&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the same time in spring 1994, Reichelt and Ina Brockmann designed a special museum exhibition tour about Barks' life and work. Also represented for the first time at this exhibition were Disney artists<space/><link><target>Al Taliaferro</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Floyd Gottfredson</target></link>. Since 1995, more than 500,000 visitors have attended the shows in Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>Reichelt also translated Michael Barrier's biography of Barks into German and published it in 1994.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Final days and death</heading><paragraph>Still living in a new home in Grants Pass, Oregon which he and Gar had built next door to their original home, Barks died in 2000 at the age of 99, seven years after Gar had died.</paragraph><paragraph>Although he was undergoing<space/><link><target>chemotherapy</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>leukemia</target></link><space/>he was, according to caregiver Serene Hunickle, &quot;funny up to the end.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Barks' influence</heading><paragraph>Barks' Donald Duck stories were rated #7 on<space/><link><target>The Comics Journal#The Journal's Top 100 Comics list</target><part>''The Comics Journal'' list of 100 top comics</part></link>; his Uncle Scrooge stories were rated #20.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Steven Spielberg</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>George Lucas</target></link><space/>have acknowledged that the rolling-boulder booby trap in the opening scene of<space/><italics><link><target>Raiders of the Lost Ark</target></link></italics><space/>was inspired by the 1954 Carl Barks Uncle Scrooge adventure &quot;The Seven Cities of Cibola&quot; (<italics><link><target>Uncle Scrooge</target></link></italics><space/>#7). Lucas and Spielberg have also said that some of Barks's stories about space travel and the depiction of aliens had an influence on them.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,921233,00.html'></link>, Lucas comments on the influence of Bark's style of story flow.</extension>Lucas wrote the foreword to the 1982<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge McDuck: His Life and Times</italics>. In it he calls Barkss stories &quot;cinematic&quot; and &quot;a priceless part of our literary heritage&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Walt Disney Treasures</target></link><space/>DVD set<space/><italics><link><target>Walt Disney Treasures: Wave Five#The Chronological Donald, Volume 2</target><part>Chronological Donald, Volume 2</part></link></italics><space/>includes a salute to Barks.</paragraph><paragraph>Carl Barks has an<space/><link><target>asteroid</target></link><space/>named after him,<space/><link><target>2730 Barks</target></link>. A<space/><link><target>Cornell University</target><part>Cornell</part></link><space/>scientist was inspired by Barks' tale &quot;Island in the Sky&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Almere</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link><space/>a street was named after him: Carl Barksweg. The same neighborhood also includes a Donald Ducklaan and a Goofystraat.</paragraph><paragraph>Japanese animator and cartoonist<space/><link><target>Osamu Tezuka</target></link>, who created<space/><link><target>manga</target></link><space/>such as &quot;<link><target>Astro Boy</target></link>&quot; and &quot;<link><target>Black Jack (manga)</target><part>Black Jack</part></link>&quot;, was a fan of Barks' work.<space/><italics>New Treasure Island</italics>, one of Tezuka's first works, was partly influenced by<space/><link><target>Donald Duck Finds Pirate Gold</target></link>.<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="tcj.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tcj.com/manga-finds-pirate-gold-the-case-of-new-treasure-island/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Manga Finds Pirate Gold: The Case of ''New Treasure Island''<space/></arg><arg name="last">Holmberg</arg><arg name="first">Ryan</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">The Comics Journal<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">September 21, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 1949 Donald Duck ten-pager features Donald raising a yacht from the ocean floor by filling it with<space/><link><target>ping pong</target></link><space/>balls. In December 1965 Karl Kryer, a Dane, lifted the sunken freight vessel<space/><italics>Al Kuwait</italics><space/>in the Kuwait Harbor by filling the hull with 27 million tiny inflatable balls of<space/><link><target>polystyrene</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bpib"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.starch.dk/isi/kroyer/schrooge.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Karl Kroyer - "The Sunken Yacht" by Carl Barks<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-03-04</arg></template></extension>Although the suggestion is often made, Kryer denies having been inspired by this Barks story. Some sources claim Kryer was denied a Dutch patent registration (application number NL 6514306) for his invention on the grounds that the Barks story was a<space/><link><target>prior art</target><part>prior publication</part></link><space/>of the invention. However no definite proof of this story is available.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iusmentis.com/patents/priorart/donaldduck/'>The &quot;Donald Duck as prior art&quot; case (in Patents : When is something prior art @ iusmentis.com</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20070927075256<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.octrooicentrum.nl/actueel/nieuws/20060601-1.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">''Donald Duck verslaat uitvinder! donderdag'' 1 juni 2006</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Kryer later successfully raised another ship off Greenland using the same method, and several other sunken vessels worldwide have since been raised by modified versions of this concept. The television show<space/><link><target>MythBusters</target></link><space/>also tested this method and was able to raise a small boat.</paragraph><paragraph>For those currently drawing Disney Duck comics, the influence of Barks cannot be overstated. For artists such as<space/><link><target>Daan Jippes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Freddy Milton</target></link>, Barks' comics have made a great impact.<space/><link><target>Don Rosa</target></link>, one of the most popular living Disney artists, and possibly the one who has been most keen on connecting the various stories into a coherent universe and chronology, considers (with few exceptions) all Barks' duck stories as<space/><link><target>Canon (fiction)</target><part>canon</part></link>, and all others as<space/><link><target>Apocrypha (fiction)</target><part>apocryphal</part></link>. Rosa has said that a number of novelists and movie-makers cite Carl Barks as their 'major influence and inspiration'.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bpib"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bpib.com/illustra2/barks2.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Don Rosa on Carl Barks' Conquest of Europe<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rosa<space/></arg><arg name="first">Don<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 15, 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The popularity of Barks' work in Europe is high, and has been that way for years. When the news of Barks' passing was hardly covered by the press in America, &quot;in Europe the sad news was flashed instantly across the airwaves and every newspaper&amp;nbsp; they realized the world had lost one of the most beloved, influential and well-known creators in international culture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="bpib"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Dozens of noted comic book artists have taken up elements of Barks' style, especially his ink and pen work.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template><space/>In the US elements of Barks' oil painting style of the ducks were evident in the computer animated, 3-D look<space/><italics><link><target>Mickey's Twice Upon a Christmas</target></link></italics><space/>released to video in 2005.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The video game<space/><italics><link><target>Donald Duck: Goin' Quackers</target></link></italics><space/>is dedicated to the memory of Carl Barks.</paragraph><paragraph>Carl Barks drew an early<space/><link><target>Andy Panda</target></link><space/>comic book story published in<space/><italics>New Funnies</italics><space/>#76, 1943. It is one of his few stories to feature humans interacting with<space/><link><target>funny animal</target></link><space/>characters (another is<space/><italics>Dangerous Disguise</italics>,<space/><link><target>Four Color</target></link><space/>#308, 1951<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://coa.inducks.org/story.php?c=W+OS++308-02'>&quot;Dangerous Disguise&quot; at the INDUCKS</link></extension>). See<space/><link><target>List of Fictional Pandas</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The life story of Carl Barks, largely drawing upon his relationship with Disney and the phonetic similarity of his name to<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link>, serves as a loose inspiration to one of the subplots in<space/><italics><link><target>The Last Song of Manuel Sendero</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Ariel Dorfman</target></link>, though his biography in this novel veers sharply into science fiction fantasy and symbolism.</paragraph><paragraph>The first image ever to be displayed on an<space/><link><target>Apple Macintosh</target></link><space/>was a scan of Carl Barks' Scrooge McDuck.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.folklore.org/StoryView.py?project</arg><arg name="title">Macintosh Stories : Scrooge McDuck by Andy Hertzfeld</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-03-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Coo Coo</italics><space/>#1, Hamilton Comics, 1997 (a facsimile of one of the racy magazines Barks did cartoons for in the thirties).</listitem><listitem><italics>The Carl Barks' Big Book of Barney Bear</italics><space/>(ISBN 978-1-60010-929-4), 2011 collection edited by<space/><link><target>Craig Yoe</target></link><space/>and published by<space/><link><target>IDW Publishing</target><part>IDW</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Barney Bear</target></link><space/>and Benny Burro stories that originally appeared in<space/><link><target>Our Gang#The MGM era</target><part>Our Gang Comics</part></link><space/>#1136 (May/June 1944 June 1947); Barks' one substantial non-Disney series.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Carl Barks Library</target></link></italics>, 19841990, 30 hardback volumes in black and white published by<space/><link><target>Another Rainbow Publishing</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Carl Barks Library</italics><space/>(graphic album format, in color) 19921998</listitem><listitem><italics>O Melhor da Disney: As Obras Completas de Carl Barks</italics><space/>20042008, 41 volume limited edition published by<space/><link><target>Editora Abril</target><part>Abril Jovem</part></link><space/>in Brazil, compiling all the stories written by Barks, with his oil paitings as the cover art.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Carl Barks Collection</target></link></italics><space/>20052009, 30 volume limited edition published by<space/><link><target>Egmont (media group)</target><part>Egmont</part></link><space/>in Norway, Sweden, Denmark, and Germany, and by<space/><link><target>Sanoma</target></link><space/>in Finland. Edited by Barks expert Geoffrey Blum.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Complete Carl Barks Disney Library</target></link></italics><space/>2011?, hardback volumes with separate Uncle Scrooge and Donald Duck volumes from<space/><link><target>Fantagraphics Books</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Filmography</heading><paragraph>Films where Barks served as storyman or story director:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrae">Andrae (2006), p. 279-280</extension><space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Modern Inventions</target></link></italics><space/>(May 29, 1937). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Ostrich</target></link></italics><space/>(December 10, 1937).</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Self Control (film)</target><part>Self Control</part></link></italics><space/>(February 11, 1938). Barks served as the story director.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Better Self</target></link></italics><space/>(March 11, 1938). Barks served as the story director.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Nephews</target></link></italics><space/>(April 15, 1938).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Good Scouts</target></link></italics><space/>(July 8, 1938). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Golf Game</target></link></italics><space/>(November 4, 1938). Barks served as the story director.</listitem><listitem><italics>Donald's Lucky Day</italics><space/>(January 13, 1939). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Hockey Champ</italics><space/>(April 28, 1939). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Cousin Gus</target></link></italics><space/>(May 19, 1939). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Sea Scouts (film)</target><part>Sea Scouts</part></link></italics><space/>(June 30, 1939). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>Donald's Penguin</italics><space/>(August 11, 1939). Barks served as the story director.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Autograph Hound</target></link></italics><space/>(September 1, 1939).</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Mr. Duck Steps Out</target></link></italics><space/>(June 7, 1940). Barks served as the story director.</listitem><listitem><italics>Put-Put Troubles</italics><space/>(June 19, 1940).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Bone Trouble</target></link></italics><space/>(June 28, 1940).</listitem><listitem><italics>Donald's Vacation</italics><space/>(August 9, 1940).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>Window Cleaners</italics><space/>(September 20, 1940). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>Fire Chief</italics><space/>(December 13, 1940). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Timber (film)</target><part>Timber</part></link></italics><space/>(January 10, 1941). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>Golden Eggs</italics><space/>(March 7, 1941).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>Early to Bed</italics><space/>(July 11, 1941). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Truant Officer Donald</target></link></italics><space/>(August 1, 1941). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Old MacDonald Duck</target></link></italics><space/>(September 12, 1941). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>Chef Donald</italics><space/>(December 5, 1941). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Village Smithy</italics><space/>(January 16, 1942).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald's Snow Fight</target></link></italics><space/>(April 10, 1942). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Donald Gets Drafted</target></link></italics><space/>(May 1, 1942). Barks served as the story director.<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>The Army Mascot</italics><space/>(May 22, 1942).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Vanishing Private</target></link></italics><space/>(September 25, 1942). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Sky Trooper</target></link></italics><space/>(November 6, 1942).<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>Bellboy Donald</italics><space/>(December 18, 1942). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Old Army Game</target></link></italics><space/>(November 5, 1943). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics>Home Defense</italics><space/>(November 26, 1943). Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Trombone Trouble</target></link></italics><space/>(February 18, 1944). Barks served as the story director. Barks also drew many of the storyboards for the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Plastics Inventor</target></link></italics><space/>(September 1, 1944).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notable stories</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>List of Disney comics by Carl Barks</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Donald Duck Finds Pirate Gold</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Four Color</target></link></italics><space/>#9, October 1942</listitem><listitem>&quot;The Mummy's Ring&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#29, September 1943, presciently dealt with the repatriation of antiquities to their country of origin. This has become a major issue in the contemporary art world and among museums (an example is the dispute between<space/><link><target>Machu Picchu#Controversy with Yale University</target><part>Yale and Peru</part></link><space/>over artifacts from Machu Picchu)</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Christmas on Bear Mountain</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#178, December 1947, first appearance of<space/><link><target>Scrooge McDuck</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Old Castle's Secret</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#189 June 1948</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Sheriff of Bullet Valley</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#199, October 1948</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Lost in the Andes!</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#223, April 1949</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Vacation Time</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Vacation Parade</italics><space/>#1, July 1950</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>A Financial Fable</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</italics><space/>#126, March 1951</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Donald Duck in Old California!</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#328, May 1951</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>A Christmas for Shacktown</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#367, January 1952</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Only a Poor Old Man</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#386 (<italics><link><target>Uncle Scrooge</target></link></italics><space/>#1), March 1952</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Flip Decision</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</italics><space/>#149, June 1952</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Golden Helmet</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#408, July 1952</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Back to the Klondike</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Four Color</italics><space/>#456 (<italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#2), March 1953</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Tralla La</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#6, June 1954</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Fabulous Philosopher's Stone</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#10, June 1955</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Golden Fleecing</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#12, December 1955</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Land Beneath the Ground!</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#13, March 1956</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Money Well</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#21, March 1958</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>The Golden River (cartoon)</target><part>The Golden River</part></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#22, 1958</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Island in the Sky (cartoon)</target><part>Island in the Sky</part></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#29, March 1960</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>North of the Yukon</target></link>&quot;,<space/><italics>Uncle Scrooge</italics><space/>#59, September 1965</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Awards</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>The Shazam Award for Best Writer (Humor Division) in 1970</listitem><listitem>The Academy of Comic Book Arts Hall of Fame Award in 1973</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Inkpot Award</target><part>Inkpot</part></link><space/>in 1977 from the<space/><link><target>Comic-Con International</target><part>San Diego Comic Con</part></link></listitem><listitem>Inducted into the<space/><link><target>List of Eisner Award winners#The Will Eisner Award Hall of Fame</target><part>Eisner Awards Hall of Fame</part></link><space/>in 1987.</listitem><listitem>Inducted into the<space/><link><target>National Cartoon Museum#William Randolph Hearst Cartoon Hall of Fame</target><part>William Randolph Hearst Cartoon Hall of Fame</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Comics Buyer's Guide</target></link><space/>Fan Award for Favorite Writer in 1996.</listitem><listitem>The Walt Disney Company bestowed a<space/><link><target>Duckster</target></link><space/>award in 1971 and their<space/><link><target>Disney Legends</target></link><space/>award in 1991</listitem><listitem>The series<space/><italics>Carl Barks Library</italics><space/>received the Comics Buyer's Guide Fan Award for Favorite Reprint Graphic Novel/Album for 1996.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Art materials</heading><paragraph>Barks was an enthusiastic user of<space/><link><target>Esterbrook</target></link><space/>pens. He particularly used a N 356 model to ink and letter his Donald Duck comic-book pages.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://davewesselscomix.blogspot.com/2010/11/carl-barks-esterbrook-356.html
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Barks' Esterbook 356
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-03-04
<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-11-15</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>"... I used a #356 Esterbrook art and drafting pen which could do everything from thin 'fadeaways' to broad accented curve sweeps on foreground circles such as the ducks' forms. The trick of breaking in a new pen, I discovered, is to soak it for several minutes in the ink bottle. Then wipe off the ink and the pen's varnish. For some weird reason most new pens then start out flexible and free-flowing&nbsp;..." (Letter to Scott Matheson, March 21, 1973)<ref>[http://hans.presto.tripod.com/isbn/1578065011.html Carl Barks letters - Hans Presto nibs website]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Disney comics by Carl Barks</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of non-Disney comics by Carl Barks</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Citations</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Sources</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">[[The Carl Barks Collection|Carl Barks samlade verk]]<space/></arg><arg name="last">Blum<space/></arg><arg name="first">Geoffrey<space/></arg><arg name="volume">XXX<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Egmont Group|Egmont Kärnan AB]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Malmö<space/></arg><arg name="language">Swedish<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-91-7405-077-6<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Andrae</arg><arg name="first">Tom</arg><arg name="title">Carl Barks and the Disney Comic Book: Unmasking the Myth of Modernity<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">A Carl Barks Filmography</arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University Press of Mississippi]]</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781578068586</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.gr/books?id</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Carl Barks And the Disney Comic Book<space/></arg><arg name="last">Andrae<space/></arg><arg name="first">Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University Press of Mississippi<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1578068586<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Carl Barks: Conversations<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ault<space/></arg><arg name="first">Donald<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Donald Ault<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University Press of Mississippi<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1578065011<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Carl Barks and the Art of the Comic Book<space/></arg><arg name="last">Barrier<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Michael Barrier (historian)<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">M. Lilien<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0960765201<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template><space/><xhtml:small>The book contains some of the most important interviews Barks made between 1962 and 2000 (Thomas Andrae, Michael Barrier, Bill Blackbeard, E. B. Boatner, Glenn Bray, Paul Ciotti, Sbastien Durand, Bob Foster, Didier Ghez, Stephen Gong, Leonardo Gori, Bruce Hamilton,<space/><link><target>Gottfried Helnwein</target></link>, Markku Kiveks, Michael Naiman,<space/><link><target>Graphic Story Magazine</target><part>Bill Spicer</part></link>, Francesco Stajano, Klaus Strzyz,<space/><link><target>Edward Summer</target></link>, Erik Svane,<space/><link><target>Don Thompson (Comics Buyer's Guide)</target><part>Don Thompson</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Maggie Thompson</target></link>, Malcolm Willits, Nicky Wright, and Lynda Ault).</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0055119/publicity'>List of Carl Barks interviews and articles in the international press</link></listitem><listitem>Carl Barks,<space/><link><target>Edward Summer</target></link><space/><italics>Walt Disney's Uncle Scrooge McDuck: His Life and Times</italics>, Berkeley, California: Celestial Arts, 1981 (first trade edition 1987).</listitem><listitem>Edward Summer.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.michaelspornanimation.com/splog/?p=2232'>&quot;Of Ducks and Men: Cark Barks Interviewed.</link><space/><italics>Panels</italics><space/>#2 (1981)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.brucehamilton.com/hamilton/unexpurgated.html'>''The Unexpurgated Carl Barks''</link>, Hamilton Comics, 1997</listitem><listitem>Gottfried Helnwein,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.helnweincomic.homestead.com/carlbarks.html'>'Wer ist Carl Barks' (Who is Carl Barks?)</link>, texts by Roy Disney, Gottfried Helnwein, Carsten Laqua, Andreas Platthaus und Ulrich Schrder, (ISBN 3-8118-5341-4).</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fernández<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Manuel<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Carl Barks and the Disney Comic Book: Unmasking the Myth of Modernity<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[The Journal of Popular Culture]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>41<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>539–540<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Blackwell Publishing]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 2008<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1540-5931.2008.00534_2.x</arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Alfons Molin,<space/><italics>Carl Barks, un viento crata</italics>, Madrid: Ediciones Sinsentido, Coleccin Sin palabras / serie A, nm.16 (2007).</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Inducks author</target><arg>CB</arg><arg>Carl Barks</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lambiek.net/artists/b/barks.htm'>Carl Barks</link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Lambiek</target><part>Lambiek Comiclopedia</part></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>IMDb name</target><arg name="id">0055119</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Carl Barks</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.barksbase.de/english/'>The HTML Barks base</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cbarks.dk/'>Carl Barks.dk</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.michaelbarrier.com/Essays/Barks/essay_barks.htm'>''Thoughts on Carl Barks's Hundredth Birthday''</link><space/>An essay by<space/><link><target>Michael Barrier (historian)</target><part>Michael Barrier</part></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20071015153642<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://library.csun.edu/Collections/SCA/SC/FG/fdgds4b.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Carl Barks Correspondance, 1963 - 1984<space/></arg></template><space/>A finding Guide by Tony Gardner</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.iusmentis.com/patents/priorart/donaldduck/'>The &quot;Donald Duck as prior art&quot; case</link><space/>Patent case discussion on<space/><italics>Ius Mentis</italics></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Disney comics navbox</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Barks, Carl
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Illustrator, comic book creator
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>March 27, 1901
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Merrill, Oregon, United States
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>August 25, 2000
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Grants Pass, Oregon, United States
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Barks, Carl</target></template><link><target>Category:1901 births</target></link><link><target>Category:2000 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:American cartoonists</target></link><link><target>Category:American male screenwriters</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Dutch descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Scottish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American comics artists</target></link><link><target>Category:Disney comics writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Disney comics artists</target></link><link><target>Category:American illustrators</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in Oregon</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from leukemia</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Grants Pass, Oregon</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Klamath County, Oregon</target></link><link><target>Category:Will Eisner Award Hall of Fame inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Temecula, California</target></link></paragraph></article>