<article title='Amerigo_Vespucci'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the explorer</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Amerigo Vespucci (disambiguation)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>pp-semi-indef</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="image"><space/>Amerigo Vespucci01.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Statue outside the [[Uffizi]], Florence.
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>March 9, 1454
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Florence]], [[Republic of Florence]], in present-day [[Italy]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>February 22, 1512
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Seville]], [[Crown of Castile]], in present-day [[Spain]]
</arg><arg name="other_names"><space/>Américo Vespucio [''[[Spanish (language)|es]]'']<br /><space/>Americus Vespucius [''[[Latin language|la]]'']<br />Américo Vespúcio [''[[Portuguese language|pt]]'']<br />Alberigo Vespucci
</arg><arg name="known_for"><space/>Demonstrating that the [[New World]] was not [[Asia]] but a previously unknown fourth [[continent]].{{ref label|4th|a|a}}
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>[[Merchant]], [[Explorer]], [[Cartographer]]
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>[[Italian people|Italian]]
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>AmerigoVespucci Signature.png
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Amerigo Vespucci</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>ameˈriːɡo vesˈputtʃi</arg></template>; March 9, 1454<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>February 22, 1512) was an<space/><link><target>Italian people</target><part>Italian</part></link><space/><link><target>explorer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>financier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>navigator</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cartographer</target></link><space/>who first demonstrated that<space/><link><target>Brazil</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link><space/>did not represent Asia's eastern outskirts as initially conjectured from<space/><link><target>Voyages of Christopher Columbus</target><part>Columbus' voyages</part></link>, but instead constituted an entirely separate landmass hitherto unknown to<space/><link><target>Afro-Eurasia</target><trail>ns</trail></link>. Colloquially referred to as the<space/><link><target>New World</target></link>, this second super continent came to be termed &quot;<link><target>Americas</target><part>America</part></link>&quot;, deriving<space/><link><target>America (name)</target><part>its name</part></link><space/>from<space/><bold>Americus</bold>, the<space/><link><target>Latinisation of names</target><part>Latin</part></link><space/>version of Vespucci's<space/><link><target>given name</target><part>first name</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See e.g. Encyclopdia Britannica Online,<space/><italics>Amerigo Vespucci</italics>; and Room, Adrian. 2004. Placenames of the world: origins and meanings of the names for over 5000 natural features, countries, capitals, territories, cities and historic sights:<space/><italics>America</italics><space/>believed to have<space/><link><target>Americas#Naming</target><part>derived their name</part></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Grammatical gender</target><part>feminized</part></link><space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>version of his<space/><link><target>given name</target><part>first name</part></link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Rival explanations have been proposed (see Arciniegas, Germn.<space/><italics>Amerigo and the New World: The Life &amp; Times of Amerigo Vespucci</italics>. Translated by Harriet de Ons. New York: Octagon Books, 1978.<template><target>specify</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template>) For example, some have speculated that the name's origin may lie with<space/><link><target>Richard Amerike</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/tudors/americaname_03.shtml'></link>, or with the region<space/><link><target>Amerrique</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Nicaragua</target></link>. None of these theories has been accepted in mainstream academia.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Birthplace of Amerigo Vespucci HHWIX645.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>The birthplace of Amerigo Vespucci.</part></link>Amerigo Vespucci was born and raised in<space/><link><target>Republic of Florence</target><part>Florence</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Italian Peninsula</target><part>Italy</part></link>. He was the third son of Ser Nastagio (Anastasio), a Florentine notary, and Lisabetta Mini.<extension extension_name='ref' name="markham">C.R. Markham (1894) &quot;Introduction&quot;, in<space/><italics>The Letters of Amerigo Vespucci and other documents illustrative of his career</italics>. London: Hakluyt.</extension><space/>Amerigo Vespucci was educated by his uncle, Fra Giorgio Antonio Vespucci, a<space/><link><target>Dominican Order</target><part>Dominican friar</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>San Marco, Florence</target><part>the monastery of San Marco</part></link><space/>in Florence.</paragraph><paragraph>While his elder brothers were sent to the<space/><link><target>University of Pisa</target></link><space/>to pursue scholarly careers, Amerigo Vespucci embraced a mercantile life, and was hired as a clerk by the Florentine commercial<space/><link><target>Medici bank</target><part>house of Medici</part></link>, headed by<space/><link><target>Lorenzo de' Medici</target></link>. Vespucci acquired the favor and protection of<space/><link><target>Lorenzo di Pierfrancesco de' Medici</target></link><space/>who became the head of the business after the elder Lorenzo's death in 1492. In March 1492, the Medici dispatched the thirty-eight-year-old Vespucci and Donato Niccolini as confidential agents to look into the Medici branch office in<space/><link><target>Cdiz</target></link><space/>(Spain), whose managers and dealings were under suspicion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="markham"></extension><space/>In April 1495, by the intrigues of Bishop<space/><link><target>Juan Rodrguez de Fonseca</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Crown of Castile</target></link><space/>broke their monopoly deal with<space/><link><target>Christopher Columbus</target></link><space/>and began handing out licenses to other navigators for the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link>. Just around this time (149596), Vespucci was engaged as the executor of Giannotto Berardi, an Italian merchant who had recently died in Seville. Vespucci organized the fulfillment of Berardi's outstanding contract with the Castilian crown to provide twelve vessels for the Indies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="markham"></extension><space/>After these were delivered, Vespucci continued as a provision contractor for Indies expeditions, and is known to have secured beef supplies for at least one (if not two) of Columbus' voyages.<extension extension_name='ref' name="markham"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Expeditions</heading><paragraph>At the invitation of king<space/><link><target>Manuel I of Portugal</target></link>, Vespucci participated as observer in several voyages that explored the east coast of<space/><link><target>South America</target></link><space/>between 1499 and 1502. On the first of these voyages he was aboard the ship that discovered that South America extended much further south than previously thought.</paragraph><paragraph>The expeditions became widely known in Europe after two accounts attributed to Vespucci were published between 1502 and 1504. In 1507,<space/><link><target>Martin Waldseemller</target></link><space/>produced a world map on which he named the new continent<space/><link><target>Americas</target><part>America</part></link><space/>after the feminine Latin version of Vespucci's first name, which is Americus. In an accompanying book, Waldseemller published one of the Vespucci accounts, which led to criticism that Vespucci was trying to upset<space/><link><target>Christopher Columbus</target></link>' glory. However, the rediscovery in the 18th century of other letters by Vespucci has led to the view that the early published accounts, notably the<space/><link><target>The Americas#Etymology and naming</target><part>Soderini Letter</part></link>, could be fabrications, not by Vespucci, but by others.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical role</heading><paragraph>In 1508 the position of chief of navigation of Spain (<italics>piloto mayor de Indias</italics>) was created for Vespucci, with the responsibility of planning navigation for voyages to the Indies.<link><target>File:Vespucci arrives in New World.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Vespucci's first encounter with native Americans in Honduras, 1497 (<link><target>Theodor de Bry</target><part>De Bry</part></link>'s illustration, c.1592)</part></link>Two letters attributed to Vespucci were published during his lifetime.<space/><italics><link><target>Mundus Novus</target></link></italics><space/>(New World) was a Latin translation of a lost Italian letter sent from<space/><link><target>Lisbon</target></link><space/>to Lorenzo di Pierfrancesco de' Medici. It describes a voyage to South America in 15011502.<space/><italics>Mundus Novus</italics><space/>was published in late 1502 or early 1503 and soon reprinted and distributed in numerous European countries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="formisano">Formisano, Luciano (Ed.) (1992).<space/><italics>Letters from a New World: Amerigo Vespucci's Discovery of America</italics>. New York: Marsilio. ISBN 0-941419-62-2. Pp. xixxxvi.</extension><italics>Lettera di Amerigo Vespucci delle isole nuovamente trovate in quattro suoi viaggi</italics><space/>(Letter of Amerigo Vespucci concerning the isles newly discovered on his four voyages), known as<space/><italics>Lettera al Soderini</italics><space/>or just<space/><italics>Lettera</italics>, was a letter in Italian addressed to<space/><link><target>Piero Soderini</target></link>. Printed in 1504 or 1505, it claimed to be an account of four voyages to the Americas made by Vespucci between 1497 and 1504. A Latin translation was published by the German<space/><link><target>Martin Waldseemller</target></link><space/>in 1507 in<space/><italics><link><target>Cosmographiae Introductio</target></link></italics>, a book on<space/><link><target>cosmography</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>geography</target></link>, as<space/><italics>Quattuor Americi Vespucij navigationes</italics><space/>(Four Voyages of Amerigo Vespucci).<extension extension_name='ref' name="formisano"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On March 22, 1508,<space/><link><target>Ferdinand II of Aragon</target><part>King Ferdinand</part></link><space/>made Vespucci chief navigator of Spain at a huge salary<extension extension_name='ref'>Ober, p. 234</extension><space/>and commissioned him to found a school of navigation, in order to standardize and modernize navigation techniques used by Iberian sea captains then exploring the world. Vespucci even developed a rudimentary, but fairly accurate method of determining longitude (which only more accurate chronometers would later improve upon).<link><target>File:Cannibalism in the New World, from Vespucci.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>200px</part><part>The first known depiction of<space/><link><target>cannibalism</target></link><space/>in the New World. Engraving by Johann Froschauer for an edition of Amerigo Vespucci's ''Mundus Novus'', published in Augsburg in 1505.</part></link>In the 18th century three unpublished familiar letters from Vespucci to Lorenzo de' Medici were rediscovered. One describes a voyage made in 14991500 which corresponds with the second of the &quot;four voyages&quot;. Another was written from<space/><link><target>Cap-Vert</target><part>Cape Verde</part></link><space/>in 1501 in the early part of the third of the four voyages, before crossing the Atlantic. The third letter was sent from Lisbon after the completion of that voyage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="formisano"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some have suggested that Vespucci, in the two letters published in his lifetime, was exaggerating his role and constructed deliberate fabrications. However, many scholars now believe that the two letters were not written by him but were fabrications by others based in part on genuine letters by Vespucci.It was the publication and widespread circulation of the letters that might have led Waldseemller to name the new continent<space/><link><target>Americas</target><part>America</part></link><space/>on his world map of 1507 in<space/><link><target>Lorraine (province)</target><part>Lorraine</part></link>. Vespucci used a<space/><link><target>Latinization (literature)</target><part>Latinised</part></link><space/>form of his name,<space/><bold>Americus Vespucius</bold>, in his<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>writings, which Waldseemller used as a base for the new name, taking the feminine form<space/><italics>America</italics>, according to the prevalent view (for other hypotheses, see the footnote in the introduction). The book accompanying the map stated: &quot;I do not see what right any one would have to object to calling this part, after Americus who discovered it and who is a man of intelligence, Amerige, that is, the Land of Americus, or America: since both Europa and Asia got their names from women&quot;. It is possible that Vespucci was not aware that Waldseemller had named the continent after him.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ray, p.93</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The two disputed letters claim that Vespucci made four voyages to America, while at most two can be verified from other sources. At the moment there is a dispute between historians on when Vespucci visited the mainland the first time. Some historians like Germn Arciniegas and Gabriel Camargo Prez think that his first voyage was made in June 1497 with the Spanish Pilot Juan de la Cosa.</paragraph><paragraph>Vespucci's real historical importance may well rest more in his letters, whether he wrote them all or not, than in his discoveries. From these letters, the European public learned about the newly discovered continents of the Americas for the first time; its existence became generally known throughout Europe within a few years of the letters' publication.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Voyages</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Domenico ghirlandaio, amerigo vespucci, ognissanti, Firenze.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Portrait of Amerigo Vespucci as a child, part of the<space/><link><target>:File:Domenico ghirlandaio, madonna della misericordia, ognissanti, Firenze.jpg</target><part>''Madonna della Misericordia''</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Domenico Ghirlandaio</target></link><space/>at the Ognissanti church in Florence</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The first and fourth voyages are disputed to have occurred, while the second and third are certain voyages.</paragraph><heading level='3'>First voyage</heading><paragraph>A letter published in 1504 purports to be an account by Vespucci, written to Soderini, of a lengthy visit to the New World, leaving Spain in May 1497 and returning in October 1498. However, modern scholars have doubted that this voyage took place, and consider this letter a forgery.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/papers/canaday.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Life of Amerigo Vespucci<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Millersville.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-02-28</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20100328011335/http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/papers/canaday.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>28 March 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></extension><space/>Whoever did write the letter makes several observations of native customs, including use of<space/><link><target>hammock</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sweat lodge</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1497vespucci%2Damerica.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Account of alleged 1497 voyage<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fordham.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-02-28</arg></template></extension><space/>The names of Amerigo Vespucci's ships were the<space/><italics>San Antiago</italics>,<space/><italics>Repertaga</italics>,<space/><italics>Wegiz</italics>, and the<space/><italics>Girmand</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Second voyage</heading><paragraph>About 14991500, Vespucci joined an expedition in the service of Spain, with<space/><link><target>Alonso de Ojeda</target></link><space/>(or Hojeda) as the fleet commander. The intention was to sail around the southern end of the African mainland into the<space/><link><target>Indian Ocean</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OGorman"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>O'Gorman<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Edmundo<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Edmundo O'Gorman<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Invention of America<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Indiana University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1961<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>106–107</arg></template></extension><space/>After hitting land at the coast of what is now<space/><link><target>Guyana</target></link>, the two seem to have separated. Vespucci sailed southward, discovering the mouth of the<space/><link><target>Amazon River</target></link><space/>and reaching 6S, before turning around and seeing<space/><link><target>Trinidad</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Orinoco River</target></link><space/>and returning to Spain by way of<space/><link><target>Hispaniola</target></link>. The letter, to Lorenzo di Pierfrancesco de' Medici, claims that Vespucci determined his longitude celestially<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vcelest"><preblock><preline><space/><space/>on a rainy and stormy day with calm seas, stars could be identified</preline><preline><space/><space/>near the horizon to judge<space/><link><target>latitude</target></link>/<link><target>longitude</target></link></preline><preline><space/><space/>celestially. Although South America's<space/><link><target>continental shelf</target></link></preline><preline><space/><space/>drops quickly into the deep ocean beyond the<space/><link><target>Orinoco River</target></link>,</preline><preline><space/><space/>the mouth is on the shelf, avoiding the ocean swells</preline><preline><space/><space/>and waves which hinder visibility of stars near the</preline><preline><space/><space/>horizon. Seamen who could navigate from Europe to America</preline><preline><space/><space/>and back could chart stars on the horizon, especially</preline><preline><space/><space/>for a<space/><link><target>cartographer</target></link><space/>like Vespucci.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2009</arg></template></preline></preblock></extension>on August 23, 1499, while on this voyage. However, that claim may be fraudulent,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vcelest"></extension><space/>which could cast doubt on the letter's credibility.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Third voyage</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Amerigo Vespucci (with turban).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Portrait of Vespucci which titles him &quot;discoverer and conqueror of Brazilian land&quot;.</part></link>The last certain voyage of Vespucci was led by<space/><link><target>Gonalo Coelho</target></link><space/>in 15011502 in the service of<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link>. Departing from<space/><link><target>Lisbon</target></link>, the fleet sailed first to<space/><link><target>Cap-Vert</target><part>Cape Verde</part></link><space/>where they met two of<space/><link><target>Pedro lvares Cabral</target></link>'s ships returning from<space/><link><target>India</target></link>. In a letter from Cape Verde, Vespucci says that he hopes to visit the same lands that lvares Cabral had explored, suggesting that the intention is to sail west to Asia, as on the 14991500 voyage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OGorman"></extension><space/>On reaching the coast of<space/><link><target>Brazil</target></link>, they sailed south along the coast of<space/><link><target>South America</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Rio de Janeiro</target></link>'s bay. If his own account is to be believed, he reached the latitude of<space/><link><target>Patagonia</target></link><space/>before turning back, although this also seems doubtful, since his account does not mention the broad estuary of the<space/><link><target>Ro de la Plata</target></link>, which he must have seen if he had gotten that far south. Portuguese maps of South America, created after the voyage of Coelho and Vespucci, do not show any land south of present-day<space/><link><target>Canania</target></link><space/>at 25 S, so this may represent the southernmost extent of their voyages.</paragraph><paragraph>After the first half of the expedition, Vespucci mapped<space/><link><target>Alpha Centauri</target><part>Alpha</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Beta Centauri</target></link>, as well as the<space/><link><target>constellation</target></link><space/><link><target>Crux</target></link>, the Southern Cross and the Coalsack Nebula.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dekker, Elly (1990),<space/><italics>Annals of Science</italics>, vol. 47, pp. 535543.</extension><space/>Although these<space/><link><target>star</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>had been known to the ancient<space/><link><target>Greece</target><part>Greeks</part></link>, gradual<space/><link><target>precession (astronomy)</target><part>precession</part></link><space/>had lowered them below the<space/><link><target>Europe</target><trail>an</trail></link><space/>horizon so that they had been forgotten. On his return to Lisbon, Vespucci wrote in a letter to Medici that the land masses they explored were much larger than anticipated and different from the Asia described by<space/><link><target>Ptolemy</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Marco Polo</target></link><space/>and therefore, must be a New World, that is, a previously unknown fourth continent, after Europe, Asia, and Africa.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Fourth voyage</heading><paragraph>Vespucci's fourth voyage was another expedition for the Portuguese crown down the eastern coast of Brazil, that set out in May 1503 and returned to Portugal in June 1504. Like his alleged first voyage, Vespucci's last voyage in 15031504 is also disputed to have taken place.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ray, p.91</extension><space/>The only source of information for the last voyage is the<space/><italics>Letter to Soderini</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Markham, pp.5256</extension><space/>but as several modern scholars dispute Vespucci's authorship of the letter to Soderini, it is also sometimes doubted whether Vespucci undertook this trip.<template><target>ref label</target><arg>5th</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>b</arg></template><space/>However, Portuguese documents do confirm a voyage to Brazil was undertaken in 150304 by the captain<space/><link><target>Gonalo Coelho</target></link>, very likely the same captain of the 1501 mapping expedition (Vespucci's third voyage), and so it is quite possible that Vespucci went on board this one as well.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fernndez-Armesto (2007: p.168-69).</extension><space/>However, it is not independently confirmed Vespucci was aboard and there are some difficulties in the reported dates and details.</paragraph><paragraph>The letters caused controversy after Vespucci's death, especially among the supporters of Columbus who believed Columbus' priority for the discovery of America was being undermined, and seriously damaged Vespucci's reputation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ray, pp.9697; Arciniegas (1955:p.16)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal</heading><paragraph>Vespucci was a cousin of the husband of<space/><link><target>Simonetta Vespucci</target></link>. He married Maria Cerezo. One of the very few references to Amerigo's wife is contained in a royal decree dated May 22, 1512 giving his widow, Maria Cerezo a lifetime pension of ten thousand marvedis per annum deducted from the salary of her husband's successor.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://books.google.co.in/books?id=T3AYguU0HcgC&amp;pg=PT160&amp;dq=amerigo+vespucci+death&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=g3SqVJXCFIKjugTDyYLgCQ&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAw</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Final years</heading><paragraph>Not long after his return to Spain, Vespucci became a Spanish citizen. On March 22, 1508 he was made the pilot major of Spain by<space/><link><target>Ferdinand II of Aragon</target></link><space/>in honor of his discoveries. Vespucci also ran a school for navigators. He died on February 22, 1512 at his home in<space/><link><target>Seville</target></link>, Spain and was buried at Vespucci family burial place in<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link>, Italy.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://books.google.co.in/books?id=QvP-m6EuU3UC&amp;pg=PA20&amp;dq=amerigo+vespucci+death&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=qm2qVN3eDcaSuAT_9IHICQ&amp;ved=0CBsQ6AEwAA</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>https://books.google.co.in/books?id=0eLn3I6iUtkC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=amerigo+vespucci+death&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=qm2qVN3eDcaSuAT_9IHICQ&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwBQ</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>note label</target><arg>4th</arg><arg>a</arg><arg>a</arg></template>Europeans had long conceptualized the<space/><link><target>Afro-Eurasia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>landmass as divided into the same three continents known today:<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Asia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>. Once<space/><link><target>cosmographer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>realized that the<space/><link><target>New World</target></link><space/>was not connected to the<space/><link><target>Old World</target><part>Old</part></link><space/>(but before its true<space/><link><target>geography</target></link><space/>was fully<space/><link><target>map</target><trail>ped</trail></link>), they considered the<space/><link><target>Americas</target></link><space/>to be a single, fourth<space/><link><target>continent</target></link>.</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>note label</target><arg>5th</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>b</arg></template><space/>The question of the authenticity of Vespucci's authorship of the 1504<space/><italics>Mundus Novus</italics><space/>and the 1505<space/><italics>Letter of Soderini</italics>, the only two texts published in Vespucci's lifetime, was famously raised by Magnaghi (1924). He proposed the Soderini letter was<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>written by Vespucci, but rather cobbled together by unscrupulous Florentine publishers, cutting and pasting together various accounts, some from Vespucci, others from elsewhere. Magnaghi was the first to propose that only the second and third voyages were true (as they are corroborated in Vespucci's other manuscript letters), while the first and fourth voyages (which are only found in the Soderini text) were fabricated by the publishers. The later (1937) discovery of a corrobotary Vespucci manuscript letter for the first voyage the &quot;Ridolfi fragment&quot; (Formisiano, 1992: p.37-44) means only the fourth voyage is really found in Soderini alone. The Magnaghi thesis has been a bitterly divisive factor in Vespucci scholarship. The Magnaghi thesis was accepted and popularized by Pohl (1944) but rejected by Arciniegas (1955), who posited all four voyages as truthful. Formisiano (1992) also rejects the Magnaghi thesis (although recognizing publishers probably fiddled with it), and declares all four voyages genuine, but in details (esp. the first) differing from Arciniegas. Fernndez-Armesto (2007: p.128) declares the authenticity question &quot;inconclusive&quot;, hypothesizes that the first voyage is probably just another version of the second, the third is unassailable, and the fourth probably true (but too mangled to be sure).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Amerigo Vespucci (Charles Lester Edwards, Amerigo Vespucci) [2009] Viartis ISBN 978-1-906421-02-1</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Arciniegas, German (1955)<space/><italics>Amerigo and the New World: The Life &amp; Times of Amerigo Vespucci</italics>. New York: Knopf. 1955 English translation by Harriet de Ons. First edition published in Spanish in 1952 as<space/><italics>Amerigo y el Nuevo Mundo</italics>, Mexico: Hermes.</listitem><listitem>Fernndez-Armesto, Felipe (2007)<space/><italics>Amerigo: The Man Who Gave his Name to America</italics>. New York: Random House.</listitem><listitem>Formisano, Luciano (1992)<space/><italics>Letters from a New World: Amerigo Vespucci's Discovery of America</italics>. New York: Marsilio.</listitem><listitem>Magnaghi, Alberto (1924)<space/><italics>Amerigo Vespucci: Studio critico, con speciale riguardo ad una nuova valutazione delle fonti e con documenti inediti tratti dal Codice Vaglienti</italics>, 2 vols, 1926 (2nd.) ed., Rome: Treves</listitem><listitem>Pohl, Frederick J. (1944)<space/><italics>Amerigo Vespucci: Pilot Major</italics>. New York: Columbia University Press.</listitem><listitem>Ober, Frederick A. (1907)<space/><italics>Heroes of American History: Amerigo Vespucci</italics><space/>New York: Harper &amp; Brothers</listitem><listitem>Schulz, Norbert<space/><italics>Amerigo Vespucci, Mundus Novus (mit Zweittexten)</italics>. M.M.O., Verlag zur Frderung des Mittel- und Neulat (Vivarium (Series neolatina, Band II))) ISBN 978-3-9811144-2-3</listitem><listitem>Markham, Clements R. (1894)<space/><italics>The Letters of Amerigo Vespucci, and Other Documents Illustrative of His Career</italics>.<space/><link><target>Hakluyt Society</target></link>. (Reissued by<space/><link><target>Cambridge University Press</target></link>, 2010. ISBN 978-1-108-01286-7)</listitem><listitem>Ray, Kurt (2003)<space/><italics>Amerigo Vespucci: Italian Explorer of the Americas</italics>, The Rosen Publishing Group, 2003 ISBN 0823936155.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target></template><template><target>Appletons' Poster</target><arg name="year">1900</arg><arg>Amerigo Vespucci</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target><arg>Vespucci, Amerigo</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Canaday, James A.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/papers/canaday.html'>The Life of Amerigo Vespucci</link></italics></listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Vespucci,+Amerigo<space/></arg><arg name="name">Amerigo Vespucci</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Amerigo Vespucci</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Vespucci, Amerigo.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1497vespucci%2Damerica.html'>&quot;Account of His First Voyage 1497 (Letter to Pier Soderini, Gonfalonier of the Republic of Florence)&quot;</link>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/modsbook.html'>Internet Modern History Sourcebook-Fordham University (U.S.)</link></listitem><listitem>Mason, Wyatt,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/02/magazine/02wwln-lede-t.html'>'I am America. (And So?)'</link><space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics>, December 12, 2007.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no</arg><arg name="viaf">8183531</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Martin Waldseemller, Franz Wieser (Ritter von), Edward Burke (trans),<space/><link type='external' href='http://archive.org/details/cosmographiintr00waldgoog'>''The Cosmographi Introductio of Martin Waldseemller in facsimile: followed by the Four voyages of Amerigo Vespucci''</link>, The United States Catholic Historical Society, 1908.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/geogmap/waldexh.html'>1507 Waldseemller Map</link><space/>from the US<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/preserv/tops/france-easton.html'>TOPS Lecture at Library of Congress, Drs. France and Easton</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>World Digital Library</target></link><space/>presentation of<space/><link type='external' href='http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.wdl/wdl.369'>the 1507 Waldseemller Map in the Library of Congress</link>. This is the only known surviving copy of the wall map edition of which it is believed 1,000 copies were printed. Four originals of the 1507 globe gore map are in existence in Germany, UK and US.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://hos.ou.edu/galleries//15thCentury/Vespucci/'>Online Galleries, History of Science Collections, University of Oklahoma Libraries</link><space/>High resolution images of works by and/or portraits of Amerigo Vespucci in .jpg and .tiff format.</listitem><listitem>Soderini Letters in<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com.au/books?id=iZ5TZHXOnYcC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=Ramusio+%22Primo+Volume+delle+Nauigationi+et+Viaggi,+%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=mGhaUbbPFM7PkAX654CIDg&amp;amp;redir_esc=y'>Giovanni Battista Ramusio, ''Primo Volume delle Nauigationi et Viaggi,'' Venetia, 1550, fol.138-140.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Vespucci, Amerigo
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Italian explorer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>March 9, 1454
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Florence]], [[Republic of Florence]], in present-day [[Italy]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>February 22, 1512
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Seville]], [[Crown of Castile]], in present-day [[Spain]]
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Vespucci, Amerigo</target></template><link><target>Category:1454 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1512 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:15th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century explorers</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from malaria</target></link><link><target>Category:Explorers of South America</target></link><link><target>Category:Infectious disease deaths in Spain</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian cartographers</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian explorers</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian Roman Catholics</target></link><link><target>Category:Maritime history of Portugal</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Florence</target></link><link><target>Category:World Digital Library related</target></link><link><target>Category:Cartographers of North America</target></link><link><target>Category:Medieval cartographers</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century cartographers</target></link></paragraph></article>