<article title='Brabham'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg></arg><arg>people with the surname</arg><arg>Brabham (surname)</arg><arg>the place in Australia</arg><arg>Brabham, Western Australia</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template><template><target>Featured article</target></template><template><target>Former F1 team</target><arg name="Short_name"><space/>Brabham
</arg><arg name="Long_name"><space/>Motor Racing Developments, Ltd.
</arg><arg name="Logo"><space/>[[File:Brabham91.png]]
</arg><arg name="Base"><space/>[[Milton Keynes]], United Kingdom
</arg><arg name="Founders"><space/>[[Jack Brabham]]<br>[[Ron Tauranac]]
</arg><arg name="Staff"><space/>[[Bernie Ecclestone]]<br>[[Gordon Murray]]<br>[[Ron Dennis]]<br>[[Charlie Whiting]]<br>[[John Judd]]<br>[[Herbie Blash]]
</arg><arg name="Drivers"><space/>{{flagicon|AUS}} [[Jack Brabham]]<br>{{flagicon|USA}} [[Dan Gurney]]<br>{{flagicon|NZL}} [[Denny Hulme]]<BR>{{flagicon|AUT}} [[Jochen Rindt]]<br>{{flagicon|BEL}} [[Jacky Ickx]]<br>{{flagicon|GBR}} [[Graham Hill]]<br>{{flagicon|ARG}} [[Carlos Reutemann]]<br>{{flagicon|AUT}} [[Niki Lauda]]<br>{{flagicon|BRA}} [[Nelson Piquet]]<br>{{flagicon|ITA}} [[Riccardo Patrese]]<br>{{flagicon|ITA}} [[Elio de Angelis]]<br>{{flagicon|GBR}} [[Derek Warwick]]<br>{{flagicon|ITA}} [[Stefano Modena]]<br>{{flagicon|GBR}} [[Martin Brundle]]<br>{{flagicon|AUS}} [[David Brabham]]<br>{{flagicon|GBR}} [[Damon Hill]]<br>{{flagicon|MEX}} [[Héctor Rebaque]]<br>{{flagicon|GBR}} [[John Watson (racing driver)|John Watson]]<br>{{flagicon|BRA}} [[Carlos Pace]]
</arg><arg name="Debut"><space/>[[1962 German Grand Prix]]
</arg><arg name="Races"><space/>402
</arg><arg name="Cons_champ"><space/>2 ({{f1|1966}}, {{f1|1967}})
</arg><arg name="Drivers_champ"><space/>4 ({{f1|1966}}, {{f1|1967}}, {{f1|1981}}, {{f1|1983}})
</arg><arg name="Wins"><space/>35
</arg><arg name="Poles"><space/>40
</arg><arg name="Fastest_laps"><space/>42
</arg><arg name="Points"><space/>832
</arg><arg name="Podiums"><space/>120
</arg><arg name="Last race"><space/>[[1992 Hungarian Grand Prix]]
</arg></template><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Formula One</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Motor Racing Developments Ltd.</bold>, commonly known as<space/><bold>Brabham</bold><space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>r</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>əm</arg></template>, was a British<space/><link><target>race car</target><part>racing car</part></link><space/>manufacturer and<space/><link><target>Formula One</target></link><space/>racing team. Founded in 1960 by two Australians, driver<space/><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><space/>and designer<space/><link><target>Ron Tauranac</target></link>, the team won four<space/><link><target>List of Formula One World Drivers' Champions</target><part>Drivers'</part></link><space/>and two<space/><link><target>List of Formula One World Constructors' Champions</target><part>Constructors'</part></link><space/>World Championships in its 30-year Formula One history. Jack Brabham's 1966 Drivers' Championship remains the only such achievement using a car bearing the driver's own name.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1960s, Brabham was the world's largest manufacturer of<space/><link><target>open wheel car</target><part>open wheel racing cars</part></link><space/>for sale to customer teams, and had built more than 500 cars by 1970. During this period, teams using Brabham cars won championships in<space/><link><target>Formula Two</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Formula Three</target></link>. Brabham cars also competed in the<space/><link><target>Indianapolis 500</target></link><space/>and in<space/><link><target>Formula 5000</target></link><space/>racing. In the 1970s and 1980s, Brabham introduced innovations such as the<space/><link><target>Gordon Murray</target></link><space/>designed &quot;<link><target>fan car</target></link>&quot;which won its only race before being withdrawnin-race refuelling, carbon brakes, and<space/><link><target>hydropneumatic suspension</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The team won two more Formula One Drivers' Championships in the 1980s with Brazilian<space/><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link>. He won his first championship in<space/><template><target>f1</target><arg>1981</arg></template><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Ground effect (cars)</target><part>Ground effects</part></link><space/><link><target>Brabham BT49</target><part>BT49</part></link>-<link><target>Cosworth DFV</target><part>Ford</part></link>, and became the first to win a Drivers' Championship with a<space/><link><target>turbocharger</target><part>turbocharged</part></link><space/>car in<space/><template><target>f1</target><arg>1983</arg></template>. In 1983 the<space/><link><target>Brabham BT52</target></link>, driven by Piquet and Italian<space/><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link>, was powered by the<space/><link><target>BMW M12</target></link><space/><link><target>Straight-4</target></link><space/>engine, and powered Brabham to four of the team's 35 Grand Prix victories.</paragraph><paragraph>British businessman<space/><link><target>Bernie Ecclestone</target></link><space/>owned Brabham during most of the 1970s and 1980s, and later became responsible for administering the commercial aspects of Formula One. Ecclestone sold the team in 1988. Its last owner was the Middlebridge Group, a Japanese engineering firm. Midway through the<space/><link><target>1992 Formula One season</target><part>1992 season</part></link>, the team collapsed financially as Middlebridge was unable to make repayments against loans provided by Landhurst Leasing. The case was investigated by the United Kingdom<space/><link><target>Serious Fraud Office (UK)</target><part>Serious Fraud Office</part></link>. In 2009, an unsuccessful attempt was made by a German organisation to enter the<space/><link><target>2010 Formula One season</target></link><space/>using the Brabham name.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:BrabhamJack1966B.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><space/>was 40 when he won the F1 drivers' title in a Brabham car.</part></link>The Brabham team was founded by<space/><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ron Tauranac</target></link>, who met in 1951 while both were successfully building and racing cars in their native Australia. Brabham was the more successful driver and went to the United Kingdom in 1955 to further his racing career. There he started driving for the<space/><link><target>Cooper Car Company</target></link><space/>works team and by 1958 had progressed with them to Formula One, the highest category of<space/><link><target>open wheel racing</target></link><space/>defined by the<space/><link><target>Fdration Internationale de l'Automobile</target></link><space/>(FIA), motor sport's world governing body.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;FIA&quot; has been used throughout this article to refer to the motor sports governing body. Until 1978 motor sport was governed directly by the Commission Sportive Internationale (CSI) and from 1978 by the Fdration Internationale du Sport Automobile (FISA), both subsidiary bodies of the FIA. In 1992 the FIA subsumed FISA and its governing role.</extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>1959 Formula One season</target><part>1959</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>1960 Formula One season</target><part>1960</part></link>, Brabham won the Formula One World Drivers' Championship in Cooper's revolutionary<space/><link><target>mid-engine</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>cars.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 1719</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite their innovation of putting the engine behind the driver, the Coopers and their Chief Designer<space/><link><target>Owen Maddock</target></link><space/>were generally resistant to developing their cars. Brabham pushed for further advances, and played a significant role in developing Cooper's highly successful 1960 T53 &quot;lowline&quot; car, with input from his friend Tauranac.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 18, 22. Brabham had consulted Tauranac by letter on technical matters since arriving in the UK. He used a gear cluster designed by Tauranac for several years and Tauranac also advised on the suspension geometry of the Cooper T53 &quot;lowline&quot; car.</extension><space/>Brabham was confident he could do better than Cooper, and in late 1959 he asked Tauranac to come to the UK and work with him, initially producing upgrade kits for<space/><link><target>Sunbeam Rapier</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Triumph Herald</target></link><space/>road cars at his car dealership, Jack Brabham Motors, but with the long-term aim of designing racing cars.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 224. Jack had already tried to buy Cooper in association with fellow-driver<space/><link><target>Roy Salvadori</target></link></extension><space/>Brabham describes Tauranac as &quot;absolutely the only bloke I'd have gone into partnership with&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brabham, Nye (2004) p. 140</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To meet that aim, Brabham and Tauranac set up Motor Racing Developments Ltd. (MRD), deliberately avoiding the use of either man's name. The new company would compete with Cooper in the market for customer racing cars; as Brabham was still employed by Cooper, Tauranac produced the first MRD car, for the entry level<space/><link><target>Formula Junior</target></link><space/>class, in secrecy. Unveiled in the summer of 1961, the &quot;MRD&quot; was soon renamed. Motoring journalist<space/><link><target>Grard Crombac</target><part>Jabby Crombac</part></link><space/>pointed out that &quot;[the] way a Frenchman pronounces those initialswritten phonetically, 'em air day'sounded perilously like the French word...<space/><italics><link><target>Wiktionary:Merde</target><part>merde</part></link>.</italics>&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Scarlett (May 2006) p. 43. Although compare pronunciation with the related verb<space/><link><target>wiktionary:emmerder</target><part>emmerder</part></link>. This is the story as recalled by both Ron Tauranac and Brabham mechanic Michael Scarlett. The British journalist Alan Brinton has also been credited with pointing out this unfortunate fact to Brabham. See Drackett (1985) p. 21.</extension><space/>The cars were subsequently known as Brabhams, with type numbers starting with BT for &quot;Brabham Tauranac&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drackett (1985) p. 21. The first prototype FJunior car therefore became the BT1 and its production version the BT2.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the<space/><link><target>1961 Formula One season</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Team Lotus</target><part>Lotus</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Scuderia Ferrari</target><part>Ferrari</part></link><space/>teams had developed the mid-engined approach further than Cooper. Brabham had a poor season, scoring only four points, andhaving run his own private Coopers in non-championship events during 1961left the company in 1962 to drive for his own team: the Brabham Racing Organisation, using cars built by Motor Racing Developments.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Law31">Lawrence (1999) p. 31</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Brabham, Nye (2004) pp. 14, 1459. Brabham's and Tauranac's (Lawrence 1999 p. 32) accounts differ on whether the BRO was formed for the purpose of F1, or was already in existence.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Racing historyFormula One</heading><heading level='3'>Jack Brabham and Ron Tauranac (19611970)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham racing organisation logo.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The Brabham Racing Organisation entered the &quot;works&quot; cars until 1968</part></link>Motor Racing Developments initially concentrated on making money by building cars for sale to customers in lower formulae, so the new car for the Formula One team was not ready until partway through the<space/><link><target>1962 Formula One season</target></link>. The Brabham Racing Organisation (BRO) started the year fielding customer<space/><link><target>Team Lotus</target><part>Lotus</part></link><space/>chassis, in which Brabham took two points finishes, before the turquoise-<link><target>livery</target><part>liveried</part></link><space/>Brabham BT3 car made its debut at the<space/><link><target>1962 German Grand Prix</target></link>. It retired with a<space/><link><target>throttle</target></link><space/>problem after 9 of the 15 laps, but went on to take a pair of fourth places at the end of the season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 2122. Brabham bought a new spaceframe Lotus 24, but had to use a 1961-vintage Lotus 21 in the early races after a workshop fire. Team Lotus reserved the monocoque Lotus 25 for their own use that season.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham BT3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Brabham BT3</target></link>, the first Brabham Formula One design.</part></link>From the<space/><link><target>1963 Formula One season</target><part>1963 season</part></link>, Brabham was partnered by American driver<space/><link><target>Dan Gurney</target></link>, the pair now running in Australia's<space/><link><target>List of international auto racing colors</target><part>racing colours</part></link><space/>of green and gold.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brabham, Nye (2004) p. 147</extension><space/>Jack Brabham took the team's first win at the non-championship<space/><link><target>Solituderennen</target><part>Solitude Grand Prix</part></link><space/>in 1963.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 28</extension><space/>Gurney took the<space/><link><target>marque</target></link>'s first two wins in the world championship, at the 1964<space/><link><target>1964 French Grand Prix</target><part>French</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>1964 Mexican Grand Prix</target><part>Mexican</part></link><space/>Grands Prix. Brabham works and customer cars took another three non-championship wins during the<space/><link><target>1964 Formula One season</target><part>1964 season</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 3541</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>1965 Formula One season</target><part>1965 season</part></link><space/>was less successful, with no championship wins. Brabham finished third or fourth in the Constructors' Championship for three years running, but poor reliability marred promising performances on several occasions. Motor sport authors Mike Lawrence and David Hodges have said that a lack of resources may have cost the team results, a view echoed by Ron Tauranac.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tauranac says (Lawrence (1999) p. 48) that he feels a third mechanic would have reduced the reliability problems. Lawrence himself notes (Lawrence (1999) p. 71) that &quot;If only Jack had been prepared to spend a little more money, the results could have been so much better.&quot; Hodges (1990) p. 32 notes &quot;Economy was a watchword. (...) It was this attitude, perhaps, which cost [Brabham] some races.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The FIA doubled the Formula One engine capacity limit to 3&amp;nbsp;litres for the<space/><link><target>1966 Formula One season</target><part>1966 season</part></link><space/>and suitable engines were scarce. Brabham used engines from Australian engineering firm<space/><link><target>Repco</target></link>, which had never produced a Formula One engine before, based on aluminium V8<space/><link><target>engine block</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from the defunct American<space/><link><target>Oldsmobile</target></link><space/>F85 road car project, and other off the shelf parts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 5152</extension><space/>Consulting and design engineer<space/><link><target>Phil Irving</target></link><space/>(of<space/><link><target>Vincent Motorcycle</target></link><space/>fame) was the project engineer responsible for producing the initial version of the engine. Few expected the Brabham-Repcos to be competitive,<extension extension_name='ref'>Unique p. 43. The team was the only one not contracted by<space/><link><target>John Frankenheimer</target></link><space/>for the shooting of the film<space/><italics><link><target>Grand Prix (1966 film)</target><part>Grand Prix</part></link></italics><space/>at world championship races that year.</extension><space/>but the light and reliable cars ran at the front from the start of the season. At the<space/><link><target>1966 French Grand Prix</target><part>French Grand Prix</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Reims-Gueux</target></link>, Jack Brabham became the first man to win a Formula One world championship race in a car bearing his own name. Only his former team mate,<space/><link><target>Bruce McLaren</target></link>, has since matched the achievement. It was the first in a run of four straight wins for the Australian veteran. Jack Brabham won his third title in 1966, becoming the only driver to win the Formula One World Championship in a car carrying his own name (<italics>cf</italics><space/><link><target>Surtees</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hill (constructor)</target><part>Hill</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Fittipaldi Automotive</target></link>). In<space/><link><target>1967 Formula One season</target><part>1967</part></link>, the title went to Brabham's team mate, New Zealander<space/><link><target>Denny Hulme</target></link>. Hulme had better reliability through the year, possibly due to Jack Brabham's desire to try new parts first.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 92. Hulme, Tauranac and Frank Hallam, Repco-Brabham's chief engineer, all shared this view.</extension><space/>The Brabham team took the Constructors' World Championship in both years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fearnley (May 2006) pp. 3440</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>1968 Formula One season</target><part>1968</part></link><space/>Austrian<space/><link><target>Jochen Rindt</target></link><space/>replaced Hulme, who had left to join<space/><link><target>McLaren</target></link>. Repco produced a more powerful version of their V8 to maintain competitiveness against Ford's new<space/><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link>, but it proved very unreliable. Slow communications between the UK and Australia had always made identifying and correcting problems very difficult. The car was fastRindt set<space/><link><target>pole position</target></link><space/>twice during the seasonbut Brabham and Rindt finished only three races between them, and ended the year with only ten points.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fearnley (May 2006) p. 41</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:1970 Brands Hatch Race of Champions Jack Brabham BT33.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Brabham BT33. Technically conservative, Brabham did not produce a<space/><link><target>monocoque</target></link><space/>car until 1970.</part></link>Although Brabham bought Cosworth DFV engines for the<space/><link><target>1969 Formula One season</target><part>1969 season</part></link>, Rindt left to join Lotus. His replacement,<space/><link><target>Jacky Ickx</target></link>, had a strong second half to the season, winning in<space/><link><target>1969 German Grand Prix</target><part>Germany</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>1969 Canadian Grand Prix</target><part>Canada</part></link>, after Jack Brabham was sidelined by a testing accident.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry p. 85</extension><space/>Ickx finished second in the Drivers' Championship, with 37&amp;nbsp;points to<space/><link><target>Jackie Stewart</target></link>'s 63. Brabham himself took a couple of pole positions and two top three finishes, but did not finish half the races. The team were second in the Constructors' Championship, aided by second places at<space/><link><target>1969 Monaco Grand Prix</target><part>Monaco</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>1969 United States Grand Prix</target><part>Watkins Glen</part></link><space/>scored by<space/><link><target>Piers Courage</target></link>, driving a Brabham for the<space/><link><target>Frank Williams Racing Cars</target></link><space/>privateer squad.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 7980</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jack Brabham intended to retire at the end of the 1969 season and sold his share in the team to Tauranac. However, Rindt's late decision to remain with Lotus meant that Brabham drove for another year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 109 &amp; Brabham, Nye (2004) pp. 230231. He was therefore technically a team employee in his final season.</extension><space/>He took his last win in the opening race of the<space/><link><target>1970 Formula One season</target><part>1970 season</part></link><space/>and was competitive throughout the year, although mechanical failures blunted his challenge.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 93</extension><space/>Aided by number two driver<space/><link><target>Rolf Stommelen</target></link>, the team came fourth in the Constructors' Championship.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ron Tauranac (1971)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:1971 Race of Champions G Hill Brabham BT34.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Brabham BT34</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Graham Hill</target></link><space/>took his final Formula One win in the non-championship<space/><link><target>BRDC International Trophy</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Silverstone Circuit</target><part>Silverstone</part></link>.</part><trail>Tauranac</trail></link><space/>signed double world champion<space/><link><target>Graham Hill</target></link><space/>and young Australian<space/><link><target>Tim Schenken</target></link><space/>to drive for the<space/><link><target>1971 Formula One season</target><part>1971 season</part></link>. Tauranac designed the unusual 'lobster claw' BT34, featuring twin<space/><link><target>radiator (engine cooling)</target><part>radiator</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>mounted ahead of the front wheels, a single example of which was built for Hill. Although Hill, no longer a front-runner since his 1969 accident, took his final Formula One win in the non-championship<space/><link><target>BRDC International Trophy</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Silverstone Circuit</target><part>Silverstone</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 11417</extension><space/>the team scored only seven&amp;nbsp;championship points.</paragraph><paragraph>Tauranac, an engineer at heart, started to feel his Formula One budget of around 100,000 was a gamble he could not afford to take on his own and began to look around for an experienced business partner.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 113</extension><space/>He sold the company for 100,000 at the end of 1971 to British businessman<space/><link><target>Bernie Ecclestone</target></link>, Jochen Rindt's former manager and erstwhile owner of the<space/><link><target>Connaught Engineering</target><part>Connaught</part></link><space/>team. Tauranac stayed on to design the cars and run the factory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 116</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bernie Ecclestone (19721987)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham BT44 front.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Brabham BT44</target></link><space/>on display in 2003. The car was used in the<space/><template><target>F1</target><arg>1974</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>F1</target><arg>1975</arg></template><space/>seasons.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Tauranac left Brabham early in the<space/><link><target>1972 Formula One season</target><part>1972 season</part></link><space/>after Ecclestone changed the way the company was organised without consulting him. Ecclestone has since said &quot;In retrospect, the relationship was never going to work&quot;, noting that &quot;[Tauranac and I] both take the view: 'Please be reasonable, do it my way'&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence. pp. 116118</extension><space/>The highlights of an aimless year, during which the team ran three different models, were pole position for Argentinian driver<space/><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><space/>at his home race at<space/><link><target>Buenos Aires</target></link><space/>and a victory in the non-championship Interlagos Grand Prix. For the<space/><link><target>1973 Formula One season</target><part>1973 season</part></link>, Ecclestone promoted the young South African engineer<space/><link><target>Gordon Murray</target></link><space/>to chief designer and moved Herbie Blash from the Formula Two programme to become the Formula One team manager. Both would remain with the team for the next 15 years. For 1973, Murray produced the triangular cross-section BT42, with which Reutemann scored two podium finishes and finished seventh in the Drivers' Championship.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>1974 Formula One season</target><part>1974 season</part></link>, Reutemann took the first three victories of his Formula One career, and Brabham's first since 1970. The team finished a close fifth in the Constructors' Championship, fielding the much more competitive<space/><link><target>Brabham BT44</target><part>BT44s</part></link>. After a strong finish to the 1974 season, many observers felt the team were favourites to win the<space/><link><target>1975 Formula One season</target><part>1975 title</part></link>. The year started well, with a first win for Brazilian driver<space/><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Carlos Pace</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Autdromo Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Interlagos</part></link><space/>circuit in his native<space/><link><target>So Paulo</target></link>. However, as the season progressed, tyre wear frequently slowed the cars in races.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gill (ed.) (1976) p. 103</extension><space/>Pace took another two podiums and finished sixth in the championship; while Carlos Reutemann had five podium finishes, including a dominant win in the<space/><link><target>1975 German Grand Prix</target></link>, and finished third in the Drivers' Championship. The team likewise ranked third in the Constructors' Championship at the end of the year.</paragraph><paragraph>While rival teams Lotus and McLaren relied on the Cosworth DFV engine from the late 1960s to the early 1980s, Ecclestone sought a competitive advantage by investigating other options. Despite the success of Murray's Cosworth-powered cars, Ecclestone signed a deal with Italian motor manufacturer<space/><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>to use their large and powerful<space/><link><target>flat-12</target></link><space/>engine from the<space/><link><target>1976 Formula One season</target><part>1976 season</part></link>. The engines were free, but they rendered the new BT45s, now in red<space/><link><target>Martini Racing</target></link><space/>livery, unreliable and overweight.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 159161</extension><space/>The 1976 and<space/><link><target>1977 Formula One season</target><part>1977 seasons</part></link><space/>saw Brabham fall toward the back of the field again. Reutemann negotiated a release from his contract before the end of the 1976 season and signed with<space/><link><target>Scuderia Ferrari</target><part>Ferrari</part></link>. Ulsterman<space/><link><target>John Watson (racing driver)</target><part>John Watson</part></link><space/>replaced him at Brabham for 1977. Watson lost near certain victory in the French Grand Prix (Dijon) of that year when his car ran low on fuel on the last lap and was passed by Mario Andretti's Lotus, with Watson's second place being the team's best result of the season. The car often showed at the head of races, but the unreliability of the Alfa Romeo engine was a major problem. The team lost Carlos Pace early in the 1977 season when he died in a<space/><link><target>light aircraft</target></link><space/>accident.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 164, 167</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For the<space/><link><target>1978 Formula One season</target><part>1978 season</part></link>, Murray's<space/><link><target>Brabham BT46</target><part>BT46</part></link><space/>featured several new technologies to overcome the weight and packaging difficulties caused by the Alfa engines. Ecclestone signed then two-time Formula One world champion<space/><link><target>Niki Lauda</target></link><space/>from Ferrari through a deal with Italian dairy products company<space/><link><target>Parmalat</target></link><space/>which met the cost of Lauda ending his Ferrari contract and made up his salary to the 200,000 Ferrari was offering. 1978 was the year of the dominant<space/><link><target>Lotus 79</target></link><space/>&quot;wing car&quot;, which used<space/><link><target>aerodynamic</target></link><space/><link><target>ground effect in cars</target><part>ground effect</part></link><space/>to stick to the track when cornering, but Lauda won two races in the BT46, one with the controversial &quot;B&quot; or &quot;<link><target>Brabham BT46#Brabham BT46B .E2.80.93 the .22Fan car.22</target><part>fan car</part></link>&quot; version.<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph>Details of BT46 and 1978 season: Henry (1985) p. 171, pp. 179189</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Lauda's move and salary: Lovell (2004) p. 98</listitem></list></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The partnership with Alfa Romeo ended during the<space/><link><target>1979 Formula One season</target><part>1979 season</part></link>, the team's first with young Brazilian driver<space/><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link>. Murray designed the full-ground effect BT48 around a rapidly developed new Alfa Romeo V12 engine and incorporated an effective &quot;carbon-carbon braking&quot; system<link><target>#Technical innovation</target><part>a technology Brabham pioneered in 1976</part></link>. However, unexpected movement of the car's aerodynamic<space/><link><target>center of pressure (fluid mechanics)</target><part>centre of pressure</part></link><space/>made its handling unpredictable and the new engine was unreliable. The team dropped to eighth in the Constructors' Championship by the end of the season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 191</extension><space/>Alfa Romeo started testing their own Formula One car during the season, prompting Ecclestone to revert to Cosworth DFV engines, a move Murray described as being &quot;like having a holiday&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 213, 215</extension><space/>The new, lighter, Cosworth-powered<space/><link><target>Brabham BT49</target><part>BT49</part></link><space/>was introduced before the end of the year at the<space/><link><target>1979 Canadian Grand Prix</target><part>Canadian Grand Prix</part></link>; where after practice Lauda announced his immediate retirement from driving, later saying that he &quot;was no longer getting any pleasure from driving round and round in circles&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 216</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:2005 Brands Hatch A1GP 25 Sept Christian Glaesel Brabham BT49D.jpg</target><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Brabham BT49</target></link><space/>competed over four seasons, winning one championship.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The team used the BT49 over four seasons. In the<space/><link><target>1980 Formula One season</target><part>1980 season</part></link><space/>Piquet scored three wins and the team took 3rd in the Constructors' Championship with Piquet second in the Drivers' Championship. This season saw the introduction of the blue and white livery that the cars would wear through several changes of sponsor, until the team's demise in 1992. With a better understanding of ground effect, the team further developed the BT49C for the<space/><link><target>1981 Formula One season</target><part>1981 season</part></link>, incorporating a hydropneumatic suspension system to avoid<space/><link><target>ride height</target></link><space/>limitations intended to reduce downforce. Piquet, who had developed a close working relationship with Murray,<extension extension_name='ref' name="RoePiq">Roebuck (1986) p. 114</extension><space/>took the drivers' title with three wins, albeit<space/><link><target>#Controversy</target><part>amid accusations of cheating</part></link>. The team finished second in the Constructors' Championship, behind the<space/><link><target>WilliamsF1</target><part>Williams team</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Renault F1</target><part>Renault</part></link><space/>had introduced<space/><link><target>turbocharged</target></link><space/>engines to Formula One in 1977. Brabham had tested a<space/><link><target>BMW in Formula One</target><part>BMW</part></link><space/>4-cylinder<space/><link><target>BMW M12</target><part>M12</part></link><space/>turbocharged engine in the summer of 1981. For the<space/><link><target>1982 Formula One season</target><part>1982 season</part></link><space/>the team designed a new car, the BT50, around the BMW engine which, like the Repco engine 16 years previously, was based on a road car engine block, the<space/><link><target>BMW M10</target></link>. Brabham continued to run the Cosworth-powered BT49D in the early part of the season while reliability and driveability issues with the BMW units were resolved. The relationship came close to ending, with the German manufacturer insisting that Brabham use their engine. The turbo car took its first win at the<space/><link><target>1982 Canadian Grand Prix</target><part>Canadian Grand Prix</part></link>. In the Constructors' Championship, the team finished fifth, the drivers<space/><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link>, who scored the last win of the Brabham-Ford combination in the<space/><link><target>1982 Monaco Grand Prix</target><part>Monaco Grand Prix</part></link>, 10th and World Champion Piquet a mere 11th in the Drivers' Championship. In the<space/><link><target>1983 Formula One season</target><part>1983 season</part></link>, Piquet took the championship lead from<space/><link><target>Renault F1</target><part>Renault's</part></link><space/><link><target>Alain Prost</target></link><space/>at the last race of the year, the<space/><link><target>1983 South African Grand Prix</target><part>South African Grand Prix</part></link><space/>to become the first driver to win the Formula One Drivers' World Championship with a turbo-powered car. The team did not win the Constructors' Championship in either 1981 or 1983, despite Piquet's success.<space/><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link><space/>was the only driver other than Piquet to win a race for Brabham in this periodthe drivers in the second car contributed only a fraction of the team's points in each of these championship seasons. Patrese finished 9th in the Drivers' Championship with 13 points, dropping the team behind Ferrari and Renault to third in the Constructors' Championship.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Piquet - Brabham-BMW BT 54 1985-08-02.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><space/>and his BT54 were hampered by<space/><link><target>Pirelli</target></link><space/>tyres in<space/><template><target>F1</target><arg>1985</arg></template>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Piquet took the team's last wins: two in 1984 by winning the 7th and 8th race of that season, the<space/><link><target>1984 Canadian Grand Prix</target><part>Canadian Grand Prix</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>1984 Detroit Grand Prix</target><part>Detroit Grand Prix</part></link>, and one in 1985 by winning the<space/><link><target>1985 French Grand Prix</target><part>French Grand Prix</part></link>, before reluctantly leaving for the<space/><link><target>WilliamsF1</target><part>Williams</part></link><space/>team at the end of the season. After seven years and two world championships, he felt he was worth more than Ecclestone's salary offer for 1986. Piquet finished 5th in 1984 and a mere 8th in 1985 in the respective Drivers' Championships.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RoePiq"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>1986 Formula One season</target><part>1986 season</part></link><space/>was a disaster. Murray's radical long and low<space/><link><target>Brabham BT55</target><part>BT55</part></link>, with its BMW M12 engine tilted over to improve its aerodynamics and lower its centre of gravity, scored only two points. Driver<space/><link><target>Elio de Angelis</target></link><space/>became the Formula One team's only fatality when he died in a testing accident at the<space/><link><target>Circuit Paul Ricard</target><part>Paul Ricard</part></link><space/>circuit.<space/><link><target>Derek Warwick</target></link>, who replaced de Angelis, was close to scoring two points for fifth in the<space/><link><target>1986 British Grand Prix</target><part>British Grand Prix</part></link>, but a problem on the last lap dropped him out of the points. In August, BMW after considering running their own in-house team, announced their departure from Formula One at the end of the season. Murray, who had largely taken over the running of the team as Ecclestone became more involved with his role at the<space/><link><target>Formula One Constructors Association</target></link>, felt that &quot;the way the team had operated for 15 years broke down&quot;. He left Brabham in November to join<space/><link><target>McLaren</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BGEnd">Lovell (2004) pp. 161164</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ecclestone held BMW to their contract for the<space/><link><target>1987 Formula One season</target><part>1987 season</part></link>, but the German company would only supply the laydown engine. The upright units, around which Brabham had designed their new car, were sold for use by the<space/><link><target>Arrows (F1)</target><part>Arrows</part></link><space/>team. Senior figures at Brabham, including Murray, have admitted that by this stage Ecclestone had lost interest in running the team. The 1987 season was only slightly more successful than the previous yearPatrese and de Cesaris scoring 10 points between them, including two third places at the<space/><link><target>1987 Belgian Grand Prix</target><part>Belgian Grand Prix</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>1987 Mexican Grand Prix</target><part>Mexican Grand Prix</part></link>. Unable to locate a suitable engine supplier, the team missed the FIA deadline for entry into the 1988 world championship and Ecclestone finally announced the team's withdrawal from Formula One at the Brazilian Grand Prix in April 1988. During the season ending<space/><link><target>1988 Australian Grand Prix</target><part>Australian Grand Prix</part></link>, Ecclestone announced he had sold MRD to<space/><link><target>EuroBrun</target></link><space/>team owner<space/><link><target>Walter Brun</target></link><space/>for an unknown price.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Joachim Luhti (1989)</heading><paragraph>Brun soon sold the team on, this time to Swiss financier Joachim Luhti, who brought it back into Formula One for the<space/><link><target>1989 Formula One season</target><part>1989 season</part></link>. The new<space/><link><target>Brabham BT58</target></link>, powered by a<space/><link><target>Judd (engine)</target><part>Judd</part></link><space/><link><target>V8 engine</target></link><space/>(originally another of Jack Brabham's companies), was produced for the<space/><link><target>1989 Formula One season</target><part>1989 season</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brabham, Nye (2004) p. 254. Engine Developments, the company which builds Judd engines, was a company Jack Brabham set up in partnership with John Judd after his retirement from driving in 1970. Judd had previously worked for Brabham on the Repco project. John Judd had based the engine, dubbed the<space/><bold>CV</bold>, on a<space/><link><target>Honda</target></link><space/>block and was something the Japanese company was looking at as it looked to move into the North American based<space/><link><target>Champ Car</target><part>Indycar racing</part></link>.</extension><space/>Italian driver<space/><link><target>Stefano Modena</target></link>, who had driven for the team in the<space/><link><target>1987 Australian Grand Prix</target></link><space/>in a one off drive for the team, drove alongside the more experienced<space/><link><target>Martin Brundle</target></link><space/>who was returning to Formula One after spending 1988 winning the<space/><link><target>1988 World Sportscar Championship season</target><part>World Sportscar Championship</part></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Jaguar Cars</target><part>Jaguar</part></link>. Modena took the team's last podium: a third place at the<space/><link><target>1989 Monaco Grand Prix</target><part>Monaco Grand Prix</part></link><space/>(Brundle, who had only just scraped through pre-qualifying by 0.021 seconds before qualifying a brilliant 4th, had been running third but was forced to stop to replace a flat battery, finally finishing sixth). The team also failed to make the grid sometimes: Brundle failed to prequalify at the<space/><link><target>1989 Canadian Grand Prix</target><part>Canadian Grand Prix</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>1989 French Grand Prix</target><part>French Grand Prix</part></link>. The team finished 9th in the Constructors' Championship at the end of the season.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Middlebridge Racing (19891992)</heading><paragraph>After Luhti's arrest on tax fraud charges in mid-1989,<extension extension_name='ref'>Slevin, Gary (2008)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.f1rejects.com/centrale/submitted/brabham/index.html'>The Decline of Brabham</link>. Formula One Rejects. Retrieved 10 June 2009</extension><space/>several parties disputed the ownership of the team. Middlebridge Group Limited, a Japanese engineering firm owned by billionaire Koji Nakauchi, was already involved with established<space/><link><target>International Formula 3000</target><part>Formula 3000</part></link><space/>team Middlebridge Racing and gained control of Brabham for the<space/><link><target>1990 Formula One season</target><part>1990 season</part></link>. Herbie Blash had returned to run the team in 1989 and continued to do so in 1990. Middlebridge paid for its purchase using 1&amp;nbsp;million loaned to them by finance company Landhurst Leasing,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landhurst"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Formula One obsession led to pounds 50m Landhurst fraud</arg><arg name="author"><space/>John Willcock</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/formula-one-obsession-led-to-pounds-50m-landhurst-fraud-1236602.html</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Independent (newspaper)|The Independent]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>18 October 1997</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2011</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>but the team remained underfunded and would only score a few more points finishes in its last three seasons. Jack Brabham's youngest son,<space/><link><target>David Brabham</target><part>David</part></link>, raced for the Formula One team for a short time in 1990 including the season ending<space/><link><target>1990 Australian Grand Prix</target><part>Australian Grand Prix</part></link><space/>(the first time a Brabham had driven a Brabham car in an<space/><link><target>Australian Grand Prix</target></link><space/>since<space/><link><target>1968 Australian Grand Prix</target><part>1968</part></link>). 1990 was a disastrous year, with Modena's fifth place in the season opening<space/><link><target>1990 United States Grand Prix</target><part>United States Grand Prix</part></link><space/>being the only top six finish. The team finished ninth in the Constructors' Championship. Brundle and fellow Briton<space/><link><target>Mark Blundell</target></link>, scored only three points during the<space/><link><target>1991 Formula One season</target><part>1991 season</part></link>. Due to poor results in the first half of 1991, they had to prequalify in the second half of the season, Blundell failed to do so in Japan, as did Brundle in Australia. The team finished 10th in the Constructors' Championship, behind another struggling British team, Lotus. In 1992,<space/><link><target>Damon Hill</target></link>, the son of another former Brabham driver and World Champion, debuted in the team after<space/><link><target>Giovanna Amati</target></link><space/>was dropped when her sponsorship failed to materialise. Amati was the fifth woman to attempt a Formula One race, but her three attempts were unsuccessful.</paragraph><paragraph>Argentine<space/><link><target>Sergio Rinland</target></link><space/>designed the team's final cars around Judd engines, except for 1991 when<space/><link><target>Yamaha Motor Company Ltd.</target><part>Yamaha</part></link><space/>powered the cars. In the<space/><link><target>1992 Formula One season</target><part>1992 season</part></link><space/>the cars (which were updated versions of the 1991 car) rarely qualified for races. Hill gave the team its final finish, at the<space/><link><target>1992 Hungarian Grand Prix</target><part>Hungarian Grand Prix</part></link>, where he crossed the finish line 11th and last, four laps behind the winner,<space/><link><target>Ayrton Senna</target></link>. After the end of that race the team ran out of funds and collapsed. Middlebridge Group Limited had been unable to continue making repayments against the 6&amp;nbsp;million ultimately provided by Landhurst Leasing, which went into<space/><link><target>Administration order</target><part>administration</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Serious Fraud Office (UK)</target><part>Serious Fraud Office</part></link><space/>investigated the case. Landhurst's managing directors were found guilty of corruption and imprisoned, having accepted bribes for further loans to Middlebridge.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landhurst"></extension><space/>It was one of four teams to leave Formula One that year. (<italics>cf</italics><space/><link><target>March Engineering</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Fondmetal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Andrea Moda Formula</target></link>). Although there was talk of reviving the team for the following year, its assets passed to Landhurst Leasing and were auctioned by the company's<space/><link><target>Administrative receivership</target><part>receivers</part></link><space/>in 1993.<extension extension_name='ref'>Baker (10 October 1993)</extension><space/>Among these was the team's old factory in Chessington, which was acquired by Yamaha Motor Sports and used to house Activa Technology Limited, a company manufacturing composite components for race and road cars run by Herbie Blash. The factory was bought by the<space/><link><target>Carlin DPR</target></link><space/><link><target>GP2 Series</target><part>GP2</part></link><space/>motor racing team in 2006.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.autosport.com/news/report.php/id/55796</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Carlin to enter GP2 in 2007</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Glenn Freeman</arg><arg name="date"><space/>27 November 2006</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Autosport.com</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 December 2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Potential F1 revival (2010)</heading><paragraph>On 4 June 2009,<space/><link><target>Franz Hilmer</target></link><space/>confirmed that he had used the name to lodge an entry for the 2010 Formula One season as a cost capped team under the new budget cap regulations.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.autosport.com/news/report.php/id/75798</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham name owner submits F1 entry</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Jonathan Noble</arg><arg name="date"><space/>4 June 2009</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Autosport.com</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The Brabham family was not involved and announced that it was seeking legal advice over the use of the name.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.autosport.com/news/report.php/id/75806</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham family seeking legal advice</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Edd Straw</arg><arg name="date"><space/>4 June 2009</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Autosport.com</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The team's entry was not accepted, and the Brabham family later obtained legal recognition of their exclusive rights to the Brabham brand.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.crash.net/f1/news/187189/1/brabham-family-name-wins-eu-legal-protection.html</arg><arg name="title">Brabham family name wins EU legal protection</arg><arg name="publisher">crash.net</arg><arg name="date">2013-01-10</arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-11-09</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Brabham Racing (2014)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Brabham Racing</arg></template>In September 2014,<space/><link><target>David Brabham</target></link>&amp;mdash;the son of Brabham founder<space/><link><target>Jack Brabham</target><part>Sir Jack Brabham</part></link>&amp;mdash;announced the reformation of the Brabham Racing team under the name<space/><bold>Project Brabham</bold>, with plans to enter the 2015<space/><link><target>FIA World Endurance Championship</target></link><space/>and 2015<space/><link><target>24 Hours of Le Mans</target></link><space/>in the LMP2 category using a<space/><link><target>crowdsourcing</target></link><space/>business model.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.speedcafe.com/2014/09/25/brabham-team-reborn-f1sports-cars-targetted/</arg><arg name="title">Brabham team reborn, F1/sports cars targeted</arg><arg name="work">Speedcafe</arg><arg name="date">25 September 2014</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The team is also aiming to enter the<space/><link><target>FIA Formula E Championship</target></link><space/>and return to<space/><link><target>Formula One</target></link><space/>in the future.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Motor Racing Developments</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:1969 British Grand Prix P Courage Brabham BT26.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Several F1 teams used Brabhams (<link><target>Piers Courage</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Frank Williams Racing Cars</target><part>FWRC</part></link>, 1969)</part></link><link><target>File:Repco brabham logo.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>120px</part><part>The Repco Brabham logo from the 1960s, illustrating the joint branding of the period.</part></link>Brabham cars were also widely used by other teams, and not just in Formula One. Jack Brabham and Ron Tauranac called the company they set up in 1961 to design and build<space/><link><target>formula racing</target></link><space/>cars to customer teams Motor Racing Developments (MRD), and this company had a large portfolio of other activities. Initially, Brabham and Tauranac each held 50&amp;nbsp;percent of the shares.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Law31"></extension><space/>Tauranac was responsible for design and running the business, while Brabham was the test driver and arranged corporate deals like the Repco engine supply and the use of the MIRA wind tunnel. He also contributed ideas to the design process and often machined parts and helped build the cars.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tauranac referred to this as Brabham's trade; they had first met at the small<space/><link><target>machine shop</target></link><space/>Brabham ran in Sydney in the early 1950s.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From 1963 to 1965, MRD was not directly involved in Formula One, and often ran works cars in other formulae. A separate company, Jack Brabham's Brabham Racing Organisation, ran the Formula One works entry.<extension extension_name='ref'>To confuse the relationship between the two companies further, MRD was renamed Brabham Racing Developments between 1962 and 1964. Henry (1985) p. 24</extension><space/>Like other customers, BRO bought its cars from MRD, initially at 3,000 per car,<extension extension_name='ref'>Fearnley (May 2006) p. 39</extension><space/>although it did not pay for development parts. Tauranac was unhappy with his distance from the Formula One operation and before the 1966 season suggested that he was no longer interested in producing cars for Formula One under this arrangement. Brabham investigated other chassis suppliers for BRO, however the two reached an agreement and from 1966 MRD was much more closely involved in this category.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 7475</extension><space/>After Jack Brabham sold his shares in MRD to Ron Tauranac at the end of 1969, the works Formula One team was MRD.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite only building its first car in 1961, by the mid-1960s MRD had overtaken established constructors like Cooper to become the largest manufacturer of single-seat racing cars in the world,<extension extension_name='ref'>Unique p. 111</extension><space/>and by 1970 had built over 500 cars.<extension extension_name='ref' name="car numbers">Lawrence (1999) p. 207</extension><space/>Of the other Formula One teams which used Brabhams,<space/><link><target>Frank Williams Racing Cars</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Rob Walker Racing Team</target></link><space/>were the most successful. The<space/><link><target>1965 British Grand Prix</target></link><space/>saw seven Brabhams compete, only two of them from the works team, and there were usually four or five at championship Grands Prix throughout that season. The firm built scores of cars for the lower formulae each year, peaking with 89 cars in 1966.<extension extension_name='ref' name="car numbers"></extension><space/>Brabham had the reputation of providing customers with cars of a standard equal to those used by the works team, which worked &quot;<link><target>wiktionary:out of the box</target><part>out of the box</part></link>&quot;. The company provided a high degree of support to its customersincluding Jack Brabham helping customers set up their cars. During this period the cars were usually known as &quot;Repco Brabhams&quot;, not because of the Repco engines used in Formula One between 1966 and 1968, but because of a smaller-scale sponsorship deal through which the Australian company had been providing parts to Jack Brabham since his Cooper days.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 53</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham BT40 of Tim Kuchel.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The BT40 was the last<space/><link><target>Formula Two</target></link><space/>model from Brabham</part></link>At the end of 1971 Bernie Ecclestone bought MRD. He retained the Brabham brand, as did subsequent owners. Although the production of customer cars continued briefly under Ecclestone's ownership, he believed the company needed to focus on Formula One to succeed. The last production customer Brabhams were the Formula Two BT40 and the Formula Three BT41 of 1973,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hodges (1990) p. 39</extension><space/>although Ecclestone sold ex-works Formula One BT44Bs to<space/><link><target>RAM Racing</target></link><space/>as late as 1976.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 156. Henry claims Ecclestone did this to ensure the team would focus on its troublesome new Alfa Romeo powered BT45s.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1988 Ecclestone sold Motor Racing Developments to Alfa Romeo. The Formula One team did not compete that year, but Alfa Romeo put the company to use designing and building a prototype &quot;Procar&quot;a racing car with the silhouette of a large saloon (the<space/><link><target>Alfa Romeo 164</target></link>) covering a composite racing car chassis and mid mounted race engine. This was intended for a racing series for major manufacturers to support Formula One Grands Prix, and was designated the Brabham BT57.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.grandprix.com/gpe/cref-mcdall.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>People: Allen McDonald</arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>grandprix.com</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2011</arg></template></extension><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Racing historyother categories</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham BT25.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>220px</part><part>Brabham's last USAC race-winning carthe Brabham BT25 IndyCar of 1968.</part></link><link><target>File:2005 Goodwood Festival of Speed F2 Brabham BT18 Honda.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>220px</part><part>The Brabham BT18-Honda completely dominated<space/><link><target>Formula Two</target></link><space/>in 1966</part></link><link><target>File:1969 F3 Guards Trophy Brands Hatch James Hunt Brabham BT21.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>220px</part><part>Top drivers used Brabham F3 cars in their early careers. (<link><target>James Hunt</target></link>, 1969)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Indycar</heading><paragraph>Brabham cars competed at the<space/><link><target>Indianapolis 500</target></link><space/>from the mid-1960s to the early 1970s. After an abortive project in 1962,<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 30</extension><space/>MRD was commissioned in 1964 to build an Indycar chassis powered by an American<space/><link><target>Offenhauser</target></link><space/>engine. The resultant BT12 chassis was raced by Jack Brabham as the &quot;Zink-Urschel Trackburner&quot; at the<space/><link><target>1964 Indianapolis 500</target><part>1964 event</part></link><space/>and retired with a fuel tank problem. The car was entered again in<space/><link><target>1966 Indianapolis 500</target><part>1966</part></link>, taking a third place for<space/><link><target>Jim McElreath</target></link>. From 1968 to 1970, Brabham returned to Indianapolis, at first with a 4.2&amp;nbsp;litre version of the Repco V8 the team used in Formula Onewith which<space/><link><target>Peter Revson</target></link><space/>finished fifth in 1969before reverting to the Offenhauser engine for 1970.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brabham, Nye (2004) p. 240</extension><space/>The Brabham-Offenhauser combination was entered again in 1971 by<space/><link><target>Christopher J.C. Agajanian</target><part>J.C. Agajanian</part></link>, finishing fifth in the hands of<space/><link><target>Bill Vukovich II</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 114</extension><space/>Although a Brabham car never won at Indianapolis, McElreath won four<space/><link><target>United States Automobile Club</target></link><space/>(USAC) races over 1965 and 1966 in the BT12. The &quot;Dean Van Lines Special&quot; in which<space/><link><target>Mario Andretti</target></link><space/>won the 1965 USAC national championship was a direct copy of this car, made with permission from Brabham by Andretti's crew chief Clint Brawner.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 57. Brawner repaired BT12 after a crash in 1964. As part of the deal he was allowed to make a copy of the then still unusual mid-engined design.</extension><space/>Revson took Brabham's final USAC race win in a BT25 in 1969, using the Repco engine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BrabIndy">Lawrence (1999) p. 99</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Formula Two</heading><paragraph>In the 1960s and early 1970s, drivers who had reached Formula One often continued to compete in<space/><link><target>Formula Two</target></link>. In 1966 MRD produced the BT18 for the lower category, with a<space/><link><target>Honda</target></link><space/>engine acting as a stressed component. The car was extremely successful, winning 11 consecutive Formula Two races in the hands of the Formula One pairing of Brabham and Hulme. Cars were entered by MRD and not by the Brabham Racing Organisation, avoiding a direct conflict with Repco, their Formula One engine supplier.<extension extension_name='ref'>Unique p. 117</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Formula Three</heading><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>Formula Three</target></link><space/>Brabham, the BT9, won only four major races in 1964. The BT15 which followed in 1965 was a highly successful design. 58 cars were sold, which won 42 major races. Further developments of the same concept, including wings by the end of the decade, were highly competitive up until 1971. The BT38C of 1972 was Brabham's first production monocoque and the first not designed by Tauranac. Although 40 were ordered, it was less successful than its predecessors. The angular BT41 was the final Formula Three Brabham.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hodges (1998) pp. 3439</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Formula 5000</heading><paragraph>Brabham also made cars for<space/><link><target>Formula 5000</target></link><space/>racing, most notably in Australia. Former<space/><link><target>Australian Drivers' Championship</target><part>Australian Drivers' Champion</part></link><space/><link><target>Kevin Bartlett (racing driver)</target><part>Kevin Bartlett</part></link><space/>used a<space/><link><target>Chevrolet small-block engine</target><part>Chevrolet</part></link><space/>powered Brabham BT43 to finish 3rd in the<space/><link><target>1978 Australian Drivers' Championship</target></link><space/>before finishing 5th in the<space/><link><target>1978 Australian Grand Prix</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sports cars</heading><paragraph>Tauranac did not enjoy designing sports cars and could only spare a small amount of his time from MRD's very successful single-seater business. Only 14 sports car models were built between 1961 and 1972, out of a total production of almost 600 chassis.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 205207</extension><space/>The BT8A was the only one built in any numbers, and was quite successful in national level racing in the UK in 1964 and 1965.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 55</extension><space/>The design was &quot;stretched&quot; in 1966 to become the one-off BT17, originally fitted with the 4.3&amp;nbsp;litre version of the Repco engine for<space/><link><target>Can-Am</target></link><space/>racing. It was quickly abandoned by MRD after engine reliability problems became evident.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 8485</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Technical innovation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Brabham bt45.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Brabham BT45</target></link><space/>driven by<space/><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:2001 Goodwood Festival of Speed Brabham BT46B Fan car.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The 1978<space/><link><target>Brabham BT46</target><part>BT46B &quot;Fan car&quot;</part></link><space/>won its only race before being banned.</part></link>Brabham was considered a technically conservative team in the 1960s, chiefly because it persevered with traditional &quot;<link><target>spaceframe</target></link>&quot; cars long after Lotus introduced lighter, stiffer &quot;<link><target>monocoque</target></link>&quot; chassis to Formula One in 1962. Chief designer Tauranac reasoned that monocoques of the time were not usefully stiffer than well designed spaceframe chassis, and were harder to repair and less suitable for MRD's customers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) pp. 4445</extension><space/>His &quot;old fashioned&quot; cars won the Brabham team the 1966 and 1967 championships, and were competitive in Formula One until rule changes forced a move to monocoques in 1970.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nye (1986) p. 60. Brabham's BT26As and Matra's experimental four wheel drive MS84 of 1969 were the last cars with spaceframe chassis cars in F1. For 1970 the FIA mandated the use of &quot;bag tanks&quot; for fuel, which were to be carried inside box structures. This effectively forced the team to design a monocoque structure. From 1968 Brabham's Indycars were monocoques for the same reason.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the perceived conservatism, in 1963 Brabham was the first Formula One team to use a<space/><link><target>wind tunnel</target></link><space/>to hone their designs to reduce<space/><link><target>drag (physics)</target><part>drag</part></link><space/>and stop the cars lifting off the ground at speed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 39. The initial tests were carried out at the<space/><link><target>Motor Industry Research Association</target></link><space/>wind tunnel under the auspices of Malcolm Sayer, who had been responsible for the aerodynamics of the<space/><link><target>Jaguar D-type</target></link><space/>Le Mans winning car.</extension><space/>The practice only became the norm in the early 1980s, and is possibly the most important factor in the design of modern cars. Towards the end of the 1960s, teams began to exploit aerodynamic<space/><link><target>downforce</target></link><space/>to push the cars' tyres down harder on the track and enable them to maintain faster speeds through high-speed corners. At the<space/><link><target>1968 Belgian Grand Prix</target></link>, Brabham were the first, alongside Ferrari, to introduce full width rear wings to this effect.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence (1999) p. 100</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The team's most fertile period of technical innovation came in the 1970s and 1980s when<space/><link><target>Gordon Murray</target></link><space/>became technical director. During 1976, the team introduced &quot;carbon-carbon<space/><link><target>Disc brake</target><part>brakes</part></link>&quot; to Formula One, which promised reduced &quot;<link><target>unsprung weight</target></link>&quot; and better stopping performance due to carbon's greater<space/><link><target>coefficient of friction</target></link>. The initial versions used<space/><link><target>reinforced carbon-carbon</target><part>carbon-carbon composite</part></link><space/><link><target>brake pads</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>steel</target></link><space/>disc faced with carbon &quot;pucks&quot;. The technology was not reliable at first; in 1976, Carlos Pace crashed at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>180</arg><arg>mi/h</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>at the<space/><link><target>sterreichring</target></link><space/>circuit after heat build-up in the brakes boiled the<space/><link><target>brake fluid</target></link>, leaving him with no way of stopping the car.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 163</extension><space/>By 1979, Brabham had developed an effective carbon-carbon braking system, combining structural carbon discs with carbon brake pads.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carbon Fibre">Howard (June 2006) p. 52. Interview with Gordon Murray and<space/><link><target>John Barnard</target></link><space/>on the early uses of Carbon Fibre in Formula One for brakes and chassis structure.</extension><space/>By the late 1980s, carbon brakes were used by all competitors in almost all top level motor sports.</paragraph><paragraph>Although Brabham experimented with airdams and underbody skirts in the mid-1970s, the team, like the rest of the field, did not immediately understand Lotus's development of a<space/><link><target>ground effect in cars</target><part>ground effect</part></link><space/>car in 1977. The<space/><link><target>Brabham BT46</target><part>Brabham BT46B</part></link><space/>&quot;Fan car&quot; of 1978, generated enormous downforce with a fan, which sucked air from beneath the car, although its claimed use was for engine cooling. The car only raced once in the Formula One World Championship<link><target>Niki Lauda</target></link><space/>winning the<space/><link><target>1978 Swedish Grand Prix</target></link>before a<space/><link><target>wiktionary:loophole</target><part>loophole</part></link><space/>in the regulations was closed by the FIA.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 186187. It is often claimed that the car was never banned, but rather withdrawn by Ecclestone. Ecclestone did agree to withdraw it after three races, but the FIA changed the regulations to render &quot;fan cars&quot; in general, not the BT46B in particular, illegal before it could race again.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although in 1979 Murray was the first to use lightweight &quot;<link><target>Carbon fibre reinforced plastic</target><part>carbon fibre composite</part></link>&quot; panels to stiffen Brabham's<space/><link><target>aluminium</target><part>aluminium alloy</part></link><space/>monocoques, he echoed his predecessor Tauranac in being the last to switch to the new fully composite monocoques. Murray was reluctant to build the entire chassis from composite materials until he understood their behaviour in a crash, an understanding achieved in part through an instrumented<space/><link><target>crash test</target></link><space/>of a BT49 chassis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carbon Fibre"></extension><space/>The team did not follow McLaren's 1981 MP4/1 with their own fully composite chassis until the &quot;lowline&quot; BT55 in 1986,<extension extension_name='ref' name="AZBrabham">Hodges (1998) p. 43</extension><space/>the last team to do so. This technology is now used in all top level single seater racing cars.</paragraph><paragraph>For the 1981 season the FIA introduced a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>minimum<space/><link><target>ride height</target></link><space/>for the cars, intended to slow them in corners by limiting the downforce created by aerodynamic ground effect. Gordon Murray devised a &quot;<link><target>hydropneumatic suspension</target></link>&quot; system for the BT49C, which allowed the car to settle to a much lower ride height at speed. Brabham were accused of cheating by other teams, although Murray believes that the system met the letter of the regulations. No action was taken against the team and others soon produced systems with similar effects.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) pp. 223225</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the<space/><link><target>1982 British Grand Prix</target></link>, Brabham reintroduced the idea of re-fuelling and changing the car's tyres during the race, unseen since the<space/><link><target>1957 Formula One season</target></link>, to allow their drivers to sprint away at the start of races on a light fuel load and soft tyres. After studying techniques used at the<space/><link><target>Indianapolis 500</target></link><space/>and in<space/><link><target>NASCAR</target></link><space/>racing in the United States, the team were able to refuel and re-tyre the car in 14 seconds in tests ahead of the race. In 1982 Murray felt the tactic did little more than &quot;get our sponsors noticed at races we had no chance of winning&quot;, but in 1983 the team made good use of the tactic.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hamilton (ed.) (1983) pp. 6372<space/><italics>Pitstops: A split-second spectacle</italics><space/>feature by<space/><link><target>Denis Jenkinson</target></link>.</extension><space/>Refuelling was banned for 1984, and did not reappear until the<space/><link><target>1994 Formula One season</target><part>1994 season</part></link><space/>(until it was banned again in<space/><link><target>2010 Formula One season</target><part>2010</part></link><space/>as a part of cost cutting measures), but tyre changes have remained part of Formula One.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Hamilton</arg><arg name="first">Maurice</arg><arg name="title">Ayrton Senna would applaud formula one's 2010 rebirth</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/blog/2009/may/03/formula-one-2010-refuelling-ayrton-senna</arg><arg name="work">The Guardian</arg><arg name="publisher">Guardian News and Media Ltd</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2011</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="date">3 May 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Controversy</heading><paragraph>The fan car and hydropneumatic suspension exploited loopholes in the sporting regulations. In the early 1980s, Brabham was accused of going further and breaking the regulations. During 1981, Piquet's first championship year, rumours circulated of illegal underweight Brabham chassis. Driver<space/><link><target>Jacques Laffite</target></link><space/>was among those to claim that the cars were fitted with heavily ballasted<space/><link><target>Coachwork</target><part>bodywork</part></link><space/>before being weighed at<space/><link><target>scrutineer</target><trail>ing</trail></link>. The accusation was denied by Brabham's management. No formal protest was made against the team and no action was taken against them by the sporting authorities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 225</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From 1978, Ecclestone was president of the<space/><link><target>Formula One Constructors Association</target></link><space/>(FOCA), a body formed by the teams to represent their interests. This left his team open to accusations of having advance warning of rule changes. Ecclestone denies that the team benefited from this and Murray has noted that, contrary to this view, at the end of 1982 the team had to abandon their new BT51 car, built on the basis that ground effect would be permitted in 1983. Brabham had to design and build a replacement, the BT52, in only three months.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry (1985) p. 255</extension><space/>At the end of the 1983 season, Renault and Ferrari, both beaten to the Drivers' Championship by Piquet, protested that the<space/><link><target>Octane rating</target><part>Research Octane Number</part></link><space/>(RON) of the team's fuel was above the legal limit of 102. The FIA declared that a figure of up to 102.9 was permitted under the rules, and that Brabham had not exceeded this limit.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drackett (1985) p. 133. Although &quot;protested&quot;, as used by Drackett, implies a formal protest, he does not specify this, and Henry (1985) p. 267 says &quot;no action was ever taken&quot;.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Championship results</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Brabham Grand Prix results</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Results achieved by the &quot;works&quot; Brabham team.<space/><bold>Bold</bold><space/>results indicate a championship win.</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Season</tablehead><tablehead>Entrant</tablehead><tablehead>Car</tablehead><tablehead>Tyres</tablehead><tablehead>Engine</tablehead><tablehead>Drivers</tablehead><tablehead>Constructors' Championship</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1962 Formula One season</target><part>1962</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Lotus 24</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT3</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Dunlop</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Coventry Climax FWMV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>7th (9 points)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1963 Formula One season</target><part>1963</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT3</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT7</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Lotus 25</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Dunlop</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Coventry Climax FWMV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Dan Gurney</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3rd (28 points)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1964 Formula One season</target><part>1964</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT7</target></link><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><link><target>Brabham BT11</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Dunlop</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Coventry Climax FWMV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Dan Gurney</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4th (33 points)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1965 Formula One season</target><part>1965</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT7</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT11</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Dunlop</target></template><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Coventry Climax FWMV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Dan Gurney</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Denny Hulme</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Giancarlo Baghetti</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3rd (27 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1966 Formula One season</target><part>1966</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT19</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT20<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT22</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Repco</target></link><space/>620<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Coventry Climax FPF</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><bold><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link></bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Denny Hulme</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Champion</bold><space/>(42 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1967 Formula One season</target><part>1967</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT19</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT20<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT24</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Repco</target></link><space/>620<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Repco</target></link><space/>740</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><bold><link><target>Denny Hulme</target></link></bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Champion</bold><space/>(37 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1968 Formula One season</target><part>1968</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Brabham Racing Organisation</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT24</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT26</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Repco</target></link><space/>740<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Repco</target></link><space/>860</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jochen Rindt</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Dan Gurney</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>8th (10 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1969 Formula One season</target><part>1969</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT26/A</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jacky Ickx</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2nd (51 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1970 Formula One season</target><part>1970</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT33</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jack Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Rolf Stommelen</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4th (35 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1971 Formula One season</target><part>1971</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT33<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT34</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Graham Hill</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Tim Schenken</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Dave Charlton</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (5 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1972 Formula One season</target><part>1972</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT33<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT34<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT37</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Graham Hill</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Wilson Fittipaldi Jnior</target><part>Wilson Fittipaldi</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (7 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1973 Formula One season</target><part>1973</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Ceramica Pagnossin Team MRD</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT37</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT42</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Wilson Fittipaldi Jnior</target><part>Wilson Fittipaldi</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Andrea de Adamich</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Rolf Stommelen</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>John Watson (racing driver)</target><part>John Watson</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>4th (49 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1974 Formula One season</target><part>1974</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT42<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT44</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Carlos Pace</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Rikky von Opel</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Richard Robarts</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Teddy Pilette</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>5th (35 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1975 Formula One season</target><part>1975</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Martini Racing</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT44</target><part>Brabham BT44B</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Carlos Pace</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2nd (54 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1976 Formula One season</target><part>1976</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Martini Racing</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT45</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>115-12</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Carlos Reutemann</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Carlos Pace</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Rolf Stommelen</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Larry Perkins</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (9 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1977 Formula One season</target><part>1977</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Martini Racing</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT45/B</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>115-12</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Jos Carlos Pace</target><part>Carlos Pace</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>John Watson (racing driver)</target><part>John Watson</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Hans-Joachim Stuck</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Giorgio Francia</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>5th (27 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1978 Formula One season</target><part>1978</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Parmalat Racing Team</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT45C<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT46</target><part>Brabham BT46/B/C</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>115-12</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Niki Lauda</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>John Watson (racing driver)</target><part>John Watson</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3rd (53 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1979 Formula One season</target><part>1979</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Parmalat Racing Team</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT46</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT48</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT49</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>115-12<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Alfa Romeo in Formula One</target><part>Alfa Romeo</part></link><space/>1260<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Niki Lauda</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Ricardo Zunino</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>8th (6 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1980 Formula One season</target><part>1980</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Parmalat Racing Team</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT49</target><part>Brabham BT49/B</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Michelin</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Ricardo Zunino</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Hctor Rebaque</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3rd (55 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1981 Formula One season</target><part>1981</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Parmalat Racing Team</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT49</target><part>Brabham BT49/B/C</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Michelin</target></template><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><bold><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link></bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Hctor Rebaque</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Ricardo Zunino</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2nd (61 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1982 Formula One season</target><part>1982</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Parmalat Racing Team</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT49</target><part>Brabham BT49D</part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT50</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cosworth DFV</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>5th (41 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1983 Formula One season</target><part>1983</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Fila Sport</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT52</target><part>Brabham BT52/B</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Michelin</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13</tablecell><tablecell><bold><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link></bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3rd (72 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1984 Formula One season</target><part>1984</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>MRD International</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT53</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Michelin</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Teo Fabi</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Corrado Fabi</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Manfred Winkelhock</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4th (38 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1985 Formula One season</target><part>1985</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments Ltd</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT54</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Pirelli</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nelson Piquet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Marc Surer</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Franois Hesnault</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>5th (26 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1986 Formula One season</target><part>1986</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments Ltd</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT54</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT55</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Pirelli</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13/1</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Elio de Angelis</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Derek Warwick</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (2 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1987 Formula One season</target><part>1987</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments Ltd</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT56</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>BMW M12</target></link>/13/1</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Riccardo Patrese</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Andrea de Cesaris</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Stefano Modena</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>8th (10 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1989 Formula One season</target><part>1989</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT58</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Pirelli</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Judd (engine)</target><part>Judd EV</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Martin Brundle</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Stefano Modena</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (8 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1990 Formula One season</target><part>1990</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT58</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Brabham BT59</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Pirelli</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Judd (engine)</target><part>Judd EV</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Stefano Modena</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>David Brabham</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Gregor Foitek</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>10th (2 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1991 Formula One season</target><part>1991</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments Ltd</tablecell><tablecell>Brabham BT59Y<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Brabham BT60</target><part>Brabham BT60Y</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Pirelli</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Yamaha Motor Company</target><part>Yamaha</part></link><space/>OX99</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Martin Brundle</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Mark Blundell</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>9th (3 pts)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow style="vertical-align: top"><tablehead><link><target>1992 Formula One season</target><part>1992</part></link></tablehead><tablecell>Motor Racing Developments Ltd</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Brabham BT60</target><part>Brabham BT60B</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Goodyear</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Judd (engine)</target><part>Judd GV</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Eric van de Poele</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Giovanna Amati</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Damon Hill</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>NC (0 pts)</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Brabham Racing Organisation</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Books</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bamsey
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ian
<space/></arg><arg name="author2"><space/>Benzing, Enrico</arg><arg name="author3">Staniforth, Allan</arg><arg name="author4">Lawrence, Mike
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The 1000 BHP Grand Prix cars
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">G T Foulis & Co Ltd
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1988
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-85429-617-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="surname1">Brabham
<space/></arg><arg name="given1">Jack
<space/></arg><arg name="surname2">Nye
<space/></arg><arg name="given2">Doug
<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004
<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Jack Brabham Story
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Motorbooks International
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7603-1590-6
<space/></arg><arg name="url">
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">
</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Collings
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Timothy
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Piranha Club
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Virgin Books
<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7535-0965-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Drackett
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Phil
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham—Story of a racing team
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Arthur Baker Ltd
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1985
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-213-16915-0<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gill
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Barrie (ed.)
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The World Championship 1975 – [[John Player & Sons|John Player]] Motorsport yearbook 1976
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Queen Anne Press Ltd.
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1976
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-362-00254-1<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hamilton
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Maurice (ed.)
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Autocourse 1983–1984
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hazleton Publishing
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1983
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-905138-25-2<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Henry
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alan
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham, the Grand Prix Cars
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1985
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-905138-36-8<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hodges
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A-Z of Formula Racing Cars 1945–1990
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bay View books
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-901432-17-3<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lawrence
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mike
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham+Ralt+Honda: The Ron Tauranac story
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Motor Racing Publications
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-899870-35-0<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lovell
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Terry
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bernie's Game
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Metro Books
<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84358-086-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Nye
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Doug
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Autocourse history of the Grand Prix car 1966–85
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hazleton publishing
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-905138-37-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Roebuck
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Nigel
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Grand Prix Greats
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Patrick Stephens Ltd
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-85059-792-7<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Tremayne
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Hughes, Mark
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concise Encyclopedia of Formula One
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Parragon
<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1998</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="edition">updated
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7525-6735-7<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Unique
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>(Various)
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham – the man and the machines
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Unique Motor Books
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84155-619-X<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Newspapers and Magazines</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baker
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Andrew
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sport Almanack: Racing cars for sale: one careful owner
<space/></arg><arg name="page">
<space/></arg><arg name="language">
<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Independent<space/></arg><arg name="location">UK
<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 October 1993<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fearnley
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The powerhouse that Jack built
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>41
<space/></arg><arg name="language">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[http://www.motorsportmagazine.com/ Motorsport]
<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2006<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Howard
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Keith
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Carbon fibre
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>52
<space/></arg><arg name="language">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Motorsport
<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 2006<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Murray
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alasdair
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tycoon's drive and a formula worth millions
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>4
<space/></arg><arg name="language">
<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Times<space/></arg><arg name="location">UK
<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 November 1987<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Scarlett
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Team Building
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>43
<space/></arg><arg name="language">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Motorsport
<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2006<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Websites</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.grandprix.com/gpe/con-brabh.html
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Brabham (Motor Racing Developments Ltd.)
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>7 December 2006
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>GrandPrix.com
<space/></arg><arg name="first">
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">www.grandprix.com
<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20060307165926/http://www.grandprix.com/gpe/con-brabh.html
<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>7 March 2006<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.sfo.gov.uk/publications/annual_1998.asp
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Serious Fraud Office Annual Report 1997–98
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>7 December 2006
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Wright
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rosalind
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">www.sfo.gov.uk
<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://replay.web.archive.org/20040812185226/http://www.sfo.gov.uk/publications/annual_1998.asp
<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>12 August 2004</arg></template><space/>Also available in hardcopy. Published by<space/><link><target>Office of Public Sector Information</target><part>HMSO</part></link><space/>July 1998. ISBN 0-10-551856-5</listitem></list><paragraph>All race and championship results are taken from the Official Formula 1 Website.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.formula1.com/results/season/1962/'>1962 Season review.</link><space/>www.formula1.com. Retrieved 27 April 2006</paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.forix.com/8w/jbrabham.html'>www.forix.com</link><space/>Biography of Jack Brabham, with significant content on the early years of the Brabham team.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nvo.com/brabhams/pictures/'>www.nvo.com</link><space/>Picture gallery of historic Brabhams.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.motorracing-archive.com/pdfs/Brabham_Chassis.pdf'>www.motorracing-archive.com</link><space/>Summary history of Brabham 19611972, including significant race results and production numbers for all models. (Archived<space/><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20050115120539/http://www.motorracing-archive.com/pdfs/Brabham_Chassis.pdf'>here</link>).</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oldracingcars.com/marques/brabham'>www.oldracingcars.com</link><space/>Complete race history of all Brabham F1 models from 1966 to 1982 and links to Brabham research projects on other models.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.f3history.co.uk/'>www.f3history.co.uk</link><space/>History of Formula Three, including Brabham (under 'Manufacturers'). (Archived<space/><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20051216113158/f3history.co.uk/Manufacturers/Brabham/brabham.htm'>here</link>)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.autocoursegpa.com/team_team.asp?teamsroot_id=8095'>www.autocoursegpa.com</link><space/>Complete world championship Brabham team statistics</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-sports</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Team Lotus|Lotus]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Formula One World Constructors' Champions|Formula One Constructors' Champion]]</arg><arg name="years">{{f1|1966}}–{{f1|1967}}</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Team Lotus|Lotus]]</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template><template><target>Brabham</target></template><template><target>Formula One constructors</target></template><template><target>Formula One World Constructors' Champions</target></template><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Defunct motor vehicle manufacturers of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Companies established in 1960</target></link><link><target>Category:Vehicle manufacturing companies disestablished in 1992</target></link><link><target>Category:Formula One constructors</target></link><link><target>Category:Formula Two constructors</target></link><link><target>Category:Formula One entrants</target></link><link><target>Category:Formula Two entrants</target></link><link><target>Category:British auto racing teams</target></link><link><target>Category:British racecar constructors</target></link><link><target>Category:1960 establishments in the United Kingdom</target></link></paragraph></article>