<article title='Blizzard'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the winter storm condition</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Weather</target></template><link><target>Image:Blizzard1 - NOAA.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Visibility</target></link><space/>reduced by blowing snow during a blizzard</part></link>A<space/><bold>blizzard</bold><space/>is a severe snowstorm characterized by strong sustained winds of at least<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>56</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>and lasting for a prolonged period of timetypically three hours or more. A<space/><italics>ground blizzard</italics><space/>is a weather condition where snow is not falling but loose snow on the ground is lifted and blown by strong winds.<link><target>File:Tochal sport complex 16.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Blizzard into<space/><link><target>Tochal Complex</target><part>Tochal Skiing resort</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Tehran</target></link><space/>and involved skiers.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Definition</heading><paragraph>In the United States, the<space/><link><target>National Weather Service</target></link><space/>defines a blizzard as a severe<space/><link><target>snowstorm</target></link><space/>characterized by strong winds causing<space/><link><target>blowing snow</target></link><space/>that results in low visibilities. The difference between a blizzard and a snowstorm is the strength of the wind, not the amount of snow. To be a blizzard, a snow storm must have sustained winds or frequent gusts that are greater than or equal to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>56</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>with blowing or drifting snow which reduces<space/><link><target>visibility</target></link><space/>to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>400</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">or</arg></template><space/>or less and must last for a prolonged period of timetypically three hours or more.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.weather.gov/glossary/index.php?letter</arg><arg name="title">Blizzard at the US National Weather Service glossary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Weather.gov<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-06-25<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-18</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"><link type='external' href='http://www.ussartf.org/blizzards.htm'>Blizzards</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Covilhanevao.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Impact of blizzard in<space/><link><target>Serra da Estrela</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link></part></link><space/>While severe cold and large amounts of<space/><link><target>snowdrift</target><part>drifting snow</part></link><space/>may accompany blizzards, they are not required. Blizzards can bring<space/><link><target>Whiteout (weather)</target><part>whiteout</part></link><space/>conditions, and can paralyze regions for days at a time, particularly where snowfall is unusual or rare.</paragraph><paragraph>A severe blizzard has winds over<template><target>convert</target><arg>72</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, near zero visibility, and temperatures of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>-12</arg><arg>C</arg></template><space/>or lower.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2"><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/69478/blizzard'>&quot;Blizzard&quot;</link><space/><italics>Encyclopdia Britannica Online</italics><space/>retrieved 17 March 2012</extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Antarctica</target></link>, blizzards are associated with winds spilling over the edge of the ice plateau at an average velocity of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>160</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated2"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Ground blizzard</target></link><space/>refers to a weather condition where loose snow or ice on the ground is lifted and blown by strong winds. The primary difference between a ground blizzard as opposed to a regular blizzard is that in a ground blizzard no precipitation is produced at the time, but rather all the precipitation is already present in the form of snow or ice at the surface.<link><target>File:Old farm at Overtown in deep snow in 1963.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Drifted snow near<space/><link><target>Burrow-with-Burrow</target></link>, Lancashire, England, January 1963</part></link>The Australia Bureau of<space/><link><target>Meteorology</target></link><space/>describes a blizzard as, &quot;Violent and very cold wind which is laden with snow, some part, at least, of which has been raised from snow covered ground.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bom.gov.au/info/wwords/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blizzard definition, Weather Words, Australian Government Bureau of Meteorology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bom.gov.au<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-18</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Blizzard conditions of cold temperatures and strong winds can cause<space/><link><target>wind chill</target></link><space/>values that can result in<space/><link><target>hypothermia</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>frostbite</target></link>. The wind chill factor is the amount of cooling the human body feels due to the combination of wind and temperature.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Blizzards in Australia</heading><paragraph>Blizzards are not common in mainland<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>, but occur frequently in the Snowy Mountains in New South Wales and Victoria. When blizzards do occur, they can affect the Tasmanian Highlands and, particularly,<space/><link><target>Mount Wellington (Tasmania)</target><part>Mount Wellington</part></link>, which towers over the Tasmanian capital Hobart. Blizzards do not affect any major towns or cities, because there are no populated areas located in the mountains except for the ski resort towns of New South Wales and Victoria.</paragraph><heading level='2'>United States storm systems</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Duluth blizzard, December 2007.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Duluth blizzard, December 2007</part><part><link><target>Duluth, Minnesota</target></link><space/>blizzard, March 2007</part></link><link><target>File:Blizzard2 - NOAA.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>March blizzard in North Dakota, 1966. Caption jokingly reads &quot;I believe there is a train under here somewhere!&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, storm systems powerful enough to cause blizzards usually form when the<space/><link><target>jet stream</target></link><space/>dips far to the south, allowing cold, dry polar air from the north to clash with warm, humid air moving up from the south.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.weather.com/encyclopedia/winter/blizzard.html'>weather.com - Storm Encyclopedia</link></extension><space/>They are most common in the Great Plains, the Great Lakes states, and the northeastern states along the coast, and less common in the Pacific Northwest.</paragraph><paragraph>When cold, moist air from the Pacific Ocean moves eastward to the<space/><link><target>Rocky Mountains</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Great Plains</target></link>, and warmer, moist air moves north from the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Mexico</target></link>, all that is needed is a movement of cold polar air moving south to form potential blizzard conditions that may extend from the<space/><link><target>Texas Panhandle</target></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>Great Lakes</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Another storm system occurs when a cold core low over the<space/><link><target>Hudson Bay</target></link><space/>area in Canada is displaced southward over southeastern Canada, the Great Lakes, and<space/><link><target>New England</target></link>. When the rapidly moving cold front collides with warmer air coming north from the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Mexico</target></link>, strong surface winds, significant cold air<space/><link><target>advection</target></link>, and extensive wintry precipitation occur.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Nearwhiteoutinminnesota.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Conditions approaching a blizzard whiteout in<space/><link><target>Minnesota</target></link>, on March 1, 2007. Note the unclear horizon near the center.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Low pressure systems</target></link><space/>moving out of the Rocky Mountains onto the Great Plains, a broad expanse of flat land, much of it covered in<space/><link><target>prairie</target></link>,<space/><link><target>steppe</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>grassland</target></link>, can cause thunderstorms and rain to the south and heavy snows and strong winds to the north. With few trees or other obstructions to reduce wind and blowing, this part of the country is particularly vulnerable to blizzards with very low temperatures and<space/><link><target>whiteout (weather)</target><part>whiteout</part></link><space/>conditions. In a true whiteout there is no visible horizon. People can become lost in their own front yards, when the door is only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>away, and they would have to feel their way back. Motorists have to stop their cars where they are, as the road is impossible to see.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nor'easter blizzards</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:TotallyFreeImages com-281074-Standard-preview.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>200 px</part><part>The Great Blizzard of 1888</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>nor'easter</target></link><space/>is a macro-scale<space/><link><target>storm</target></link><space/>along the<space/><link><target>East Coast of the United States</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Atlantic Canada</target></link>; it gets its name from the direction the wind is coming from. The usage of the term in North America comes from the wind associated with many different types of storms some of which can form in the North Atlantic Ocean and some of which form as far south as the Gulf of Mexico. The term is most often used in the coastal areas of<space/><link><target>New England</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Atlantic Canada</target></link>. This type of storm has characteristics similar to a<space/><link><target>hurricane</target></link>. More specifically it describes a<space/><link><target>low-pressure area</target></link><space/>whose center of<space/><link><target>rotation</target></link><space/>is just off the East Coast and whose leading winds in the left-forward quadrant rotate onto land from the northeast. High storm waves may sink ships at sea and cause coastal flooding and beach erosion. Notable nor'easters include The<space/><link><target>Great Blizzard of 1888</target></link>, one of the worst blizzards in U.S. history. It dropped<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>50</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of snow and had sustained winds of more than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>45</arg><arg>mph</arg></template><space/>that produced snowdrifts in excess of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>. Railroads were shut down and people were confined to their houses for up to a week. It killed 400 people, mostly in New York.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historic events</heading><heading level='3'>1972 Iran blizzard</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>1972 Iran blizzard</target><part>1972 Iran Blizzard</part></link>, which caused approximately 4,000 deaths, was the deadliest blizzard in recorded history. Dropping as much as<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>26</arg><arg>feet</arg><arg>meters</arg></template><space/>of snow, it completely covered 200 villages. After a snowfall lasting nearly a week, an area the size of<space/><link><target>Wisconsin</target></link><space/>was entirely buried in snow.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mentalfloss.com/article/29930/40-years-ago-iran-was-hit-deadliest-blizzard-history'>40 Years Ago, Iran Was Hit by the Deadliest Blizzard in History | Mental Floss</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Snow Winter of 18801881</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Train stuck in snow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A snow blockade in southern Minnesota. On March 29, 1881, snowdrifts in Minnesota were higher than locomotives.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The winter of 18801881 is widely considered the most severe winter ever known in the United States. Many childrenand their parentslearned of &quot;The Snow Winter&quot; through the children's book<space/><italics><link><target>The Long Winter (novel)</target><part>The Long Winter</part></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Laura Ingalls Wilder</target></link>, in which the author tells of her family's efforts to survive. The snow arrived in October 1880 and blizzard followed blizzard throughout the winter and into March 1881, leaving many areas snowbound throughout the entire winter. Accurate details in Wilder's novel include the blizzards' frequency and the deep cold, the<space/><link><target>Chicago and North Western Railway</target></link><space/>stopping trains until the spring thaw because the snow made the tracks impassable, the near-starvation of the townspeople, and the courage of her future husband Almanzo and another man, who ventured out on the open prairie in search of a cache of wheat that no one was even sure existed.</paragraph><paragraph>The October blizzard brought snowfalls so deep that two-story homes had snow up to the second floor windows. No one was prepared for the deep snow so early in the season and farmers all over the region were caught before their crops had even been harvested, their grain milled, or with their fuel supplies for the winter in place. By January the train service was almost entirely suspended from the region. Railroads hired scores of men to dig out the tracks but it was a wasted effort: As soon as they had finished shoveling a stretch of line, a new storm arrived, filling up the line and leaving their work useless.</paragraph><paragraph>There were no winter thaws and on February 2, 1881, a second massive blizzard struck that lasted for nine days. In the towns the streets were filled with solid drifts to the tops of the buildings and tunneling was needed to secure passage about town. Homes and barns were completely covered, compelling farmers to tunnel to reach and feed their stock.</paragraph><paragraph>When the snow finally melted in late spring of 1881, huge sections of the plains were flooded. Massive ice jams clogged the<space/><link><target>Missouri River</target></link><space/>and when they broke the downstream areas were ravaged. Most of the town of<space/><link><target>Yankton, South Dakota</target><part>Yankton</part></link>, in what is now South Dakota, was washed away when the river overflowed its banks.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archives.gov/publications/prologue/2003/winter/little-town-in-nara-2.html</arg><arg name="title">Prologue</arg><arg name="date">8 March 2012</arg><arg name="work">archives.gov</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">http://files.usgwarchives.net/sd/history/robinson/liii.txt</arg><arg name="title">Chapter LIII: Dakota Territory History - 1880-1881</arg><arg name="work">History of South Dakota</arg><arg name="author">Doane Robinson</arg><arg name="volume">1</arg><arg name="date">1904</arg><arg name="p">306–309</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Storm of the Century</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:1993 Storm of the Century Asheville, North Carolina snowfall.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Under the weight of snow, a tree falls next to a car in<space/><link><target>Asheville, North Carolina</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>1993 Storm of the Century</target><part>Storm of the Century</part></link>, also known as the Great Blizzard of 1993, was a large<space/><link><target>cyclone</target><part>cyclonic</part></link><space/>storm that formed over the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Mexico</target></link><space/>on March 12, 1993, and dissipated in the North Atlantic Ocean on March 15. It is unique for its intensity, massive size and wide-reaching effect. At its height, the storm stretched from Canada towards Central America, but its main impact was on the Eastern United States and Cuba. The cyclone moved through the Gulf of Mexico, and then through the Eastern United States before moving into Canada. Areas as far south as central Alabama and Georgia received<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>to</arg><arg>8</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of snow and areas such as<space/><link><target>Birmingham, Alabama</target></link>, received up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>with isolated reports of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>16</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. Even the<space/><link><target>Florida Panhandle</target></link><space/>reported up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>4</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ncdc-event-details"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Event Details<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[National Climatic Data Center]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www4.ncdc.noaa.gov/cgi-win/wwcgi.dll?wwevent~ShowEvent~194933<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">December 22, 2010</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]]</arg></template></extension><space/>with<space/><link><target>Wind#Wind force scale</target><part>hurricane-force</part></link><space/>wind gusts and record low<space/><link><target>barometric pressure</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Between Louisiana and Cuba, hurricane-force winds produced high storm surges across northwestern Florida, which along with scattered<space/><link><target>tornado</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>killed dozens of people. Record cold temperatures were seen across portions of the South and East in the wake of this storm. In the United States, the storm was responsible for the loss of<space/><link><target>electricity</target><part>electric power</part></link><space/>to over 10&amp;nbsp;million customers. It is purported to have been directly experienced by nearly 40&amp;nbsp;percent of the country's population at that time. A total of 310 people, including 10 from Cuba, perished during this storm.</paragraph><heading level='2'>List of blizzards</heading><heading level='3'>United States</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>The Snow Winter of 18801881</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Schoolhouse Blizzard</target></link><space/>of 1888, North American Great Plains. January 1213, 1888. What made the storm so deadly was the timing (during work and school hours), the suddenness, and the brief spell of warmer weather that preceded it. In addition, the very strong wind fields behind the cold front and the powdery nature of the snow reduced visibilities on the open plains to zero. People ventured from the safety of their homes to do chores, go to town, attend school, or simply enjoy the relative warmth of the day. As a result, thousands of peopleincluding many schoolchildrengot caught in the blizzard.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Blizzard of 1888</target></link><space/>March 1113, 1888. One of the most severe recorded blizzards in the history of the United States. On March 12, an unexpected northeaster hit New England and the mid-Atlantic, dropping up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>of snow in the space of two days. Some 400 people died, including many sailors aboard vessels that were beset by gale-force winds and turbulent seas. In parts of New York City, snowdrifts reached up to the second story of some buildings.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Blizzard of 1899</target></link><space/>February 1114, 1899. An extremely unusual blizzard in that it reached into the far southern states of America. It hit in February, and the area around Washington, D.C., experienced 51 hours straight of snowfall. The port of New Orleans was totally iced over; revelers participating in the New Orleans<space/><link><target>Mardi Gras</target></link><space/>had to wait for the parade routes to be shoveled free of snow. Concurrent with this blizzard was the extremely cold arctic air. Many city and state record low temperatures date back to this event, including all-time records for locations in the Midwest and South. State record lows: Nebraska reached<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>-47</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template>, Ohio experienced<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>-39</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template>, Louisiana bottomed out at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>-16</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template>, and Florida dipped below zero to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>-2</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template>.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Lakes Storm of 1913</target></link><space/>November 710, 1913, was the deadliest and most destructive<space/><link><target>natural disaster</target></link><space/>ever to hit the<space/><link><target>Great Lakes Basin</target></link><space/>in the Midwestern United States and the Canadian province of<space/><link><target>Ontario</target></link>. Termed a &quot;November<space/><link><target>gale</target></link>&quot;, it produced<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>90</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>wind gusts,<space/><link><target>ocean surface wave</target><part>waves</part></link><space/>over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>35</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>high, and<space/><link><target>whiteout (weather)</target><part>whiteout</part></link><space/><link><target>snowsquall</target><trail>s</trail></link>. It killed more than 250 people, destroyed 19 ships, and stranded 19 others. Perhaps the most well-known ship to go down in a November gale was the<space/><italics><link><target>SS Edmund Fitzgerald</target></link></italics><space/>in 1975.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>1920 North Dakota blizzard</target></link><space/>March 1518, 1920</listitem><listitem><link><target>Knickerbocker Storm</target></link><space/>January 2728, 1922</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Armistice Day Blizzard</target></link><space/>November 1012, 1940. Took place in the Midwest region of the United States on<space/><link><target>Armistice Day</target></link>. This &quot;<link><target>Panhandle hook</target></link>&quot; winter storm cut a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1000</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="adj">mid</arg><arg>-wide path</arg></template><space/>through the middle of the country from<space/><link><target>Kansas</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Michigan</target></link>. The morning of the storm was unseasonably warm but by mid afternoon conditions quickly deteriorated into a raging blizzard that would last into the next day. A total of 145 deaths were blamed on the storm, almost a third of them duck hunters who had taken time off to take advantage of the ideal hunting conditions. Weather forecasters had not predicted the severity of the oncoming storm, and as a result the hunters were not dressed for cold weather. When the storm began many hunters took shelter on small islands in the Mississippi River, and the<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>winds and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>waves overcame their encampments. Some became stranded on the islands and then froze to death in the single-digit temperatures that moved in over night. Others tried to make it to shore and drowned.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 1947</target></link><space/>December 2526, 1947. Was a record-breaking snowfall that began on Christmas Day and brought the Northeast United States to a standstill. It was not accompanied by high winds, but the snow fell steadily with drifts reaching<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template>. Seventy-seven deaths were attributed to the blizzard.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Appalachian Storm of November 1950</target></link><space/>November 2430, 1950</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 1966</target></link><space/>January 2731, 1966</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chicago Blizzard of 1967</target></link><space/>January 2627, 1967</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 1969 nor'easter</target></link><space/>February 810, 1969</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Great Storm of 1975</target></link><space/>known as the Super Bowl Blizzard or Minnesota's Storm of the Century. January 912, 1975</listitem><listitem><link><target>Groundhog Day gale of 1976</target></link><space/>February 2, 1976</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blizzard of 1977</target></link><space/>January 28-February 1, 1977</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Blizzard of 1978</target></link><space/>also called the Cleveland Superbomb. January 2527, 1978. Was one of the worst snowstorms the Midwest has ever seen. Wind gusts approached<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template>, causing snowdrifts to reach heights of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in some areas, making roadways impassable.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Northeastern United States Blizzard of 1978</target></link><space/>- February 67, 1978</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chicago Blizzard of 1979</target></link><space/>January 1314, 1979</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>1991 Halloween blizzard</target></link><space/>Upper Mid-West US, October 31-November 3, 1991</listitem><listitem><link><target>December 1992 nor'easter</target></link><space/>December 1012, 1992</listitem><listitem><link><target>1993 Storm of the Century</target></link><space/>March 1215, 1993. While the southern and eastern U.S. and Cuba received the brunt of this massive blizzard, the Storm of the Century impacted a wider area than any in recorded history.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blizzard of 1996</target></link><space/>January 610, 1996</listitem><listitem><link><target>April Fool's Day Blizzard</target></link><space/>March 31-April 1, 1997. US East Coast</listitem><listitem><link><target>1997 Western Plains winter storms</target></link><space/>October 2426, 1997</listitem><listitem><link><target>Blizzard of 1999</target></link><space/>January 24, 1999</listitem><listitem><link><target>January 25, 2000 Southeastern United States winter storm</target></link><space/>January 25, 2000. North Carolina and Virginia</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 2003</target></link><space/>February 1419, 2003 (Presidents' Day Storm II)</listitem><listitem><link><target>December 2003 nor'easter</target></link><space/>December 67, 2003</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 2005</target></link><space/>January 2023, 2005</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 2006</target></link><space/>February 1113, 2006</listitem><listitem><link><target>Early winter 2006 North American storm complex</target></link><space/>Late November 2006</listitem><listitem><link><target>Colorado Holiday Blizzards (200607)</target></link><space/>December 2029, 2006 Colorado</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 2007 North America blizzard</target></link><space/>February 1220, 2007</listitem><listitem><link><target>January 2008 North American storm complex</target></link><space/>January, 2008 West Coast US</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 2008</target></link><space/>March 610, 2008</listitem><listitem><link><target>2009 Midwest Blizzard</target></link><space/>68 December 2009, a bomb cyclogenesis event that also affected parts of Canada</listitem><listitem><link><target>North American blizzard of 2009</target></link><space/>December 1620, 2009</listitem><listitem><link><target>2009 North American Christmas blizzard</target></link><space/>December 2228, 2009</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 56, 2010 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>February 56, 2010 Referred to at the time as<space/><link><target>Snowmageddon</target></link><space/>was a Category 3 (&quot;major&quot;) nor'easter and severe weather event.</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 910, 2010 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>February 910, 2010</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 2527, 2010 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>February 2527, 2010</listitem><listitem><link><target>October 2010 North American storm complex</target></link><space/>October 2328, 2010</listitem><listitem><link><target>December 2010 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>December 2629, 2010</listitem><listitem><link><target>January 31 February 2, 2011 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>January 31-February 2, 2011. Groundhog Day Blizzard of 2011</listitem><listitem><link><target>2011 Halloween nor'easter</target></link><space/>October 28-Nov 1, 2011</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hurricane Sandy</target></link><space/>October 2931, 2012. West Virginia, western North Carolina, and southwest Pennsylvania received heavy snowfall and blizzard conditions from this hurricane</listitem><listitem><link><target>November 2012 nor'easter</target></link><space/>November 710, 2012</listitem><listitem><link><target>December 1722, 2012 North American blizzard</target></link><space/>December 1722, 2012</listitem><listitem><link><target>December 2528, 2012 North American storm complex</target></link><space/>December 2528, 2012</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 2013 nor'easter</target></link><space/>February 720, 2013</listitem><listitem><link><target>February 2013 Great Plains blizzard</target></link><space/>February 19-March 6, 2013</listitem><listitem><link><target>March 2013 nor'easter</target></link><space/>March 6, 2013</listitem><listitem><link><target>October 2013 North American storm complex</target></link><space/>October 35, 2013</listitem><listitem><link><target>January 2015 North American blizzard</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Saskatchewan blizzard of 2007</target></link><space/>- January 10, 2007 Canada</listitem></list><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Winter of 19461947 in the United Kingdom</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Winter of 19621963 in the United Kingdom</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>February 2009 Great Britain and Ireland snowfall</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other locations</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>1954 Romanian blizzard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>1972 Iran blizzard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Winter of 19901991 in Western Europe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>2008 Chinese winter storms</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Winter storms of 20092010 in East Asia</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lake effect blizzard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nor'easter</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Whiteout (weather)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Blowing Snow Advisory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ground blizzard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Severe weather terminology (Canada)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Snowsquall</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Blowing snow</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target><arg>Blizzard</arg><arg>Blizzard</arg></template><template><target>Americana Poster</target></template><template><target>Wikivoyage</target><arg>Travelling in cold weather</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wintercenter.homestead.com/photoindex.html'>Digital Snow Museum Photos of historic blizzards and snowstorms.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.farmersalmanac.com/weather/2008/12/15/historic-blizzards/'>Farmers Almanac List of Worst Blizzards in the United States</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ussartf.org/blizzards.htm'>United States Search and Rescue Task Force: About Blizzards</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.drrichardwild.co.uk/pdf/What%20is%20a%20Blizzard.pdf'>A Historical Review On The Origin and Definition of the Word Blizzard</link><space/>Dr Richard Wild</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Natural disasters</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Blizzards</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Snow or ice weather phenomena</target></link><link><target>Category:Storm</target></link><link><target>Category:Weather hazards</target></link></paragraph></article>