<article title='Eindhoven_University_of_Technology'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox university</target><arg name="name"><space/>Eindhoven University of Technology
</arg><arg name="native_name"><space/>Technische Universiteit Eindhoven
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:TU Eindhoven.jpg|300px]]
</arg><arg name="latin_name">
</arg><arg name="motto"><space/>''Mens Agitat Molem''
</arg><arg name="mottoeng"><space/>Mind moves matter<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="established"><space/>23 June 1956<ref name</arg><arg name="type"><space/>[[Public university|Public]], [[Technical University|Technical]]
</arg><arg name="budget"><space/>€287.4M<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="president">
</arg><arg name="rector"><space/>Prof.dr. ir. F.P.T. Baaijens
</arg><arg name="city"><space/>[[Eindhoven]]
</arg><arg name="province"><space/>[[North Brabant]]
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>[[Netherlands]]
</arg><arg name="campus"><space/>Urban, {{convert|121|ha|acre|abbr</arg><arg name="former_names"><space/>Technische Hogeschool Eindhoven
</arg><arg name="students"><space/>7100
</arg><arg name="staff"><space/>2200
</arg><arg name="affiliations"><space/>[[3TU]], [[CESAER Association|CESAER]], [[Santander Network|Santander]], [[CLUSTER]], [[European University Association|EUA]] and [[Eurotech Universities|Eurotech]]
</arg><arg name="colors"><space/>Red and dark blue<ref name</arg><arg name="logo"><space/>[[File:TUeLOG SLO D RGB -Converted-.svg|300 px|Eindhoven University of Technology logo]]
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>[https://www.tue.nl/ www.tue.nl]
</arg><arg name="coor"><space/>{{coord|51|26|53|N|5|29|23|E|region:NL_type:edu|display</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold><italics>Eindhoven University of Technology</italics></bold><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>lang-nl</target><arg>'''Technische Universiteit Eindhoven'''</arg></template>,<space/><link><target>Abbreviation</target><part>abbr.</part></link><space/><bold><template><target>lang</target><arg>nl</arg><arg>''TU/e''</arg></template></bold>.</extension><space/>is a<space/><link><target>University of Technology</target><part>university of technology</part></link><space/>located in<space/><link><target>Eindhoven</target></link>, Netherlands. Its motto is<space/><italics>Mens agitat molem</italics><space/>(Mind moves matter). The university was the second of its kind in the Netherlands, only<space/><link><target>TU Delft</target><part>Delft University of Technology</part></link><space/>existed previously. Until mid-1980 it was known as the<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>nl</arg><arg>''Technische Hogeschool Eindhoven''</arg></template><space/>(abbr.<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>nl</arg><arg>''THE''</arg></template>). In 2011<space/><link><target>QS World University Rankings</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.topuniversities.com/institution/eindhoven-university-technology/wur<space/></arg><arg name="title">Where to Study<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Top Universities<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension><space/>placed Eindhoven at 146th internationally, but 61st globally for Engineering &amp; IT. Furthermore, in 2011 Academic Ranking of World Universities (ARWU) rankings,<extension extension_name='ref' name="shanghairanking.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.shanghairanking.com/Institution.jsp?param</arg><arg name="title">Eindhoven University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Shanghairanking.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension><space/>TU/e was placed at the 52-75 bucket internationally in Engineering/Technology and Computer Science (ENG) category and at 34th place internationally in the field of Computer Science. In 2003 a European Commission report ranked TU/e at third place among all European research universities (after Cambridge and Oxford and at equal rank with TU Munich), thus making it the highest ranked Technical University in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref' name="The university model for the 21st century"><link type='external' href='ftp://ftp.cordis.europa.eu/pub/indicators/docs/3rd_report_snaps10.pdf'>EU commission report (PDF)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:URE05e.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The full electric<space/><link><target>Formula Student</target></link><space/>car developed and built by 60 students of the Eindhoven University of Technology</part></link><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of rectores magnifici of the Eindhoven University of Technology</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Eindhoven University of Technology was founded as the<space/><italics>Technische Hogeschool Eindhoven</italics><space/>(THE) on 23 June 1956 by the Dutch government. The University was acknowledged for its research in Automobile sector. It was the second institute of its kind in the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>, preceded only by the<space/><link><target>Delft University of Technology</target></link>. It is located on its own campus in the center of Eindhoven, just north of the central station. It is currently home to about 240 professors, 7200 students, 250 PDEng-students, 600 Ph.D. students, 200 post-doc students and 3000 regular employees. It supports about 100 student associations and 15 alumni associations.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://w3.tue.nl/en/the_university/management/facts_and_figures/'>TU/e: Facts and figures</link><space/>URL accessed on 3 July 2006</extension><space/>Yearly, the Eindhoven University of Technology produces almost 3000 scientific publications, 140 PhD-awards, and 40 patents.</paragraph><paragraph>The Eindhoven University of Technology is main participant in the technological top institutes DPI and<space/><link><target>Technological Topinstitute</target><part>M2i</part></link>. One of its former students is<space/><link><target>Gerard Kleisterlee</target></link>, a former CEO of<space/><link><target>Philips</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The university is in an area where several companies active in technology are doing their research, like<space/><link><target>Philips</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ASML Holding</target><part>ASML</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>DAF Trucks</target><part>DAF</part></link>. The university maintains close contacts with most of these companies.</paragraph><paragraph>As of 29 April 2005, Prof.dr.ir. C.J. van Duijn has the position of rector magnificus.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2006, the university celebrated its 50th birthday.</paragraph><paragraph>In a 2003 European Commission report,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='ftp://ftp.cordis.europa.eu/pub/indicators/docs/3rd_report_snaps10.pdf'>European Commission ranking of the 22 European universities with the highest scientific publication impact</link>, (see<space/><link type='external' href='http://cordis.europa.eu/indicators/third_report.htm'>cordis.europa.eu</link><space/>for the full report)</extension><space/>TU/e was ranked as 3rd among European research universities (after Cambridge and Oxford, at equality with TU Munich and thus making it the highest ranked Technical University in Europe), based on the impact of its scientific research. In 'The Times Higher Education Supplement World University Ranking 2005'.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gse.nus.edu.sg/document/Tech%20top%2010.pdf'>The worlds top 100 technology universities</link><space/>URL accessed on 3 July 2006</extension><space/>it was ranked 74th among world universities, and 67th in 2006.</paragraph><paragraph>The university operates several international cooperations with other universities all over the world; the Brain Bridge with<space/><link><target>Zhejiang University</target></link>, People's Republic of China, is an example of such a cooperation. Also, the university maintains partnerships with several Dutch universities and announced a &quot;preferred partnership&quot; with the<space/><link><target>Universiteit Utrecht</target></link><space/>on 3 January 2011.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AnnouncementPreferredPartnershipUU"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/nieuws/artikel/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Strategische alliantie TU/e met Universiteit Utrecht en UMC Utrecht<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">Strategic Alliance TU/e with University of Utrecht and the UMC<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 January 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eindhoven University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 January 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Strategic Vision 2020</heading><paragraph>On 3 January 2011, ir. Arno Peels presented the university's strategic vision document for the period up to 2020, the &quot;Strategic Plan 2020&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="StratPlanAnnouncement"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/nieuws/artikel/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D</arg><arg name="title">Strategisch Plan 2020 vergt 700 miljoen euro<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">Strategic Plan 2020 will take 700 million euro</arg><arg name="date">3 January 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eindhoven University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Dutch</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 January 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Despite the economic crisis and the budget cutbacks announced by the Dutch government for the period up to 2014, the university has set itself an ambitious strategic vision for the period up to 2020. This vision includes establishing a University College to foster both in-depth and wide-interest, society-interest driven education for upcoming engineers; establishing a combined Graduate School to manage the graduate programs; an increase of the student body by 50 percent; a 50 percent increase in the number of annual Ph.D graduations; an increase of knowledge valorisation to a campus-wide score of 4.2; increasing the international position of the university to within the top-100 universities; and increasing the embedding of the university within the city and the Brainport region by transforming the campus into a high-grade science park with laboratories, housing facilities for 700 students and researchers and supporting facilities. Particularly the science park of the vision is costly, with an expected 700 million euro investment in the campus needed for realization of the plan.<extension extension_name='ref' name="StratPlan2020"><template><target>nl icon</target></template><space/><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.tue.nl/fileadmin/de_universiteit/Strategie_TUe2020/TUE_2020_Strategisch_Plan_NL.pdf Strategisch Plan 2020]</arg><arg>3.0Mb</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Organization</heading><paragraph>The Eindhoven University of Technology is a public university of the Netherlands. As such its general structure and management is determined by the<space/><italics>Wet op het Hoger Onderwijs en Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek</italics><space/>(English:<space/><italics>Law on Higher Education and Scientific Research</italics>). Between that law and the statutes of the university itself, the management of the university is organized according to the following chart:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Organogram"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/de_universiteit/organogram/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Organogram<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Organogram of the management of the Eindhoven University of Technology.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>600px</part><part>Organization chart of the TU/e management</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Executive college</heading><paragraph>The day-to-day running of the university is in the hands of the Executive College (Dutch:<space/><italics>College van Bestuur</italics>). The College provides oversight for the departments, the service organizations and the Innovation Lab, plus the local activities of the<space/><link><target>Stan Ackermans Institute</target></link>. The College consists of three people, plus a secretary:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>The chairman</defkey><defval><space/>The chairman is the chairman of the college and the main face of the university to the outside world. Technically almost anybody can be chairman, as long as they have plenty of management experience. Over the last few years the post has been held by people from outside the university, chosen from industry top levels, in order to strengthen the ties between the university and industrial partners. The current chairman is ir. Jan Mengelers.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>The rector magnificus</defkey><defval><space/>The<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link><space/>is the one member of the College whose membership is mandated by law. The law allows the university to appoint a rector in any way, but the university statutes determine that the rector magnificus must be an active professor at the university (and must have been that before being appointed rector); in practice the rector is always a former department dean. The rector is the voice of the academic staff in the College and guards the academic interests of the university in the College. The current rector magnificus is<space/><link><target>Hans van Duijn</target></link>.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>The third member</defkey><defval><space/>The third member is a &quot;tie-breaker&quot; member of the College. The post is open to anybody (but generally not filled by an academic staff member). The current third member is Jo van Ham.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>The secretary</defkey><defval><space/>The secretary is not a member of the College but a university functionary who does secretarial work for the College: he keeps the minutes and the records, plus takes care of the communication between the College and the university (posting announcements and so on). The College secretary is usually the secretary for the entire university. The current secretary is dr. M.M.N. (Nicole) Ummelen.</defval></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Oversight of the executive college</heading><paragraph>There are two bodies that provide oversight over the Executive College:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The Oversight Board is an external board of five people appointed by the Minister of Education (one member is appointed at the suggestion of the University Council). The Board provides external oversight of the running of the university, including changing of the statutes, the budget and other management decisions.</listitem><listitem>The University Council is a council of 18 people, half of whom are elected from the university staff (academic and otherwise) and half from the student body. The University Council is informed of the running of the university by the College at least twice a year and may advise the College as it sees fit. It guards against discrimination within the university. And the council must agree to changes in the management structure. The Council membership is open to all students and personnel, except those persons who are in the Oversight Board, the Executive College or who are the University Secretary.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Departments and service organizations</heading><paragraph>Most of the work at the university is done in the departments and the service organizations.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>#Departments</target><part>departments</part></link><space/>take care of most of the research and education at the university; each one is run by its professors, headed by the<space/><link><target>dean (education)</target><part>dean</part></link>. The deans are all members of the executive deliberation meeting, which is a regular meeting of the deans and the rector.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>#Service organizations</target><part>service organizations</part></link><space/>provide services to the inhabitants of the university campus. Examples of these organizations include the housing organization, the ICT organization and the Communication Expertise Center (which does external communications, including to the press). Each service organization is headed by an organization head.</listitem></list><paragraph>Both for the departments and the service organizations, the staff (and students) are involved with the running of the body. For that reason both types of bodies have advisory councils which have advisory and co-decision authorities.</paragraph><heading level='3'>TU/e Holding B.V.</heading><paragraph>Over the past two decades, the TU/e has increasingly developed commercial interests and off-campus ties. These include commercial agreements and contracts directly between the university and external companies, but also interests in<space/><link><target>#Spinoffs</target><part>spinoff companies</part></link>. In order to manage these kinds of contractual obligations the university started the TU/e Holding B.V. in 1997. The Holding is a<space/><link><target>limited company</target></link>, dedicated to the commercial exploitation of scientific knowledge.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TUEHolding"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/de_universiteit/tue_holding_bv/<space/></arg><arg name="title">TU/e Holding B.V.<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Education</heading><heading level='3'>Departments</heading><paragraph>The scientific departments (or<space/><link><target>faculty (division)</target><part>faculties</part></link>; Dutch:<space/><italics>faculteiten</italics>) are the primary vehicles for teaching and research in the university. They employ the majority of the academic staff, are responsible for teaching and sponsor the research schools and institutions.</paragraph><paragraph>The vast majority of education is undergraduate education provided by the departments to students, who are adults with no other academic qualifications than a secondary education diploma. Some education is also provided to members of the postgraduate designer programs, but they are employed by the university and do not count as part of the student body.</paragraph><paragraph>Undergraduate education was given in four- or five-year programs until 2002, styled along the lines of the German system of education; graduates of these programs were granted an engineering title and allowed to prefix their name with the title<space/><italics>ir.</italics><space/>(an abbreviation of ingenieur; not to be confused with graduates of technical<space/><italics>hogescholen</italics>, who were engineers abbreviated<space/><italics>ing.</italics>). Starting in 2002, following the entry into force of the<space/><link><target>Bologna Process</target><part>Bologna Accords</part></link>, the university switched to the bachelor/master structure (students graduating in 2002 were given both an old-style engineering title and a new master's title). The undergraduate programs are now split into two programs each, a three-year bachelor program and a two-year master program. These programs are completely independent, in the sense that a bachelor can leave the university with his title and go to work, can enter a master's program at another university or continue on to the master's program of his department at the university. Of course bachelors from other universities can also enroll in the new master's programs.</paragraph><paragraph>The departments also offer Ph.D programs (Dutch:<space/><italics>promotiefase</italics>) whereby a qualified master may earn a Ph.D. Unlike in<space/><link><target>anglo-saxon</target></link><space/>countries these are not educational programs, however; rather, a person working towards promotion is a<space/><link><target>research assistant</target></link>, employed by the department, with teaching responsibilities in addition to his research work.</paragraph><paragraph>The TU/e has nine departments:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Biomedical Engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Architectural engineering</target><part>Department of the Built Environment</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electrical Engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Industrial Design</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chemical Engineering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Chemistry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Industrial Engineering</target></link><space/>&amp; Innovation Sciences (formerly<space/><link><target>Technology Management</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Applied Physics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mechanical Engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mathematics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Computer Science</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Honors programs</heading><paragraph>The university offers two honors programs for &quot;top students&quot;: students who have proven to have a knack for studying, have the capacity to handle a higher academic load and have an interest in more depth in their programs. There are two honors programs, both aimed at the bachelor students:<extension extension_name='ref' name="HorizonGeneral"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/diensten/daz/honors_program/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Honors program<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Honors Horizon</defkey><defval><space/>The Honors Horizon program (started in September 2006) is aimed at bachelor students who are interested in introducing a<space/><link><target>multidisciplinary</target></link><space/>component into their program. Honors Horizon is intended to &quot;expand students' horizon&quot;, by offering multidisciplinary honors classes, research activities and other activities that encourage academic well-roundedness. The Horizon project is an addition to the second and third years of the bachelor program.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HonorsHorizon"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/diensten/daz/honors_program/honors_horizon/#c115269<space/></arg><arg name="title">Honors Horizon program<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010</arg></template></extension></defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Honors Star</defkey><defval><space/>The Honors Star program (started in September 2010) is complementary to the Horizon program; where Horizon is multidisciplinary, Star is aimed at providing more depth within the program of the student's own department. Activities are still being fleshed out, but are expected to include more in-depth questions in exams and more practical projects. The Star program is an addition to the full duration of the bachelor program.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HonorsStar"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/diensten/daz/honors_program/honors_star/#c115268<space/></arg><arg name="title">Honors Star program<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010</arg></template></extension></defval></listitem></list><paragraph>Qualifying students can choose between the Honors programs, or follow both at the same time.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Shared minors</heading><paragraph>As of September 2010 the university offers bachelors in their third year a<space/><link><target>minor (Academic)</target><part>minor</part></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>sustainable energy</target></link>. This minor will focus on providing students with skills needed to work in the sustainable energy industry, or to start their own company in this industry. For that reason the minor is driven entirely by problems supplied by industry and knowledge institutes, which minor students must solve in multidisciplinary teams. In addition, students must come up with an innovative plan and develop a start-up company.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MinorSustainable"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nieuws:Onderwijs<space/></arg><arg name="periodical"><space/>Matrix, kwartaalblad van de Technische Universiteit Eindhoven<space/></arg><arg name="publication-place"><space/>Eindhoven<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eindhoven University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>17<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>Fall 2010<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>15<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>1380-247X<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Postgraduate designer programs</heading><paragraph>The university started a number of postgraduate designer programs together with the other Dutch technical universities in 1986. These programs are currently managed by the<space/><link><target>Stan Ackermans Institute</target></link><space/>on behalf of the<space/><link><target>3TU</target><part>3TU Federation</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SAI"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.3tu.nl/en/education/sai/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stan Ackermans Institute<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">3tu.nl<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-12-07<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension><space/>Each program is two years in length and graduates earn a<space/><link><target>Professional Doctorate in Engineering</target></link><space/>and may call themselves &quot;technical designers&quot;. There are a total of eleven program active, of which eight are available at the TU/e:<extension extension_name='ref' name="TUEPDEng"><link type='external' href='http://w3.tue.nl/en/services/cec/study_information/after_your_masters_degree/post_msc_designer_programs/'>Post MSc designer programs</link><space/>from the TU/e website</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>TU/e Post MSc designer programs:<list type='bullet'><listitem>Design and Technology of Instrumentation</listitem><listitem><link><target>Information technology</target><part>Information</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Communication technology</target><part>Communication Technology</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Logistics management</target><part>Logistics Management Systems</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Applied mathematics</target><part>Mathematics for Industry</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Process Design</target><part>Process</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Product design</target><part>Product Design</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Smart Energy Buildings &amp; Cities</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Software engineering</target><part>Software Technology</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>User System Interaction (USI)</target><part>User-System Interaction</part></link></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>The post-MSc program as a whole graduated its 3.000th technical designer (Dipl.-Eng. Sissy Papatheologou, PDEng) on 16 September 2010.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SAI3000"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/nieuws/artikel/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D</arg><arg name="title">TU's leveren 3000ste technologisch ontwerper af<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eindhoven University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Other educational programs</heading><paragraph>The university hosts a number of other educational programs that are in some way related to the main educational programs. These include the teacher's program and an MBA program.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Eindhoven School of Education</target></link>: Teacher's education for masters, to get their higher education teaching certificate. Also does research into educational sciences and innovation in education.</listitem><listitem><link><target>TIAS School for Business and Society</target></link>: A shared<space/><link><target>MBA</target></link><space/>program with the<space/><link><target>University of Tilburg</target></link>, for university graduates.</listitem><listitem>HBO minor program: Bachelor programs for students of HBO universities (four-year bachelor programs), to allow them access to university master programs.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Research</heading><paragraph>The TU/e does not only host research in its departments. The TU/e participates in a large number of research institutes which balance in different ways between pure science and applied science research. Some of these institutes are bound strictly to the university, others combine research across different universities. Some have even been designated to be of national importance.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Top in research partnerships with industry</heading><paragraph>The TU/e is among the worlds ten best-performing research universities in terms of research cooperation with industry in 2011 (Number 1 in 2009). Ten to 20 percent of the scientific publications of these ten universities in the period 20062008 were the result of partnerships with researchers in industry. As well as TU/e and Delft University of Technology, the top 10 also includes two universities in Japan (Tokyo Institute of Technology and Keio University in Tokyo), two in Sweden (CTH Chalmers University of Technology and KTH Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm), and one each in Denmark (DTU Technical University of Denmark in Lyngby), Finland (University of Helsinki), Norway (Norwegian University of Science and Technology in Trondheim) and the USA (Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, New York).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tue.nl/en/university/news-and-press/news/tue-among-world-top-in-research-partnerships-with-industry/<space/></arg><arg name="title">TU/e among world top in research partnerships with industry<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Tue.nl<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-03-08<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Research institutes</heading><table><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>ADEPT</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>A consortium of European research institutes that develops new concepts in electric propulsion for different types of vehicles. The TU/e coordinates the consortium, which also includes the<space/><link><target>University of Oxford</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Politecnico di Milano</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Technical University of Munich</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jaguar</target></link>/<link><target>Landrover</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>IHC Merwede</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ADEPTe"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tue.nl/universiteit/nieuws-en-pers/nieuws/03-10-2013-project-adept-van-start/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Consortium gaat nieuwe elektrische aandrijvingen ontwikkelen en specialisten opleiden<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 October 2013</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>BEST/e</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Institute of Biomedical Engineering Sciences &amp; Technology</target></link>/Eindhoven is the Eindhoven chapter of the BEST institute. BEST is dedicate to offering research and educational programs in the field of biomedical engineering.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BESTe"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.bmt.tue.nl/en/beste/mission_statement/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission statement<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 October 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>CWT/e</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Center for Wireless Technology Eindhoven</target></link><space/>is a research institute which combines the research of five different research groups of the department of Electrical Engineering. This research spans all forms of wireless technology and communication and includes research into<space/><link><target>electromagnetism</target></link>, mixed-signal microelectronics, signal processing systems and electro-optical communication<extension extension_name='ref' name="CWTe"><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.ele.tue.nl/fileadmin/ele/ELE_CWT_E/general/CWTe_brochure_A4_-_20091201.pdf Brochure of the CWT/e]</arg><arg>1.0Mb</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>ECIS</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Eindhoven Center for Innovation Studies</target></link><space/>is a research institute dedicated to the understanding of innovation processes. To this end the institute studies sources of innovation, the nature of innovation processes and the effects of those processes on society. The institute considers innovation to be a process of societal actors, so its research is multidisciplinary and spans technological as well as social studies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ECIS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ecis.ieis.tue.nl/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Welcome to ECIS!<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ECIS<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 October 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>EIRASS</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>European Institute of Retailing and Services Studies</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>ESI</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Eindhoven Embedded Systems Institute</target></link><space/>offers educational and research programs in the field of<space/><link><target>embedded systems</target></link>. It helps industrial partners with knowledge creation, knowledge valorization and product development.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EESI"><template><target>PDFlink</target><arg>[http://www.esi.nl/institute/flyers/ESI_company_profile_LR.pdf ESI General Introduction flyer|1.0Mb]</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>EURANDOM</target></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>European Institute for Statistics, Probability, Stochastic Operations Research and its Applications</target></link><space/>is an institute dedicated to fostering research in the stochastic sciences and their applications. To this end the institute actively attracts young talent for its research and doctoral programs, facilitates research and actively seeks European cooperation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Eurandom"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.eurandom.tue.nl/mission.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission statement<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eurandom<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 October 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>ICMS</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Institute for Complex Molecular Systems</target></link><space/>is a multidisciplinary research institute dedicated to building knowledge of complex molecular systems, as well as infrastructure for creating and studying such systems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ICMS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.icms.tue.nl/en/mission_and_goals/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission and Goals<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 October 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>ILI</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>The<space/><link><target>Intelligent Lighting Institute</target></link><space/>is a research institute started at the TU/e in 2010. It combines the research capacities of six different university departments in order to research and produce lighting-related products. The institute studies lighting technology, but also the interaction between lighting and the environment and the psychological impact of lighting.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ILI"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/en/institutes/intelligent_lighting_institute/profile/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Profile<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ILI (TU/e)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>TNO</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Netherlands Organisation for Applied Scientific Research</target></link><space/>(Eindhoven branch, housed on the university campus)</tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>&amp;nbsp;</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="margin-left:-0.75em"><tablerow><tablehead>Twinning</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>an incubator for technology startups (in conjunction with<space/><link><target>Brainport (Eindhoven)</target><part>Brainport</part></link>)</tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Technological Topinstitutes</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>Technological Topinstitute</target></link><space/>is a research institute that is a combined effort of different universities, commercial entities and the government. The Dutch government has identified a number of areas of research as &quot;key areas&quot; of vital, national interest and has commissioned a Top Institute for each of them. The TU/e hosts and manages two of them:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Technological Topinstitute</target><part>DPI</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Technological Topinstitute</target><part>M2i</part></link><space/>(formerly NIMR)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Research schools</heading><paragraph>The TU/e is commissioner and participant of a number of research schools:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Commissioner</tablehead><tablehead>Participant</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">J.F. Schouten School for User System Interaction</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>J.F. Schouten School for User System Interaction</target></link><space/>is a research institute of the TU/e dedicated to user interaction with man-made systems (including<space/><link><target>Human Computer Interaction</target></link>). The institute maintains research programs and provides a Ph.D program, with a mission to<space/><italics>develop and maintain a research program in the area of user-system interaction, and to offer an education program to PhD students who have entered the field</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JFSchouten"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.industrialdesign.tue.nl/jfschouten/organisation/organisation.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Organisation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">J.F. Schouten School<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">NIOK</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Netherlands Institute for Catalysis Research</target></link><space/>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Nederlands Instituut voor Onderzoek in de Katalyse</italics>) is a virtual research institute focused on<space/><link><target>catalysis</target></link>. The institute is virtual, meaning that it doesn't have any physical facilities of its own. Instead, it manages and coordinates the research activities of different catalysis groups at the participating universities. NIOK also provides Ph.D programs in the area of catalytic sciences. NIOK is managed from the<space/><link><target>University of Utrecht</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NIOK"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.niok.eu/en/introduction/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">NIOK<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">EIDMA</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Euler Institute for Discrete Mathematics and its Applications</target></link><space/>is a shared research institute of the Dutch technical universities. It was founded in 1994 in order to<space/><italics>promote and organize research programs on a large scale, to support and stimulate young research fellows and to be a natural helpdesk to turn to for solutions to discrete mathematical problems in industry</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EIDMA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.win.tue.nl/math/eidma/organization.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Organization<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EIDMA<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20090713032253/http://www.win.tue.nl/math/eidma/organization.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">13 July 2009<space/></arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">DISC</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Dutch Institute of Systems and Control</target></link><space/>is an inter-university research institute offering research and Ph.D programs in the area of<space/><link><target>control theory</target><part>systems and control theory</part></link>. DISC is a virtual institute with a board consisting of representatives of all participating universities and an external member, plus a scientific director who is chosen by rotation from the participating universities. The secretarial facilities are hosted by the<space/><link><target>Delft University of Technology</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="DISC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.disc.tudelft.nl/<space/></arg><arg name="title">DISC home<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">DISC<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="DISCStruct"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.disc.tudelft.nl/about-disc/structure.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">DISC structure<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">DISC<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">EPL</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><paragraph><link><target>Eindhoven Polymer Laboratories</target></link><space/>do research into polymers and polymer materials. The EPL is distinct from the<space/><link><target>Technological Topinstitute</target><part>Dutch Polymer Institute</part></link><space/>in that it has different focus areas, namely:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Complex Molecular Systems</listitem><listitem>Functional Polymers and Devices</listitem><listitem>Multi-scale Modeling and Advanced Characterization</listitem></list><paragraph>The EPL maintains long-term research programs into all these focus areas and offers Ph.D courses as well.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EPL"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.epl.nu/mission.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EPL<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">JMBC</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>J.M. Burgercentrum</target></link><space/>is the Dutch research centre into<space/><link><target>fluid dynamics</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JMBC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jmburgerscentrum.nl/organisation.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">JMBC<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">BETA</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Institute for Business Engineering and Technology Applications</target></link><space/>is a cross-university research school focusing on<space/><link><target>operations management</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>logistics</target></link>. Its main focus is on Ph.D education in all areas relating to these fields.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BETA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://beta.ieis.tue.nl/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Home<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BETA<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">OSPT</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Research School for Process Technology</target></link><space/>is a virtual, cross-university institute dedicated to strengthening the academic position of process technology in the Netherlands, through coordinated research and education. The key areas of coordinated research are physical transport phenomena, chemical reaction engineering, separation technology, process integration and development and the input of these disciplines in multi-disciplinary projects. The secretarial services of the virtual institute are hosted at the<space/><link><target>University of Twente</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OSPT"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ospt.tnw.utwente.nl/ospt4/?page_id</arg><arg name="title">Mission<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">OSPT<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">CPS</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Center for Plasma Physics and Radiation Technology</target></link><space/>is a joint research institute of five Dutch universities and research institutions into plasma physics and radiation technologies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CPS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.phys.tue.nl/cps/<space/></arg><arg name="title">CPS<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">DRSTP</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><paragraph><link><target>Dutch Research School of Theoretical Physics</target></link><space/>is a joint research institute of six universities and research organizations into the area of<space/><link><target>theoretical physics</target></link>. Its mission is<extension extension_name='ref' name="DRSTP"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www1.phys.uu.nl/drstp/Organization/Mission%20statement.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission statement<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">DRSTP<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>to implement a joint programme of graduate education in theoretical physics that draws upon a dynamic research environment;</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>to maintain and strengthen research in theoretical physics from a broad unifying perspective that exploits the interrelationships between different fields of theory;</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>to strengthen, both in research and graduate education, connections with experimental physics, and other disciplines such as mathematics, computational science, astrophysics, earth science, physical chemistry and the life sciences.</italics></listitem></list></extension></paragraph></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">IPA</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Institute for Programming Research and Algorithms</target></link><space/>is a cooperative research school involving university education, research and industry work. The IPA's main mission is to provide researches with education in the areas of programming research and algorithms. The institute provides Ph.D programs, does research into a number of key areas and assists industry partners in solving problems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="IPA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.win.tue.nl/ipa/about.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">About IPA<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">IPA<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">BOUW</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Research School Integral Design of Structures</target></link><space/>is a research institute that focuses on all aspects of building: building processes, structural and engineering design and so forth. It is hosted by the<space/><link><target>Delft University of Technology</target></link>, with a mission &quot;<italics>to generate deeper and broader scientific knowledge in structural design, structural engineering and building processes but also to disseminate that knowledge and stimulate its application</italics>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BOUW"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.osbouw.nl/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Research School Integral Design of Structures<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BOUW<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">EM</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Graduate School on Engineering Mechanics</target></link><space/>is a coordinating institute that coordinates research and education in engineering mechanics across the three Dutch technical universities. Its primary aims are to &quot;<italics>provide additional education and training for PhD students of the participating institutions and to foster scientific contacts and collaboration</italics>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EM"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.em.tue.nl/aboutem/<space/></arg><arg name="title">About the EM Graduate School<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EM<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><paragraph>|</paragraph><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">TRAIL</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>TRAIL Research School</target></link><space/>is a research institute dedicated to providing Ph.D programs and doing theoretical and applied research in the areas of mobility, transport, logistics, traffic, infrastructure and transport systems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRAIL"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rstrail.nl/<space/></arg><arg name="title">TRAIL Research School<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TRAIL<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">COBRA</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>Inter-University Research School on Communication Technologies Basic Research and Applications</target></link><space/>does research and industrial development of communication technologies and materials. It also provides Ph.D programs in these areas and knowledge transfer to industry.Its mission is to<space/><italics>excel in acquisition, transfer and application of knowledge in communication technology by doing high-quality research combined with offering a prestigious post-academic educational program for PhDs and PostDocs</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="COBRA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.ele.tue.nl/en/cobra/home<space/></arg><arg name="title">COBRA Research School<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">COBRA / TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">NETHUR</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><link><target>Netherlands Graduate School for Housing and Urban Research</target></link><space/>is a cross-university research and educational institute focusing on urban and regional development. It hosts Ph.D programs and research programs for joint research by Ph.D candidates and their supervisors. The institute is hosted by the<space/><link><target>University of Utrecht</target></link><space/>and has as its mission &quot;<italics>to promote and support urban and regional research of a high international scientific standard in the Netherlands</italics>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NETHUR"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nethur.nl/index.php?sid</arg><arg name="title">Scientific Mission<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">NETHUR<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">SIKS</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>School for Information and Knowledge Systems</target></link><space/>is a virtual research institute managed from the<space/><link><target>Delft University of Technology</target></link>, whose purpose is to coordinate the different research and educational activities among its participants in the area of<space/><link><target>knowledge systems</target></link>. The focus areas of SIKS include different types of<space/><link><target>information systems</target></link>,<space/><link><target>human-computer interaction</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Software agent</target><part>agent technologies</part></link>, computational intelligence and<space/><link><target>data management</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIKS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.siks.nl/mission_and_research.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission and Research Foci<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SIKS<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">Thomas Stieltjes Institute for Mathematics</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>Thomas Stieltjes Institute for Mathematics</target></link><space/>was a joint research institute of six Dutch universities and two mathematical institutes, which carried out research in the areas of<space/><link><target>Algebra</target></link><space/>&amp;<space/><link><target>Geometry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mathematical analysis</target><part>Analysis</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Stochastics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Operations research</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stieltjes"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.stieltjes.org/index.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">Home<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Thomas Stieltjes Institute<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>It has now become part of the<space/><link><target>WONDER</target></link>.</tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">CIPV</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>Center for Integrated Manufacturing and Development</target></link><space/>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Centrum voor Integrale Productievernieuwing</italics>) is a joint center focusing on product development. The center (which is hosted by the<space/><link><target>University of Twente</target></link>) participates in the development of individual products and spans all areas of the product development (including design, process planning, factory floor planning, operations management and handling, assembly, recycling, manufacturing systems, materials and more). Its mission is &quot;<italics>[t]he development and transfer of knowledge regarding the integrated approach of technical design and manufacturing of industrial products</italics>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CIPV"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cipv.utwente.nl/en/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">CIPV – Home<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CIPV<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20090906232303/http://www.cipv.utwente.nl:80/en/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">6 September 2009<space/></arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">Posthumus-Institute</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Posthumus-Institute</target></link><space/>is an interuniversity research institute for research and graduate training in economic and social history. The institute is hosted by the<space/><link><target>University of Leiden</target></link>; its mission is<extension extension_name='ref' name="PosthumusInstitute"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hum.leiden.edu/posthumus/about/mission-goals<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mission and Goals<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">N.W. Posthumus Institute<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>to promote innovative and advanced interdisciplinary research in economic and social history by stimulating joint research programs of the Dutch and Belgian universities and research institutes.</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>to provide graduate training in economic and social history across a broad front through programs on a national scale that meet international standards.</italics></listitem></list></extension></paragraph></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">LaQuSo</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>Laboratory for Quality Software</target></link><space/>is a cooperative effort of the Eindhoven University of Technology and the<space/><link><target>Radboud University of Nijmegen</target></link><space/>to develop and increase the understanding of software with respect to its quality. This is done by focusing on analysis tools and techniques and the industrialization, validation, and application of results of fundamental/strategic technological research. LaQuSo is also a research lab of the<space/><link><target>Netherlands Institute for Research on ICT</target></link><space/>and a center of excellence of the<space/><link><target>3TU</target><part>3TU Federation</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LaQuSo"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.laquso.com/about.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">About Us<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">LaQuSO<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><table class="collapsible collapsed" style="border:none"><tablerow><tablehead style="border:none">ICO</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none">The<space/><link><target>Inter-university Center for Educational Research</target></link><space/>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Interuniversitair Centrum voor Onderwijsonderzoek</italics>) is an inter-university research institute dedicated to the understanding of learning processes and development of instruction techniques. Originally founded to provide Ph.D programs in this area, it was later expanded to include research. The ICO is a cooperative effort of thirteen universities, including the Dutch<space/><link><target>Open University (Netherlands)</target><part>Open University</part></link><space/>(a &quot;virtual university&quot; for distance learning) and two Belgian universities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ICO"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ou.nl/eCache/DEF/1/90/985.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Research School ICO<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Open Universiteit<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2010</arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Off-campus activities</heading><paragraph>The TU/e plays a central role in the academic,<space/><link><target>economy</target><part>economic</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>society</target><part>social</part></link><space/>life of<space/><link><target>Eindhoven</target></link><space/>and the surrounding region. In addition the university maintains relations with institutions far beyond that region as well and participates in national and international events (sometimes through the student body).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Economic and research motor</heading><paragraph>The TU/e is enormously important to the economy of the<space/><link><target>Eindhoven</target></link><space/>region, as well as the wider areas of<space/><link><target>BrabantStad</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Samenwerkingsverband Regio Eindhoven</target></link>. It provides highly skilled labor for the local<space/><link><target>knowledge economy</target></link><space/>and is a knowledge and research partner for technology companies in the area.</paragraph><paragraph>The historic basis for the university's role as an economy and research motor was the interaction with<space/><link><target>Philips</target></link>. The university was founded primarily to address the need of Philips for local personnel with academic levels of education in<space/><link><target>electronics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chemistry</target></link><space/>and later<space/><link><target>computer science</target></link>. Later that interest spread to<space/><link><target>DAF Trucks</target><part>DAF</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Royal Dutch Shell</target></link><space/>(which became the primary employer for graduates of the chemistry department). There was also a synergy with these companies in that senior personnel were hired from them to form the academic staff of the university (which led to the Eindhoven joke that the university trains the engineers and Philips trains the professors).</paragraph><paragraph>Changing economic times and business strategies changed the relationship during the 1980s and 1990s. As Philips started moving away from the region, its importance to the region and the university decreased. A struggle for economic survival forced the university to seek closer ties with the city and region of Eindhoven in the 19891995 period, resulting in the creation of the<space/><link><target>Brainport (Eindhoven)</target><part>Brainport</part></link><space/>initiative to draw high tech business and industry to the region. The university started expending more effort in knowledge<space/><link><target>valorisation</target></link>, in incubating technology startups, in providing direct knowledge support for local technology companies. Also the academic interests of the research shifted with the times, with more effort going into energy efficiency research, green technologies, and other areas of interest driven by social relevance (the call for better technology in the medical field, for example, led to cooperation with the<space/><link><target>Catharina Hospital (Eindhoven)</target><part>Catharina Hospital</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>University of Maastricht</target></link><space/>medical department and finally the creation of the Biomedical Technology department).</paragraph><paragraph>The TU/e is host (and in some cases also commissioner) of a number of highly successful research schools, including the<space/><link><target>Eindhoven Embedded Systems Institute</target><part>ESI</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Dutch Polymer Institute</target><part>DPI</part></link>. These research institutes are a source of high-tech knowledge for high-tech companies in the area, such as<space/><link><target>ASML Holding</target><part>ASML</part></link>,<space/><link><target>NXP Semiconductors</target><part>NXP</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>FEI Company</target><part>FEI</part></link>. The university also plays a large role as knowledge and personnel supplier to other companies in the<space/><link><target>High Tech Campus Eindhoven</target></link><space/>and helps incubate startups through the Eindhoven<space/><link><target>Twinning Center</target></link>. It is also a knowledge supporter of the<space/><link><target>automotive</target></link><space/>industry in the<space/><link><target>Helmond</target></link><space/>region.</paragraph><paragraph>In the extended region, the TU/e is part of the backbone of the Eindhoven-Leuven-Aachen triangle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ELAt"><link type='external' href='http://www.elat.org'>ELAt.org</link><space/>The ELAt website</extension><space/>This economic cooperation agreement between three cities in three countries has created one of the most innovative regions in the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>(measured in terms of money invested in technology and knowledge economy); the agreement is based on the cooperative triangle that connects the three technical universities in those cities.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Eindhoven Energy Institute</heading><paragraph>As of the summer of 2010, the TU/e is host to the Eindhoven Energy Institute (EEI). The EEI is a virtual research institute (meaning that it doesn't have any actual offices or facilities), which manages and coordinates the activities of a large number of groups and subinstitutes in the general area of sustainable and alternative energy technologies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EEIOverview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/en/the_university/research/research_schools_and_institutes/eindhoven_energy_institute/this_is_eei/<space/></arg><arg name="title">This is EEI<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The scientific director of the institute is prof.dr.ir. David Smeulders. He is pro forma head of the research department, which is split into four key areas:<space/><italics>Built Environment</italics><space/>(energy usage and patterns in building, headed by prof.dr.ir. Jan Hensen from the Department of the Built Environment),<space/><italics>Future Fuels</italics><space/>(headed by prof.dr. Philip de Goey of Mechanical Engineering),<space/><italics>Energy Conversion</italics><space/>(headed by prof.dr.ir.<space/><link><target>Ren Janssen</target></link><space/>from Chemical Engineering) and<space/><italics>Fusion and Plasma</italics><space/>(headed by prof.dr. Niek Lopes Cardozo from Physics). The EEI also incorporates the Graduate School on Sustainable Energy, which the TU/e had already established together with the<space/><link><target>Technical University Munich</target><part>TU Munich</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Technical University of Denmark</target><part>DTU Lyngby</part></link>. Secretarial services will be provided by the Center Technology for Sustainable Development (TDO) which also already existed at the TU/e (since 1994).<extension extension_name='ref' name="MatrixEEI"><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.tue.nl/fileadmin/csc/matrix/matrix2010_2.pdf Matrix, the TU/e quarterly publication, summer edition 2010]</arg><arg>2.3Mb; p.4-7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Energy research at the TU/e is among the best in academic Europe (a February 2010 study by Reed Elsevier puts it second only to<space/><link><target>Imperial College London</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReedElsevierResearch"><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.tue.nl/fileadmin/nieuws_tue/2010/03/Q2226.SciVal.Spt.Alternative_Energy_ReportV3.pdf Alternative Energy Leadership Study]</arg><arg>1.6Mb</arg></template></extension><space/>This fact, as well as the unique attention to energy in the built-up environment, drew the attention of the<space/><link><target>European Institute of Innovation and Technology</target></link>. The EEI is now a full co-location of EIT's KIC on Sustainable Energy (InnoEnergy).<extension extension_name='ref' name="EEIOverview"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>International cooperation and appeal</heading><paragraph>The TU/e sets a lot of store by international contacts and cooperation. The university maintains active, academic cooperation with sister institutions in several different countries, for example:<extension extension_name='ref' name="TUESamenWerking"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://stuvo.tue.nl/scholieren/studeren-aan-de-tue/where-innovation-starts/samenwerking.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Samenwerking<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tue.nl/en/education/studying-at-tue/why-study-at-tue/inter-national-partnerships/<space/></arg><arg name="title">(Inter-)national partnerships<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Tue.nl<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-07-22<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>National University of Singapore</target></link>, Singapore</listitem><listitem><link><target>Zhejiang University</target></link>, China</listitem><listitem><link><target>Shanghai Jiao Tong University</target></link>, China</listitem><listitem><link><target>Fudan University</target></link>, China</listitem><listitem><link><target>Northeastern University (China)</target></link>, China</listitem><listitem><link><target>International Institute of Information Technology, Bangalore</target></link>, India</listitem><listitem><link><target>International Institute of Information Technology, Hyderabad</target></link>, India</listitem><listitem><link><target>Manipal Academy of Higher Education</target></link>, India</listitem><listitem><link><target>Georgia Institute of Technology</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>Northwestern University</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>Carnegie Mellon University</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>RMIT University</target></link>, Australia</listitem><listitem><link><target>Middle East Technical University</target></link>, Turkey</listitem><listitem><link><target>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</target></link>, Belgium</listitem></list><paragraph>The TU/e also provides education to an increasing number of foreign students and graduates. According to the 2009 annual report<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jaarverslag2009"><template><target>nl icon</target></template><space/><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.tue.nl/uploads/media/Jaarverslag2009.pdf Jaarverslag 2009]</arg><arg>799.5kb</arg></template></extension><space/>in the academic year 20082009 there were 490<space/><link><target>Student exchange program</target><part>exchange students</part></link>, 103 foreign nationals registered in a bachelor program, 430 in a master program, 158 in a professional doctorate program (79% of the total). In 2009 the university employed 37 foreign professors (15.9% of the total) and 16 foreign associate professors (12.8%). Overall, 29.5% of the university staff was non-Dutch.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2011/2012, the TU/e has Erasmus bilateral agreements with many universities in 30 countries across Europe in a diverse range of subjects for student exchange.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tue.nl/en/education/exchange-programs/erasmus-and-leonardo-program/partner-institutions/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Partner institutions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Tue.nl<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-02-23<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Technological sports</heading><paragraph>In addition to the &quot;regular&quot; types of sports practiced among the student body and by the staff, the TU/e collaborates with the student body in a number of &quot;technology sporting efforts&quot;. These usually take the form of cross-department projects, which makes them<space/><link><target>multidisciplinary</target></link><space/>efforts. Some examples include:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>Robot football</target></link></defkey><defval><space/>In 2010<space/><link><target>TechUnited</target></link>, the university's robot football team, won the European Championship,<extension extension_name='ref' name="TechUnitedEC2010"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.scientias.nl/tu-eindhoven-europees-kampioen-robotvoetbal/7561<space/></arg><arg name="title">TU Eindhoven Europees kampioen robotvoetbal<space/></arg><arg name="author">Tim Kraaijvanger<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">scientias.nl<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><space/>came second for the third time in a row at the world championship in Singapore and finally won the world championship in 2012.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TechUnitedWC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/nieuws/artikel/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D</arg><arg name="title">Tech United tweede op WK robotvoetbal<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 June 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU Eindhoven<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="TechUnitedWC2012"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nu.nl/tech/2842846/nederland-wereldkampioen-robotvoetbal.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Nederland wereldkampioen robotvoetbal<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Nu.nl<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 July 2012</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><space/>The team is part of the Mid-Size league of<space/><link><target>RoboCup</target></link>.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Auto racing</target></link></defkey><defval>The TU/e hosts and sponsors a student race team,<space/><link><target>University Racing Eindhoven</target></link><space/>(URE). This team competes annually in the<space/><link><target>Formula Student</target></link><space/>and other races with self-built racers. Starting in 2010 the team switched from a petrol engine to an electric car; this car came third at<space/><link><target>Silverstone Circuit</target><part>Silverstone</part></link>, second at<space/><link><target>Hockenheim</target></link><space/>and won the Formula Student in its first year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="URE"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/nieuws/artikel/?tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D</arg><arg name="title">University Racing Eindhoven rijdt naar eerste plek in Oostenrijk<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 August 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><space/>The university also entered a car named<space/><italics>Stella</italics><space/>into the<space/><link><target>World Solar Challenge#2013</target><part>World Solar Challenge in 2013</part></link>, winning the Cruiser class race.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stella2013"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.tue.nl/onderzoek/strategic-area-energy/over-energy/energy-events/2014-solar-plus/stella/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stella<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">25 January 2015</arg></template></extension></defval></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Student organizations and facilities</heading><paragraph>The university offers many different facilities for its student body and hosts many different student organizations<extension extension_name='ref' name="TU Eindhoven Student/Study/Sport/Culture/International associations"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.tue.nl/nl/navigatie/portals/studentenverenigingen/</arg><arg name="title">TU Eindhoven associations for students</arg><arg name="publisher">TU Eindhoven</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-09-19</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension><space/>on campus as well.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Student and study associations</heading><paragraph>There are two main types of student clubs at Dutch universities: student associations (Dutch:<space/><italics>studentenvereniging</italics>) and study associations (Dutch:<space/><italics>studievereninging</italics>). The first are somewhat analogous to<space/><link><target>fraternity</target><part>fraternities</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sorority</target><part>sororities</part></link><space/>in the United States, except that they tend to be<space/><link><target>coed</target></link>. The second are linked to the departments and educational programs.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Study associations</heading><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Department</tablehead><tablehead>Study association</tablehead><tablehead>Alumni association</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Biomedical Engineering</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Protagoras (study association)</target><part>Protagoras</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Willem Einthoven</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Architectural engineering</target><part>Built Environment</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Cheops (study association)</target><part>Cheops</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>VEBI</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Electrical Engineering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Automotive</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Thor (study association)</target><part>Thor</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>EDUNA</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Industrial Design</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Lucid (study association)</target><part>Lucid</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Not yet incorporated</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Chemical Engineering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Chemistry</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>T.S.V. 'Jan Pieter Minckelers'</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>VSI</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Industrial Engineering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Innovation Sciences</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Intermate (study association)</target><part>Intermate</part></link>/<link><target>Industria (study association)</target><part>Industria</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>VBI/ITEM</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Applied Physics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link type='external' href='http://www.vdwaals.nl/'>SVTN &quot;J.D. van der Waals&quot;</link></tablecell><tablecell><link type='external' href='http://www.veni.nl/'>VENI</link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Mechanical Engineering</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>W.S.V. Simon Stevin</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>WIE/ASE/Schoone Leij</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Mathematics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Computer Science</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>s.v. GEWIS</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>WIRE/VIE</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='4'>Student associations</heading><paragraph>There are three main student associations associated with the TU/e, plus a number of independent clubs:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Student associations:<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Eindhovense Studentenvereniging Demos</target><part>E.S.V. Demos</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Eindhovens Studenten Corps</target><part>ESC</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>General Student Society SSRE</target><part>SSRE</part></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Disputes<list type='bullet'><listitem>Onafhankelijk Heerendispuut Camelot Excalibur</listitem><listitem>Heerendispuut Dignitates</listitem><listitem>Rhetoricadispuut TAU<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dispuuttau.nl/</arg><arg name="title">Rhetoricadispuut Tau - Eindhoven - MCMXCVI</arg><arg name="work">Rhetoricadispuut Tau</arg></template></extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Other<list type='bullet'><listitem>l'Attaque Attique</listitem><listitem>Borrelgenootschap Nargileh</listitem><listitem>C.T.D. Kekul</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Culture, international association and spirituality</heading><paragraph>There are several associations, clubs and circles associated with the TU/e, which are meant to help students and staff develop themselves in non-academic areas. Such areas include cultural development, building international contacts and investigating spiritual beliefs.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Cultural activities</heading><paragraph>The following associations organize activities with cultural or social/societal relevance:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Bigband Studentproof</defkey><defval><space/>A<space/><link><target>big band</target></link><space/>consisting of university students.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Cultuurcentrum.nl</defkey><defval><space/>Organizes courses on dance, music, theater and so on.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>ESDV Footloose</defkey><defval><space/>Student dance association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>ESTV Doppio</defkey><defval><space/>Student theatre association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>ESFF Dekate Mousa</defkey><defval><space/>Film and photography association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>ESMG Quadrivium</defkey><defval>Student classical music ensemble</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>ESRG Knights of the Kitchen Table</defkey><defval><space/>Board game and role play</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>JCES Kinjin</defkey><defval><space/>Japanese culture association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>La Tunia</defkey><defval><space/>The<space/><link><target>tuna (music)</target><part>tuna</part></link><space/>for female students</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Studium Generale</target></link></defkey><defval><space/>Group that organizes lectures, expositions, outings and other activities</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Tuna Ciudad de Luz</defkey><defval><space/>The university<space/><link><target>tuna (music)</target><part>tuna</part></link>.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Virus festival</target></link></defkey><defval>The organization of the cultural festival that is open for all students, staff and all other comers</defval></listitem></list><heading level='4'>International associations</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>AEGEE</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>AIESEC</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European BEST Engineering Competition</target><part>BEST</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>ESTIEM</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European Week Eindhoven</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>IEEE</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Erasmus Student Network</target><part>International Student Network Eindhoven</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>TU/e African Students Union</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Spirituality and philosophy</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>4u2 Int. Studenten Groep Eindhoven</defkey><defval>Christian student group</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Emt Qenee (C.S.F.R.)</defkey><defval>Bible study group</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Humanistisch Studentenraadswerk</defkey><defval><space/>Humanist organization</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Ichthus</defkey><defval>Eindhoven Christian student association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Mosaic</defkey><defval>Multicultural student union</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>TINT</defkey><defval>oecumenical association</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>VGSEi</defkey><defval>Eindhoven reformed student association</defval></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Sport associations</heading><paragraph>There are many sports associations within the university. They are overseen by the general sports council ESSF.</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Association</tablehead><tablehead>Sport</tablehead><tablehead>Association</tablehead><tablehead>Sport</tablehead><tablehead>Association</tablehead><tablehead>Sport</tablehead><tablehead>Association</tablehead><tablehead>Sport</tablehead><tablehead>Association</tablehead><tablehead>Sport</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>ESAC</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Mountain climbing</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Asterix</tablecell><tablecell>Athletics</tablecell><tablecell>Panache</tablecell><tablecell>Badminton</tablecell><tablecell>Tantalus</tablecell><tablecell>Basketball</tablecell><tablecell>Samourais</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Bud</target><part>Budo</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Vertigo</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Frisbee</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>De Club</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Golf</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Oktopus</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Team handball</target><part>Handball</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Da Vinci</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Archery</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Concorde</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Horseback riding</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Ice Hawks</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Ice hockey</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Okawa</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Canoeing</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Attila</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Korfball</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>All Terrain</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Outdoor activity</target><part>Outdoorsport</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Thta</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Rowing (sport)</target><part>Rowing</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Hoc Habet</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Fencing</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Avalanche Boarders</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Snow boarding</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Quatsh</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Squash (sport)</target><part>Squash</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Ilyeo</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Taekwondo</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>TAVERES</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Table tennis</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Suca</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Gymnastics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Pusphaira</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Association football</target><part>Football</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Hajraa</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Volleyball</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Nayade</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Water polo</target></link>/<link><target>Swimming (sport)</target><part>swimming</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Weth</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Windsurfing</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Boreas</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Sailing (sport)</target><part>Sailing</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>ZES</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Gliding</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Impulso</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Capoeira</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Blub</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Diving</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Don Quishoot</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Field hockey</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>THE Studs</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Baseball</target></link>/<link><target>softball</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>The Elephants</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Rugby football</target><part>Rugby</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Isis</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Ice skating</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Fellenoord</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tennis</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Squadra Veloce</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Bicycle racing</target><part>Cycling</part></link>/<link><target>triathlon</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Qi Dao</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Wushu (sport)</target><part>Wushu</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Totelos</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Indoor soccer</target><part>Indoor football</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Screaming Eagles</tablecell><tablecell>Men's<space/><link><target>lacrosse</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Screaming Unicorns</tablecell><tablecell>Women's lacrosse</tablecell><tablecell>		Blue</tablecell><tablecell>Pole Fitness</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Service organizations</heading><paragraph>There university is more than just the departments, research bodies and the students. There are several ancillary activities necessary to the running of the university, activities that cross the boundaries and interests of the different departments. These activities are carried out by the universities' service organizations.</paragraph><paragraph>The university has the following service organizations:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Organization</tablehead><tablehead>Full name</tablehead><tablehead>Purpose</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">DAZ</tablecell><tablecell style="width:250px; vertical-align:top;">General Affairs Service<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst Algemene Zaken</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Organizational and secretarial functions for varied activities, the alumni organization and the Student Sport Center</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">CEC</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Communications Expertise Center<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Communicatie Expertise Centrum</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Responsible for all university communications and announcements, including interacting with the<space/><link><target>news media</target><part>press</part></link><space/>and communications regarding external billing and payments. CEC also handles the printing and distribution of university brochures and guards the uniform application of the university's house style.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">DPO</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Human Resources Management<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst Personeel en Organisatie</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">All<space/><link><target>Human resources</target><part>HR-related</part></link><space/>activities, from vacancies and pension plans to regulations about health and workplace safety, to the bicycle plan (a tax break for personnel to buy a bicycle).</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">DFEZ</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Financial and Economic Services<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst Financile en Economische Zaken</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">University finances.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">DH</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Housing service<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst Huisvesting</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Management of all real estate belonging university</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">ICT</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">ICT Service<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst ICT</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Management of university computers and student laptops, networks, network security, shared storage facilities, university<space/><link><target>Sharepoint</target></link><space/>sites, plus codes of conduct relating to those systems</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">IEC</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Information Expertise Center<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Informatie Expertise Centrum</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">The university library (both physical and digital).</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">DIZ</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Internal Affairs Service<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Dienst Interne Zaken</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Internal services, such as the BedrijfsHulpVerlening (Emergency Assistance for catastrophes like fires, heart attacks and so on), Logistics, Purchasing and Contract Management.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">STU</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Student Service Center<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Onderwijs en Studenten Service Centrum</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Student services (admission and registries, information for highschool students and other, future students, laptop service, et cetera).</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">GTD</tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Common Technical Service<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><xhtml:small>(Dutch:<space/><italics>Gemeenschappelijke Technische Dienst</italics>)</xhtml:small></tablecell><tablecell valign="top">Provides technical services to departments (e.g. building of experiments, bespoke machinery, prototypes, specialized software).</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Distinguished alumni</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camiel Eurlings.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Camiel Eurlings</target></link></part></link><link><target>Image:Jan Dietz portret.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Jan Dietz</target></link></part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Wil van der Aalst</target></link>, Dutch<space/><link><target>Computer scientist</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wiel Arets</target></link>, Dutch architect</listitem><listitem><link><target>Michiel Boersma</target></link>, former chairman of the board at<space/><link><target>Essent</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jo Coenen</target></link>, Dutch architect and former<space/><link><target>Chief Architect of the Netherlands</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Frank van Dalen</target></link>, chairman<space/><link><target>COC Nederland</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Martijn van Dam</target></link>, member of the<space/><link><target>House of Representatives of the Netherlands</target><part>House of Representatives</part></link><space/>(<link><target>List of members of the House of Representatives of the Netherlands (20062010)</target><part>20062010</part></link>,<space/><link><target>List of members of the House of Representatives of the Netherlands (2010present)</target><part>2010present</part></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Marijn Dekkers</target></link>, Chairman of the Board of Management of<space/><link><target>Bayer AG</target></link><space/>(per 1 October 2010)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jan Dietz</target></link>, Dutch computer scientist</listitem><listitem><link><target>Teun van Dijck</target></link>, member of the<space/><link><target>House of Representatives of the Netherlands</target><part>House of Representatives</part></link><space/>(<link><target>List of members of the House of Representatives of the Netherlands (20062010)</target><part>20062010</part></link>,<space/><link><target>List of members of the House of Representatives of the Netherlands (2010present)</target><part>2010present</part></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Camiel Eurlings</target></link>, Dutch Minister of<space/><link><target>Ministry of Transport, Public Works and Water Management (Netherlands)</target><part>Transport, Public Works and Water Management</part></link><space/>since 2006</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gerard Kleisterlee</target></link>, Chairman of<space/><link><target>Vodafone</target></link><space/>and a former President and Chief Executive Officer of Royal<space/><link><target>Philips</target></link><space/>Electronics</listitem><listitem><link><target>Betje Koolhaas</target></link>, actor</listitem><listitem><link><target>John Krmeling</target></link>, artist and architect</listitem><listitem><link><target>Arno Kuijlaars</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mathematician</target></link>, professor at the<space/><link><target>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Karel Luyben</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chemical engineering</target><part>chemical engineer</part></link>, professor of bioprocess technology,<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Delft University of Technology</target></link><space/>per 1 January 2010</listitem><listitem><link><target>G.M. Nijssen</target></link>, Dutch computer scientist</listitem><listitem><link><target>Harry Otten</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link>, founder and first director of<space/><link><target>Meteo Consult</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kees A. Schouhamer Immink</target><part>Kees Schouhamer Immink</part></link>, scientist and president Turing Machines Inc, co-inventor of the compact disc</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sjoerd Soeters</target></link>, architect</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ren van Zuuk</target></link>, Dutch architect</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Distinguished and otherwise notable faculty</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Edsger Wybe Dijkstra.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Edsger W. Dijkstra</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:AWUitje085.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Harry Lintsen</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Wietse Venema.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Wietse Venema</target></link></part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Riek Bakker</target></link>,<space/><link><target>city planner</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Annelies van Bronswijk</target></link>, winner<space/><link><target>Ig Nobelprize</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nicolaas Govert de Bruijn</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mathematician</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Henk Buck</target></link>, professor of<space/><link><target>chemistry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jo Coenen</target></link>, Dutch architect and former<space/><link><target>Chief Architect of the Netherlands</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Henk Dorgelo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link><space/>and first<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Edsger W. Dijkstra</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mathematician</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>computer science</target><part>computer scientist</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Helga Fassbinder</target></link>,<space/><link><target>urban planning</target><part>urban planner</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hugo Christiaan Hamaker</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hubert-Jan Henket</target></link>, architect</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alexandre Horowitz</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mechanical engineering</target><part>mechanical engineer</part></link>; inventor of the<space/><link><target>Philishave</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Niek Lopes Cardozo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link>, member of the Board of Governors of<space/><link><target>FOM Fachhochschule fuer Oekonomie und Management</target><part>FOM</part></link>, head of the Fusion Research Division at FOM Rijnhuizen, Rijnhuizen representative at the<space/><link><target>ITER</target></link><space/>project</listitem><listitem><link><target>Arie Andries Kruithof</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link>, discovered the<space/><link><target>Kruithofeffect</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kruithofcurve</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jean Leering</target></link>, architect, director of the<space/><link><target>Van Abbemuseum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Piet Lemstra</target></link>, inventor of the<space/><link><target>Dyneema</target></link><space/>fibre</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jack van Lint</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mathematician</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Harry Lintsen</target></link>, historian in technology history, former chairman<space/><link><target>Foundation for the History of Technology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Archer Martin</target></link>, Fellow of the Royal Society, 1952<space/><link><target>Nobel Prize in Chemistry</target><part>Nobel laureate in chemistry</part></link><space/>(professor TU/e 19641974)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bert Meijer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chemical engineering</target><part>chemical engineer</part></link>, pioneer in polymer research</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sjoerd Romme</target></link>, professor of Entrepreneurship &amp; Innovation</listitem><listitem><link><target>Rutger van Santen</target></link>, 1997<space/><link><target>Spinozapremie</target></link>, former<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link>, 2005 KNAW-professor, 2008 Fellow of the<space/><link><target>National Academy of Engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Johan Schot</target></link>, historian, professor of technology history</listitem><listitem><link><target>Piet Steenkamp</target></link>, lawyer, co-founder of the<space/><link><target>Christen-Democratisch Appl</target><part>CDA</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Martinus Tels</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chemical engineering</target><part>chemical engineer</part></link>,<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link>, pioneer of waste management processes in the Netherlands</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ton van Trier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>rector magnificus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ministry of Education, Culture and Science (Netherlands)</target><part>Minister of Education</part></link><space/>in the cabinet<space/><link><target>Netherlands cabinet Van Agt-1</target><part>Van Agt-I</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wietse Venema</target></link>,<space/><link><target>programmer</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Notable honors for research done at the university</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>prof. dr. ir.<link><target>Ren de Borst</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Spinozapremie</target></link><space/>(1999)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Spinoza1995-2000"><template><target>nl icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nwo.nl/nwohome.nsf/pages/NWOP_865AY4'>Spinozawinnaars 19952000</link></extension></listitem><listitem>prof. dr.<space/><link><target>Bert Meijer</target></link>:<space/><link><target>KNCV</target></link><space/>Gold Medal (1993),<space/><link><target>Arthur K. Doolittle Award</target></link><space/>(1995),<space/><link><target>Spinozapremie</target></link><space/>(2001),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Spinoza2001Verder"><template><target>nl icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nwo.nl/nwohome.nsf/pages/NWOP_87MF8R'>Spinozawinnaars vanaf 2001</link></extension><space/>Wheland Medal 2010/2011<extension extension_name='ref' name="MatrixBMWheland"><template><target>PDFLink</target><arg>[http://w3.tue.nl/fileadmin/csc/matrix/matrix2010_2.pdf Matrix, the TU/e quarterly publication, summer edition 2010]</arg><arg>2.3Mb; p.54</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>prof. dr.<space/><link><target>Philip de Goey</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Simon Stevin Master</target><part>Simon Stevin Master 2010</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="SSTevin2010"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://w3.wtb.tue.nl/en/research/research_groups/combustion_technology/news_combustion_technology/news_article/?tx_ttnews[tt_news]</arg><arg name="title">Prof. De Goey becomes "Simon Stevin Meester" 2010<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 March 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">TU/e<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2010</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>prof.dr.ir.<space/><link><target>Ren Janssen</target></link>: KIvI/NIRIA Speurwerkprijs 2010,<space/><link><target>Spinoza Prize</target><part>Spinozapremie</part></link><space/>(2015)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nwo.nl/actueel/nieuws/2015/nwo-spinozapremies-voor-rene-janssen-birgit-meyer-aad-van-der-vaart-en-cisca-wijmenga.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">NWO-Spinozapremies voor René Janssen, Birgit Meyer, Aad van der Vaart en Cisca Wijmenga<space/></arg><arg name="language">Dutch<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 June 2015<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">12 June 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>prof. dr.ir.<space/><link><target>Arthur van Roermund</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Simon Stevin Master</target><part>Simon Stevin Master 2004</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="SSTevin2004"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.stw.nl/Nieuws/20040830.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Uitreiking Simon Stevin Meesterschap; Simon Stevin Meester zet half miljoen in voor intelligente elektronica<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 August 2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">{{Ill|nl|Technologiestichting STW}}<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>prof. dr.<space/><link><target>Rutger van Santen</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Spinozapremie</target></link><space/>(1997)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Spinoza1995-2000"></extension></listitem><listitem>prof. dr.ir.<space/><link><target>Jaap Schouten</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Simon Stevin Master</target><part>Simon Stevin Master 2006</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="SSTevin2006"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.stw.nl/Nieuws/20061012.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Uitreiking Simon Stevin Meesterschap 2006; Half miljoen voor slimme procestechnologie<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 October 2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Technologiestichting STW<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 September 2010</arg><arg name="language">nl</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Spinoffs</heading><paragraph>Over the years several spin off companies have been started by TU/e graduates, based on some research done at the university. Examples include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>B-Invented:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.b-invented.com/</arg><arg name="title">Bouwen aan nieuwe perspectieven - B-invented</arg><arg name="work">b-invented.com</arg></template></extension><space/>green innovations in<space/><link><target>building materials</target></link></listitem><listitem>Dolphys Medical:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dolphys.com/</arg><arg name="title">Dolphys</arg><arg name="work">dolphys.com</arg></template></extension><space/>medical devices</listitem><listitem>EmulTech:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.emultech.nl/</arg><arg name="title">EmulTech</arg><arg name="work">emultech.nl</arg></template></extension><space/>technology for precision delivery of medicines</listitem><listitem>Fistuca:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fistuca.com/</arg><arg name="title">Fistuca</arg><arg name="work">fistuca.com</arg></template></extension><space/>Construction equipment engineering</listitem><listitem>Flowid:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flowid.nl/</arg><arg name="title">Home - Flowid</arg><arg name="work">Flowid</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>microreactor</target></link><space/>expertise for<space/><link><target>chemistry</target><part>chemical</part></link><space/>analysis</listitem><listitem>Fluxicon:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fluxicon.com</arg><arg name="title">Process Mining and Process Analysis - Fluxicon</arg><arg name="work">fluxicon.com</arg></template></extension><space/>process mining technology</listitem><listitem>Ioniqa:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ioniqa.com</arg><arg name="title">Ioniqa Technologies Eindhoven, Ferrofluid, PET Recycling, Ionic Liquids</arg><arg name="work">ioniqa.com</arg></template></extension><space/>smart magnetic materials.</listitem><listitem>Novameer:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.novameer.com/</arg><arg name="title">Domeinregistratie - Theiner</arg><arg name="work">Theiner</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>polymer</target></link><space/><link><target>Composite material</target><part>composite</part></link><space/>panels and fabrics (e.g. for bulletproof doors)</listitem><listitem>OptiMal Forming Solutions:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.optimalforming.nl</extension><space/>thermoplastic forming moulds</listitem><listitem>Progression Industry<extension extension_name='ref'><list type='ident'><listitem>http://www.progression-industry.com/</listitem></list></extension><space/>green<space/><link><target>automotive</target></link><space/>technologies</listitem><listitem>QTIS:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.qtis.nl/</arg><arg name="title">Home - Xeltis</arg><arg name="work">Xeltis</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>cardiovascular</target></link><space/>tissue engineering</listitem><listitem>SlimRenoveren:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.slimrenoveren.nl/welkom/index.php</arg><arg name="title">SlimRenoveren - Advies en Productontwikkeling voor Renovatie en Onderhoud</arg><arg name="work">slimrenoveren.nl</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>home improvement</target></link><space/>expertise</listitem><listitem>Sorama:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sorama.eu/</arg><arg name="title">Sorama - sound solutions</arg><arg name="work">sorama.eu</arg></template></extension><space/>sound and vibration visualization</listitem><listitem>SPINID:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.spinid.nl</arg><arg name="title">Home - Flowid</arg><arg name="work">Flowid</arg></template></extension><space/>Designs and engineers chemical reactors and separators based on a spinning disc technology developed at the TU/e.</listitem><listitem>Studio:Ludens:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.studioludens.com/</arg><arg name="title">studio:ludens - design tools for creatives</arg><arg name="work">studioludens.com</arg></template></extension><space/>Pattern Design</listitem><listitem>UXsuite:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.uxsuite.com</arg><arg name="title">Measure, control and improve experiences of your users… in real-time!</arg><arg name="work">uxsuite.com</arg></template></extension><space/>product usage mapping software</listitem><listitem>Vabrema:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.vabrema.com</extension><space/>knowledge and technologies for<space/><link><target>cell culture</target></link><space/>manipulation</listitem></list><heading level='2'>International acclaim</heading><paragraph>On the 2009<space/><link><target>THEQS World University Rankings</target></link><space/>(From 2010 two separate rankings will be produced by the<space/><link><target>Times Higher Education World University Rankings</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>QS World University Rankings</target></link>)list, the Eindhoven University of Technology was ranked inside the top 200 for the fifth consecutive year. An overview of the 20052009 rankings can be seen below. In 2010 the<space/><link><target>QS World University Rankings</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2010/results</arg><arg name="title">QS World University Rankings 2010 Results</arg></template></extension><space/>ranked the university 126th in the world. On the<space/><link><target>Times Higher Education</target></link><space/>ranking of 2010<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html#uni-906</arg><arg name="title">Times Higher Education Ranking 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Eindhoven University of Technology is the highest ranked (#114) University of the Netherlands. They are followed by<space/><link><target>Leiden University</target></link><space/>(#124).</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Year</tablehead><tablehead>THE Ranking (Change)</tablehead><tablehead>QS Ranking (Change)</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2005</tablecell><tablecell>70</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2006</tablecell><tablecell>67 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>3)</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2007</tablecell><tablecell>130 (<template><target>decrease</target></template><space/>63)</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2008</tablecell><tablecell>128 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>2)</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2009</tablecell><tablecell>120 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>8)</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2010</tablecell><tablecell>114 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>6)</tablecell><tablecell>126</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2010-11</tablecell><tablecell>115 (<template><target>decrease</target></template><space/>1)</tablecell><tablecell>146 (<template><target>decrease</target></template><space/>20)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2012-13</tablecell><tablecell>114 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>1)</tablecell><tablecell>158 (<template><target>decrease</target></template><space/>12)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2013-14</tablecell><tablecell>106 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>8)</tablecell><tablecell>157 (<template><target>increase</target></template><space/>1)</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>In a 2003 European Commission report, TU/e was ranked as third among European research universities (after Cambridge and Oxford, at equality with TU Munich and thus making it the highest ranked Technical University in Europe), based on the impact of its scientific researches.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">ftp://ftp.cordis.europa.eu/pub/indicators/docs/3rd_report_snaps10.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">ftp.cordis.europa.eu<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-04</arg></template></extension>In 2011 Academic Ranking of World Universities (ARWU) rankings,<extension extension_name='ref' name="shanghairanking.com"></extension><space/>TU/e was placed at the 52-75 bucket internationally in Engineering/Technology and Computer Science ( ENG ) category and at 34th place internationally in the Computer Science subject field.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>DevLab (research alliance)</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Technologist (magazine)</target><part>Technologist</part></link></italics>, magazine published by<space/><link><target>Eurotech Universities</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Technische Universiteit Eindhoven</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Official website</target><arg>http://www.tue.nl</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://w3.tue.nl/en/departments/'>Departments at TU/e</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://w3.tue.nl/nl/navigatie/portals/studentenverenigingen/'>List of student societies (dutch)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mastersportal.eu/students/browse/university/1/eindhoven-university-of-technology.html'>All Masters at TU/e</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tiasnimbas.edu'>TiasNimbas, the business school of Eindhoven University of Technology and Tilburg University</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ecis.ieis.tue.nl/'>ECIS (Eindhoven Centre for Innovation Studies)</link><space/>a research centre based at the School of Innovation Sciences at TU/e</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Dutch universities</target></template><template><target>Santander Network</target></template><template><target>CESAER</target></template><template><target>Networks of European universities</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Eindhoven University Of Technology</target></template><link><target>Category:Eindhoven University of Technology</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Educational institutions established in 1956</target></link><link><target>Category:Technical universities and colleges</target></link><link><target>Category:Universities in the Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:Science and technology in the Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:1956 establishments in the Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:Buildings and structures in Eindhoven</target></link><link><target>Category:Education in Eindhoven</target></link></paragraph></article>