<article title='Flag_of_Denmark'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox National flag</target><arg name="Name"><space/>Denmark
</arg><arg name="Type">
</arg><arg name="Image"><space/>Flag of Denmark.svg
</arg><arg name="Nickname"><space/>'''Dannebrog'''
</arg><arg name="Morenicks">
</arg><arg name="Use"><space/>100100
</arg><arg name="Proportion"><space/>28:34 to 28:37
</arg><arg name="Adoption"><space/>Versions in use since at least c. 1400;<ref>Inge Adriansen, ''Nationale symboler'', Museum Tusculanum Press, 2003, p. 129: "Fra begyndelsen af 1400-tallet kan Dannebrog med sikkerhed dokumenteres som rigsflag, det vil sige statsmagtens og kongens flag" (English: "Dannebrog can with certainty be documented as flag of the [[Reich|realm]], that is the flag of the authority of state and the of the king, from the beginning of the 1400s")</ref><space/>official design for civil ensign adopted 1748 (slightly greater length tolerated since 1893); private use on land sanctioned 1854.</arg><arg name="Design"><space/>A red field charged with a white cross extending to the edges; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side. Dimensions: 3:1:3 width / 3:1:4.5 to 3:1:5.25 length.
</arg><arg name="Designer">
</arg><arg name="Image2">Flag of Denmark (state).svg 
</arg><arg name="Noborder2"><space/>yes
</arg><arg name="Use2"><space/>010010
</arg><arg name="Proportion2"><space/>56:107
</arg><arg name="Symbol2"><space/>{{FIAV|normal}}
</arg></template><link><target>File:Dannebrog 3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=A Danish flag flies from a flagpole against the sky.</part><part>Dannebrog in flight.</part></link>The<space/><bold>Flag of<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link></bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-da</target><arg>'''Dannebrog'''</arg></template><space/><template><target>IPA-da</target><arg>ˈdanəˌbʁoˀ</arg><arg>-</arg><arg></arg></template>) is red with a white<space/><link><target>Nordic Cross Flag</target><part>Scandinavian cross</part></link><space/>that extends to the edges of the flag; the vertical part of the cross is shifted to the hoist side. The<space/><link><target>Christian cross</target><part>cross</part></link><space/>design, which represents<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeroen Temperman"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="author">Jeroen Temperman</arg><arg name="title">State Religion Relationships and Human Rights Law</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Martinus Nijhoff Publishers]]</arg><arg name="quote">Many predominantly Christian states show a cross, symbolising Christainity, on their national flag. Scandinavian crosses or Nordic crosses on the flags of the Nordic countries–Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway and Sweden–also represent Christianity.</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-12-31</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrew Evans"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="author">Andrew Evans</arg><arg name="title">Iceland</arg><arg name="publisher">Bradt</arg><arg name="quote">Legend states that a red cloth with the white cross simply fell from the sky in the middle of the 13th-century Battle of Valdemar, after which the Danes were victorious. As a badge of divine right, Denmark flew its cross in the other Scandinavian countries it ruled and as each nation gained independence, they incorporated the Christian symbol.</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-12-31</arg></template></extension><space/>was subsequently adopted by other<space/><link><target>Nordic countries</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Flag of Sweden</target><part>Sweden</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Flag of Norway</target><part>Norway</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Flag of Finland</target><part>Finland</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Flag of Iceland</target><part>Iceland</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Flag of the Faroe Islands</target><part>Faroe Islands</part></link>, as well as the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>British</part></link><space/>archipelagos of<space/><link><target>Flag of Shetland</target><part>Shetland</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Flag of Orkney</target><part>Orkney</part></link>. During the<space/><link><target>Denmark-Norway</target><part>Danish-Norwegian</part></link><space/>personal union, Dannebrog (&quot;Danish cloth&quot;) was also the flag of Norway and continued to be, with slight modifications, until Norway adopted<space/><link><target>Flag of Norway</target><part>its current flag</part></link><space/>in 1821.</paragraph><paragraph>The design of the Dannebrog is recorded on a seal from 1397.<extension extension_name='ref'>Swedish Encyclopedia &quot;National Encyclopedin&quot;, &quot;NE2000&quot;,digital version, article &quot;Dannebrogen&quot;</extension><space/>According to legend, the flag came into Danish possession during the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lyndanisse</target></link><space/>in 1219. The Danes were on a failing crusade in<space/><link><target>Estonia</target></link>, but after praying to God a flag fell from the sky. After this event, Danish King<space/><link><target>Valdemar II of Denmark</target><part>Valdemar II</part></link><space/>went on to defeat the Estonians. The first recorded use of the flag appears one hundred years later.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bjerg">&quot;Dannebrog&quot; by Hans Christian Bjerg, p.12, ISBN 87-7739-906-4.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legendary origin</heading><paragraph>The legend states the origin of the flag to the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lyndanisse</target></link>, also known as the Battle of Valdemar (Danish: &quot;<italics>Volmerslaget</italics>&quot;), near<space/><link><target>Lyndanisse</target></link><space/>(Tallinn) in<space/><link><target>Estonia</target></link>, on June 15, 1219.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Iceland<space/></arg><arg name="last">Evans<space/></arg><arg name="first">Andrew<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bradt Travel Guides<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="page">27<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Andrew Evans"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The battle was going badly, and defeat seemed imminent. However the Danish Bishop<space/><link><target>Anders Sunesen</target></link><space/>on top of a hill overlooking the battle prayed to God with his arms raised, which meant that the Danes moved closer to victory the more he prayed. When he raised his arms the Danes surged forward and when his arms grew tired and he let them fall, the Estonians turned the Danes back. Attendants rushed forward to raise his arms once again and the Danes surged forward again. At a second he was so tired in his arms that he dropped them and the Danes then lost the advantage and were moving closer to defeat. He needed two soldiers to keep his hands up and when the Danes were about to lose, 'Dannebrog' miraculously fell from the sky and the King took it, showed it to the troops and their hearts were filled with courage and the Danes won the battle.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Danmarks flag 1219 Lorentzen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Dannebrog falling from the sky during the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lyndanisse</target></link>, June 15, 1219. Painted by<space/><link><target>Christian August Lorentzen</target></link><space/>in 1809. Original located at<space/><link><target>Statens Museum for Kunst</target></link>, Denmark</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>No historical record supports this legend. The first record of the legend dates from more than 300 years after the campaign, and the first record connects the legend to a much smaller battle, though still in Estonia; the battle of Fellin (<link><target>Viljandi</target></link>) in 1208. Though no historical support exists for the flag story in the Fellin battle either, it is not difficult to understand how a small and unknown place is replaced with the much grander battle of<space/><link><target>Reval</target></link><space/>(Tallinn) from the Estonia campaign of King<space/><link><target>Valdemar II of Denmark</target><part>Valdemar II</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>This story originates from two written sources from the early 16th century.</paragraph><paragraph>The first is found in<space/><link><target>Christiern Pedersen</target></link>'s &quot;<italics>Danske Krnike</italics>&quot;, which is a sequel to<space/><link><target>Saxo Grammaticus</target><part>Saxo</part></link>s<space/><link><target>Gesta Danorum</target></link>, written 1520 23. It is not mentioned in connection to the campaign of King Valdemar II in Estonia, but in connection with a campaign in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>. He also mentions that this flag, falling from the sky during the Russian campaign of King Valdemar II, is the very same flag that King<space/><link><target>Eric of Pomerania</target></link><space/>took with him when he left the country in 1440 after being deposed as King.</paragraph><paragraph>The second source is the writing of the Franciscan monk<space/><link><target>Petrus Olai</target></link><space/>(Peder Olsen) of<space/><link><target>Roskilde</target></link>, from 1527. This record describes a battle in 1208 near a place called &quot;<italics>Felin</italics>&quot; during the Estonia campaign of King Valdemar II. The Danes were all but defeated when a lamb-skin banner depicting a white cross falls from the sky and miraculously leads to a Danish victory. In another record by<space/><italics>Petrus Olai</italics><space/>called &quot;<italics>Danmarks Tolv Herligheder</italics>&quot; (Twelve Splendours of Denmark), in splendour number nine, the same story is re-told almost to the word; however, a paragraph has been inserted correcting the year to 1219.</paragraph><paragraph>Some historians<template><target>Who</target><arg name="date">April 2010</arg></template><space/>believe that the story by<space/><italics>Petrus Olai</italics><space/>refers to a source from the first half of the 15th century, making this the oldest reference to the falling flag.</paragraph><paragraph>It is believed that the name of the capital of<space/><link><target>Estonia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tallinn</target></link>, came into existence after the battle. It is derived from &quot;Taani linn&quot;, meaning &quot;Danish town&quot; in Estonian.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Continuation of the romantic legend</heading><paragraph>According to tradition, the original flag from the Battle of Lyndanisse was used in the small campaign of 1500 when<space/><link><target>Hans of Denmark</target><part>King Hans</part></link><space/>tried to conquer<space/><link><target>Dithmarschen</target></link><space/>(in western<space/><link><target>Holstein</target></link><space/>in north<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>). The flag was lost in a devastating defeat at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Hemmingstedt</target></link><space/>on 17 February 1500. In 1559, King<space/><link><target>Frederick II of Denmark</target><part>Frederik II</part></link><space/>recaptured it during his own<space/><link><target>Dithmarschen</target></link><space/>campaign. In the capitulation terms it is stated that all Danish banners lost in 1500 were to be returned.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Hans Kniepers 1585.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>left</part><part>One of<space/><link><target>Hans Knieper</target></link>s heroic tapestries of Danish kings from 1585. King<space/><link><target>Eric VI of Denmark</target><part>Erik Menved</part></link><space/>storming a castle. Note the two Danish flags. Original located at<space/><link><target>Kronborg</target><part>Kronborg Castle</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>This legend is found in two sources,<space/><link><target>Hans Svaning</target></link>'s<space/><italics>History of King Hans</italics><space/>from 15581559 and<space/><link><target>Johan Rantzau</target></link>'s<space/><italics>History about the Last<space/><link><target>Dithmarschen</target></link><space/>War</italics>, from 1569.Both claim that this was the original flag, and consequently both writers knew the legend of the falling flag. In 1576, the son of<space/><italics>Johan Rantzau</italics>,<space/><link><target>Henrik Rantzau</target></link>, also writes about the war and the fate of the flag. He notes that the flag was in a poor condition when returned.</paragraph><paragraph>Sources from<space/><link><target>Dithmarschen</target></link>, written shortly after the battle of 1500, do mention banners, including the Royal banner, being captured from the Danes, but there is no mention of<space/><italics>Dannebrog</italics><space/>or the &quot;original&quot; flag.It is quite plausible that the kings personal banner as well as the leading banner of the army were both lost, as the battle was led by the King himself. However, it is more questionable if he indeed was carrying the &quot;original&quot; flag.</paragraph><paragraph>In a letter dated 22 February 1500 to<space/><link><target>Oluf Stigsn</target></link>, King John describes the battle, but does not mention the loss of an important flag. In fact, the entire letter gives the impression that the lost battle was nothing more than an &quot;unfortunate affair&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>An indication that we are dealing with multiple flags, are the 1570 writings of<space/><link><target>Niels Hemmingsn</target></link><space/>regarding a bloody battle between Danes and Swedes near the Swedish town of<space/><link><target>Uppsala</target></link><space/>in 1520. He writes that the &quot;Danish head banner&quot; (&quot;<italics>Danmarckis Hoffuitbanner</italics>&quot;) was nearly captured by the Swedes. It was saved only by the combined efforts of the banner-carrier<space/><link><target>Mogens Gyldenstierne</target></link>, taking multiple wounds, and a young man coming to his rescue. This young man was<space/><link><target>Peder Skram</target></link>. This &quot;<italics>Danmarckis Hoffuitbanner</italics>&quot; was probably nothing short of the &quot;<italics>Banner of the Realm'&quot; (</italics>Rigsbanner<italics>), the<space/></italics>Dannebrog''.</paragraph><paragraph>This is however not the end of the story. A priest and historian from<space/><link><target>Dithmarschen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Neocorus</target></link>, wrote in 1598 that the banner captured in 1500, was brought to the church in<space/><link><target>Whrden</target></link><space/>and hung there for the next 59 years, until it was returned to the Danes as part of the peace settlement in 1559.<link><target>Henrik Rantzau</target></link><space/>states in his writing of 1576 that the flag was brought to<space/><link><target>City of Schleswig</target><part>Slesvig city</part></link><space/>and placed in the cathedral, following its return.</paragraph><paragraph>A historian from<space/><link><target>Schleswig</target><part>Slesvig</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Ulrik Petersen</target></link><space/>(16561735), wrote in the late 17th century that the flag hung in<space/><italics>Slesvig</italics><space/>cathedral till about 1660 until it simply crumbled away, thus ending its more than 400-year-old story.</paragraph><paragraph>Historically, it is of course impossible to prove or disprove that these records speak of the same flag, or if the flag of 1208 or 1219 ever existed. Many of these legends are apparently built on earlier ones.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historic use</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Saxo Chr P front version 002.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>The Danish flag from the front page of<space/><link><target>Christiern Pedersen</target></link>s version of<space/><link><target>Saxo Grammaticus</target><part>Saxo</part></link>s<space/><link><target>Gesta Danorum</target></link>, 1514. Full frontpage can be seen<space/><link><target>:File:Saxo Chr P front version 001.jpg</target><part>here</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Caspar Paludan-Mller</heading><paragraph>The Danish historian<space/><link><target>Caspar Paludan-Mller</target></link><space/>in 1873 in his book &quot;<italics>Sagnet om den himmelfaldne Danebrogsfane</italics>&quot; put forth the theory that it is a banner sent by the<space/><link><target>Pope</target></link><space/>to the Danish King to use in his crusades in the<space/><link><target>Baltic countries</target></link>. Other kings and lords certainly received such banners.</paragraph><paragraph>One would imagine, though, that if this story were true, some kind of record ought to exist of the event, and presumably Danish historians would not have failed to mention it in some way. Being granted a banner by the Pope would have been a great honour, but despite the many letters of the popes relating to the<space/><link><target>crusades</target></link>, none of them mentions granting a banner to a King of Denmark. On the other hand, the letter in question might simply have been lost.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Johan Stckel</heading><paragraph>A similar theory was suggested by Danish explorer, adventurer and Captain<space/><link><target>Johan Stckel</target></link><space/>in the early 20th century. He suggested that it was not a papal banner to the King but a papal banner to the Churchly legate in the North, more specifically to archbishop<space/><link><target>Andreas Sunesn</target></link>, which he without the knowledge of the King brought with him on the King's crusade in the Baltic countries, in an effort to make the army take on a Christian symbol (over the king's symbol) and thereby strengthen the power of the church.</paragraph><paragraph>It is unlikely that the very fair and loyal archbishop would do such a thing behind the king's back. Moreover, it is unlikely that the pope would send such a banner, given the fact that they already had one, namely the banner of the<space/><link><target>Knights Hospitaller</target></link><space/>(Danish: &quot;Johanitterne&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Adolf Ditlev Jrgensen</heading><paragraph>A theory brought forth by the Danish historian<space/><link><target>Adolf Ditlev Jrgensen</target></link><space/>in 1875 in his book &quot;<italics>Danebroges Oprindelse</italics>&quot; is that the Danish flag<space/><italics>is</italics><space/>the banner of the<space/><link><target>Knights Hospitaller</target></link>. He notes that the order came to Denmark in the latter half of the 12th century and during the next centuries spread to major cities, like<space/><link><target>Odense</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Viborg, Denmark</target><part>Viborg</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Horsens</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ribe</target></link><space/>and their headquarters in<space/><link><target>Slagelse</target></link>, so by the time of the<space/><link><target>Northern Crusades</target><part>Baltic crusade</part></link>, the symbol was already a known symbol in Denmark.</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, he claims that<space/><link><target>Theoderich, Bishop of Estonia</target><part>Bishop Theoderich</part></link>, already co-initiator of the<space/><link><target>Livonian Brothers of the Sword</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Livonia</target></link>, had the idea of starting a similar order in Estonia; and that he was the original instigator of the inquiry from Bishop<space/><link><target>Albert of Buxhoeveden</target></link><space/>to King<space/><link><target>Valdemar II of Denmark</target><part>Valdemar II</part></link><space/>in 1218, that set the whole Danish participation in the Baltic crusades in motion.</paragraph><paragraph>In the contemporary writing of the priest<space/><link><target>Henry of Livonia</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Riga</target></link><space/>it is said that Bishop Theoderich was killed during the 1219 battle, when the enemy stormed his tent, thinking it was the King's tent. Adolf Ditlev Jrgensen explains that it was Bishop Theoderich who carried the flag, planted outside his tent; thus as an already well-known symbol of the Knights Hospitaller in Livonia, the enemy thought this was the King's symbol and mistakenly stormed Bishop Theoderich tent. He claims that the origin of the legend of the falling flag comes from this confusion in the battle.</paragraph><heading level='3'>L. P. Fabricius</heading><paragraph>The Danish church-historian<space/><link><target>L. P. Fabricius</target></link><space/>proposed yet another theory, explained in his study of 1934, titled &quot;<italics>Sagnet om Dannebrog og de ldste Forbindelser med Estland</italics>&quot;. He ascribes the origin to the 1208 Battle of<space/><link><target>Fellin</target></link>, not the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lyndanisse</target></link><space/>in 1219, based on the earliest source available about the story.</paragraph><paragraph>He says in this theory that it might have been Archbishop<space/><link><target>Andreas Sunesn</target></link>'s personal ecclesiastical banner or perhaps even the flag of Archbishop<space/><link><target>Absalon</target></link>, based on his tireless efforts to expand<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link><space/>to the Baltic countries. Under his initiative and supervision several smaller crusades had already been conducted in Estonia. The banner would then already be known in Estonia. He repeats the story about the flag being planted in front of Bishop Theodorik's tent, which the enemy mistakenly attacks believing it to be the tent of the King.</paragraph><paragraph>All these theories centre on two battles in Estonia, Fellin (1208) or Lyndanisse (1219), and thus try to explain the origin in relation to the tale brought forth over 300 years after the event.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Fabricius and Helga Bruhn</heading><paragraph>A much different theory is briefly discussed by<space/><italics>Fabricius</italics><space/>and elaborated more by<space/><link><target>Helga Bruhn</target></link><space/>in her book &quot;<italics>Dannebrog</italics>&quot; from 1949. She claims that it is neither the battle nor the banner that is central to the tale, but rather the<space/><link><target>cross</target></link><space/>in the sky. Similar tales of appearances in the sky at critical moments, particularly of crosses, can be found all over Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>Bruhn mentions a battle (also mentioned by<space/><italics>Fabricius</italics>) taking place on September 10, 1217 between Christian knights and<space/><link><target>Moors</target><part>Moor</part></link><space/>warriors on the<space/><link><target>Iberian Peninsula</target></link><space/>near the castle<space/><link><target>Alcazar</target></link><template><target>disambiguation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template>, where it is said that a golden cross on white appeared in the sky, to bring victory to the Christians.Likewise an almost identical<space/><link><target>Sweden</target><part>Swedish</part></link><space/>tale from the 18th century about a golden cross on blue appearing in 1157 during a Swedish battle in<space/><link><target>Finland</target></link>. Probably a later invention to counter the legendary origins of the Danish flags, but nevertheless of the same nature.The<space/><link><target>Flag of England</target><part>English flag</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Saint George</target></link>'s Cross is also claimed to have appeared in the sky during a critical battle, in this case in<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link><space/>during the crusades.</paragraph><paragraph>The similarities to the legends is obvious. In Spain, the colours of the Pope appears in the sky, in Finland the Swedish colours. In Estonia it is the Danish colours, and in Jerusalem the English colours. Basically, these are all variations of the same legend.</paragraph><paragraph>Since King Valdemar II of Denmark was married to the Portuguese princess, Berengria of Portugal, it is not unthinkable that the origin of the story, if not the flag, was the Spanish tale or a similar tale, which again might have been inspired by an even older legend.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Medieval use of the cross design in coats of arms</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Erikafpommernsdanskeunionssegl.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>left</part><part>Seal of<space/><link><target>Eric of Pomerania</target></link><space/>as king of the<space/><link><target>Kalmar union</target></link>, 1398. Note the small Dannebrog banner in the top-left corner.</part></link>Several coins, seals and images exist, both foreign and domestic, from the 13th to 15th centuries and even earlier, showing heraldic designs similar to Dannebrog, alongside the royal coat of arms (three blue lions on a golden shield.) This<space/><link><target>Coat of Arms of Denmark</target><part>coat of arms</part></link><space/>remains in use to this day.</paragraph><paragraph>An obvious place to look for documentation is in the<space/><link><target>Estonia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>city of<space/><link><target>Tallinn</target></link>, the site of the legendary battle. In Tallinn, a coat-of-arms resembling the flag is found on several buildings and can be traced back to the middle of the 15th century where it appears in the coat-of-arms of the &quot;Die Grosse<space/><link><target>guild</target><part>Gilde</part></link>&quot;, a sort of merchant consortium which greatly influenced the city's development. The symbol later became the coat-of-arms of the city. Efforts to trace it from Estonia back to Denmark have, however, been in vain.</paragraph><paragraph>The national<space/><link><target>Coat of Arms of Estonia</target></link>, three blue lions on a golden shield, is almost identical to the<space/><link><target>Coat of Arms of Denmark</target></link>, and its origin can be traced directly back to King<space/><link><target>Valdemar II</target></link><space/>and Danish rule in<space/><link><target>Estonia</target></link><space/>1219-1346.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Gelre armorial</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gelre Folio 55v.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>Page 55 verso in the Dutch<space/><link><target>Gelre Armorial</target></link>. Displaying the earliest known undisputed coloured image of a white-on-red cross on a flag attributed to a Danish ruler.</part></link>The earliest source that indisputably links the red flag with a white cross to a Danish King, and to the realm itself, is found in a<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/><link><target>armorial</target></link>, the &quot;<link><target>Gelre Armorial</target></link>&quot; (Dutch:<space/><italics>Wapenboek<space/><link><target>Guelders</target><part>Gelre</part></link></italics>), written between 1340 and 1370 (some sources say 1378 or 1386). Most historians claim that the book was written by<space/><link><target>Geldre Claes Heinen</target></link>. The book displays some 1,700 coats-of-arms from all over Europe, in colour. It is now located at the Royal Library of Brussels (the &quot;<link><target>Bibliothque royale Albert Ier</target></link>&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>On page 55 verso we find the Danish coat-of-arms surmounted by a helmet with<space/><link><target>Ermine (heraldry)</target><part>ermine-clad</part></link><space/><link><target>Wisent</target><part>bison</part></link><space/>horns (<template><target>lang-da</target><arg>vesselhorn</arg></template>). Behind the sinister horn is a lance tip with a banner, displaying a white cross on red. The text left of the coat of arms says &quot;die coninc van denmarke&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flaggenlexikon.de/fdaen.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">National Flagge des Königreich Dänemark</arg><arg name="accessdate">2005-02-14<space/></arg><arg name="author">Volker Preuß</arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/></arg><arg name="language">de</arg></template></extension><space/>(<italics>The King of Denmark</italics>). This is the earliest known undisputed colour rendering of the Dannebrog.</paragraph><paragraph>This image has been used to acknowledge a previously disputed theory that the cross found in<space/><link><target>Valdemar IV of Denmark</target><part>Valdemar Atterdag</part></link>'s coats of arms located in his Danlog seal (<italics>Rettertingsseglet</italics>) from 1356 is indeed the cross from the Danish flag.</paragraph><paragraph>This image from the Armorial Gelre is nearly identical to an image found in a 15th-century coats of arms book now located in the<space/><link><target>National Archives of Sweden</target></link>, (<italics>Riksarkivet</italics>)</paragraph><paragraph>From the time of King<space/><link><target>Eric of Pomerania</target></link><space/>there is also a case that undisputedly links the Dannebrog to Denmark. His seal from 1398 as king of the<space/><link><target>Kalmar union</target></link><space/>displays the arms of Denmark chief dexter, three lions. In this version, the lions are holding a Danebrog banner. The cross quartering the shields has also been identified as a Dannebrog cross, but this claim is disputed. Since the seal represents all of the three realms of the union, it is more likely that the cross refers to the union banner that King Eric tried to introduce, a red cross on yellow.</paragraph><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:State Banner of Denmark (14th Century).svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Dannebrog as depicted in the Gelre Armorial</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Royal Banner of Denmark (14th Century).svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>The Royal Banner of the Kings of Denmark based on the royal arms.</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern use</heading><heading level='3'>As a civil ensign</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:CyclingTeamPursuitBeijing2008.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The Danish flag at the medal ceremony for the<space/><link><target>Cycling at the 2008 Summer Olympics Men's team pursuit</target><part>men's team pursuit</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>2008 Summer Olympics</target></link><space/>in Beijing.</part></link>The size and shape of the<space/><link><target>civil ensign</target></link><space/>(&quot;<italics>Koffardiflaget</italics>&quot;) for merchant ships is given in the regulation of June 11, 1748, which says:<space/><italics>A red flag with a white cross with no split end. The white cross must be 1/7 of the flag's height. The two first fields must be square in form and the two outer fields must be 6/4 lengths of those</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The proportions are thus: 3:1:3 vertically and 3:1:4.5 horizontally. This definition are the absolute proportions for the Danish national flag to this day, for both the civil version of the flag (&quot;<italics>Stutflaget</italics>&quot;), as well as the merchant flag (&quot;<italics>Handelsflaget</italics>&quot;). Both flags are identical.</paragraph><paragraph>A somewhat curious regulation came in 1758 concerning Danish ships sailing in the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean</target></link>. These had to carry the King's<space/><link><target>Royal cypher</target><part>cypher logo</part></link><space/>in the center of the flag, to distinguish them from Maltese ships, due to the similarity of the flag of the Order of St. John (also known as the<space/><link><target>Knights Hospitaller</target></link>). To the best of knowledge, this regulation has never been revoked, however it is probably no longer done.</paragraph><paragraph>According to the regulation of June 11, 1748 the colour was simply red, which is common known today as &quot;Dannebrog rd&quot; (&quot;<italics>Dannebrog red</italics>&quot;). The only available red fabric dye in 1748 was made of<space/><link><target>Rubia</target><part>madder root</part></link>, which can be processed to produce a brilliant red dye (used historically for British soldiers' jackets). The private company,<space/><link><target>Dansk Standard</target></link>, regulation number 359 of 2005, defines the red colour of the flag as<space/><link><target>Pantone</target></link><space/>186c. No official nuance definition of &quot;Dannebrog rd&quot; exists.</paragraph><paragraph>During the next about 150 years nobody paid much attention to actually abide fully to the proportions of the flag given in the 1748 regulation, not even the government.</paragraph><paragraph>As late as 1892 it was stated in a series of regulations that the correct lengths of the two last fields in the flag were 6/4. Some interested in the matter made inquires into the issue and concluded that the 6/4 length would make the flag look blunt. Any new flag would also quickly become unlawful, due to wear and tear. They also noted that the flag currently used had lengths, of the last two fields, anywhere between 7/4 to 13/6. So in May 1893 a new regulation to all chiefs of police, stated that the police should not intervene, if the two last fields in the flag were longer than 6/4 as long as these did not exceed 7/4, and provided that this was the only rule violated. This regulation is still in effect today and thus the legal proportions of the National flag is today anywhere between<space/><italics>3:1:3 width / 3:1:4.5 length</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>3:1:3 width / 3:1:5.25 length</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>That some confusion still exists in this matter can be seen from the regulation of May 4, 1927, which once again states that Danish merchant ships have to fly flags according to the regulation of 1748.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Variants</heading><heading level='4'>Splitflag and Orlogsflag</heading><paragraph><template><target>flag image</target><arg name="Image"><space/>Flag of Denmark (state).svg</arg><arg name="Caption"><space/>The ''Splitflag'' - the Danish State Flag. [[File:FIAV 011010.svg|23px]] Proportions: 56:107<ref name</arg></template>The<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>have similar shapes but different sizes and shades of red. Legally, they are two different flags. The<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>is a Danish flag ending in a swallow-tail, it is<space/><italics>Dannebrog red</italics>, and is used on land. The<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>is an elongated<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>with a deeper red colour and is only used on sea.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Naval Ensign of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>The ''Orlogsflag'' - the Danish Naval Flag.<space/><link><target>File:FIAV 000001.svg</target><part>23px</part></link><space/>Proportions: 7:17<extension extension_name='ref' name="encyklopdien"></extension></part></link>The<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>with no markings, may only be used by the<space/><link><target>Royal Danish Navy</target></link>. There are though a few exceptions to this. A few institutions have been allowed to fly the clean<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics>. The same flag with markings has been approved for a few dozen companies and institutions over the years.</paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore, the<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>is only described as such if it has no additional markings. Any swallow-tail flag, no matter the color, is called a<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>provided it bears additional markings.</paragraph><paragraph>The first regulation regarding the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>dates from March 27, 1630, in which King<space/><link><target>Christian IV of Denmark</target><part>Christian IV</part></link><space/>orders that Norwegian<space/><italics>Defensionskibe</italics><space/>(armed merchants ships) may only use the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>if they are in Danish war service.In 1685 an order, distributed to a number of cities in<space/><link><target>Duchy of Schleswig</target><part>Slesvig</part></link>, states that all ships must carry the Danish flag, and in 1690 all merchant ships are forbidden to use the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>, with the exception of ships sailing in the<space/><link><target>East Indies</target></link>,<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link><space/>and along the coast of<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>.In 1741 it is confirmed that the regulation of 1690 is still very much in effect; that merchant ships may not use the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>. At the same time the<space/><link><target>Danish East India Company</target></link><space/>is allowed to fly the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>when past the<space/><link><target>equator</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>It is obvious that some confusion must have existed regarding the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>. In 1696 the Admiralty presented the King with a proposal for a standard regulating both size and shape of the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>. In the same year a royal resolution defines the proportions of the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>, which in this resolution is called<space/><italics>Kongeflaget</italics><space/>(the King's flag), as follows:<space/><italics>The cross must be 1/7 of the flags height. The two first fields must be square in form with the sides three times the cross width. The two outer fields are rectangular and 1 the length of the square fields. The tails are the length of the flag</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:DannebrogUpDSR.ogv</target><part>thumb</part><part>Splitflag raised at opening of DSR rowing club</part></link>These numbers are the basic for the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>, or<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics>, today, though the numbers have been slightly altered. The term<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>dates from 1806 and denotes use in the Danish Navy.</paragraph><paragraph>From about 1750 to early 19th century a number of ships and companies which the government has interests in, received approval to use the<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics>. From the mid-19th century to 1899, and especially after 1870, additional institutions and private companies received approval to use the Splitflag.</paragraph><paragraph>In the royal resolution of October 25, 1939 for the Danish Navy, it is stated that the<space/><italics>Orlogsflag</italics><space/>is a<space/><italics>Splitflag</italics><space/>with a deep red (&quot;<italics>dybrd</italics>&quot;) or madder red (&quot;<italics>Kraprd</italics>&quot;) colour. Like the National flag, no nuance is given, but in modern days this is given as 195U.Furthermore, the size and shape is corrected in this resolution to be: &quot;The cross must be 1/7 of the flag's height. The two first fields must be square in form with the height of 3/7 of the flag's height. The two outer fields are rectangular and 5/4 the length of the square fields. The tails are 6/4 the length of the rectangular fields&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus, if compared to the standard of 1696, both the rectangular fields and the tails have decreased in size.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Royal Standards</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Monarch</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>The current version of the<space/><link><target>royal standard</target></link><space/>was introduced on 16 November 1972 when the<space/><link><target>Margrethe II of Denmark</target><part>Queen</part></link><space/>adopted a new version of her personal coat of arms. The royal standard is the flag of Denmark with a swallow-tail and charged with the<space/><link><target>Coat of arms of Denmark</target><part>monarchs coat of arms</part></link><space/>set in a white square. The centre square is 32 parts in a flag with the ratio 56:107.<link><target>File:Royal Standard of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>center</part><part>Royal Standard of Denmark</part></link></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Other members of the royal family</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Standard of the Crown Prince of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Standard of<space/><link><target>Frederik, Crown Prince of Denmark</target><part>Frederik</part></link><space/>the Crown Prince of Denmark.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Standard of Prince Consort Henrik of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Standard of<space/><link><target>Henrik, Prince Consort of Denmark</target><part>Henrik</part></link><space/>the Prince Consort of Denmark.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Standard of the Regent of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Standard of the Regent of Denmark</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Standard of the Royal House of Denmark.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Standard of the Royal House- used by other members of the<space/><link><target>Danish Royal Family</target><part>Royal Family</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='3'>Superstitions</heading><paragraph>Danish culture states that the Dannebrog is not allowed to touch the ground because it came from heaven. It also states that the Dannebrog is not allowed to be or remain hoisted at night, because it is said that such is to salute the Devil.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Other flags of the Kingdom of Denmark</heading><paragraph><link><target>Greenland</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Faroe Islands</target></link><space/>are additional autonomous countries within the Kingdom of Denmark. These countries have their own official flags.</paragraph><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Flag of the Faroe Islands.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:small>8:11</xhtml:small><space/><template><target>FIAV</target><arg>110110</arg></template><space/><link><target>Flag of the Faroe Islands</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Flag of Greenland.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:small>2:3</xhtml:small><space/><template><target>FIAV</target><arg>110110</arg></template><space/><link><target>Flag of Greenland</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='3'>Regional Flags</heading><paragraph>Some areas in Denmark have unofficial flags, listed below. The regional flags of Bornholm and r are known to be in active use. The flags of Vendsyssel (Vendelbrog) and the Jutlandic flag (&quot;Den jyske fane&quot;) are obscure. None of these flags have legal recognition in Denmark, and are officially considered to be &quot;fantasy flags&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.harteg.dk/bornholmsflag/?Artikler:Bornholms_omr%E5deflag_afvist'></link><space/>harteg.dk Bornholms omrdeflag afvist</extension><space/>Denmark reserves official recognition to official flags and regional flags (<italics>omrdeflag</italics>) from other jurisdictions.</paragraph><table border="2" cellpadding="4" cellspacing="0" style="margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse;"><tablerow bgcolor="#efefef"><tablehead width="110">Flag</tablehead><tablehead width="100">Date</tablehead><tablehead width="250">Use</tablehead><tablehead width="250">Description</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Flag of Denmark Bornholm.svg</target><part>100px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>1970s Present</tablecell><tablecell>Unofficial<space/><link><target>flag of Bornholm</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nordic Cross Flag</target></link><space/>in red and green. Also known in a version with a white fimbriation of the green cross in a style similar to design of the<space/><link><target>Flag of Norway</target><part>Norwegian flag</part></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Flag of r.svg</target><part>100px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>1633 Present</tablecell><tablecell>Unofficial flag of<space/><link><target>r</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tricolour (flag)</target><part>Tricolour</part></link><space/>in yellow, green and red<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Very similar to the<space/><link><target>Flag of Lithuania</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Unofficial flag of Vendsyssel.svg</target><part>100px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>1976 Present</tablecell><tablecell>Unofficial<space/><link><target>flag of Vendsyssel</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nordic Cross Flag</target></link><space/>in blue, orange and green.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.klauber-flag.dk/flag.asp?cmd=details&amp;amp;flag=3884'></link><space/>klauber-flag.dk - Vendelbrog</extension><space/>Designed by Mogens Bohj.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://nordjyske.dk/nyheder/det-faldt-ikke-nedfra-himlen----/d7dd1a00-9f34-4eef-ab98-c88111bbf75e/4/1513'>nordjyske.dk Det faldt ikke nedfra himlen ...</link></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Flag of Jutland.svg</target><part>100px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>1975 Present</tablecell><tablecell>Unofficial flag of<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>A<space/><link><target>Nordic Cross Flag</target></link><space/>in blue, green and red. Designed by Per Kramer in 1975.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.klauber-flag.dk/flag.asp?cmd=details&amp;amp;flag=1796'></link><space/>klauber-flag.dk</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>The flag of<space/><link><target>Volyn Oblast</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ukraine</target></link><space/>is very similar to the Dannebrog.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Denmark</arg><arg>Faroe Islands</arg><arg>Greenland</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Flag of Greenland</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Flag of the Faroe Islands</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of flags of Denmark</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nordic Cross flag</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Raven banner</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template><template><target>more footnotes</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.danmarks-samfundet.dk/aspbite/categories/index.asp?intCatID=31'>Danmarks-Samfundet</link><space/>- several rules and customs about the use of Dannebrog</listitem><listitem><italics>Dannebrog</italics>, Helga Bruhn, Forlaget Jespersen og Pios, Copenhagen 1949</listitem><listitem><italics>Danebrog - Danmarks Palladium</italics>, E. D. Lund, Forlaget H. Hagerups, Copenhagen 1919</listitem><listitem><italics>Dannebrog - Vort Flag</italics>, Lieutenant Colonel Thaulow, Forlaget Codan, Copenhagen 1943</listitem><listitem><italics>DS 359:2005 Flagdug</italics>, Dansk Standard, 2005</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Flags of Denmark</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>FOTW</target><arg name="id">dk</arg><arg name="title">Denmark</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tourism.tallinn.ee/fpage/explore/attractions/old_town/newwin-place/print/id-174827'>Danish flag legendary birthplace in Estonia</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>-</target></template><template><target>Denmark topics</target></template><template><target>Flag of Europe</target></template><template><target>nationalflags</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Flag Of Denmark</target></template><link><target>Category:National symbols of Denmark</target></link><link><target>Category:National flags</target><part>Denmark</part></link><link><target>Category:Flags of Denmark</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Nordic Cross flags</target><part>Denmark</part></link><link><target>Category:Red and white flags</target><part>Denmark</part></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>